<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei-print.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="global.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>Account of I. Coates, J. Sharpless, &amp; J. Pierce, visits to Indian
                    Reservation, NY: Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Haverford College Quaker Collection</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>FHL staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Journal transcribed by</resp>
                    <name>Crowd-sourced</name>


                </respStmt>

            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 237 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Haverford College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street/>
                    <addrLine>Haverford, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode/>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>This work is the property of Haverford College Special COlleciotn. It may be
                        copied freely by individuals for personal use, research, and teaching
                        (including distribution to classes) as long as this statement of
                        availability is included in the text. It may be linked to freely in Internet
                        editions of all kinds, including for—profit works.</p>
                    <p>Publishers, libraries, and other information providers interested in
                        providing this text in a commercial or non—profit product or from an
                        information server must contact Swarthmore College for licensing and cost
                        information.</p>
                    <p> Scholars interested in changing or adding to these texts by, for example,
                        creating a new edition of the text (electronically or in print) with
                        substantive editorial changes, may do so only with the permission of Friends
                        Historical Library of Swarthmore College. This is the case whether the new
                        publication will be made available at a cost or free of charge.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2015">2015</date>
                <idno type="local">HV_IC_1798_1799</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Native Americans and Quakers: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Haverford College Quaker &amp; Special
                            Collections</institution>
                        <collection/>
                        <idno>MC 950</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>116 pp. (1 volume)</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Account of I. Coates, J. Sharpless, &amp; J. Pierce, visits to Indian
                    Reservation manuscript is housed at the Haverford College Quaker Collection</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> The transcribers and editor attempted to render the author’s orthography and
                    grammar as they appear on the page of his journal, even when the author’s own
                    spelling and usage are inconsistent. Additionally, many questions remain about
                    spelling the names of his Quaker acquaintances, individual Native Americans who
                    populate his journal, and Indian villages and towns. The transcribers and editor
                    attempted to remain faithful to the author’s Anglicized spellings in all cases. </p>
                <p>The author of the original journal does not include page numbers on his
                    manuscript; the page numbers have been interpolated by the transcribers to
                    correspond with the manuscript sheets.</p>
                <p>This journal appears to be a edited compilation, written in 1898.</p>
            </editorialDecl>

        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written in <date when="1799">1799</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Society of Friends</item>


                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>

        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item>
                    <date when="2015"/></item>

            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="preface">

                <pb n="4" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_004"/>
                <p>The following account of <lb/>visits to these Indian Reservations in <lb/>Western
                        <placeName key="newyo">New York</placeName>, has been compiled <lb/>from the
                    accounts kept by <persName key="icoat1">Isaac <lb/>Coates</persName>, <persName
                        key="jshar1">Joshua Sharpless</persName> and <persName key="jpier1">John
                        <lb/>Pierce</persName> of their visits to those Indians <lb/>in the years
                        <date when="1798">1798</date> and <date when="1799">1799</date>. It appears
                    <lb/>that the above named persons were <lb/>highly esteemed by their friends in
                    <lb/>general and they were often appoint-<lb/>ed on important business in the
                    <lb/>Friends Society of which they were<lb/>members.</p>
                <p>The <orgName key="pymindian">Indian Committee</orgName> procur-<lb/>ed various
                    articles for the Indians' <lb/>use in agricultural industry &amp;c <lb/>which
                    they forwarded to <placeName key="pitts">Pittsburg</placeName>
                    <lb/>about the time those Friends start<lb/>ed who went in <date when="1798"
                        >1798</date>.</p>


            </div>


        </front>
        <body>


            <div type="narrative">
                <pb n="6" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_006"/>
                <head>Visit to the Indians in <date when="1798">1798</date>.</head>
                <p><orgName key="pym">Philadephia Yearly Meeting</orgName>'s <orgName
                        key="pymindian">Committee</orgName>
                    <lb/>having concluded to make an attempt at <lb/>civilizing some of the Indian
                    Natives on the<lb/>North Western border of <placeName key="penns"
                        >Pennsylvania</placeName>, re-<lb/>siding on the <geogName key="alleg"
                        >Alleghany river</geogName>, in the state<lb/>of <placeName key="newyo">New
                        York</placeName>. Several of their number visited said Indians,
                    accom-<lb/>panied by their friends, <persName key="hsimm1">Henry
                        Simmons</persName>, <persName key="jswai1">Joel<lb/>Swayne</persName> and
                        <persName key="hjack1">Halliday Jackson</persName>, who <emph
                        rend="underline">went</emph> with<lb/>the prospect of remaining a <emph
                        rend="underline">while</emph> with the Indians<lb/>to instruct them in
                    cultivating their lands &amp;c.</p>
                <p>Three of the <orgName key="pymindian">Committee</orgName> kep some account<lb/>of
                    their travels and experiences in this journey<lb/>from which the following is
                    compiled.</p>
                <p>Those three friends were <persName key="jshar1">Joshua
                        Sharpless</persName><lb/><persName key="jpier1">John Pierce</persName> and
                        <persName key="icoat1">Isaac Coates</persName>, of whom we will<lb/>speak as
                    Our Travellers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="chestc"/>
                    <date when="1798-05-01"/></dateline>
                <p>They set out from Chester County the 1st of 5th Mo. 1798.<lb/>One of them says
                        <q>This day left our habi-<lb/>tations after experiencing a humbling time
                        in<lb/> parting with our families and connections, and<lb/>were accompanied
                        from home by <persName key="hsimm1">Henry Simmons</persName><lb/>who called
                        on us, and next day we were met by<lb/><persName key="hjack1">Haliday
                            Jackson</persName> and <persName key="jswai1">Joel Swayne</persName>, at
                        the house of<lb/><persName key="agibb1">Abraham Gibbons</persName> where we
                        all set out in the<lb/>afternoon, about 2 o clock; and after several days<lb/>
                        <pb n="7" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_007"/> fatiguing ride, we arrived at
                            <persName key="rcadw1">Reese Cadwallider</persName>'s<lb/> in <placeName
                            key="redst1">Redstone</placeName> where we rested ourselves and
                        horses<lb/> about two days. Attended their meeting and
                        then<lb/>proceeded</q> on the journey.</p>
                <p>Let us leave "Our Travellers" while we reflect<lb/>that in the undeveloped and
                    thinly settled state<lb/>of the country at the time they made this
                        visit,<lb/><emph rend="underline">such</emph> journeys involved an amount of
                    hardship,<lb/>fatigue, and exposure, of which it is difficult at<lb/>this day to
                    form an adequate conception. (<date when="1898">1898</date>.)</p>
                <p>A member of the <orgName key="pymindian">Indian Committee</orgName> can
                    now<lb/>leave <placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName> in a luxuriously
                    furnished rail-<lb/>road car, and in less than a day find himself<lb/>on the
                        <placeName key="alleg2">Alleghany Indian Reservation</placeName>. Then his
                    prede-<lb/>cessor in the same good work was compelled to<lb/>ride his horse day
                    after day over the Mountains<lb/>for two or three weeks, often with very
                    indiferent<lb/>lodging and food to reach the same spot.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="stras"/>
                    <date when="1798-05-01" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p>Now let us return to "Our Travellers, who<lb/> have ridden through <placeName
                        key="shipp">Shippensburg</placeName> and are<lb/>taking a view of the houses
                    as they ride through<lb/>the village of <placeName key="stras"
                        >Strasburg</placeName>, of which there are perhaps<lb/>40 built of squared
                    logs, One says, <q>Shortly after, we<lb/> began to assend the <geogName
                            key="bluem">Blue Mountain</geogName> an high<lb/>towering iminence steep
                        and very rockey.</q></p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="bluem"/><date when="1798-05-04"/></dateline>
                <p>On the 4th assended another Mountain, <q>When<lb/>we arrived at its summit we had
                        a delightful view<lb/>of a well improved valley, two or more miles in width,<lb/>
                        <pb n="8" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_008"/>with a lofty mountain beyond,
                        Then through <placeName key="fanne">Fannets-<lb/>burg</placeName> a village
                        of perhaps 30 log houses. Then over <geogName key="sidel"
                            >Sideling<lb/>hill</geogName>, we rode four miles along its summit,
                        which<lb/>was very high, but our prospect was not very extensive<lb/>by
                        reason of some mountains near by on each hand.</q></p>
                <q><p>As we began to descend a noble view presented as<lb/>far as the eye could
                        reach, having the <geogName key="allmo">Alleghany moun-<lb/>tains</geogName>
                        in full view at 20 or more miles distant.</p>
                    <p>The extensive prospect between looked like a delight-<lb/>ful plain
                        checquered with a few plantations, but<lb/>when we come to traverse it we
                        found many lofty<lb/>hills or mountains one was the steepest hill
                        we<lb/>have met with since we left home. It is admirable<lb/>that so many
                        wagons which pass this road should<lb/>be able to get up it. I suppose have
                        passed by 20<lb/>this day mostly with families going to new coun-<lb/>tries,
                        a number of them were crowded with children:<lb/>17 persons of diferent
                        discriptions belonged to one.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><geogName key="junia"/><date when="1798-05-04">4th</date></dateline>
                <p>Our Travellers lodged this night at one <persName key="hart1"
                    >Hartleys</persName>,<lb/>near the banks of the Juniata, Next day rode<lb/>
                    through <placeName key="bedfo">Bedford</placeName>, a village containing a
                    number of<lb/>good stone buildings, They passed on over moun-<lb/>tains,
                    crossing streams, through, what we called,<lb/><placeName key="glade">the
                        Glades</placeName>, to the foot of the <geogName key="allem">Great
                        Alleghany</geogName> where<lb/>is some good land, and luxuriant growth
                    of<lb/> vegetation. The assent of this mountain is better<lb/>land than any of
                    the others, being covered with<lb/>lofty timbers of divers sorts, On top of the
                        highest<lb/><pb n="9" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_009"/>of these mountains
                    they passed was a fine spring<lb/>of water. This night the <date
                        when="1798-05-05">5th</date> they lodged in a<lb/>dutch town called
                        <placeName key="berli">Berlin</placeName> in <placeName key="somsc">Somerset
                        County</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="berli"/><date when="1798-05-06">6th</date></dateline>
                <p><q>We started early this morning with some<lb/>hopes of reaching a Friends house
                        this ivining which<lb/>was very desirable. We all took notice when
                        on<lb/>the <geogName key="allmo">Alleghany's</geogName> and for many miles
                        this side<lb/>how very backward the trees were. When we<lb/>left home (<date
                            when="1798-05-01">1st of 5th mo</date>) they were putting out
                        fast<lb/>and the weather being very warm they made rapid<lb/>progress. Yet
                        [here] this morning we remarked<lb/>that the buds of the Chestnut and White
                        Oak<lb/>were not formed into leaves so as to make an<lb/> appearance, yet
                        the same day as we descended<lb/>from <geogName key="cheri">Chestnut
                            Ridge</geogName> the trees were all green,</q></p>
                <p>It was curious to see such a diference. <persName key="jshar1"
                    >J.S.</persName><lb/>says <said who="jshar1">I think there is, at least, in
                        three miles<lb/>riding two weeks diference in the seasons.</said></p>
                <p><q>From <placeName key="chehi">Chestnut Hill</placeName> there is one of the
                        most<lb/>extensive prospects that is to be met with in trav-<lb/>elling--.
                        to the North: to the West: and to the South,<lb/>I had no doubt but the view
                        was of 50 miles ex-<lb/>tent.</q>
                    <persName key="icoat1">I.C.</persName> says <said who="icoat1">When we got to
                        the top of the<lb/>mountain where we had the first sight of<lb/><placeName
                            key="pitts">Pittsburg</placeName> we soon began to decend the
                        steepest<lb/>hill I ever saw a wagon road upon, which to<lb/>me appeared
                        almost impracticable for a good<lb/>team to draw an empty wagon up,
                            Neverthe-<lb/><pb n="10" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_010"/>less, the
                        inhabitants say, they frequently go up<lb/>loaded, When we descended to the
                        bottom we<lb/>crossed the beautiful <geogName key="monon"
                            >Monongahela</geogName>, and im-<lb/>mediately entered the
                    town.</said></p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="pitts"/><date when="1798-05-06" type="unattested"
                    /></dateline>
                <p><persName key="jshar1">J. Sharpless</persName> says, <said who="jshar1">It was
                        the time of the sitting<lb/>of the Supreme Court when we arrived here and we
                        had<lb/>some fears whether we should get accommodations for<lb/>our-selves
                        and our horses; but having enquired for the best<lb/>tavern, before we
                        crossed the river, we were recommen-<lb/>ded to the <q>Green Tree,</q> where
                        after some hesitation<lb/><lb/>we were taken in, and found good
                        accommodations.</said></p>
                <q><p>Some discouragement attended my mind on<lb/>the way hither, concerning the
                        business we were go-<lb/>ing on. -- being important and to be
                        transacted<lb/>among a people of strange language, in a wilder-<lb/>ness
                        country, and under great uncertainty how<lb/>we should be able to get the
                        goods we have in<lb/>care, to our desired part: but upon our arrival<lb/>
                        here, and being introduced to some for whom we<lb/>had letters of credit, we
                        met with a very kind re-<lb/>ception, and they appeared hearty in
                        assisting<lb/>us, and informed us that the goods sent<lb/>from <placeName
                            key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName> arrived safely a few days<lb/>ago,
                        and were in the public storehouse.</p><p>We had a satisfactory conference
                        with<lb/>the deputy Quarter Master, from whom we learn-<lb/>ed that
                            <persName key="gwilk2">General Wilkinson</persName> had directed<lb/>him
                        to assist us in forwarding our goods<lb/><pb n="11"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_011"/>up the <geogName key="alleg"
                            >Alleghany</geogName> to <placeName key="cornp">Cornplanters
                            settle-<lb/>ment</placeName>. We also manifested an obliging<lb/>and
                        attentive disposition relative to the<lb/>business, and appeared well
                        satisfied with the<lb/> object of our visit and promised to have a
                        boat<lb/>ready tomorrow for the purpose, and kindly<lb/>offered to introduce
                        us to <persName key="gwilk2">General Wilkinson</persName> as<lb/>early in
                        the morning as would be convenient.</p>
                    <p>We next paid attention to procuring<lb/>such articles of provision as
                        appeared necessary,<lb/>having been informed at <placeName key="redst1"
                            >Redstone</placeName> that no ad-<lb/>vantage would be derived from
                        purchasing<lb/>them in that neighborhood, or any where<lb/>short of this
                        place, The following articles<lb/>were agreed to be necessary and
                        accordingly<lb/>purchased viz.</p>
                    <p>4 1/2 bushels of potatoes,<lb/>3 " " wheat flour,<lb/>2 " " Indian
                        meal,<lb/>2 " " " corn,<lb/>3 1/2 " " oats,<lb/>1 " " dried apples,<lb/>1/2
                        " " salt,<lb/>35 pounds " sugar,<lb/>136 " " bacon,<lb/>30 " "
                        biscuit,<lb/>28 " " cheese,<lb/>8 1/2 " " lard.<lb/><pb n="12"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_012"/>12 lights of window glass,<lb/>2 sets
                        of irons,<lb/>1 pair of pot hooks,<lb/>1 small iron kettle, and several
                        other<lb/>small articles.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="pitts"/><date when="1798-05-11">11th. Sixth
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q>
                    <p> This morning in company<lb/>with <persName key="icrag1">major
                            Craig</persName> waited on <persName key="gwilk2">General
                            Wilkinson</persName><lb/> at his own house, who received us with
                        much<lb/>respect, expressed his great satisfaction to see<lb/>us on our
                        present errand, and manifested a<lb/>disposition desirous of contributing
                        both to our<lb/>encouragement and assistance, He also renewed,<lb/>in our
                        presenence, his directions to the aforesaid<lb/><persName key="icrag1">major
                            Craig</persName>, deputy Quarter Master, to forward our<lb/>goods up the
                        river, and invited us to take dinner<lb/> with him, which kindness we
                        acknowledged,<lb/>but excused our selves, on account of our bus-<lb/> iness.
                        The <persName key="icrag1">deputy Quarter Master</persName> said it<lb/>was
                        about 140 miles by land to <placeName key="cornp"
                            >Cornplanter's<lb/>village</placeName>, but much more by water, -- that
                        it was<lb/> a good time for them to go, the river being<lb/>neither too low,
                        nor too high. So that the<lb/>prospect of things looks a little more
                        lightsome.</p>
                    <p>About three in the afternoon a<lb/>boat was in readiness, and the Quarter
                        Master<lb/> furnishing a wagon we soon got our goods<lb/>collected to the
                        water-side, weighed and put<lb/>on board, amounting in the whole to 4,734
                            <lb/><pb n="13" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_013"/>lbs. for which the
                        boatman was to have<lb/>twenty shillings per hundred weight for<lb/>taking
                        up to the <placeName key="cornp">settlement</placeName>, which
                        we<lb/>afterwards understood from him, was 270<lb/>miles by water, He agreed
                        to set-off in two<lb/>or three days, estimating it would take
                        eight-<lb/>teen days to reach the <placeName key="cornp"
                            >settlement</placeName>.</p>
                    <p> We next attended to providing some ne-<lb/>cessary articles of provision to
                        carry with us<lb/>on horse back.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="pitts"/><date when="1798-05-12">12th. 1st
                    day</date></dateline>
                <q><p> About 8 in in the morning several<lb/>of our number again waited on the
                            <persName key="gwilk2">General</persName><lb/>agreeable to his request
                        of yesterday, and had<lb/>a satisfactory interview, in which he
                        expressed<lb/>his good wishes for the success of the cause<lb/>we were
                        engaged in, And to encourage the<lb/> business and assist therein he
                        presented us<lb/>with the following letters; and when we<lb/>came away
                        accompanied us through the<lb/>guards and respectfully took his leave of
                        us.</p>
                    <floatingText type="letter">
                        <body>
                            <opener>To <persName key="cfowl1">Captain Fowler</persName> Agent of
                                Quarter<lb/>Master General, <placeName key="ffran">Fort
                                    Franklin</placeName>.<lb/><dateline>Head Quarters, <placeName
                                        key="pitts">Pittsburgh</placeName>.<lb/><date
                                        when="1798-05-12">May the 12th 1798</date>.</dateline>
                                <salute>Sir:--</salute></opener>
                            <p>This will be handed to you by <persName key="jpier1">Mr.
                                    <lb/>Pierce</persName>, of the <orgName key="pym">Society of
                                    Friends in Philadelphia</orgName><lb/><pb n="14"
                                    facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_014"/>who with several associates is
                                on a visit to the<lb/><orgName key="seneca">Seneca Nation</orgName>
                                with views to make some es-<lb/>tablishment which may prove useful
                                to those<lb/>people, and interesting to the rights of
                                hu-<lb/>manity. You will be pleased to furnish<lb/><persName
                                    key="jpier1">Mr. Pierce</persName> a guide provisions, and
                                any<lb/> accommodations he may need, charging<lb/>the occurring
                                expenses to the proper head.</p>
                            <closer><salute>With respect and esteem, I am Sir,<lb/>Your obedient
                                    servant.</salute><signed><persName key="gwilk2">James
                                        Wilkinson</persName>.</signed></closer>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                    <floatingText type="letter">
                        <body>
                            <opener>To <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> and the Village
                                Chiefs of the<lb/><orgName key="seneca">Seneca Nation</orgName>.
                                    <salute>Friends and Brothers,</salute></opener>
                            <p>The bearer, one of out be-<lb/>loved men among the people called
                                Quakers,<lb/> visits you, with several good men from the
                                same<lb/>Society, who intend to sit down amongst you, in<lb/>order
                                to instruct our red brethren in works<lb/>of usefulness, and to
                                point out to them the<lb/>path of virtue, which leads to the
                                blissful<lb/>mansions of the Great Spirit, the Father<lb/>of light
                                and life.</p>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>, I charge you to take
                                this<lb/>our beloved man, and his companions, by<lb/>the hand, and
                                to treat them with kindness<lb/>and sincerity. Open your ears and
                                listen to<lb/><pb n="15" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_015"/>what they
                                say;- open your eyes and follow<lb/>their footsteps: then will your
                                old men, your<lb/>wives, your children, and your children's
                                chil-<lb/>dren live in security, and enjoy the com-<lb/>forts of
                                life; and the red people, and the white<lb/>people on this great
                                island, will soon become<lb/>as one.</p>
                            <p>Brethren and Children, let this<lb/>admonition sink deep into your
                                hearts,<lb/>and may you be blessed with a clear sky,<lb/>smoothe
                                roads and plentiful harvests to<lb/>the end of your days. I command
                                yo to<lb/>the care of the Great Spirit, and am in heart<lb/>your
                                friend,</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName key="gwilk2">James
                                    Wilkinson</persName>,<lb/>Commander-in-chief of the troops of
                                    the<lb/>United States.</signed></closer>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                    <p>Being now ready to depart, we took leave of<lb/>several of the first
                        characters of this place<lb/>who wished us success, and affectionately
                        bade<lb/>us farewell. About 9 o clock we left <placeName key="pitts"
                            >Pittsburgh</placeName>.</p>
                    <p>Crossing the <geogName key="alleg">Alleghany</geogName> just opposite
                        the<lb/>town, we entered a wilderness county, but<lb/>little inhabited, the
                        settlements not more<lb/>than two or three years old, and scarce of
                        pro-<lb/>visions for man and horse. We traveled at<lb/>several stages about
                        33 miles, having fed at<lb/><pb n="16" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_016"
                        />Durkins 18 miles, we got in the evening to a place<lb/>called the
                            <placeName key="doubl">Double Cabin</placeName>, a poor house with
                        earthen<lb/>floor, on which we lodged, wrapped in our blankets,<lb/>this
                        night, but could get nothing for our horses:<lb/> neither pasture, hay, corn
                        nor oats, nor even<lb/>an enclosure of any kind to secure them, so<lb/>we
                        tied them to stumps and fed them with some<lb/>oats we had with us, and
                        tried to get some sleep<lb/>on our earthen bed, after having partaken of
                        some of<lb/>our victuals.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="doubl"/><date when="1798-05-13">13th.</date></dateline>
                <q><p> We were stirring betimes this morn-<lb/>ing, as our bed was not inviting to
                        indulge nature,<lb/>and in 7 1/2 miles came to a poor cabin.</p>
                    <p>Here we got some oats for our horses<lb/>and let them pick a little in the
                        woods.</p>
                    <p>We found a great change [here also from<lb/>what it was when] we left
                            <placeName key="redst1">Redstone</placeName>, the season<lb/>is backward
                        the leaves just putting out and there<lb/>is next to no pasture in the
                        woods, that it looks<lb/> likely our horses will suffer much when we
                        get<lb/>among the Indians. We breakfasted on our own<lb/>provisions, and
                        proceeded 12 miles further, where<lb/>after feeding our horses, we took
                        dinner in like<lb/>manner, and got to <placeName key="ffran">Fort
                            Franklin</placeName> before 4oclock.<lb/>14 1/2 miles, 34 since morning,
                        feeling pretty much<lb/>fatigued. From <placeName key="pitts"
                            >Pittsburgh</placeName> to this place trav-<lb/>elling is difficult,
                        part of the roads extremely<lb/>bad, and accommodations next to
                            intolerable<lb/><pb n="17" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_017"/>and we
                        sensibly felt the effect of our<lb/>poor nights lodging. We met with few
                        houses<lb/>in this days ride.</p>
                    <p>The country was pretty level except about<lb/><geogName key="sandy">Sandy
                            Creek</geogName>. The town of <placeName key="frank"
                            >Franklin</placeName> [now <placeName key="venan">Ve-<lb/>nago
                            county</placeName>] is situated close on the side of <geogName
                            key="french">French<lb/>Creek</geogName>; it contains ten or twelve log
                        houses: they<lb/>were built under cover of an old fort, which is
                        now<lb/>demolished, and a new one erected half a mile<lb/>lower down the
                        creek just above its junction<lb/>with the <geogName key="alleg">Alleghany
                            River</geogName>.</p>
                    <p>Two of us waited on <persName key="cfowl1">Captain Fowler</persName>,
                        and<lb/>presented <persName key="gwilk2">General Wilkinson</persName>'s
                        letter: upon read-<lb/>ing which he manifested great respect, and a<lb/>full
                        disposition to comply with its contents.</p>
                    <p>He kindly invited us to take breakfast with him<lb/>in the morning.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="ffran"/><date when="1798-05-14">14th</date></dateline>
                <q><p> We breakfasted with the <persName key="cfowl1">Captain</persName>,
                        and<lb/>got of him, upon credit of <persName key="gwilk2">General
                            Wilkinson</persName>'s<lb/>letter, four bushels of corn to feed our
                        horses through<lb/>the wilderness; half a hundred of flour, and two<lb/>
                        quarts of salt to take to the Indian village.</p>
                    <p><persName key="jjohn1">Joseph Johnson</persName>, a surveyor to the <orgName
                            key="hollco">Holland<lb/>Company</orgName>, who was going to the mouth
                        of the<lb/><geogName key="concr">Conewango Creek</geogName>, within 16 miles
                        of <placeName key="cornp">Cornplanter's<lb/>residence</placeName> agreed to
                        pilot us thither, and to procure<lb/>us another from that place.</p>
                    <p>After dining at the tavern where we put up<lb/><pb n="18"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_018"/>last evening, we took our departure,
                        being willing<lb/>to leave this dear place, having paid three shillings
                        a<lb/> meal, four shillings for each horse at very coarse hay,<lb/>fifteen
                        shillings a bushel for corn, and yesterday fifteen<lb/>shillings a bushel
                        for oats.</p>
                    <p>We crossed <geogName key="french">French Creek</geogName>, and for about
                        twelve<lb/>miles had a stony road, and through a poor country,<lb/>when we
                        came to a rich bottom on a small stream,<lb/>where we found plenty of
                        pasture, being the first<lb/> we had seen in the woods since we left
                        home,</p>
                    <p>About six miles we came to a house near <geogName key="oilcr"
                            >Oil<lb/>Creek</geogName>, the second we have seen since leaving
                            <placeName key="frank">Frank-<lb/>lin</placeName>. This is the most
                        desirable spot we have seen<lb/>for many miles back - a fine fertile bottom
                        on<lb/>the creek with suitable plough land, a large stream<lb/>not far
                        distant, and a noble spring just by the<lb/>door, large enough to turn a
                        mill.</p>
                    <p>Here we put up for the night, and with some concern turned<lb/>our horses
                        loose to pasture in the woods without<lb/>any enclosure, for the first time
                        since leaving<lb/> home. We lodged pretty comfortably on our blan-<lb/>kets.
                            <geogName key="oilcr">Oil Creek</geogName> is so termed from an
                        oily<lb/>fluid, collected from its surface, arrising either<lb/>from springs
                        near its margin, or from diferent<lb/>parts of the creek, It is called
                        Seneca oil, [because]<lb/>it resembles the Seneca or British oil in
                        smell.</p></q>
                <p><q>We were informed that one man gathered<lb/>three barrels last year which sold
                        at <placeName key="pitts">Pittsburgh</placeName><lb/><pb n="19"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_019"/>for four dollars per gallon.</q> A year
                    or two later<lb/>when <persName key="icoat1">Isaac Coates</persName> again
                    passed through this<lb/>section of the country, he speaks of there being a
                    great<lb/>improvement at this place. A young man by the<lb/>name of <persName
                        key="jtitu1">Titus</persName>, had purchased 400 acres of land,<lb/> the
                    most of it rich bottom, He had then about 36<lb/>acres of excellent corn in the
                    ground, and a consider-<lb/>able quantity of wheat in stock, A large spring
                    of<lb/> excellent water near the door, large enough to turn a<lb/>breast mill,
                    That upon the whole I think his<lb/>farm likely in time to be of most
                    inestimable value.</p>
                <p>He says the oil which was collected from the<lb/>surface of the waters, was
                    principally valued for<lb/>medicinal purposes, and had long been used
                    in<lb/>that way by the Indians. He then had no idea<lb/>of the wonderful changes
                    which would be effected<lb/>in it by the sinking of oil wells, and the
                    consequent<lb/>enormous developement of the production and<lb/>trade in
                    petroleum. Now let us return to "Our<lb/> Travellers" who left this desirable
                    place the next<lb/>morning which was white with frost tho' it was<lb/>the <date
                        when="1798-05-15">15th of 5th month</date>. Set off for <geogName
                        key="broke">Broken Straw</geogName>, a large<lb/>stream of water. <q>After
                        riding two miles we<lb/>entered a white pine forest, where the <orgName
                            key="hollco">Holland<lb/>Company</orgName> has a saw mill, and is
                        erecting a<lb/>grist mill, tho' there are but few houses within<lb/> twenty
                        miles.* <note rend="asterisk">* but people came there 20, 25, or more miles
                            with bags of grain on a horse, to be ground, there<lb/>being no road
                            that any carriage can pass; Indeed to those who have not seen these
                            mountainous new<lb/> countries it would appear impracticable to pass
                            with a single horse.</note> This is the first pine woods
                        worth<lb/>noticing since we crossed the mountains, To this<lb/><pb n="20"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_020"/>place there is a cut road from
                            <placeName key="pitts">Pittsburg</placeName>, but we<lb/>now enter the
                        wilderness where a number of<lb/>marked trees were to be our guides.</q></p>
                <q>
                    <p>Our journey this day was truly<lb/>wild and romantic, and a tedious day's
                        ride;<lb/> sometimes we had a blind path and some-<lb/>times none; indeed
                        our way for badness almost<lb/>surpasses description. To delineate the
                        bushes,<lb/>logs, trees, stones, roots, and bogs through and<lb/>over which
                        we passed would require great in-<lb/>genuity. The woods were very thick,
                        with much<lb/>underbrush and a succession of logs to cross<lb/>some of which
                        we jumped our horses over, and<lb/>others with difficulty we got round; in
                        other<lb/>places we were in frequent danger of getting our<lb/>horses legs
                        fast or broken in the cavities between<lb/>the rocks; and sometimes had to
                        descend<lb/>banks almost perpendicular into swamps, in<lb/> which we found
                        the roots of the firs and hemlocks<lb/>very troublesome travelling over.
                        This stage called<lb/>twenty four miles, appeared to us very long
                        taking<lb/>(12) twelve hours to get through, and for twenty miles<lb/>of the
                        way there was not one house.</p>
                    <p>The rocks, stones, old logs and the whole<lb/> surface of the ground under
                        the forest of<lb/>pine trees, were covered with moss, resem-<lb/>bling for
                        thickness a fleece of wool.</p>
                    <p>Some of the large rocks more than<lb/><pb n="21"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_021"/>12 feet high, having received seed from
                        the<lb/>neighboring trees, which sprouted and took<lb/>root, have large
                        trees of two or three feet<lb/>over growing on them, Three or four such<lb/>
                        trees we have seen growing on one rock, with<lb/>their roots spread down its
                        sides ten or more<lb/>feet, untill they enter the ground and have<lb/>grown
                        firm therein, so that the sides of the<lb/>rocks were bound with them, like
                        so many<lb/> large ropes or cables. I think we saw no improvement for
                        20<lb/>miles. We arrived at <geogName key="broke">Broken Straw
                            Creek</geogName> in the<lb/>evening, where we found plenty of pasture
                        for our<lb/>horses, and a cabin the owner of which kindly let us<lb/>have
                        quarters, After partaking of our own provi-<lb/>sion, we lay on the floor to
                        take rest, but the night<lb/>being cold and the cabin open, we often had to
                        use<lb/>and renew our fire.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><geogName key="broke"/><date when="1798-05-16">16th</date></dateline>
                <q><p> Rode seven miles down the east side<lb/>of <geogName key="broke">Broken
                            Straw</geogName> to the <geogName key="alleg">Alleghany
                        river</geogName>. The bottoms<lb/>on the creek were rich and beautifully
                        coated with a<lb/>luxurient vegetation.</p>
                    <p>We passed several sugar camps, where the Indi<lb/>ans come in the season to
                        make the maple sugar<lb/>though more than twenty miles from their
                        village.</p>
                    <p>But having plenty of good canoes they convey with<lb/>facility their kettles
                        and implements for making<lb/>sugar, down the river and up this creek to
                        the<lb/>camps. About noon we arrived at <placeName key="conew"
                            >Conewango</placeName>,<lb/><pb n="22" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_022"
                        />eighteen miles from <placeName key="cornp">Cornplanter's</placeName>: and
                        the road being<lb/>very rough, we agreed to remain here till
                        morning,<lb/>there being a good house to accommodate us,<lb/> though we had
                        to find our own provisions and<lb/>sleep again on the floor.</p>
                    <p>Near the mouth of the creek on a beau-<lb/>tiful dry place the State of
                            <placeName key="penns">Pennsylvania</placeName> has laid<lb/>out
                            <placeName key="warri">Warrentown</placeName>. [now county seat of
                            <placeName key="warrc">Warren County</placeName>.]</p>
                    <p>The <orgName key="hollco">Holland Company</orgName> have built a good
                        house<lb/>in this town where they keep a store to supply their<lb/>surveyors
                        and settlers on the land with provisions, &amp;c.<lb/>[but their's is the
                        only house in the town]</p>
                    <p><persName key="jjohn1">Joseph Johnson</persName> our pilot had the charge of
                        this<lb/> store. Here we met with twenty or more Indians,<lb/>many of whom
                        were drunk, having obtained liquor<lb/>of some settlers who were at this
                        house intending<lb/>in a few days to go up the creek.</p>
                    <p><persName key="jjohn1">Joseph Johnson</persName> immediately put a
                        stop<lb/>to the selling of liquor, and informed us that<lb/>he and his men
                        had abstained from the use<lb/>of distilled spirits in their surveying
                        business,<lb/>last summer, as was the practice of other sur-<lb/>veyors in
                        the Company's employ, and found<lb/>they were better without it.</p>
                    <p>He agreed with a young Indian who was<lb/>sober and we were informed would
                        not get<lb/>drunk to pilot us tomorrow to <placeName key="cornp"
                            >Cornplanter's<lb/>village</placeName>. He was a good countenanced lad,
                            and<lb/><pb n="23" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_023"/>appeared pleased
                        with the charge assigned him,</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="conew"/><date when="1798-05-17">17th.</date></dateline>
                <q><p> Set out with our Indian<lb/>guide, who could not speak or
                        understand<lb/>English that we know, and after riding about<lb/>four miles
                        in which we crossed the <geogName key="concr">Conewango</geogName>,<lb/>we
                        had a rough mountainous country, the road<lb/>being better calculated for an
                        Indian path, than<lb/>riding on horse back, being much obstructed
                        by<lb/>wind-fallen Timber, and the young growth being*<lb/><note
                            rend="asterisk">* so thick that if we were two sods<lb/>apart we would
                            have to call out to<lb/>each other, in fear of being lost.</note></p>
                    <p>When we reached the river we stopped to<lb/>let out horses eat grass, there
                        being plenty of it<lb/>on some of the bottoms, which was a pleasing<lb/>
                        sight, and tended to remove some fears respecting<lb/>the fare of our
                        horses, when we got among the<lb/>Indians, While here a number of
                        Indians<lb/>came by in canoes, who stopped to see us,<lb/>shook hands with
                        us and looked pleasant.</p>
                    <p>One man came down from the mountain<lb/>with a large turkey on his back,
                        which he had<lb/>just shot, and we thought it would have weighed<lb/>more
                        than twenty pounds, It conveyed the<lb/>idea that small game was plenty,
                        among them<lb/>and maybe we would come in for a share,</p>
                    <p>One of the canoes had a quantity of fine<lb/>fish, but we found when among
                        them that a<lb/>turkey, or any other small came was very seldom<lb/>taken:
                        it was rare to see a squirrel in the wilder-<lb/>ness. We saw some pheasants
                        but no partridges.<lb/><pb n="24" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_024"/>After a
                        short conference on the weighty business,<lb/>we were embarked in, we
                        proceeded up the river, not<lb/>without some exercise of mind, and would
                        have been<lb/>glad, could we have sent a messenger forward to in-<lb/>form
                        the Chiefs of our coming, but this was out of<lb/>our power, for none of the
                        Indians we met with could<lb/>talk English: we therefore moved forward with
                        our minds<lb/>attentive to best directions.</p>
                    <p>When we came in sight of the town, many Indians<lb/>appeared in view looking
                        toward us. Our guide turned<lb/>into the first cabin he came to, and would
                        go no fur-<lb/>ther, but pointed to <persName key="cornp2"
                            >Cornplanter</persName>'s house. We paid him<lb/>one dollar, and moved
                        forward, and presently saw the<lb/>Chiefs coming toward us: and on our
                        riding up and<lb/>alighting, they appeared to welcome us with
                        open<lb/>countenances. We did not know <persName key="cornp2"
                            >Cornplanter</persName>,<lb/>nor could we distinguish him by his dress,
                        but<lb/>shaking hands with one who stood foremost, we<lb/>asked if he was
                            <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName>. He informed us<lb/>in his
                        way that he was. After shaking hands<lb/>with all, we were invited to his
                        house, which<lb/> differed from others only in being larger.</p>
                    <p>We took the saddles off our horses, carried in<lb/>our baggage, and being
                        seated, <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName>, his<lb/>son <persName
                            key="habee1">Henry</persName>, and several others came in and sat
                        down.</p>
                    <p>This son <persName key="habee1">Henry</persName> had an English education
                        in<lb/>and about <placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName>, and
                        interpreted for us.<lb/>His father can neither speak nor understand<lb/><pb
                            n="25" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_025"/>English. The Chief presently
                        asked if we would<lb/>like to see his people in general Council.</p>
                    <p>We let him know we would as soon as was<lb/>convenient. Ten o'clock tomorrow
                        was therefore fix<lb/>upon, and runners dispatched immediately to
                        give<lb/>notice.</p>
                    <p>It was about two o'clock when we arrived<lb/>and some time after the
                        conference <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName><lb/>came into our
                        apartment, and asked if we could<lb/>eat in the Indian way. We replied we
                        expected<lb/>we could; and presently he brought in some dinner<lb/>in a bark
                        bowl and a tin kettle. The bowl was<lb/>placed on a seat beside us, and the
                        kettle on the<lb/>ground before us, and we unvited to eat.</p>
                    <p>What was in the bowl or kettle we knew not, or<lb/>whether they were to be
                        eaten together or separate.</p>
                    <p>The bowl contained a number of round<lb/>lumps of something tied in corn
                        husks, with<lb/>a string at each end, and one in the middle.</p>
                    <p>At length after some interrogations among<lb/>our selves, we let them know
                        that our ignorance<lb/>was such, we did not know how to begin, which<lb/>set
                        some of the young Indians laughing.</p>
                    <p>The Chief took out his knife, for they had set<lb/> neither, knives, forks,
                        nor spoons, and taking up<lb/>a dumpling he cut it in two; then
                        stripping<lb/>up the husk, he cut off a piece, and dipping it<lb/>in the
                        kettle, which we found contained bear's oil<lb/><pb n="26"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_026"/>he ate it: we followed his example, and
                        made<lb/>a light meal, the bear's oil was old and not grate<lb/>ful to our
                        palate. We have since seen that this way<lb/>of eating is often practiced
                        among them; though cold<lb/>Indian bread is more frequently used.</p>
                    <p>The name of this village is <placeName key="cornp"
                            >Jenuch-<lb/>shedago</placeName>, It is situated on the <geogName
                            key="alleg">Alleghany</geogName><lb/>in <placeName key="penns"
                            >Pennsylvania</placeName> about four miles below<lb/>the <placeName
                            key="newyo">New York</placeName> line. The land is <persName
                            key="cornp2">Cornplan-<lb/>ter</persName>'s private property: he has 660
                        acres in this<lb/> tract and two contiguous islands, one 66 and
                        the<lb/>other 53 acres, besides a tract of 303 acres below<lb/><placeName
                            key="frank">Franklin</placeName>. His land at <placeName key="hicko"
                            >Hickorytown</placeName> between<lb/>here and <placeName key="frank"
                            >Franklin</placeName> he has sold to <persName key="gwilk1">Dr.
                            Wilkins</persName>,<lb/>Most of the Indians under his particular
                        super-<lb/>intendence have left their old settlement about<lb/>9 miles up
                        the river in <placeName key="newyo">New York State</placeName>, and<lb/>are
                        settled with their Chief in this place.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="cornp"/><date when="1798-05-18">18th</date></dateline>
                <q><p> Last evening after we had lain down,<lb/>the Chief and his son came into our
                        apartment,<lb/>and informed us he would like to know<lb/>what we intended to
                        say to his people before the<lb/>council met. We told him we would
                        inform<lb/>him in the morning, which we now complied<lb/>with, letting him
                        know we could not tell them all<lb/>we might say as we believed on such
                        occasions it was<lb/>right to wait on the Great Spirit to be
                        directed:<lb/>but that we would read to him the certificate<lb/><pb n="27"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_027"/>sent by our <orgName key="pymindian"
                            >Committee</orgName>, which particularly<lb/>pointed out our business,
                        also <persName key="gwilk2">General Wilkinson</persName>'s<lb/>letter - with
                        which he appeared satisfied,</p>
                    <p>His son <persName key="habee1">Henry</persName> interpreted for us on all
                        occasions:<lb/> but he was not very ready, and we believed our
                        business<lb/>suffered on that account.</p>
                    <p>About 12 o'clock between 30 and 40 of their<lb/>principal men met in council,
                        which <persName key="cornp2">Cornp<lb/>lanter</persName> opened by a short
                        speech expressing<lb/>the satisfaction he felt on seeing us
                        coming<lb/>riding through the bushes, and that it was<lb/>the Good Spirit
                        which preserved us on our long<lb/> journey, for which they were glad.</p>
                    <p>He then informed us of their poverty, and the poor-<lb/>ness of their houses,
                        being covered with bark, and<lb/>their inability to build good ones. We
                        thought the<lb/>later part of the speech was calculated to draw on<lb/>our
                        charity.</p>
                    <p>He then staited that all were met who<lb/>were likely to attend - that the
                        women could not<lb/>come, but the men would inform them what we said
                        -,<lb/>we having particularly requested the women might<lb/>attend.</p>
                    <p>We now as at some other times, felt<lb/>our minds humblingly impressed with
                        the<lb/>weight of the business we were engaged in;<lb/>and after a short but
                        serious pause on our<lb/>part, we mentioned the love which their old<lb/><pb
                            n="28" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_028"/>friends the Quakers have for
                        them, and<lb/>that we had been made willing to leave our<lb/>beloved
                        families and comfortable dwellings,<lb/>and expose our selves to the
                        hardships and dif-<lb/>ficulties of a tedious journey, with no other
                        views<lb/>than for their improvement.</p>
                    <p>We first read, by paragraphs, the epistle<lb/>from the <orgName
                            key="pymindian">Committee</orgName>, and then <persName key="gwilk2"
                            >General Wilkinson</persName>'s<lb/>letter, which were interpreted with
                        some difficulty.</p>
                    <p>We desired them when they took our<lb/>proposals into consideration, they
                        would guard<lb/>against discouragements that might present in<lb/>looking
                        forward towards a change in their man-<lb/>ner of being. We did not doubt
                        there might be<lb/> difficulties in the way, and their progress might<lb/>be
                        slow, yet there are accounts of white people be-<lb/>yond the great waters,
                        in another island, who many<lb/> years ago, lived much like they do now, but
                        by in-<lb/>dustry and care have become good farmers, and me-<lb/>chanics of
                        all kinds: and from whom those fine leg-<lb/>gings, and other clothing they
                        had on, were procured.</p>
                    <p>We then let them know that we had a boat<lb/>coming up the <geogName
                            key="alleg">Alleghany river</geogName>, with various<lb/>kinds of goods
                        - plough-irons, hoes, axes, spades<lb/>and shovels; with carpenters' masons,
                        and<lb/>coopers tools, which we intended never to take<lb/>away. While our
                        young men stay, they should<lb/>be placed under their care to lend out to
                            them<lb/><pb n="29" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_029"/>as they wanted, and
                        when done with, were<lb/>to be returned. They were exorted to
                        stillness<lb/>and quietude and an attention to the Good Spirit<lb/>in their
                        own hearts.</p>
                    <p>Upon letting them know we had nothing<lb/>more to say amongst them at this
                        time, they in-<lb/>formed us they would take our proposals
                        into<lb/>consideration, and give us an answer tomorrow.</p>
                    <p>We may close our observations on this council<lb/>by an humble
                        acknowledgement that notwith-<lb/>standing we find some things tryingly
                        gloomy,<lb/>and discouraging, yet we have had at this<lb/>time, renewed
                        cause to believe, that the concern<lb/>in which we are engaged, is owned by
                        Him<lb/>whose regard is toward all the workmanship<lb/>of his hands.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="cornp"/><date when="1798-05-19">19th. 7
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q>
                    <p> Part of this day some of our company<lb/>were employed in baking bread, and
                        other domestic<lb/>preparations, as we are now wholly on our own cooks<lb/>
                        &amp;c. living on the provisions which we brought on<lb/>our horses from
                            <placeName key="pitts">Pittsburgh</placeName> and <placeName key="frank"
                            >Franklin</placeName>, and<lb/>which we have sometimes looked upon, with
                        some<lb/> serious thoughtfulness, as appearing a scanty al-<lb/>lowance for
                        the time set for the arrival of our<lb/>boat, and the more especially as
                            <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName><lb/>early informed us that
                        they were scarce of corn,<lb/>occasioned by an uncommon freshet <emph
                            rend="underline">sometime</emph><lb/>after the corn was planted, and by
                        an early frost<lb/><pb n="30" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_030"/>in the fall;
                        but our anxiety on this account is<lb/>now much removed, by <persName
                            key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> informing us<lb/>that he had several
                        barrels of flour which he brought<lb/>from <placeName key="pitts"
                            >Pittsburgh</placeName>, and that when we were out of<lb/>flour he would
                        supply us. We agreed with his<lb/>sister for 2 qts of milk per day at 8 cts
                        per qt. we<lb/>would like to have had 3 qts but 2 was all she<lb/>could
                        spare.</p>
                    <p>The Indians being most of this<lb/>day steadily in private council
                        concerning<lb/>the business we had laid before them, several<lb/>times sent
                        their deputies to us for explana-<lb/>tions. One question was, how they
                        should draw<lb/>their ploughs seeing they had no oxen, and were<lb/>so poor
                        they had no money to buy them with.</p>
                    <p>We replied we had seen two horses running<lb/>about their town, and they were
                        sufficient to<lb/>draw one plough, and if they would save some<lb/>of the
                        money which they received, each year,<lb/>from the white people, they could
                        buy a pair<lb/>of oxen, and <emph rend="underline">they</emph> could drawn
                        another; and our young<lb/>men would assist them with their horses
                        some-<lb/>times, and these would do to make a beginning.</p>
                    <p>We told them we did not expect great things<lb/>to be done all at once, but
                        we wanted them to<lb/>make a start, and come on by degrees as they were
                        able.</p>
                    <p>With this answer they appeared pretty<lb/>well satisfied, though we thought
                        it was not such<lb/><pb n="31" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_031"/>an one, as
                        the question was artfully designed<lb/>to draw from us.</p>
                    <p>At another time they told us, we must<lb/>wait with patience for an answer,
                        for it<lb/>was a great thing and they were all consul-<lb/>ting about it in
                        their houses.</p>
                    <p>About 5 o'clock they informed us they<lb/>were nearly ready, and wished to
                        know if it<lb/>would suit us this evening.</p>
                    <p>We answered that we were waiting<lb/>their time, but as the day was far
                        spent,<lb/>left it with them to judge whether this<lb/>evening would be
                        suitable. About 6 o'clock thirty<lb/>of them met us in public council.</p>
                    <p>The opportunity seemed to be owned, a degree<lb/>of solemnity attending.
                        After a short pause<lb/><persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> and
                        his son <persName key="habee1">Henry</persName> stood up and<lb/>opened the
                        council. The following is the<lb/>substance of his speech.</p>
                    <floatingText type="speech">
                        <body>
                            <opener><salute><emph rend="underline">Brothers the
                                    Quakers.</emph></salute></opener>
                            <p>Listen now to<lb/>what I am going to say to you, You
                                know<lb/>brothers the red people are poor, they are not<lb/>like
                                white people. The Great Spirit has<lb/> made them of another
                                language, so that<lb/>it is very hard for us to understand
                                one<lb/>another plainly, as there is no person here<lb/>that can
                                interpret very well.</p>
                            <pb n="32" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_032"/>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>,<lb/>We take great pains to
                                settle the<lb/>proposals you made to us, but we differ<lb/>in
                                opinion, and we must take great pains<lb/>to have everything
                                complete.</p>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>,<lb/>We suppose the reason you
                                came<lb/>here was to help poor Indians some way or<lb/>other; and
                                you wish the chiefs to tell their<lb/>warriors not to go on so bad
                                as they have<lb/> done: and you wish us to take up work<lb/>like the
                                white people. Now, brothers some of<lb/>our sober men will take up
                                work, and do as<lb/>you say, and if they do well then will
                                your<lb/>young men stay longer: but some others will<lb/>not mind
                                what you say.</p>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>,<lb/>We can't say a word
                                against you.<lb/> It is the best way to call Quakers,
                                brothers,<lb/>You never wished our lands, - you never<lb/>wished any
                                part of our lands, therefore we<lb/> are determined to try to learn
                                your ways:<lb/>and those young men may stay here two<lb/>years to
                                try; by that time we shall know<lb/>whether <persName key="rmorr1"
                                    >Robert Morris</persName> will leave us any<lb/>land, and
                                whether he will pay us our<lb/>money; for last summer we sold our
                                land<lb/>and we don't know yet whether we shall<lb/><pb n="33"
                                    facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_033"/>get what we reserved: but by
                                that time we<lb/> shall know, and then if they like it,<lb/>and we
                                like it, your young men may stay<lb/>longer.</p>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>,<lb/>If your young men
                                stay<lb/>here we want them to learn our children<lb/>to read and
                                write.</p>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>,<lb/>Two of you are<lb/>going
                                home again: if they hear anything<lb/>about out land or money they
                                must<lb/> write to these young men here: and they<lb/>must tell us
                                if were are like to be cheated.</p>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>,<lb/>This is all I got to say
                                at present.</p>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                    <p>After they had closed this speech we in-<lb/>formed them, that we understood
                        what<lb/>they had said to us, and that we were<lb/>satisfied with it: and
                        proposed that<lb/>our young men must have some place<lb/>to live in, and a
                        piece of land to work,<lb/>in order to set them an example, and<lb/>to raise
                        bread for themselves to eat, but<lb/>that the land should still be theirs,
                        and all<lb/>the improvements which we should put on it,<lb/> would also be
                        theirs when we left it; and in order<lb/>to know where it would be best for
                        our young men<lb/><pb n="34" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_034"/>to settle and
                        make a beginning we must look a<lb/>little about the country, and go to
                        their upper town,<lb/>and we desired some of their Chiefs might go<lb/>along
                        with us, and help to agree on some suitable<lb/>place, where our friends
                        could be of most use to their<lb/>people in general, to which they readily
                        agreed.</p>
                    <p>He next informed that we had a num-<lb/>ber of farming and other utensils,
                        coming up in<lb/>a boat which were intended for their use, and<lb/>would be
                        left with with them and never be<lb/>taken away again, but that we thought
                        it best<lb/>and most for their good, to leave them par-<lb/>ticularly under
                        our friends care, and not to give<lb/>them away at present, but only to lead
                        them<lb/>that they might have the use of them: for they<lb/>knew that some
                        of their young men were not so<lb/>good as they ought to be; and if these
                        things<lb/>were divided amongst them, some might<lb/>pawn them away for
                        whisky, and then they<lb/>would be as bad off as they were before they got
                        them.</p>
                    <p>At this observation some of the old men<lb/>and Chiefs appeared to express
                        their approbation;<lb/>whilst some of their young men manifested<lb/>their
                        sensibility of its truthfulness, by a<lb/>shamefaced good humored laugh.</p>
                    <p>After which Cornplanter expressed,<lb/>a few words indicating his
                        satisfaction with<lb/>what had been said, and that we would now<lb/><pb
                            n="35" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_035"/>shake hands as brothers, and
                        directed his people<lb/>to rise and come to us, and shake hands by
                        course,<lb/>himself first setting the example.</p>
                    <p>Thus this Council ended after letting<lb/>them know that we should want one
                        more gen-<lb/>eral Council with them before we left them.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="cornp"/><date when="1798-05-20">20th First
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q><p> We had some conversation<lb/>this morning about sitting together in
                        religious<lb/>retirement, and thought it would be right to in-<lb/>form
                            <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName>, that if he or any of his
                        sober<lb/>people inclined to sit with us, it would be accep-<lb/>table,
                        though the prospect of such an undertaking<lb/>felt weighty. Before we were
                        fully concluded, the<lb/><persName key="cornp2">Chief</persName> with his
                        son <persName key="habee1">Henry</persName> came into our apart-<lb/>ment
                        and said, he hoped we would not think<lb/>hard of their not keeping the
                        First day as the<lb/>whites do, for they could not read or right - that
                        they<lb/>were poor, and had to work on that day, and that<lb/>they were
                        often out hunting and had to attend to<lb/>their game. We let him know that
                        we did<lb/>not think hard of him about this matter; and<lb/>then informed
                        him that we intended about<lb/>10 o'clock to sit down together in stillness
                        to wait<lb/>on the Great Spirit, and if he or any of his<lb/>sober people
                        would come and sit with us it<lb/>would be acceptable. Near the time
                        appoint-<lb/>ed, <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> with several
                        others came into<lb/><pb n="36" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_036"/>our
                        apartment. He sat very still with apparent<lb/>solidity until the
                        opportunity closed: the others<lb/>sat quiet a while and then withdrew. Our
                        door being<lb/>opened, the Indians as they passed looked at us,<lb/>but
                        showed no lightness.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="cornp"/><date when="1798-05-21">21st</date></dateline>
                <q><p> Rose early this morning to bake some<lb/>bread that we might be in readiness
                        by 7 o'clock to go up<lb/>the river about ten miles with some of the
                        Chiefs<lb/>to see where is would be most suitable to settle<lb/>and make a
                        beginning amongst them.</p>
                    <p>We found it trying, rightly to judge what<lb/>was best to do on the
                        occasion.</p>
                    <p><placeName key="cornp">Jenescatego</placeName>, the town where we now are
                        being<lb/>the place of <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName>'s
                        residence, is in the middle<lb/>of a good spot of land in <placeName
                            key="penns">Pennsylvania</placeName>, on the<lb/>west side of the
                            <geogName key="alleg">Alleghany river</geogName>, 4 or 5 miles<lb/>south
                        of the <placeName key="newyo">New York</placeName> line.</p>
                    <p>The tract is his private property, as be-<lb/>fore mentioned, and most of the
                        Indians under his<lb/>superintendency live on and near it, among
                        whom<lb/>are children enough suitable to make up a large school.<lb/> These
                        considerations, with the richness of the<lb/>land made it desirable to
                        settle here. But the<lb/>land was <persName key="cornp2"
                            >Cornplanters</persName>, and if we made im-<lb/>provements on the
                        Indians clearings they would<lb/>belong to <persName key="cornp2"
                            >Cornplanter</persName> and not to the <orgName key="seneca"
                            >Nation</orgName><lb/>when we left them," All this being
                        considered<lb/>we concluded it would be best to look else-<lb/><pb n="37"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_037"/>where. The <orgName key="seneca"
                            >Nation</orgName> owns forty-two square miles on<lb/>this river,
                        beginning at the <placeName key="penns">Pennsylvania</placeName> line.</p>
                    <p>The lines of the reservation had not yet been<lb/>run, but we found that the
                        Indians had a choice that<lb/>it should lie on the river, half a mile wide
                        on<lb/>each side. About nine miles from hence<lb/>up the river, latterly
                        stood a town, called<lb/><placeName key="genes1">Genesinguhta</placeName>,
                        the inhabitants of which a<lb/>few years since, mostly removed here. About
                        ten<lb/>miles further up the river we understood a<lb/>settlement had lately
                        been made. From the<lb/> best information we could get we thought
                        some-<lb/>where near the <placeName key="genes1">Old Town</placeName> would
                        be the most suit-<lb/>able place to fix on, it being [about] half
                        way<lb/>between the upper settlement and the lower<lb/>town.</p>
                    <p>With considerable exertion we got <persName key="cornp2"
                            >Cornplanter</persName><lb/>his son and three other Indians, to embark
                        with<lb/>us five in a canoe, about nine o'clock. They put<lb/>us up the
                        river with setting poles at the rate of three<lb/>miles an hour, In places
                        the river was shallow<lb/>and rapid, in others from two to six feet
                        deep,<lb/>in six miles we came to <persName key="cornp2"
                            >Cornplanter</persName>'s saw-mill,<lb/>and stopped, at his request, to
                        view it.</p>
                    <p>The stream on which it is built, is now so<lb/> low that the mill could do
                        very little work:<lb/>and when the river is high the back water<lb/>prevents
                        it from sawing. At the <placeName key="genes1">Old Town</placeName>,<lb/><pb
                            n="38" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_038"/>three miles further up there yet
                        remain three or<lb/>four families. About 150 acres of flat land
                        have<lb/>been mostly cleared and worked with corn, part<lb/>of which is
                        again grown up with hazel &amp;c, and<lb/>part with grass that in a few
                        weeks would do<lb/> to mow. Some of the richest spots are put in<lb/>with
                        corn this spring. It lies on the northwest<lb/>side of the river: the flat
                        is about forty perches<lb/>wide, and then commences timberland,
                        mostly<lb/>white pine, suitable for building or rail timber.<lb/> That
                        within sixty perches of the flat we thought<lb/>pretty good. It lies very
                        well to the sun, and is<lb/>clear of stones. Upon viewing it, and its local
                        sit-<lb/>uation, we were united in believing, that somewhere<lb/>near this
                        place would be the best to make our<lb/>settlement, and fixed on a spot near
                        the old vil-<lb/>lage, which is in <placeName key="newyo">New York
                            State</placeName> about 4 miles<lb/> above the <placeName key="penns"
                            >Pennsylvania</placeName> line.</p>
                    <p>After we had come to this conclusion amongst<lb/> ourselves, we informed
                            <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> and those with<lb/>him,
                        that we thought across the upper end of the<lb/>cleared flat from the river
                        back taking in a<lb/>part of the wood land would be suitable for<lb/>our
                        purpose, and desiring that is they liked it,<lb/>they would tell us so, and
                        if they did not like<lb/>the place we proposed, we hoped they would be
                        plain<lb/>with us, and let us know, and we would look further,<lb/>and
                        wished <emph rend="underline">them</emph> to propose a place they should
                            like<lb/><pb n="39" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_039"/>better, To which
                            <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> returned answer<lb/>in
                        substance as follows. <said who="cornp2">Brothers, I told you our<lb/>land
                            is before you, you may choose any place you<lb/>like best,</said> and
                        expressed their full approbation<lb/>of our choice. Then said <said
                            who="cornp2">this man,</said> (meaning one of<lb/>the Chiefs who was
                        with us) <said who="cornp2">lives in this town, and<lb/>he is most like
                            yourselves, a sober man and drinks<lb/> no whisky: he is very glad your
                            young men are<lb/>going to live so near him.</said> We next
                        proposed<lb/>that our young men should have liberty to cut<lb/> trees out of
                        their wood, to build a house, make rails,<lb/>and for firewood &amp;c to
                        which he replied O, yes!<lb/>I wish you would cut all the trees down, and
                        an<lb/>other thing you may have, brothers, if you see<lb/>a deer swimming
                        across the river, or running in<lb/>the woods you may shoot him, or if you
                        see any<lb/>fish in the river you may catch him.</p>
                    <p>About 5 o'clock we left the old village and returned<lb/>with <persName
                            key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> to our lodgings at his
                    house.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="cornp"/><date when="1798-05-22">22nd.</date></dateline>
                <q><p> This morning took up the consideration<lb/>of what further propositions,
                        might with pro-<lb/>priety be made to these people, in order for
                        their<lb/>additional encouragement in civilization and<lb/> agriculture, and
                        being favored to write with what<lb/>seemed expedient they were committed to
                        writing,<lb/>in readiness for our next council, in the min-<lb/>utes of
                        which they will appear.</p>
                    <pb n="40" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_040"/>
                    <p>We were this day as well as at some other times<lb/>pretty closely
                        interrogated about <persName key="rmorr1">Robert Morris</persName><lb/>of
                            <placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName>. <persName key="cornp2"
                            >Cornplanter</persName> and other Indians<lb/>here having heard that he
                        was in jail,<lb/>appeared to be somewhat alarmed lest they should loose<lb/>
                        their money, as well as land, which we under<lb/>stand they parted with,
                        with some reluctance.</p>
                    <p>They had likewise heard that the land was<lb/>not purchased for <persName
                            key="rmorr1">Morris</persName> as they expected, but for<lb/>some others
                        whom they called the <orgName key="hollco">Holland people</orgName>.</p>
                    <p>With these things they appeared much dis-<lb/>turbed, as apprehending they
                        are altogether deceived<lb/>and cheated, and even go so far as to declare
                        if<lb/>they cannot have justice done there, they will not<lb/> receive their
                        money.</p>
                    <p>We felt cautious of giving a sen-<lb/>timent, on this business, not being
                        fully ac-<lb/>quainted with it, and would have put it off<lb/>by referring
                        them to <persName key="ichap1">Captain Chapin</persName>, as much<lb/>better
                        acquainted with it than we were, and to<lb/>whom <persName key="cornp2"
                            >Cornplanter</persName> and his son expected shortly<lb/>to go, on this
                        or some other concern; but with<lb/>this reference <persName key="cornp2"
                            >Cornplanter</persName> did not appear fully<lb/>satisfied, remarking
                        that <persName key="ichap1">Captain C.</persName> had<lb/>told him that
                            <persName key="rmorr1">Morris</persName> was a very good and<lb/>honest
                        man, and yet he was got into jail,<lb/>now he could not understand how a
                        good<lb/>and honest man could get into jail, however<lb/><pb n="41"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_041"/>he said he intended to ask <persName
                            key="ichap1">Capt. Chapin</persName> where<lb/>his good and honest man
                            <persName key="rmorr1">Morris</persName> was now.</p>
                    <p>We were at length easy to observe to them<lb/>in general terms, that it was
                        not the advise<lb/>of their brothers the Quakers, to sell their
                        land,<lb/>for we would rather they would <del>rather they
                        would</del><lb/>keep it and learn to work it themselves, but<lb/>as it was
                        now sold, and we thought they<lb/>could not get it back again, we were
                        of<lb/>the mind they had better take their money<lb/>which we apprehended
                        was, or would be, made<lb/> secure for them, and endeavor to be as
                        con-<lb/>tented as they could about it.</p>
                    <p> This evening <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> presented
                        us<lb/>with a quantity of seed corn of diferent kinds<lb/>suitable to the
                        climate, some seed potatoes,<lb/>a large proportion of beans of divers
                        kinds, &amp; a<lb/>variety of useful garden seeds, such as
                        pumpkin,<lb/>cucumber, watermelon, &amp;c. These he informed<lb/>us were a
                        collection brought in by his people<lb/>and given to us as a blessing to
                        begin with,<lb/>we acknowledge their kindness and would have<lb/>taken only
                        a part, there being much more of<lb/>each kind, excepting potatoes, than we
                        should<lb/>stand in need of for seed, but they insisted we<lb/>should take
                        the whole, for they were sent in for<lb/>that purpose: which we then did;
                        thinking the<lb/>hearty good will with which they were presented,<lb/><pb
                            n="42" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_042"/>manifested a full approbation of
                        our under-<lb/>taking.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="cornp"/><date when="1798-05-23">23rd.</date></dateline>
                <q><p> The forepart of this day some of our<lb/>company were engaged in writing and
                        arrang-<lb/>ing our business, whilst others were employed<lb/>in preparing
                        for our removal up to <placeName key="genes1"
                        >Genesinguhta</placeName><lb/>having agreed, last evening, with <persName
                            key="habee1">Henry O'Neal</persName><lb/>to go with us and be our
                        interpreter.</p>
                    <p>We have had a pretty comfortable<lb/>house much to ourselves. <persName
                            key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> has<lb/>two houses about ten feet
                        apart though roofed<lb/>over between as the other parts of the
                        house<lb/>with bark. The space between serves for an en-<lb/>try, a place to
                        pound their corn, put their weed, &amp;c.</p>
                    <p>There is a door in each apartment opens into<lb/>this entry. The room
                        assigned us is thirty feet long<lb/>the other 24 ft, each sixteen feet wide.
                        They are built<lb/>of round poles, set in close together by notches<lb/>near
                        the end; not chunked or plastered be-<lb/>tween, so that we found our end
                        pretty open and cold<lb/>enough before morning. Upon our telling
                        the<lb/>Chief they had better make their houses tighter<lb/>by plastering up
                        the cracks, he replied, if they made<lb/>their houses too warm, they would
                        not like to leave them<lb/>when winter came to go a hunting.</p>
                    <p>along each side of the apartments from the door<lb/> to the other end, were
                        berths about four feet wide<lb/>and one foot high, covered with boards; on
                            these<lb/><pb n="43" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_043"/><del>these</del>
                        deer skins are spread - these are their beds,<lb/>and they make a pretty
                        good seat always ready.</p>
                    <p>Over these, about five feet high, are<lb/>placed shelves of the same width
                        which serves<lb/>to put their kitchen furniture, corn, &amp;c. upon.</p>
                    <p>The fire is built on the ground, in<lb/>the middle of the room, the part
                        between the<lb/>berths not being floored; and there is a large<lb/>opening
                        left in the top of the roof for the<lb/> smoke to escape.</p>
                    <p>As far as I have observed this description<lb/>answers, for the other houses,
                        though they are<lb/>not so large, being about twelve or fifteen
                        feet<lb/>square with a shed before the door: and there are<lb/>about thirty
                        in this village and a number above<lb/>and below the town. They are
                        beautifully sit<lb/>uated on the west side of the river, which is
                        about<lb/>150 yards wide, and glides before the town with a<lb/>gentle
                        current. Its bank is low, and gradually<lb/> ascends to the houses, which
                        are mostly with-<lb/>in six or seven perches, so that they can
                        readily<lb/>supply themselves with water, there being no<lb/>springs in the
                        flat where the town stands.</p>
                    <p>The land is a sandy loam, easily tilled, and<lb/>if properly managed would be
                        very productive.</p>
                    <p>Fifty or sixty acres adjoining the town nearly<lb/>cleared, is chiefly put in
                        yearly with corn, beans<lb/>and potatoes, and the work is done by the
                            women<lb/><pb n="44" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_044"/>with hoes. They
                        hoe the grass and weeds<lb/>clean from the old cornhills and plant in
                        the<lb/>same place, and some time after the corn comes<lb/>up they hoe all
                        the surface of the field over so that<lb/>it looks very neat, with the corn
                        they plant<lb/>beans, squashes, and potatoes, also pumpkins.</p>
                    <p> Since we came here the women have<lb/>worked very hard: they found all the
                        corn for hominy<lb/>and bread, sift and prepare it; cut and split
                        all<lb/>their wood and and carry it home on their backs, nearly<lb/>a
                        quarter of a mile; make all their fires, and do<lb/>all their kitchen work;
                        plant and take care of,<lb/>and gather their corn and beans: and as far
                        as<lb/>I can learn (says <persName key="jshar1">J.S.</persName>) do all
                        other out door work,<lb/>except building the houses and splitting
                        the<lb/>rails that the corn land is fenced with.</p>
                    <p>It has been a busy time since we came here,<lb/>the women have risen early,
                        gone out to the corn<lb/>field with their hoes, some of them old gray
                        headed<lb/>women, and some children (girls) of 8, 10, or 12 years of<lb/>age
                        and kept pretty close to their work.</p>
                    <p>One old woman who has had her feet so frozen<lb/>that she goes altogether on
                        her knees, I have<lb/>seen carrying in wood and making the fire,<lb/>bring
                        up water from the river, and go out to<lb/> the cornfield, and return in the
                        evening with<lb/>the laborers, while the men and boys are spend-<lb/>ing
                        their time in idleness, or shooting with their <lb/><pb n="45"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_045"/>bows and arrows at a mark, a very
                        common re-<lb/>creation with them, pitching quails, jumping,<lb/>playing at
                        some kind of games, and on music-<lb/>al instruments. I have not while in
                        this<lb/>village seen either man or boy at any kind<lb/>of work. It was
                        unnatural, and to me griev-<lb/>ous, to see little girls and old women
                        working<lb/> hard, while boys of 12, 14, or 16 years of age<lb/>just by
                        them, <emph rend="underline">all</emph>
                        <emph rend="underline">day</emph>, were doing nothing<lb/>but playing.</p>
                    <p>At seasons the men hunt and fish, and<lb/>they work the canoe, at which they
                        are very<lb/>expert; but at this season there is very little<lb/>game
                        brought in; they also catch a few fish;<lb/>little however was done at this
                        while we were there.</p>
                    <p>They live poor; their chief subsistence<lb/>at this season was corn, beans,
                        and bear's oil,<lb/>prepared in diferent ways.</p>
                    <p>From my observations they eat much<lb/>less than we do - a small piece of
                        bread, or<lb/> dumpling dipped in oil, seems to satisfy<lb/>nature: and
                        their stated meals I thought<lb/> were not more than two a day.</p>
                    <p>The visits of their friends are not interrupted<lb/>by cooking, or much
                        ceremony in laying<lb/>the table, If the hominy is boiled, which<lb/>was
                        generally the case after eleven o clock, and<lb/>it was not material whether
                        cold or warm, when<lb/><pb n="46" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_046"/>their
                        acquaintances came in, the berths al-<lb/>ways made a ready seat, on which
                        they were<lb/>soon engaged in smoking and talking;<lb/>and while thus
                        employed, a kettle of hominy<lb/>with a large wooden spoon is brought
                        in,<lb/>and set on the ground before them.</p>
                    <p>He that is near it lays by his pipe<lb/>and in a few minutes appears to be
                        sat-<lb/>isfied with his repast, and moves it over<lb/>to the next, the rest
                        of the company being<lb/>engaged as if no victuals were near them.</p>
                    <p>Thus the kettle passes round in a<lb/>little time, and when done with,
                        is<lb/>hung up untill somebody else comes in.</p>
                    <p>If they have no hominy the bread and<lb/>dumpling goes round in like
                        manner.</p>
                    <p>Their clothing is generally<lb/>something tawdry, - callico shirt, and
                        hand<lb/> kerchief of gay colors, blue coat and scarlet leg-<lb/>gings and a
                        belt of various colors, ornamented<lb/>with beads, girt round the middle and
                        knees,<lb/> with the ends hanging down, They are<lb/>also fond of trinkets
                        suspended from their<lb/> ears and nose, the men particularly,
                        some-<lb/>times weighing an ounce, and hanging over<lb/> the mouth. The
                        womens ears are cut round<lb/>and loaded with diferent toys, until they<lb/>
                        are drawn down several inches. One man had<lb/><pb n="47"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_047"/>two small brass padlocks in one ear,
                        another a<lb/>toy watch, Large, silver crosses are also worn<lb/>by them in
                        the same manner. They are far<lb/>from being clean in their persons; Some of
                        their shirts<lb/>do not appear to have ever been washed, and<lb/> about the
                        shoulders they become black and<lb/>greesy; Their hair I observe to be their
                        cloth<lb/>to wipe their fingers in while eating their bread<lb/>and oil. I
                        thought the women were particularly<lb/>dirty perhaps from working harder
                        than the<lb/>men, and being more among the grease.</p>
                    <p>For more than two weeks past, the weather<lb/>has been very dry, part of the
                        time a cold<lb/>north wind, during which time we slept<lb/>in open cabins in
                        our blankets, so that<lb/>we felt the want of more covering and a
                        better<lb/>bed, there being frost-two mornings.</p>
                    <p>But for two or three days past the weather<lb/>has been warm, with a strong
                        south wind.</p>
                    <p>During this dry weather the woods have been<lb/>much on fire, clouds of smoke
                        frequently cover-<lb/>ing us so that the sun was obscured.</p>
                    <p>In the night one of the hills our rather moun-<lb/>tains, where a great
                        quantity of dead timber had<lb/>taken fire, presented a very luminous and
                        stri-<lb/>king appearance, as if the whole mountain was<lb/>on fire.</p>
                    <p>We have been under some exercise on<lb/><pb n="48"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_048"/>account of our goods, the river having
                        fallen very fast<lb/>in consequence of the dry weather; but in the
                        midst<lb/>of our trials we have still been favored, a con-<lb/>siderable of
                        rain fell last evening though no<lb/>diference appears yet in the river.</p>
                    <p>As above stated, we agreed with <persName key="habee1"
                            >Henry<lb/>O'Neal</persName> last evening to go with us to <placeName
                            key="genes1">Genesinguhta</placeName> to be<lb/>our interpreter. It is
                        now 11 o'clock, yet neither<lb/>he nor his fathers family have gotten their
                        break-<lb/>fast, though we have been hurrying him for two<lb/>hours
                        past.</p>
                    <p>About 12 o'clock two of us set off on horse<lb/>back, the other three having
                        started an hour<lb/>sooner with our baggage accompanied by<lb/><persName
                            key="habee1">Henry O'Neal</persName>. We rode across the river
                        one<lb/>mile above the town, and went up the east<lb/>side of it to the
                        shore opposite the place of<lb/>destination where we again crossed,
                        though<lb/>the stream was wide and deep.</p>
                    <p>We stopped at the house of a chief who went<lb/>with us to our intended
                        settlement, getting there<lb/>about 3 in the afternoon, where we met
                        with<lb/>our friends who came up in a canoe.</p>
                    <p>We viewed an empty house that stood near<lb/>our settlements, but not liking
                        it, we proceeded<lb/>to look further. There was one occupied by a
                        fam-<lb/>ily, who we understood proposed leaving it, and<lb/>would sell
                        their right. The woman who owned<lb/><pb n="49"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_049"/>it was willing to part with the house,
                        but hav-<lb/>ing put in a few spots of corn and vines, the whole<lb/> not
                        more than three or four perch square, she<lb/>appeared unwilling to give
                            <emph rend="underline">them</emph> up, and they<lb/>were so in our way,
                        the we thought we had<lb/>better look elsewhere for our settlement. On
                        the<lb/>Chiefs confering with her, she was willing to<lb/>part with all but
                        one of her garden patches,<lb/>and <emph rend="underline">it</emph> was not
                        much in our way, so we agreed<lb/>for the house, and its belongings
                        excepting<lb/>the one lot of corn aforesaid, which was reserved <lb/>to her
                        the present year, and understanding<lb/>that she was a sober woman, and
                        would be likely<lb/>to make good use of her money, we paid it all<lb/>at
                        once which was $20, and she relinquished<lb/>all claim thereto. With our
                        assistance and<lb/>the help of some Indian children, she moved<lb/>right
                        out, and we took up possession, cleaned out<lb/>the house, got our provision
                        and other baggage<lb/>in, and before dark our scanty furniture
                        was<lb/>arranged, and we took up our lodging here for<lb/>the night. The
                        Indian Chief sent us three<lb/>deerskins with the hair on for our beds, but
                        the<lb/>night being cold we sensibly felt the want of<lb/>better, and of
                        more bedding, before morning, and<lb/>were under the necessity of using
                        several times<lb/>to renew our fire. Our house is about 24 feet<lb/>long by
                        19 wide, and 6 high to the square,<lb/>covered with bark, with a shed over
                        the door,<lb/><pb n="50" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_050"/>and furnished
                        within, as is usual in Indian<lb/>buildings. It stands on an elevated spot,
                        with<lb/>in five perches of the river on its northeast<lb/>side.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="genes1"/><date when="1798-05-24">5 day
                    24th.</date></dateline>
                <q><p> This morning our young men set to<lb/>work, on their lot having borrowed some
                        tools of <persName key="cornp2">Cornplan-<lb/>ter</persName>, they got a
                        piece of ground, cleared of rubbish,<lb/>and dug up for a garden, and our
                        potatoes<lb/>planted that the Indians gave us, also prepared<lb/>some ground
                        for the reception of other seeds, when<lb/>they were stopped by rain which
                        continued<lb/> at intervals for most of this day.</p>
                    <p>About 11 o'clock we felt our minds engaged<lb/>to draw into our new
                        habitation, and sit down<lb/>together for religious retirement: in
                        which<lb/>we were favored with the renewed extendings<lb/>of divine regard
                        to the contriting of our spirits<lb/>and strengthening of our minds, in the
                        work<lb/>in which we are embarked, and we trust it was<lb/>a time to be
                        encouragingly remembered by<lb/>our friends when we are separated
                        from<lb/>them.</p>
                    <p>We now sensibly feel the want of our<lb/>goods, which we cannot look for in
                        less<lb/> than a week from this time, the season for<lb/>planting corn being
                        fully come, we are in some<lb/>doubts of getting much of that valuable
                        article in,<lb/>so as to answer a good purpose the present year:<lb/><pb
                            n="51" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_051"/>Our young men propose having a
                        piece of<lb/>ground cleared, and in readiness for the plough<lb/>against the
                        arrival of our boat, that no time<lb/> may be lost with respect to getting
                        in as much<lb/>of this grain as our circumstances will ad-<lb/>mit. This
                        evening our young men endeav-<lb/>ored to catch eels, but their canoe upset,
                        and<lb/>they caught a ducking.</p></q>
                <p>Their household utensils were 5 tins, three<lb/>spoons, a camp kettle, and a
                    small frying<lb/>pan, borrowed from the Indians. They wanted<lb/>dishcloths,
                    towels, soap, and something to<lb/>knead brid in. They say, <q>When we fry
                        our<lb/>meat or our fritters, we have neither dish nor<lb/>plate to put them
                        on, so we use bark dishes.</q></p>
                <q><p>Our bacon was nearly gone and our cheese<lb/>quite. A little flour left that
                        we brought<lb/>from <placeName key="frank">Franklin</placeName> with
                        chocolate and sugar are<lb/>our chief dependence as food. We have
                        received<lb/> some sugar of the Indians as a present, and<lb/>some we
                        purchased of the Indians at 1s. 6d. per lb.<lb/>(18 3/4 cts) which we find a
                        pretty good substitute<lb/>for butter and cheese, by taking a bite of
                        sugar<lb/>(it was in hard cakes) with our bread, there was<lb/>no cow in
                        this settlement. The rain to day<lb/>convinced us that our house was not
                        proof<lb/>against storms.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="genes1"/><date when="1798-05-25">25th 6th
                    day</date></dateline>
                <q><p> Still rainy, so that very little<lb/><pb n="52"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_052"/>was done at our clearing. One of our
                        young<lb/>men was employed in baking bread and<lb/>some others of our
                        company in writing,<lb/>plastering up the holes in our house, and<lb/> so
                        forth. We have had very little rain since we<lb/>left home till yesterday
                        and the river is so low,<lb/>that some of the Indians, who know this
                        nav-<lb/>igation well, began to doubt whether our<lb/>boat could come up,
                        but the present rain<lb/> appears likely to afford a seasonable and
                        plen-<lb/>tiful supply, the river is already rising.</p>
                    <p>We notice a great appearance of strawberries.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="genes1"/><date when="1798-05-26">26th 7
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q><p>This morning the river appears<lb/>to have risen about 18 inches, yet it is
                        but<lb/>very little muddy; the day being fair consider-<lb/>able progress
                        was made in our clearing; cutting and<lb/>heaping old logs, grubbing
                        &amp;c., in which we<lb/>sometimes had the help of a neighboring<lb/>Indian,
                        whose strength and activity, evince<lb/>there was nothing wanting but the
                            <emph rend="underline">will</emph>, to<lb/>make him a full workman at
                        business<lb/>of this kind.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="genes1"/><date when="1798-05-27">27th First
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q><p> This being First-day, about<lb/>11 o'clock we sat down together for religious
                        retire-<lb/>ment, which through favor was a strengthening<lb/>time to some
                        of us, May such seasons be re-<lb/>membered with gratitude and thankfulness,
                            <lb/><pb n="53" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_053"/>and may our young
                        Friends be encouraged<lb/>and strengthened to keep up such
                        religious<lb/>opportunities when we are far separated. -<lb/><said
                            who="jshar1">Which I trust they will.</said> [says <persName
                            key="jshar1">J.S.</persName>]</p>
                    <p>Soon after the close of our sitting and<lb/> whilst preparing what little
                        provisions we had<lb/>left, for our dinner, an Indian man came<lb/>into our
                        cabin, and presented us with about<lb/>four pounds of fresh venison without
                        any bone<lb/>in it. for which we offered him a quarter<lb/>of a dollar,
                        which he showed some reluctance<lb/>at taking, but as he could speak no
                        English<lb/>we were altogether at a loss to know whether<lb/>it proceeded
                        from what we had offered him<lb/>being too <emph rend="underline"
                            >little</emph> or from an intention of <emph rend="underline"
                            >giving</emph><lb/>us the meat, we however prevailed upon him
                        to<lb/>receive the money. We aftoward made him<lb/>understand we wanted to
                        go down in a canoe<lb/> to <placeName key="cornp">Cornplanters
                            village</placeName>, where we had ap-<lb/>pointed to have a Council
                        tomorrow: he made<lb/>signs that he would go with us, when the sun<lb/>got
                        to such a place, pointing with his hand.</p>
                    <p>He then left us, and we immediately pro-<lb/>ceeded to fry some of the
                        venison.</p>
                    <p>We sat down to our dinner with thank-<lb/>ful hearts for so unexpected a
                        supply, which<lb/>was very acceptable, as we had not so much<lb/> of our own
                        left as would make a meal for one<lb/><pb n="54"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_054"/>person, and had heard of none to be
                        purchased<lb/>in this country though we had made considerable<lb/>
                        inquiry.</p>
                    <p>When inquiring for bacon at <placeName key="pitts"
                        >Pittsburgh</placeName><lb/>we were told it was not necessary to carry
                        meat<lb/>here, for there was plenty in this place; however<lb/>we thought it
                        not best to trust to an uncertainty, and<lb/> have therefore 120 lbs of
                        bacon coming up in the<lb/>boat, We have only obtained one pound of
                        dried<lb/>meat, and the venison above spoken of since<lb/>being here.</p>
                    <p> About 4 in the afternoon, three of our com<lb/>pany, together with the
                        aforesaid Indian, set off in<lb/>a canoe for <placeName key="cornp"
                            >Cornplanters village</placeName>, leaving two of<lb/>our young men to
                        take care of our horses, house &amp;c.<lb/>and come down on horse-back in
                        the morning.</p>
                    <p>Sometime after we arrived the Indian who<lb/>accompanied us, handed <persName
                            key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> the money<lb/>we had given him for
                        the meat, saying something<lb/>to him in their own language, and in a few
                            minutes<lb/><persName key="habee1">Henry O'Neal</persName> (some write
                        it Obeal) informed us that he<lb/>said he intended to <emph rend="underline"
                            >give</emph> us the meat, that he was not<lb/>willing to take <emph
                            rend="underline">any</emph>
                        <emph rend="underline">pay</emph> for it, but could not make<lb/>us
                        understand him: therefore he had brought<lb/>the money along in order to
                        give it back to us.</p>
                    <p>We received the money, expressed our ap-<lb/>preciation of his kindness, and
                        presented him<lb/>with the same price for his trouble in bring-<lb/><pb
                            n="55" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_055"/>ing us down in the canoe, upon
                        which<lb/>he readily received it.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="cornp"/><date when="1798-05-27">27th 2nd
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q><p>Our young men arrived and about<lb/>12 o'clock the Indians were generally
                        collected in<lb/>council, there being 5 or 6 women also present.</p>
                    <p> Early in the opportunity, <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> made
                        a<lb/>pretty long speech, which did not appear to<lb/>be directed to us, but
                        was for an Indian<lb/>there in the house,* <note rend="asterisk">* as our
                            interpreter afterward told us.</note> who had been charged
                        with<lb/>murdering a white man: for which he had<lb/>been tried but being
                        aquitted, was now at<lb/>liberty, the expensive of which had cost <persName
                            key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName><lb/>$200. The Chiefs speech appeared
                        to be delivered<lb/>with much earnestness, and seriousness.</p>
                    <p>He then addressed himself to us, expressing<lb/> his satisfaction in seeing
                        us all in good health &amp;c.<lb/>He then informed us they were now ready to
                        hear<lb/>what we had to say to them.</p>
                    <p>After this information we sat a few<lb/>minutes in silence, wherein we felt
                        an earnest<lb/> desire that we might be renewedly favored with<lb/>best
                        direction in our communications &amp;c. to these<lb/>people. Inward
                        stillness, or anything like it,<lb/> is a state of mind that only a <emph
                            rend="underline">few</emph> of them appear<lb/>to be acquainted with. We
                        were, in a short<lb/>time, favored with a degree of weight and
                            strength<lb/><pb n="56" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_056"/>to make some
                        introductory communications,<lb/>pertaining to the nature of our business,
                        and<lb/>then <del>read</del> the following, which we had prepared
                        and<lb/>written down on the <date when="1798-05-22">22nd</date> was read and
                        interpreted.</p>
                    <floatingText type="speech">
                        <body>
                            <opener>To <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName>, and all our
                                Indian brothers of the<lb/><orgName key="seneca">Seneca
                                    Nation</orgName> now living on the <geogName key="alleg"
                                    >Alleghany<lb/>River</geogName>. <salute><emph rend="underline"
                                        >Brothers</emph>.</salute></opener>
                            <p>We have now been several days<lb/>among you, and have had councils
                                with your<lb/>Chiefs and wisemen, and have looked about
                                your<lb/>country, and have agreed upon a place for our young<lb/>men
                                to begin upon. We are glad and thankful to<lb/>the Great Spirit,
                                that every thing we have proposed<lb/>for your good, has been so
                                agreeable to your minds, that<lb/>we seem to agree like brothers,
                                having but one mind in<lb/>everything we do: and we hope, brothers,
                                we shall<lb/>continue to be of one mind about all things,
                                we<lb/>have been speaking to you of.</p>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>, you know the place we have
                                chosen<lb/>for our young men to begin upon at <placeName
                                    key="genes1">Genesinguhta</placeName>;<lb/>and we hope some of
                                your young men will settle<lb/>by them, and fence off lots for
                                themselves, as they<lb/>see our young men fence of theirs.</p>
                            <p>Our young men will be willing to assist and in-<lb/>struct them in
                                working their lots.</p>
                            <p> We do not think our young men will be able to <lb/><pb n="57"
                                    facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_057"/>raise any more of their lot
                                this year, than they will<lb/>want for themselves, but we hope
                                against another<lb/>year, they will have a little to spare. and we
                                are<lb/>willing they should give to your old and in-<lb/>firm people
                                that cannot work, one bushel<lb/>out of four, of all grain and so
                                forth, they<lb/>have to spare.</p>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>, in order to encourage<lb/>you
                                still more to take up work, and to follow<lb/>the ways we point out
                                to you, we will agree<lb/>to give you a little more. We will send
                                you<lb/>Smiths tools, when our young men write us, that<lb/>you need
                                them.</p>
                            <p>Brothers, if you are industrious<lb/>this summer, and raise a goodd
                                eal of corn,<lb/>and some wheat, we will help you build a<lb/>good
                                mill next summer, if a suitable place<lb/>can be found for it. You
                                must find half<lb/>the money to build the mill, and we will<lb/>find
                                the other half. We hope, brothers,<lb/>you will save some money*
                                    <note rend="asterisk">* annuity.</note> you get from
                                the<lb/>white people, that you may have your share<lb/>ready against
                                next spring. We think you<lb/>had better choose one of your chiefs
                                to keep this<lb/>money for you, till the time is wanted,<lb/>or
                                perhaps is may be all gone for whisky, or<lb/>something that will
                                not do as much good<lb/>as the mill would.</p>
                            <pb n="58" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_058"/>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>, We are also willing to learn
                                you<lb/>how to farm by agreeing to give some<lb/>small premiums, to
                                such of our Indian<lb/>brothers who are industrious and raise
                                a<lb/>good deal of grain,</p>
                            <p>Brothers, We will give to every Indian<lb/>man living on this river
                                who shall raise 25 bu.<lb/>of wheat or rye, in one year on his own
                                land<lb/>not worked by white people, the sum of two<lb/>dollars.</p>
                            <p>2nd For every 50 bushels of corn raised by one<lb/>man in like manner
                                afore said, the sum of<lb/>two dollars.</p>
                            <p>3rd for every 50 bushels of potatoes raised by<lb/>any one man in
                                like manner aforesaid, the<lb/>sum of two dollars.</p>
                            <p> 4th For every two tons hay raised as aforesaid<lb/>and put into a
                                stack or barn, not being mown<lb/>or drawn in, by white people, the
                                sum of two<lb/>dollars.</p>
                            <p>5th For every 12 yards of linen cloth made<lb/>by an Indian woman out
                                of flax raised on her,<lb/>or her husband's land, and spun in her
                                own<lb/>house, the sum of two dollars, to be paid to
                                the<lb/>woman.</p>
                            <p>6th For every 12 yards of woolen or linsey cloth<lb/>made by an
                                Indian woman out of the<lb/>wool of her own, or her husbands
                                    sheep,<lb/><pb n="59" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_059"/>and spun
                                in her own house, the sum of two<lb/>dollars to be paid to the
                                woman.</p>
                            <p>Brothers we will give you these pre-<lb/>miums for four years, if our
                                young men<lb/>stay here so long - upon these conditions -<lb/>that
                                the person who applies for a premium<lb/> must produce a certificate
                                from two of the<lb/>Chiefs, signifying the quantity of grain,
                                cloth,<lb/>&amp;c: for what the premium is demanded, and<lb/> that
                                it was raised, or made, in the manner<lb/>above mentioned, - and
                                that the person has<lb/>not been intoxicated with whiskey
                                at<lb/>least for the term of six months before<lb/>that time.* <note
                                    rend="asterisk">* that they apply for their premiums.</note> And
                                our friends are hereby<lb/>authorized and desired to pay the
                                above<lb/> premiums, agreeable to what is herebefore
                                ex-<lb/>pressed. <date when="1798-05-22">5th Mo. 22nd
                                1798.</date></p>
                            <signed><table>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell><persName key="jshar1">Joshua
                                            Sharpless</persName>.</cell>
                                        <cell><persName key="jpier1">John Pierce</persName>.</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell><persName key="hsimm1">Henry
                                            Simmons</persName>.</cell>
                                        <cell><persName key="jswai1">Joel Swayne</persName>.</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell><persName key="hjack1">Halliday
                                            Jackson</persName>.</cell>
                                    </row>
                                </table></signed>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                    <p>After reading these propositions, we were<lb/>again enabled, solemly to
                        expostulate<lb/>with them on various subjects, relative,<lb/>both to their
                        moral and temporal conduct:<lb/>but particularly on their excessive use
                        of<lb/>strong drink, a variety of instances whereof<lb/>we had been eye
                        witnesses to.</p>
                    <pb n="60" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_060"/>
                    <!-- page missing??? -->
                    <p>Rivers of them, as heretofore, appeared solid;<lb/>and particularly the
                        women, but much<lb/>the greater number manifested no real seriousness</p>
                    <p>They then proposed retiring into a private<lb/>council in order to consult of
                        an answer, which<lb/>they accordingly did; and returned in about an
                        hr.<lb/>when <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> made the
                        following speech.</p>
                    <floatingText type="speech">
                        <body>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>,<lb/>We now hear all what
                                you<lb/> would wish to do among us: you are come<lb/>here to see us
                                brothers. You wish us well,<lb/>you wish us to become as the white
                                people.<lb/>The white people are rich and got every-<lb/>thing: the
                                Indians are poor and have noth-<lb/>ing.</p>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>. One thing you told us, it
                                would<lb/>be good for us to build a mill: we must<lb/>find $400 and
                                you will find $400.</p>
                            <p>Brothers we cant say but few words<lb/>at this time about the mill:
                                we will consult <persName key="ichap1"
                                >Captain<lb/>Chapin</persName>: if he thinks we will receive our
                                mon-<lb/>ey, and will be able to raise the money you<lb/>propose,
                                then we will do it.</p>
                            <p>Brothers,<lb/>We know how far you have<lb/>come to see us: it is a
                                great way way from<lb/>the sea shore, where our forefathers once
                                lived.</p>
                            <p>The white people have cheated us, and got <lb/><pb n="61"
                                    facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_061"/>our land from us, and now we
                                have but<lb/>little left. We will try to learn your way.</p>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>,<lb/>You know there are some
                                bad<lb/>people amongst us: and you know that we<lb/>have been
                                cheated, and <emph rend="underline">that</emph> makes us bad,
                                and<lb/>our minds uneasy.</p>
                            <p>If we had not been cheated, we should<lb/>have been very rich people
                                and had plenty<lb/>of every thing: and then our minds would<lb/>be
                                easy, and we could think upon the Good<lb/>Spirit.</p>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>, The reason I mention to
                                you<lb/>about our being cheated some of my warriors win't<lb/>mind
                                what I say to them, but will have their<lb/>own way, because they
                                know I have often been cheat-<lb/>ed by the white people. If I had
                                never been cheat-<lb/>ed then my warriors would believe me, and
                                mind<lb/>what I say to them: but now they won't mind.</p>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>, we can't all go to work at
                                once<lb/>Some of my warriors will go a hunting to get
                                pro-<lb/>visions, and sometimes they break a gun, and<lb/>then it
                                takes a great deal of money to get a new<lb/> one. We have very few
                                hoes and axes and such<lb/>things amongst us, and we are not able to
                                get them.</p>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>,<lb/>I will go along with you
                                to <placeName key="canan">Canan-<lb/><pb n="62"
                                        facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_062"/>daigua</placeName> and
                                there we will get matters settled about<lb/>the mill, and bring it
                                to back to your young men<lb/>in writing.</p>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>, this is all I got to say, we
                                will now<lb/>shake hands.</p>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                    <p>At the close of this speech we ex-<lb/>pressed a few more words; representing
                        among<lb/>other things the unreasonableness of their present<lb/>practice,
                        in suffering their women to work<lb/>all day in the fields and woods, with
                        their<lb/>hoes and axes, whilst the men and boys were<lb/>at the same time,
                        playing with bows and<lb/>arrows; and recommending them to begin<lb/>our
                        way, by early setting their boys to business,<lb/>taking them out to hoe
                        corn &amp;c. By early ha<lb/>bituating them to work, their minds would
                        be<lb/>turned to it, and they would not think hard of<lb/>it. We concluded
                        with seriously pressing on their<lb/>minds the remembrance that it was
                        from<lb/>the Good Spirit they received every good thing:<lb/>and that he
                        could hear every word they said, and<lb/>see every thing they did: and that
                        they were, eq-<lb/>ually with the white people, objects of his
                        tender<lb/>care and regard: and that the great difference,<lb/>between them
                        and white people, in regard to<lb/>riches and poverty, of which they so
                        frequently<lb/>spoke, was the natural result of the diferent<lb/>plans
                        pursued in [endeavoring] to obtain the<lb/><pb n="63"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_063"/>blessings of this life: and that as
                        their ground<lb/>was equally good with with that possessed by
                        white<lb/>people, it would also be equally productive<lb/>if the same
                        industry and method of farming<lb/>it were pursued.</p>
                    <p>In a few minutes after we had<lb/>concluded, and informed them so, <persName
                            key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName><lb/>observed, now all things are
                        settled and done.<lb/>We will cover up the council fire.</p></q>
                <p>They dined with the chief. <q>About five<lb/>o'clock, we had a loaf of warm
                        Indian bread<lb/>with beans in it, baked in a Duch oven, and a<lb/>little
                        butter was all that was set before us. They<lb/>informed us they had no
                        meat.</q></p>
                <q><p>In the evening our young men returned to their<lb/><pb n="64"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_064"/>own house at <placeName key="genes1"
                            >Genesinguhta</placeName>, and we (<persName key="jshar1">Joshua<lb/>
                            Sharpless</persName> and <persName key="jpier1">John Pierce</persName>)
                        took boarding with<lb/><persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName>, who
                        used us kindly, and as well as<lb/>his house will afford, We had teas of
                        diferent<lb/>kinds, one was made of sassafras root, and wheat<lb/>bread
                        baked or rather fried in a pan that ate very<lb/>well. We inquired of
                            <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> respecting<lb/>the routes
                        to return, not liking the way we came,<lb/>amongst others, for a way to
                            <placeName key="canan">Canadaigua</placeName>, and how<lb/>far. He told
                        us it was 160 miles and not a very diffi-<lb/>cult road. That he and his son
                            <persName key="habee1">Henry</persName> were going there<lb/>in a few
                        days. We tarried here to settle some<lb/>matters with him relative to our
                        leaving these<lb/>parts, which we wish now to affect as soon as<lb/> we
                        should see our goods safely arrived, also to be here<lb/>when they came, [as
                        we are looking for them any time now,<lb/>and they were directed here, but
                        we do not wish them<lb/>unloaded here since our young men have settled
                        farther<lb/>up the river.]</p>
                    <p>Some time after night a messenger<lb/>arrived, here from the chiefs at
                            <placeName key="buffa">Buffalo</placeName> requesting<lb/><persName
                            key="cornp2">Cornplanters</persName> attendance at that place, the
                        sur-<lb/>veyors &amp;c being come, in order to run the line of
                        their<lb/>respective reservations, agreeable to a treaty of last
                        sum-<lb/>mer with <persName key="rmorr1">Robert Morris</persName>. <persName
                            key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> expressed a<lb/>particular desire
                        that we should attend their council<lb/>on the occasion, at the aforesaid
                        place.</p>
                    <p> We had for some time past felt our minds rather<lb/><pb n="65"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_065"/>turned toward taking <placeName
                            key="canan">Canandaigua</placeName> and <placeName key="oneid"
                            >Oneida</placeName><lb/>in our way home: and upon inquiring
                        were<lb/>informed that we could not get to <placeName key="canan"
                            >Canandaigua</placeName><lb/>from this place without going through
                            <placeName key="buffa">Buffalo</placeName><lb/>which makes the proposal
                        of the Chief for us to ac-<lb/>company them feel pleasant.</p>
                    <p>It now remained to fix on a time for<lb/>setting out, but to this end the
                        want of our goods<lb/>seemed in the way, as we had heard nothing of<lb/>them
                        since we left <placeName key="pitts">Pittsburg</placeName>; a full result
                        was<lb/>therefore deferred.</p>
                </q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="cornp"/><date when="1798-05-29">29th 3
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q>
                    <p> Most of this day and part of<lb/>the preceeding was employed in digesting
                        our min-<lb/>utes, writing letters and so forth, one of which<lb/>was to
                            <persName key="twist1">Thomas Wister</persName> showing the present
                        state<lb/>of our business at this place, and another to<lb/><persName
                            key="gwilk2">General Wilkinson</persName> containing a brief narrative
                        of<lb/>our proceedings since our arrival here.</p>
                    <p>In a private conference with <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName>
                        and<lb/>two or three others we obtained the following in-<lb/>formation;
                        that the Indians in this reservation<lb/>consist of between 3 &amp; 4
                        hundred individuals: they<lb/>have 3 horses, 14 horned cattle, 1 yoke of
                        oxen, and 12 hogs,<lb/>all private property. They have two solemnities<lb/>
                        in the year in form of public worship or Thanks-<lb/>giving to the Great
                        Spirit for his blessings, one in the Spring,<lb/>and the other about the
                        time of their corn ripening</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="cornp"/><date when="1798-05-30">30th 4th
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q>
                    <p> The fore part of this day<lb/><pb n="66" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_066"
                        />was employed in writing and so forth.</p>
                    <p> About noon our goods arrived at this<lb/>place, and were heartily welcomed
                        both by us,<lb/>and the Indians, many of whom gathered round<lb/>the shore,
                        having never seen such a <emph rend="underline">boat</emph> before.</p>
                    <p>The captain did not leave <placeName key="pitts">Pittsburg</placeName> untill
                        3<lb/>days later than he expected - he had been 15<lb/>days coming, and it
                        was 270 miles to follow<lb/>the course of the river. Both he and his
                        men<lb/>appeared tired, expressing much satisfaction<lb/>that they had
                        gotten here: but when we<lb/> let them know our house was 9
                        miles<lb/>further up the river and that we wanted the<lb/>goods taken there,
                        they were very unwilling<lb/>to comply; there was no road to wagon
                        them<lb/>up, and several of our packs were two large<lb/>for canoes. We at
                        length effected our purpose<lb/>upon the following conditions, We gave
                        them<lb/> three dollars as a present, hired an Indian<lb/>pilot for half a
                        dollar, and agreed to write<lb/>to <persName key="icrag1">Major
                            Craig</persName> of <placeName key="pitts">Pittsburg</placeName> on his
                        (the captain's)<lb/>behalf as follows. viz.</p>
                    <floatingText type="letter">
                        <body>
                            <opener><dateline><placeName key="cornp">Jenuchshedago</placeName>
                                    <date when="1798-05-31">5th Mo 31. 1798.</date></dateline>
                                <salute>Respected Friend</salute></opener>
                            <p>Yesterday <persName key="tleek1">Thomas Leeks</persName>
                                ar-<lb/>rived at <persName key="cornp">Cornplanters lower
                                    village</persName> with our<lb/>goods; and our settlement being
                                nine miles<lb/>higher up the river we prevailed with him to<lb/><pb
                                    n="67" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_067"/>continue up to that
                                place: If it accords<lb/>with thy orders to satisfy him for this
                                ex-<lb/>tra labor, the business will be settled: if<lb/>not please
                                to present these lines, with<lb/>his extra bill, to <persName
                                    key="abark1">Abner</persName> and <persName key="jbark1">Jesse
                                    Barker</persName><lb/>who are hereby authorized to settle it,
                                placing<lb/>the same to the account of <persName key="tfish1">Thomas
                                    Fisher</persName><lb/>of <placeName key="phila"
                                    >Phila</placeName>.</p>
                            <p>Note, we have made him a present of<lb/>three dollars which we do not
                                wish de-<lb/>ducted out of his reasonable bills.</p>
                            <closer><salute>I am with respect thy friend.</salute>
                                <signed><persName key="jpier1">John Pierce</persName>.</signed><lb/>
                                <persName key="icrag1">Isaac Craig</persName><lb/><placeName
                                    key="pitts">Pittsburg.</placeName></closer>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                    <p>This evening let <persName key="cornp2">Cornplant-<lb/>er</persName> know
                        that we should now be ready to de-<lb/>part for <placeName key="buffa"
                            >Buffalo</placeName>, as soon as would be conve-<lb/>nient for him. He
                        informed us he could not<lb/>be ready in less than four days. We
                        felt<lb/>some reluctance at being detained after<lb/>our business was done,
                        but submitted to<lb/> the time proposed.</p>
                    <p>Owing to the want of a suit-<lb/>able interpreter Our Travellers had but
                        little<lb/>conversation with the Indians beyond their<lb/> business affairs,
                        being now through with<lb/><emph rend="underline">that</emph>, they
                        conversed a little about their cus-<lb/>toms, in which <persName
                            key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> said they<lb/><pb n="68"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_068"/>did not keep the First day of the
                        week<lb/>but every one tried to think good in his<lb/>own mind. As we could
                        read the<lb/>Bible, he queried whether there was any<lb/>thing said in it
                        about the Indians?</p>
                    <p>We informed him, the Bible mentioned<lb/>all nations, Kindred, Younges, and
                        people;<lb/>and that included the Indians.</p>
                    <p>We would have been glad to have<lb/>told him, that though the Indians
                        could<lb/>not read the Bible, yet they were not wholy<lb/>deprived of the
                        benefits of the coming of<lb/> Christ, for, that a manifestation of
                        his<lb/>spirit, or measure of his Grace, was placed<lb/>in each of their
                        hearts, and would if minded<lb/>or given way to, reprove for all wicked
                        words,<lb/>and wicked actions, also produce peace for well<lb/>doing,- but
                        this was too refined and delicate<lb/>a subject for our interpreter to
                        handle.</p>
                </q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">

                <dateline><placeName key="cornp"/><date when="1798-05-31">31st 5th
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q><p>Took our last farewell of the<lb/>Indians in this place about 9 o'clock,
                        and<lb/>set off with <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName>, his son
                            <persName key="habee1">Henry</persName> and<lb/>a nephew, up the river
                        in a canoe to his<lb/>saw mill, where we took leave of the Chief<lb/>and his
                        son for the present, with a promise<lb/>that they would call on us at our
                        house at<lb/><placeName key="genes1">Genesinguhta</placeName>, in five days
                        to go with us to <lb/><pb n="69" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_069"/>the mouth
                        of <geogName key="buffc1">Buffalo</geogName>, in order to attend
                        the<lb/>Council there, the Nephew and son of<lb/>the Dutchman who tends the
                        saw mill,<lb/>took us up to our farm, where we found our<lb/>goods had
                        safely arrived about two hours be-<lb/>fore, and unloaded, we gave to the
                            boatman,<lb/><persName key="tleek1">Thomas Leeks</persName> the
                        aforesaid lines to <persName key="icrag1">major<lb/>Craig</persName>, Our
                        letter to <persName key="gwilk2">General Wilkinson</persName>, and<lb/>that
                        to <persName key="twist1">Thomas Wistar</persName>, with several
                        others<lb/>enclosed. The boatman having got their<lb/>business accomplished
                        respectfully bade us<lb/>farewell, and with cheerful countenances<lb/>went
                        merrily down the lively current,<lb/>expecting in four days to arrive
                            in<lb/><placeName key="pitts">Pittsburgh</placeName>.</p>
                    <p>The remainger of the day was<lb/>employed in unpacking our goods,
                        and<lb/>repacking them into our cabin, Several<lb/>of the articles were wet
                        but nothing ap-<lb/>peared much damaged.</p>
                    <p>After the things were arranged we<lb/>experience a great change. Our
                        naked<lb/>walls, empty house, and bare cupboard,<lb/>met with a rich supply;
                        our hard and<lb/>cold beds, were warmed and softened, with<lb/>blankets: we
                        are now able to make a cup<lb/>of tea or coffee, though without milk or
                        butter:<lb/>we have bacon and cheese to eat with our<lb/><pb n="70"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_070"/>bread: and one of our young men says
                        they<lb/>want nothing but a cow to make their<lb/>living equal to <placeName
                            key="chestc">Chester county</placeName>.</p>
                    <p>We are visited every day more or less<lb/>by the Indians, who are much
                        pleased<lb/> viewing several kinds of our goods: which<lb/>satisfaction is
                        increased by our giving them<lb/>some small matters. We showed
                        them<lb/>Howell's map of <placeName key="penns">Pennsylvania</placeName>,
                        with<lb/>which they were much diverted, and seem-<lb/>ed to understand it
                        pretty well, particularly<lb/>the <geogName key="alleg">Alleghany
                            river</geogName>, and the large streams<lb/>which run into it.</p>
                    <p>We have received of <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName>,
                        since<lb/>we came into this country, about fifty pounds<lb/>of flour,
                        besides several days board for two of<lb/>us, for which he refuses taking
                        any pay.</p>
                    <p>We therefore this day made him a present<lb/>of 6 Bandana handkerchiefs, one
                        for his wife,<lb/>and one for each of his five daughters, Three<lb/>fine
                        tooth combs, two pocket knives one<lb/>paper of needles, 6 thimbles and 2
                        1/4 yds. of<lb/>cloth to his son <persName key="habee1">Henry</persName>,
                        who has steadily<lb/>attended on us as interpreter.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="genes1"/><date when="1798-06-01">6th Mo. 1st 6th
                        day.</date></dateline>

                <q><p>This morning being wet our<lb/>young men were employed putting handles<lb/>to
                        their tools, hanging their grindstone &amp;c.<lb/>
                        <pb n="71" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_071"/>In the afternoon we, (that is
                            <persName key="jshar1">Joshua Sharp-<lb/>less</persName> and <persName
                            key="jpier1">John Pierce</persName>) went about a mile<lb/>up the river,
                        in order to view a small<lb/>creek, that we were informed of, as
                        most<lb/>likely to afford a millseat: we went a<lb/>considerable distance
                            <emph rend="underline">up</emph>
                        <emph rend="underline">the</emph>
                        <emph rend="underline">creek</emph>, fount<lb/>it had plenty of fall, and
                        appeared to<lb/>have a sufficiency of water, with a good<lb/>bank and place
                        for a mill, much out of<lb/>the way of floods, which are sometimes<lb/>great
                        in this river, and at the same time<lb/>so that canoes might come up a short
                        dis-<lb/>tance to the mill; but against these advan-<lb/>tages, there are
                        some disadvantages in regard to<lb/>getting the water where we want it.
                        Millseats<lb/>are very scarce in this reservation, we have yet<lb/>seen none
                        excepting the above worth building<lb/> upon.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="genes1"/><date when="1798-06-02">2nd 7th
                    day</date></dateline>
                <q><p> This day our young men got to their<lb/>cleaning again, and have about 1 1/2
                        acres ready<lb/>for the plough. We were easy to agree to<lb/>spending some
                        days at this place, and to<lb/>feel, and sympathize with our friends
                        under<lb/>their various trials: and notwithstanding<lb/>we had no power from
                        our friends at home<lb/> relative to things here. We believed the
                        ur-<lb/>gency of the occasion would justify us in<lb/><pb n="72"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_072"/>joining with them in a serious
                        considera-<lb/>tion of what might be profitably proposed<lb/>to the <orgName
                            key="oneida">Oneidas</orgName> on the subject of the young<lb/>men
                        working on the farm with our friends,<lb/>as well as the necessary
                        arrangements relative to<lb/><persName key="wgreg1">William
                            Gregory</persName>'s prospect as a smith.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="genes1"/><date when="1798-06-03">3rd First
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q>
                    <p> Two Indians one a chief paid us<lb/>a visit this morning, we being employed
                        in writing<lb/>and reading. We endeavored to let them know<lb/>that we did
                        not work on First day, though<lb/>we found it difficult to make them
                        sensible of<lb/> the reason, Since our coming into these parts<lb/>we have
                        kept meetings twice a week, Our oppor-<lb/>tunity to day, felt like a
                        parting meeting,<lb/>and a travil was experienced for the presen-<lb/>tation
                        of our young men, whom we expect short-<lb/>ly to leave, It was a time
                        wherein we witnessed<lb/>a renewal of strength.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="genes1"/><date when="1798-06-04">4th 2nd
                    day</date></dateline>
                <q><p> A wet day. <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> sent<lb/>word that a
                        number of indians are going with<lb/>him to <placeName key="buffa"
                            >Buffalo</placeName>, who were not fully ready, but<lb/>would call on us
                        tomrrow. The nights are<lb/>still cool: we have steadily had four
                        blankets<lb/>under us and the same number above, yet none too<lb/>many. I do
                        not recollect seeing the sunrise clear<lb/>since we came here [principally
                        on account of the<lb/>fog]</p></q>
            </div>
            <pb n="73" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_073"/>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="genes1"/><date when="1798-06-05">5th 3
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q><p> A pleasant morning. Not know-<lb/>ing what time <persName key="cornp2"
                            >Cornplanter</persName> and his company<lb/>would call upon us, feeling
                        the prospect of a<lb/>separation, we sat down together to take a
                        part-<lb/>ing opportunity. It was a time of retirement<lb/>wherein the
                        canopy of Divine love was spread<lb/>over us, to the contriting of our
                        spirits, and a<lb/>living travail was was experienced, that as the
                        time<lb/>was approaching when we expected to part, that<lb/>Ancient Goodness
                        might be near to them that<lb/>stayed, to comfort, strengthen, and preserve
                        them<lb/>in their lonely cottage and arduous undertaking,<lb/>which
                        considering the many favors we have ex-<lb/>perienced, since we sat out,
                        there was no cause to<lb/>doubt, that as they were truly watchful and
                        at-<lb/>tentive on their part would still be continued, -<lb/>and that we
                        who are going, might also experi-<lb/>ence the Lord's protecting power,
                        through a<lb/> solitary wilderness and a tedious journey.</p>
                    <p>The Indians did not come.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="genes1"/><date when="1798-06-06">6th 4th
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q><p> After waiting with some degree of im-<lb/>patience, untill between two and
                        three o clock<lb/>this afternoon, we were visited by <persName key="cornp2"
                            >Cornplanter</persName><lb/>his son, and two other Indians. The
                        chief<lb/> informed us that one of his daughters was taken<lb/>very ill
                        yesterday, and that a relative living in<lb/>his family had fallen from a
                        horse and broken his<lb/><pb n="74" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_074"/>arm,
                        which had prevented him from coming soon<lb/>er, and now he could not go
                        with us for three<lb/>days on this account, for which he was very<lb/>sorry:
                        but if we did not like to wait so long<lb/> he would hire a guide and send
                        him with us.</p>
                    <p>We informed him, we regretted that these<lb/>circumstances prevented our
                        having his com-<lb/>pany, but believed it would be best for us to<lb/>set
                        off tomorrow morning, for we wished to<lb/>spend a few days with our friends
                        in <placeName key="canad">Canada</placeName>:<lb/>and in seven days hoped we
                        should meet him at<lb/><placeName key="buffa">Buffalo</placeName>, where he
                        said he intended to <emph rend="underline">be</emph> on that day,<lb/>if the
                        state of his family would permit.</p>
                    <p>A guide was accordingly provided, who engaged<lb/>to call us tomorrow morning
                        by sunrise.</p>
                    <p>A heavy shower of rain this evening: the<lb/>river for several days past has
                        been nearly three<lb/>feet higher than when we first came.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="genes1"/><date when="1798-06-07">7th 5th
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q><p> About sunrise this morning, our<lb/>guide, <persName key="ijohn1">Indian
                            John</persName>, a chief that lives in this<lb/>town called on us. About
                        5 o'clock we took<lb/>an affectionate farewell of our young friends,<lb/>and
                        set off for the mouth of <geogName key="buffc1">Buffalo</geogName>,</p>
                    <p>For some time after we sat off this morn<lb/>ing, my* <note rend="asterisk">*
                                <persName key="jshar1">J.S.</persName></note> mind was uncommonly
                        easy and cheer-<lb/>ful, so that I passed along in a lively and
                        well<lb/>qualified state to make travelling pleasant; but<lb/><pb n="75"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_075"/> before evening, I found my stock of
                        spirits was<lb/>much exhausted. About 11 o'clock we had a<lb/>very heavy
                        rain, such a one as seldom hap-<lb/>pens. We got very wet. When near
                            <geogName key="catar">Cat-<lb/>taraugus river</geogName> we passed
                        through a very<lb/>rich bottom, with an uncommonly lux-<lb/>uriant growth of
                        vegetation; and about<lb/>sunset arrived at the stream, which we<lb/>found
                        to be many perches out of its banks<lb/>at the fording place. Our guide
                        made<lb/>signs to us that is would run over<lb/>our horses' backs and sweep
                        them away.</p>
                    <p>We therefore concluded to pitch<lb/>camp being in an open bottom,
                        and<lb/>where there was a pretty good supply of<lb/>grass, so that our
                        horses would have done very<lb/>well if it had not been for gnats and
                        mus-<lb/>quitos. We struck up a fire, and under<lb/>some bushes we had put
                        up to keep off the<lb/> dew, got a pretty comfortable night's rest.</p>
                    <p>We saw neither house nor cabin in this<lb/>days ride.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><geogName key="catar"/><date when="1798-06-08">8th 6th
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q><p> The <geogName key="catar">Cattaraugus</geogName> fell sev-<lb/>eral inches
                        during the night, but at the place<lb/>selected for crossing, the water ran
                        very swiftly,<lb/>We made a sign to our guide to lead the way<lb/>he being
                        well mounted on <persName key="hsimm1">Henry Simmons</persName>'<lb/>horse,
                        it being the largest in the company,<lb/><pb n="76"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_076"/>but he showed evident marks of
                        fear.</p>
                    <p> The task being likely to fall upon<lb/>me,* <note rend="asterisk">*
                                <persName key="jshar1">J.S.</persName></note> I pulled off my great
                        coat and tied<lb/>it up well behind me and raised my<lb/>saddle-bags by
                        putting some luggage<lb/>under them, and having previously cut<lb/>a pole to
                        carry in my hand, to measure<lb/>the depth of the stream, I entered
                        the<lb/>river without much fear, though not<lb/>without care, and found our
                        guide was<lb/>mistaken in its depth. And well for us<lb/>he was, for had it
                        been as deep as he sup-<lb/>posed, no horse could have stood before<lb/>the
                        stream. He gave us to expect that the<lb/>water would come within six inches
                        of<lb/>the horses' backs.</p>
                    <p>I got safely through, my companions viewing<lb/>me with anxious minds. When
                        they saw me<lb/>safely landed, they followed and arrived also safe<lb/>ly
                        with gladened hearts. We pursued our journey<lb/>down the rich bottoms of
                        the stream, and in<lb/>ten miles arrived at a village of <orgName
                            key="munsee">Muncy Indians</orgName>,<lb/>in a champaign country, being
                        the first dwell-<lb/>ings we have seen since we left <placeName key="alleg1"
                            >Alleghany</placeName>.</p>
                    <p>We stopped at a house in this village and<lb/>breakfasted on our own
                        provisions.</p>
                    <p>The town and pasture land were enclosed<lb/>in a lot of 12 or more acres,
                        which looked clean<lb/><pb n="77" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_077"/> and
                        pretty, having very good pasture within<lb/>the enclosure. The house we went
                        into had a<lb/>large quantity of corn hanging upon it; con-<lb/>siderably
                        more than I saw all the time I was<lb/>at <placeName key="alleg1"
                            >Alleghany</placeName>. We understood they sell<lb/>many bushels every
                        year.</p>
                    <p>Most of the principal men in the village<lb/> and others gathered into the
                        house where we<lb/>were, and a white man living amongst them<lb/>could
                        interpret, we informed them of what<lb/>we had been doing at <placeName
                            key="cornp">Cornplanters settlement</placeName>:<lb/>and of friends
                        concern for the Indians in general;<lb/>with which they expressed their
                        satisfaction: say-<lb/>ing they took it very kind that we had called
                        to<lb/>see them, and to inform them of what we had<lb/>beeing doing at
                            <placeName key="cornp">Jeniscatego</placeName>, for they had heard
                        some<lb/>thing about. We then shook hands and bade<lb/>them farewell.</p>
                    <p>In about 7 miles of a swampy<lb/>tedious road, we arrived at <geogName
                            key="lakee">Lake Erie</geogName>, and<lb/> enjoyed viewing this watery
                        element as we<lb/>travelled along the beach to the mouth of<lb/><geogName
                            key="buffc1">Buffalo</geogName>, 29 miles. The prospect through<lb/>the
                        remaining part of the day was pleasant,<lb/>rather heightened by our having
                        been so long con-<lb/>fined in the woods.</p>
                    <p>On our left the surf rolled gently to<lb/>the shore two or three feet high:
                        on our right<lb/><pb n="78" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_078"/> rocks, and
                        stones were piled up in places,<lb/>from 20 to 60* <note rend="asterisk">*
                            Some perhaps 100 ft.</note> feet high, as upright as the wall<lb/>of a
                        house, and in other places projecting <emph rend="underline"
                        >over</emph>,<lb/>several feet. The bottom of these rooks, by<lb/>the
                        beating of the waves, and sand, and grav-<lb/>el was worn into curious
                        shapes, and as<lb/>smoothe as polished marble.</p>
                    <p>It was interesting to see the water trickl-<lb/>ing down from the top of
                        these rocks, as<lb/>well as to note some rocks standing in the edge<lb/>of
                        the water, as large over, round, and as<lb/>smoothe as a milstone,</p>
                    <p>In a number of places the water came<lb/>up to the wall of rocks so that we
                        had<lb/>to ride 40 or more perches in the lake,<lb/>in places middle deep,
                        and the water was<lb/>very dirty with beating the sand, so that<lb/>we could
                        not see the bottom, and did<lb/>not know but the next step the
                        horses<lb/>made, might take them over their backs.</p>
                    <p>In a number of places the waves came up<lb/>against the rocks with such
                        force, at times as<lb/>to cause the water to fly over our heads,
                        making<lb/>the scene romantic.</p>
                    <p>We reached the mouth of <geogName key="buffc1">Buffalo
                        creek</geogName><lb/>before sunset. Here we met with a company<lb/>of men
                        who were going to run out <persName key="rmorr1">Robert
                        Morris</persName>'s<lb/>late purchase of the Indians into townships:
                            <persName key="jthom4">John<lb/><pb n="79"
                                facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_079"/> Thompson</persName>, an old
                        acquaintance from <placeName key="delco">Delaware<lb/>County</placeName>,
                        being one of the head surveyors. He<lb/>invited us to stay all night with
                        them, and<lb/>directed a tent to be put up for us. We acknowl-<lb/>edged his
                        kindness and accepted his offer.</p>
                    <p>We were entertained with much simplic-<lb/>ity on bread fish and chocolate,
                        and had a pretty good<lb/>nights rest, which we wanted, having travelled
                        45<lb/>miles to day. For the last 80 miles there were no
                        in-<lb/>habitants.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><geogName key="buffc1"/><date when="1798-06-09">9th 7th
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q><p> Crossed into <placeName key="canad">Canada</placeName> - a rough
                        strong<lb/>current in the river - our boat narrow and totter-<lb/>ing, and
                        one of the horses a little unruly, so that<lb/>we felt thankful when we got
                        on shore. Went<lb/>to <persName key="dpoun1">Daniel Ponds</persName> where
                        we were kindly received,<lb/>and felt glad we were once more among our
                        friends.</p>
                    <p>In the afternoon we paid a visit to <persName key="jmorr1">Joel
                            Morris</persName>'s,<lb/>who were much pleased in seeing us: and in
                        the<lb/> evening went to my old home, when here last fall,<lb/>at our friend
                            <persName key="ascho1">Asa Schooley</persName> and wife's, who
                        were<lb/>truly glad to see us, and we them,</p>
                    <p>Here we got a clean good bed which we<lb/>had not had since we left
                            <placeName key="pitts">Pittsburg</placeName>, having<lb/>for nearly four
                        weeks slept on the ground, or<lb/>on boards in our blankets.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="canad"/><date when="1798-06-10">10th, First
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q><p>Attended the meeting at <persName key="ascho1">Asy
                        Schooley</persName>'s<lb/>which was in good degree a solid
                            opportunity:<lb/><pb n="80" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_080"/>between 30
                        and 40 men and women collected, several<lb/>of whoom were hopeful young
                        persons.</p>
                    <p>In the afternoon went to <persName key="jhain3">Joseph Haines</persName>,
                            and<lb/><persName key="aburr1">Adam Burrells</persName>, where we had a
                        refreshing time,<lb/>and parted with his family in near affection.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="canad"/><date when="1798-06-11">11th 2nd
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <p> Our travellers set off early, to visit<lb/>Friends in that neighborhood and
                    others in the<lb/>vicinity which occupied three days. when they<lb/>returned to
                        <persName key="ascho1">Asa Schooleys</persName>. Here we will
                    again<lb/>trace their steps.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="canad"/><date when="1798-06-14">14th 5th
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q><p> About 9 oclock this morning we<lb/>took leave of our kind and valued friends,
                            <persName key="ascho1">Asa Schooley</persName><lb/>and wife, and their
                        children, having their,<lb/>and many Friends hearty wishes for our
                        safe<lb/>return. Arrived at the ferry at 12 o'clock,<lb/>where we found the
                        chief ferryman so in liquor,<lb/>as not to be fit to take any care, but a
                        trusty<lb/>old man who sometimes assisted, agreed to<lb/>take us over. The
                        wind was pretty high and<lb/>the river ran swiftly: so he concluded to
                        lash<lb/>two boats together, to keep the one our horses<lb/>were in
                        steadier, which was very acceptable to<lb/>us, having found when we crossed
                        before that<lb/>it was a dangerous ferry, and a rocking boat;<lb/>now we
                        went over steady, though the current beat<lb/>us down the river three
                        fourths of a mile. <lb/><pb n="81" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_081"/>Shortly
                        after getting ashore we saw a man<lb/>at a great distance riding toward us,
                        whom<lb/>we presently knew to be our <persName key="ijohn1">Indian
                            John</persName>, who was<lb/>coming to look for us. He appeared
                        much<lb/>pleased to meet with us, as we were to see<lb/> him, and find our
                        horse, rather (<persName key="hsimm1">Henry Simmons</persName>')<lb/>was
                        safe. We got to <placeName key="buffa">Buffalo</placeName> about 2
                        o'clock<lb/>and though a day later than we agreed to meet<lb/><persName
                            key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> here yet neither he nor any
                        of<lb/>his company, were come. About sunset his<lb/>son <persName
                            key="habee1">Henry</persName> and another Indian arrived,
                        and<lb/>informed us that <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> and
                        ten or twelve<lb/>more were on their way and would be here by 10 o<lb/>clock
                        tomorrow.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="buffa"/><date when="1798-06-15">15th 6th
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q><p> About 12 o'clock <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> and
                        his<lb/>company arrived at the opposite side of <geogName key="buffc1"
                            >Buffalo</geogName>,</p>
                    <p>We walked down to the river to meet them<lb/>when they came across: They
                        seemed pleased to<lb/>see us. <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName>
                        gave us a letter from our<lb/>friends, dated five days after we came
                        away,<lb/>They were well in health, and enjoyed peaceful<lb/> minds,
                            <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> having got some
                        in-<lb/>formation that we were a little uneasy<lb/>about staying, as none of
                            <persName key="rmorr1">Robert Morris</persName>'s<lb/>comimissioners
                        were arrived; this afternoon<lb/>took an opportunity with us; observing
                        that<lb/>he expected we had seen enough of the difficulty travelling<lb/><pb
                            n="82" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_082"/>in the wilderness, to know that
                        when people<lb/>were to be collected from different parts, it re-<lb/>quired
                        time: and he hoped if <persName key="ichap1">Captain
                        Chapin</persName><lb/>did not arrive this evening, we would try to
                        make<lb/>our selves as happy as we could, and stay a few<lb/>days longer,
                        for he had a great desire we should be<lb/>with them at the council, and see
                        that that all things<lb/>were fairly settled. It brought a close
                        exercise<lb/>over our minds to know what was best to<lb/> do. A number of
                        the Indians were collected,<lb/>yet it looked likely, it would be some
                        consid-<lb/>erable time before all parties would get to-<lb/>gether, as none
                        of the white people immediately<lb/>concerned were come. We let him know
                        we<lb/>would have been glad to attend council, but it<lb/>was now drawing
                        towards the <del>last of the</del> latter<lb/>end of the week, and the white
                        people did not<lb/>do business on First day; that it was not very<lb/>likely
                            <persName key="ichap1">Captain Chapin</persName> and company
                        would<lb/>leave <placeName key="canan">Canandaigua</placeName> before Second
                        day morning,<lb/>and that it would be a number of days be-<lb/>fore the
                        council would meet: however we<lb/>were willing closely to consider the
                        subject<lb/> this evening.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="buff"/><date when="1798-06-16">16th 7th
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <p><q>Our Travellers</q> endeavored to attend<lb/>to <persName key="cornp2"
                        >Cornplanters</persName> request of last evening, and<lb/>one of them felt,
                    his mind, easy to move <lb/><pb n="83" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_083"/>
                    homewards, the other said he did not wit-<lb/>ness that clearness to set out he
                    wished to<lb/>experience, yet condescended if his compan-<lb/>ion thought best
                    of letting the chief know,<lb/> that upon weighing his request, in the<lb/>best
                    manner they could they felt easy<lb/> to move homewards this morning:
                    this<lb/>information was given him.</p>
                <q><p>He with a number of others pretty<lb/>soon came to our lodgings, and
                        expressed,<lb/>he was sorry we could not make our mines<lb/>easy to have
                        stayed a few days longer, not<lb/>doubting but <persName key="ichap1"
                            >Captain Chapin</persName>, and others con-<lb/>cerned would be here to
                        day. But perhaps<lb/>as whe had been a considerable time from home,<lb/>and
                        living was expensive, we might be<lb/>much run out of the meas that would
                        enable<lb/> us to stay. I informed him that when I<lb/>left home, I expected
                        to have returned in<lb/>about 40 days, that it was now near fifty<lb/>days,
                        and if we went to <placeName key="oneid">Onida</placeName> to see
                        the<lb/>Indians there, which we proposed, it would<lb/>take near thirty days
                        more, before we could get<lb/>home: that our circumstances in regard to
                        money<lb/> were not in the way, for we had plenty.</p>
                    <p>He said he had left his home on public<lb/>business, expecting to have
                        returned in fifty<lb/>or sixty days, and it had taken him near a <lb/><pb
                            n="84" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_084"/> year before he had got back, -
                        and that he<lb/>had found it his duty, to sacrifice private<lb/>convenience
                        to pubilc good,- and he would have<lb/>us do so too, We replied that the
                        business we<lb/>were about appeared to be agreeably settled to<lb/>both
                        their and our minds: this other we<lb/>knew nothing about till since coming
                        a-<lb/>mongst them: that we would have been wil-<lb/>ling to have sat with
                        them in council, though<lb/>we did not know that we could beg any service
                        to<lb/>them; and that the business between him and<lb/><persName
                            key="ichap1">Captain Chapin</persName> relating to a mill, we
                        might<lb/>be fully informed of the result, when it was settled,<lb/>by
                        letter. He then informed us he was become<lb/>perfectly reconciled to our
                        going, but as the<lb/>council was expected to meet any day, he could<lb/>not
                        accompany us to <placeName key="canan">Canandaigua</placeName>, but
                            <persName key="ijohn1">John</persName><lb/>who had been with us, would
                        go through to the<lb/>
                        <geogName key="genes2">Genesee river</geogName>: and that he wished the
                        Good<lb/>Spirit, who had hitherto preserved us would safely<lb/>keep us on
                        our journey, untill we arrived at our<lb/>homes. He further desired we would
                        make our-<lb/>selves perfectly easy about our young men, whom<lb/>were left
                        among his people, for he would take the<lb/>necessary care of them, and they
                        would be entirely<lb/>safe. We now took an affectionate farewell<lb/>of the
                        chief, and of the Indians present who parted<lb/>with us with much respect:
                        and I (<persName key="jshar1">J.S.</persName>) can truly say <lb/><pb n="85"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_085"/> the longer I have been among that
                        people, the<lb/>more near and united they have felt to me;<lb/>and now on
                        parting, they feel like brethren, with<lb/>whom I had been intimately
                        acquainted, and for<lb/>whose welfare I feel ardent wishes</p>
                    <p> About 8 o'clock we left <placeName key="buffa">Buffalo</placeName>. Much
                        of<lb/>this days ride was through a country very thinly<lb/>timbered, grown
                        over with plenty of pretty good<lb/>grass, so that I thought thousands of
                        cattle<lb/> might have been fattened upon it, if were not<lb/>for a species
                        of large flies and mosquitoes.<lb/>We stopped twice to let our horses eat
                        grass:<lb/>but they were so worried with these insects, that<lb/>they did
                        little but run about, untill we got brush<lb/>es and kept them off. If we
                        stopped our horses<lb/>one minute in the woods, in some places,
                        the<lb/>mosquitoes would be on them in such numbers<lb/>as almost to hide
                        their color. <persName key="jshar1">Joshua Sharpless</persName>,<lb/>says,
                            <said who="jshar1">I covered my head, neck, and the most of<lb/>my face
                            with my silk handkerchief, wrapped<lb/>a pocket handkerchief round one
                            of my hands,<lb/>and with all the defence I could make, was
                            much<lb/>bitten and swolen with them. When night<lb/>came on we got no
                            relief. We took up our quarters<lb/>about sunset, beside a small stream
                            of good water<lb/>under the bough of an oak, and kindled fires in<lb/>
                            diferent places around us, in order to smoke them<lb/>off: but <emph
                                rend="underline">with</emph>
                            <emph rend="underline">all</emph>, we were worried that the whole night
                            through, <lb/><pb n="86" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_086"/>so that we
                            slept but little, Our horses us may be<lb/>supposed, fared no better. 45
                            miles [to day].</said></p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><geogName key="genes2"/><date when="1798-06-17">17th. First
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q><p> About noon we arrived at the<lb/>Plains within 18 miles of <geogName
                            key="genes2">Genesee river</geogName>.</p>
                    <p>I* <note rend="asterisk">* <persName key="jshar1">J.S.</persName></note>
                        lodged at Pearson's four and a half miles<lb/>on this side the river, having
                        left my compan-<lb/>ion* <note rend="asterisk">* <persName key="jpier1"
                                >J.P.</persName></note> a few miles behind on special
                        business.<lb/>Here our horses could eat grass without much
                    molestation.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-06-18">18th 2nd day.</date></dateline>
                <q><p> About noon he arrived at my<lb/>quarters. He had a full interview
                            with<lb/><persName key="ichap1">Captain Capin</persName> who is
                        superintendent of<lb/>the Indians for the United States.</p>
                    <p><persName key="jpier1">John Pierce</persName> gave him full information of
                        what<lb/>we had been doing at <placeName key="cornp">Cornplanter's
                            settlement</placeName>, and<lb/>of the young men we had left there. The
                            <persName key="ichap1">Captain</persName><lb/>expressed great
                        satisfaction with our proceedings<lb/>and thought there was encouragement to
                        ex-<lb/>tend labour towards that people: for he had been<lb/>some time past,
                        through the <placeName key="oneid">Onida settlement</placeName>,<lb/>and he
                        apprehended he saw considerable im-<lb/>provement since Friends extended
                        care there,</p>
                    <p>About 2 o'clock we set off towards <placeName key="canan"
                            >Canandai-<lb/>gua</placeName>, and for 9 or 10 miles, passed through
                        a<lb/>thickly settled, highly improved country, con-<lb/>sidering the
                        settlement was no more than<lb/>ten years old, which was very animating;
                        having<lb/>for 300 miles been mostly in the wilderness. <lb/><pb n="87"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_087"/> Here we had beautiful timothy and
                        clover<lb/>fields almost constantly in view, with a<lb/>good appearance of
                        wheat, Indian corn, flax,<lb/>oats &amp;c. These we showed to our Indian
                        guide.</p>
                    <p>We alighted and examined the heads of<lb/> wheat. We showed him the flax
                        that<lb/>shirts &amp;c. were made of, with which he<lb/> appeared pleased.
                        We saw four men hoe-<lb/>ing corn; these we pointed to, telling him<lb/>they
                        were not squaws or women,- and that<lb/>was the way white people did their
                        work.</p>
                    <p>He knew our meaning which he expressed<lb/>by a lively smile.</p>
                    <p>We now parted with him, having<lb/>travelled together 170 miles, he going for<lb/>
                        <placeName key="canan">Canandaigua</placeName> and we for <geogName
                            key="mudcr">Maud Creek</geogName>.</p>
                    <p>Cornplanter had informed us he was a<lb/>sober man: we had opportunity to
                        prove the asser-<lb/>tion, being several days with him at the tavern<lb/>at
                            <placeName key="buffa">Buffalo</placeName>, where the Indians were
                        drinking<lb/>spirits, and I did not see him meddle with<lb/>any. We lodged
                        at <persName key="jsmit1">Jacob Smith</persName>'s<lb/>who has a mill, and
                        saw mill on a fine<lb/>natural full. 20 miles [to day].</p></q>
                <p>They spent the most of the <date when="1798-06-19">19th</date>, <date
                        when="1798-06-20">20th</date>,<lb/>and <date when="1798-06-21">21st</date>
                    visiting friends in this part<lb/>of <placeName key="newyo">New
                    York</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><geogName key="concr"/><date when="1798-06-22">22nd. 6
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <p> They travelled onward by <geogName key="concr">Cana-<lb/><pb n="88"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_088"/>wago Creek</geogName>, that runs into
                        <geogName key="oneil">Oneida lake</geogName>. <q>As we<lb/>decended a long
                        hill to this place, we killed a<lb/> rattlesnake about four feet long it lay
                        still in<lb/>the road, neither offered to attack nor run.</q></p>
                <q><p>About 11 miles from <placeName key="oneid">Oneida village</placeName>,
                        we<lb/>passed a well improved farm with a good<lb/>house, barn, and other
                        buildings, and a<lb/>large proportion of good timothy meadow,<lb/>belonging
                        to and in the possession of an<lb/>Indian. He keeps tavern, has his
                        sign<lb/>hanging out as common at public houses.</p>
                    <p>About six in the evening we arrived at<lb/>our Friend's settlement; found
                        them all well and<lb/>very glad to see us. <persName key="wgreg1">William
                            Gregory</persName> and wife, and<lb/><persName key="hjack2">Hannah
                            Jackson</persName>, having got there three weeks a-<lb/>go, after a
                        passage of 15 days [from <placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName>];<lb/>
                        <persName key="wgreg1">William</persName>'s chief view in coming was to set
                        up<lb/>the Smith's trade, and instruct some of the Indians<lb/>in that art:
                            <persName key="hjack2">Hannah Jackson</persName> was to open
                        a<lb/>school, and besides literature, was to instruct the<lb/> girls in
                        knitting, sewing &amp;c.</p>
                    <p>Neither of them have yet opened their occu-<lb/>pations, in part occasioned
                        by some unsettlement<lb/>or uneasiness in the Indians minds, in re-<lb/>gard
                        to the sale of some of their land, and the run-<lb/>ning of their lines,
                        cominissionirs having been<lb/>engaged in the business since the arrival of
                        our<lb/>Friends. </p></q>
            </div>
            <pb n="89" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_089"/>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="oneid"/><date when="1798-06-23">23rd 7
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q><p> We went on foot this morning, <persName key="jtayl1"
                            >Jacob<lb/>Taylor</persName> bearing us company, to see the <orgName
                            key="tuscarora">Tusca-<lb/>rora</orgName> and <orgName key="stockbridge"
                            >Stockbridge Indians</orgName>. They lay south<lb/>from this place up
                        the <geogName key="onecr">Oneida Creek</geogName>: the former<lb/>two miles
                        off and the latter four.</p>
                    <p>The land is good with considerable bot-<lb/>tom up the creek, on which the
                            <orgName key="tuscarora">Tuscaroras</orgName> are<lb/>scatteringly
                        settled, most of them having some<lb/>enclosure of wheat, corn, mowing
                        ground &amp;c.,<lb/>with a considerable number of cattle, and<lb/>some
                        horses, sheep and swine, which made a<lb/>pretty clever appearance.</p>
                    <p>On arriving at the <orgName key="stockbridge">Stockbridge</orgName>
                        settlement,<lb/>the prospect of their improvement was<lb/>more delightful,
                        They have a large street<lb/>between two and three miles in length,
                        which<lb/>ascends up the middle of a valley one mile or<lb/>more in width.
                        On each side of this street<lb/> their houses are erected, 20 or 30 perches
                        from each<lb/>other. The land on this street is mostly cleared,<lb/>and
                        fenced off in small lots, which were in<lb/>with wheat, corn, and grass for
                        mowing or pas-<lb/>ture. It is about 9 years since they settled here
                        in<lb/>the woods. These first houses are mostly small<lb/>and poor: some
                        have laterly put up pretty good<lb/>houses, and others are preparing for
                        it.</p>
                    <p>They have gardens near their doors, and con- <lb/><pb n="90"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_090"/> considerable stock of horses, some
                        swine and sheep.</p>
                    <p>On the east, near enough to supply them with<lb/>water, runs the <geogName
                            key="onecr">Oneida Creek</geogName>, and on the west<lb/>in the same
                        valley, is a small stream: so that<lb/>thiy are well supplied with it.</p>
                    <p>Towards the south end of their valley, they<lb/>have a grist, and a saw mill.
                        Their grist-<lb/>mill does considerable work for white people,<lb/>and there
                        is a large quantity of logs and<lb/>boards at the saw-mill.</p>
                    <p>We called to see most of the families<lb/>of note amongst them, and paid
                        short visits, with<lb/>which they manifested great satisfaction and
                        pleas-<lb/>ure, as most of them knew one of us who had<lb/>spent some weeks
                        in that place before.</p>
                    <p>We also visited a school kept by <persName key="jquin2"
                            >John<lb/>Quincy</persName>, a religious Indian man, who
                        conducted<lb/>it with becoming solidity and order, with which<lb/>we were
                        very much pleased.</p>
                    <p>Many of the women were solid, sen-<lb/>sible, and engaging. Their houses were
                        clean<lb/>with wooden floors and glass windows: them-<lb/>selves and
                        children mostly clean and neat,-<lb/>the men and boys were hoeing corn
                        &amp;c.</p>
                    <p>There appeared to be as much difference be-<lb/>tween <persName key="cornp2"
                            >Cornplanter</persName>'s <orgName key="seneca">people</orgName>, and
                        this nation, as<lb/>between this people and the better livers among
                        the<lb/>white people. We went to see their mill which, <lb/><pb n="91"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_091"/> appeared well constructed, and capable
                        of doing<lb/>a great deal of business. We also paid a visit<lb/>to <persName
                            key="jserg1">John Sergent</persName> their treasurer, presented our
                        bill<lb/>of advance toward their mill, and were inform-<lb/>ed there was not
                        enough money in his hands to<lb/>settle it: we also discovered that he had
                        in-<lb/>dulged hopes, notwithstanding the clearness of our<lb/>article, of
                        retaining a considerable part of what<lb/>was in his hands, for some other
                        appropriations<lb/>to him more desirable: we gave him to under-<lb/>stand,
                        when we entered into articles, we always<lb/>expected to fulfill them, on
                        our parts, and wished<lb/>others to do so by us: adding that our
                        design<lb/>was to assist and encourage them in getting<lb/>a mill, which we
                        had effected, and if govern-<lb/>ment had advanced nothing towards it, we
                        should<lb/>not have been hard on them, about their deficien-<lb/>cy in
                        regard to fulfilling their part of the agre-<lb/>ment, but as government had
                        now advanced<lb/>so considerable a sum, we were most easy to<lb/>receive our
                        own, agreeable to the article, and appro-<lb/>priate it to those of their
                        brethren who appeared<lb/>more necessitous. He readily acknowledged<lb/>the
                        justness of this conclusion, and agreed to at-<lb/>tend at <placeName
                            key="oneid">Oneida</placeName> on third day next, in company<lb/>with
                        such of the <orgName key="stockbridge">Stockbridge</orgName> chiefs and
                        others as<lb/>were concerned in this business in order to<lb/>have it
                        settled.</p><pb n="92" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_092"/>
                    <p> After this conference, we went to <persName key="haupa1">Captain
                            Hen-<lb/>dricks</persName>, where we were gladly welcomed, and
                        dined<lb/> with them, after which we drew a bond, had<lb/>it signed and
                        executed by <persName key="haupa1">Captain Hendricks</persName>,<lb/>for
                        $100, agreeable to the instruction, in <persName key="hdrin1">H.
                            Drinker</persName>'s<lb/>letter to <persName key="jtayl1">J.
                            Taylor</persName> and placed the same.</p>
                    <p>In the evening we had an opportunity<lb/>with most of the principal men and
                        women of<lb/>this tribe and the house of <persName key="jquin2">John
                            Quincy</persName>, in which<lb/>we were favored with some encouraging
                        commu-<lb/>nications to a number of tried individuals, as<lb/>well as some
                        affectionate and close reasoning<lb/>with some of their leading men, on the
                        serious<lb/>importance of their setting a good example<lb/>to the rest of
                        their people, not only in the<lb/>mere exteriors of civilization, such as
                        farming &amp;c.<lb/> but in the more interesting, that of a moral
                        and<lb/>good life; the necessity of a renewed dilligence<lb/>and
                        watchfulness herein, some recent instan-<lb/>ces but two sorrowfully
                        evince.</p>
                    <p>At the close of this opportunity, a chief on<lb/>behalf of the men present
                        made a pretty long<lb/>speech: in substance expressing their
                        thankful-<lb/>ness to the Good Spirit, who had put it into<lb/>our hearts to
                        remember them, when at a great<lb/>distance, and had preserved us in our way
                        thither:<lb/> that they felt themselves much strengthened<lb/>by our good
                        words - that they were sensible<lb/><pb n="93"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_093"/> they had done that which was not
                        right, yet<lb/>they hoped by the help of the Good Spirit they<lb/>would do
                        better for the future. They wished<lb/>the Quakers would continue to
                        remember them,<lb/>for they had found them to be true men, and<lb/>that they
                        really had the poor Indians' good at<lb/>heart. They wished the Good Spirit
                        would pre-<lb/>serve us on our way home to our families and<lb/>friends.
                        Then, after a short pause, a woman,<lb/>on behalf of the women present,
                        delivered a speech<lb/>much to the foregoing import, though we
                        thought<lb/>more weighty and nervous, She particularly ob-<lb/>served,
                            <q>that they now felt their minds encour-<lb/>aged, as it were, to begin
                            a new in the good<lb/>work of religion.</q> It was a favored
                        opportunity.</p>
                    <p>We returned to <persName key="haupa1">Captain Hendricks</persName>'<lb/>where
                        we lodged in a good clean bed.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="oneid"/><date when="1798-06-24">24th First
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q><p> After breakfast we returned<lb/>to our friends at <placeName key="oneid"
                            >Oneida</placeName>, sat with them in<lb/>their meeting: in the
                        afternoon we were visited by<lb/><persName key="jsken1"
                        >Schonadon</persName>, who informed us they were a going to<lb/>get back
                        tomorrow morning, to cover the smith's<lb/>shop, and that they would meet us
                        in council<lb/> after they had done. This day wrote to our friends<lb/>at
                            <placeName key="alleg1">Alleghany</placeName>, informing of our present
                        situa-<lb/>tion, and of the welfare of our friends here;<lb/>which we
                        forwarded to <placeName key="buffa">Buffalo</placeName> by an Indian
                            <lb/><pb n="94" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_094"/> from <geogName
                            key="grand">Grand river</geogName>.</p>
                    <p> Our young men here informed us there<lb/>was some improvement among the
                            <orgName key="oneida">Oneidas</orgName><lb/>since they came, although
                        not such as they wished<lb/>to have seen.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="oneida"/><date when="1798-06-25">25th 2nd
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q><p> The <orgName key="oneida">Oneidas</orgName> not having complied<lb/>with the
                        wishes of Friends, as expressed to them two<lb/>years ago, a council was,
                        this afternoon, held on<lb/>the subject. Tere are computed to be about 600
                        of<lb/>these Indians, all told, and are scattered over 10<lb/>or 12 miles,
                        though the largest number is with-<lb/>in two miles of this place, They have
                        a large<lb/>inclosure here of perhaps two hundred acres,<lb/>where they keep
                        their horses, cows, and swine, (They<lb/>have more horses than are
                        necessary,) and in the enclo-<lb/>sure are many of their houses. They plant
                        their<lb/>corn, sow their wheat and oats, and have their mead-<lb/>ow lots
                        without any fence.</p>
                    <p>It looks likely they will have to change this<lb/>mode of farming before
                        long, for they have sold<lb/>their land, and the white people are fast
                        setteling<lb/>on it. They have put up several houses this<lb/>spring, and we
                        saw a number of cattle in the woods<lb/>within two miles of the Indian's
                        corn.</p>
                    <p>There are several good houses among the<lb/>Indians. One of the chiefs has
                        his painted red,</p>
                    <p>The main road from <placeName key="alban">Albany</placeName> to the
                            western<lb/><pb n="95" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_095"/> country, goes
                        through the enclosure there being a<lb/>gate hung at each side. Many
                        travellers stop at<lb/>the Red House and lodge: it is called a tavern.</p>
                    <p>The fore part of this day was employed<lb/>in preparing some propositions,
                        and arranging<lb/>our business for the council in the afternoon.</p>
                    <p>About 4 o'clock most of the chiefs, and a<lb/>few of their people came
                        together; being seated<lb/>they observed, they were now got together,
                        and<lb/> were ready to hear what we had to say to<lb/>them, at the same time
                        apologizing for the<lb/>smallness of their council, by informing
                        that<lb/>many of their people were gone out a fishing &amp;c.</p>
                    <p>We opened the business by letting them<lb/>know that we were very sorry to
                        find that<lb/>our friends who came last, had been more<lb/>than three weeks
                        amongst them, and<lb/>during all that time, had never been<lb/> able to get
                        them together: or to form<lb/>any arrangements; or get any thing<lb/> done
                        respecting the business, which our<lb/>friend <persName key="wgreg1">William
                            Gregory</persName> was particularly<lb/>desirous to assist to them in,
                        We next pro-<lb/>ceeded to read, our said friends letter of
                        introduction<lb/>which was carefully explained to them by<lb/>
                        <persName key="ncusi1">Nicholas Chusick</persName> our present
                        interpreter.</p>
                    <p>We next proceeded to read the following<lb/><pb n="96"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_096"/> propositions which had this morning
                        been<lb/>mutually agreed upon and signed by all our<lb/>number, viz.</p>
                    <floatingText type="speech">
                        <body>
                            <opener><salute><emph rend="underline">Brothers of the Oneida
                                        Nation</emph></salute></opener>
                            <p>You have<lb/>now heard in the letter which has been read<lb/>to you,
                                that our friend <persName key="wgreg1">William Gregory</persName>
                                has<lb/>come amongst you in order to assist and in-<lb/>struct some
                                of your young men in the use-<lb/>ful trade of a smith. He wants no
                                pay<lb/>from you, or from government for his trouble; but<lb/>
                                wishes you to provide a shop, and some coal for<lb/>the purpose.
                                    (<persName key="ichap1">Captain Chapin</persName> having
                                offered<lb/>to find iron as usual,) and that two of your<lb/>young
                                men, who want to learn the trade, should<lb/>steadily attend at the
                                shop, to do such smith<lb/>work as you may want done, and he will
                                at-<lb/>tend with them and assist them, and show them<lb/>how to do
                                it; and in order to encourage these<lb/>young men to stick steadily
                                to the work, so as<lb/>to do all the smithing you want done, and
                                to<lb/>learn the trade well, before our friend wants<lb/>to go back
                                again to his own people, we think<lb/>you might allow them such part
                                of the money<lb/>as government use to give your blacksmith<lb/>as
                                will enable them to buy themselves vic-<lb/>tuals and clothes, while
                                they are learning the<lb/>trade and doing your work.</p>
                            <pb n="97" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_097"/>
                            <p> Brothers,<lb/> We hope you will get things ready<lb/>soon, and that
                                your young men will begin<lb/>soon in this business, for our friend
                                dont<lb/>want to stay a great while here, only just<lb/>long enough
                                to learn some of your young men<lb/>this good trade.</p>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>. You remember that
                                two<lb/>years ago we proposed to you that some of your<lb/>young
                                men, should work on the farm with<lb/>our friends, as apprentices,
                                in order to learn<lb/> how to farm the ground like the white
                                people,<lb/>so that they might raise a great deal of
                                grain,<lb/>grass &amp;c. off of your good land.</p>
                            <p>Now: brothers you know two years are gone,<lb/>and none of your young
                                men are come for-<lb/>ward to work with our friends, as we
                                pro-<lb/>posed, and we understand your young men<lb/>say, they can't
                                get victuals to stick steadily<lb/>to their work: and therefore they
                                cant do as<lb/>we proposed: we will now make you
                                another<lb/>offer.</p>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>, if three or four of your
                                sober<lb/>young men above the age of 16 years, will<lb/>come and
                                work with our friends on the<lb/>farm, and stay with them 6 months,
                                we<lb/>will agree to board and lodge them; they<lb/>must stick
                                steadily to work 5 days in the<lb/><pb n="98"
                                    facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_098"/> week: the other day they may
                                have to rest,<lb/>and to go and see their friends &amp;c.</p>
                            <p>They must be sober, and mind what<lb/>our friends say to them, and do
                                the work<lb/>as they tell them it should be done, and<lb/>not go off
                                and quit their work, without<lb/>speaking to our friends about it,
                                and<lb/> knowing whether they are willing; and<lb/>they must not go
                                out at nights to frolic-<lb/>ing, but stay about home so as to be
                                ready to<lb/>go to bed at our friends common bedtime:<lb/>and if
                                these young men stay the six months<lb/>out, and behave well in the
                                manner before<lb/>mentioned, then our friends will give each
                                of<lb/>them, stuff for one cloth coat, 2 shirts, one<lb/>pair of
                                cloth leggings; 5 bushels of wheat, 10<lb/>bushels of Indian corn,
                                and 10 bushels of po-<lb/>tatoes; and if they will then go to
                                farming<lb/>for themselves; and their Chiefs will let them<lb/>have
                                separate lots of ground to fence for that<lb/>purpose, then our
                                friends will lend each of<lb/>them a plow with irons all completely,
                                for one<lb/>year, and by that time they may be able to get<lb/>some
                                for themselves and then they must be re-<lb/>turned, so that other
                                young beginners may<lb/>have them.</p>
                            <p> Brothers, We shall give a copy of these<lb/>propositions in writing,
                                signed with our names<lb/><pb n="99" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_099"
                                /> to your chiefs, and another copy will be left<lb/>with our
                                friends here, and if any of your<lb/> young men agree to begin to
                                work with<lb/>our friends as we propose they may set their<lb/>names
                                to these writings, so that both sides may<lb/> understand every
                                thing plain and clear, and<lb/>have it all in writing to keep our
                                memories<lb/>bright.</p>
                            <closer><dateline><date when="1798-06-25">6th month 25th
                                1798</date>.<placeName key="oneid"
                                    /></dateline>
                                <signed><list type="simple">
                                        <item><persName key="jshar1">Joshua
                                            Sharpless</persName>.</item>
                                        <item><persName key="jpier1">John Pierce</persName>.</item>
                                        <item><persName key="wgreg1">William
                                            Gregory</persName>.</item>
                                        <item><persName key="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName>.</item>
                                        <item><persName key="jthom2">Jona Thomas</persName>.</item>
                                    </list></signed></closer>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                    <p>After reading these propositions, we let them<lb/>know in very plain terms
                        that we were sensibly<lb/>affected with the manifest coldness and
                        in-<lb/>attention which they had latterly appeared among-<lb/>st them
                        towards our friends; the ungrateful<lb/>whisperings and surmises that they
                        had given<lb/>way to relative to our having a design to take<lb/>away their
                        lands from them: reminding them<lb/>of the various steps we had taken
                        amongst<lb/>them from the beginning: the great expense<lb/>we were at in
                        mantaining our friends here a-<lb/>mongst them; the improvements we
                        were<lb/>making on their land, which they saw with <lb/><pb n="100"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_100"/> their own eyes; the wheat and clover
                        they saw<lb/>growing where there use to be none; the barn<lb/>that was
                        built, and the house that was on its<lb/>way; that all these things could
                        not be done<lb/>without a great deal of money, that we had<lb/> never asked
                        them for any, nor should:<lb/>that we had never asked them for any of
                        their<lb/>land: nor would be take it of them, if<lb/>they would offer it to
                        us: that we had told<lb/>them before, and would now tell them
                        again,<lb/>that whenever they were tired of us, and<lb/>wished us away only
                        to tell us so, and we<lb/>would leave both their land and their<lb/>country:
                        that we had no inducement<lb/>to stay here among them, spending<lb/>both our
                        money and time, but purely for<lb/>their good.</p>
                    <p>Shortly after these observations<lb/>their speaker, Christian, spoke to us
                        as<lb/>follows.</p><floatingText type="speech">
                            <body><dateline><date when="1798-06-25"/><placeName key="oneid"/></dateline>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>, we will say a few
                                words<lb/>to you about the blacksmith which is<lb/>come from
                                    <placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName> to instruct us
                                in<lb/>the trade; you know we don't govern our<lb/>young men; if
                                they ain't willing to<lb/>come, we cant force them: but we
                                want<lb/>to know how he intends to work: whether<lb/>for the Indians
                                in common, or whether he <lb/><pb n="101"
                                    facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_101"/> will do so much a day, and
                                give it into the hands<lb/>of their chiefs to be divided amongst the
                                people,<lb/>adding, that if he worked for the Indians<lb/>in
                                general, it would be too hard for him, for<lb/>they would be always
                                plaguing him.</p>
                            <p>So this we replied,</p>
                            <p>That the design<lb/>of our friend in coming here was to
                                instruct<lb/>their young men, and show them how to<lb/>do their
                                work, and not to do it all him<lb/>self: and though we did not wish
                                them<lb/>to <emph rend="underline">force</emph> their young men: yet
                                if they could<lb/>not be prevailed upon to come forward in<lb/>the
                                way proposed, our friend's prospect would<lb/>not be answered, and
                                he would therefore<lb/>be likely to make but a short stay
                                with<lb/>them: but as to the <emph rend="underline">manner</emph> of
                                working,<lb/>our friend would leave that to the chiefs</p>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                    <p>Their speaker then proceeded as<lb/>follows.</p>
                    <floatingText type="speech">
                        <body><dateline><date when="1798-06-25"/><placeName key="oneid"/></dateline>
                            <p>
                                <emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>, We are very glad to
                                hear<lb/>again the same words which you said to<lb/>us two years
                                ago, and we are now of the same<lb/>mind we were then: we remember
                                your<lb/>words and we believe you are a true people.<lb/> We have
                                heard our fathers tell, that the<lb/>Quakers were always friends of
                                the Indians: <lb/><pb n="102" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_102"/> and
                                what they told us when we wer boys<lb/>we find it to be <emph
                                    rend="underline">true</emph>
                                <emph rend="underline">now</emph> we are old men.</p>
                            <p>
                                <emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>.<lb/> We are very glad and
                                happy<lb/>to hear that your minds continue the same<lb/>towards us
                                about learning to farm: we be-<lb/>lieve it would be good for us,
                                and we will<lb/>try to do what you propose.</p>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>.<lb/>Now it is very true,
                                there<lb/>are some bad people, who have spoke against<lb/>you, that
                                you had a mind to take away<lb/>our land: and some times when our
                                minds<lb/>were not right, we believed such talk, and<lb/>this made
                                our minds feel very ugly, but <emph rend="underline">now</emph>
                                we<lb/>are convinced, and <emph rend="underline">sorry</emph> we
                                believed such<lb/>things: and we are fully satisfied, that you
                                are<lb/>true people, and we will continue to be of
                                this<lb/>mind.</p>
                            <p>Brothers, we always attend to what you<lb/>said from the beginning,
                                we know you<lb/>want us to cultivate the ground so that<lb/>we may
                                live comfortably, and our wishes<lb/> and desires are to what you
                                say so far as we<lb/>are able, and to learn the farming
                                business:<lb/>we, the chiefs are determined to do all that<lb/> we
                                are able; but if we dont do all that you<lb/>would wish, we hope you
                                wont get discouraged,<lb/><pb n="103"
                                    facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_103"/> but continue to do whatever is
                                in your minds:<lb/>and if we dont improve, the fault will be
                                our<lb/> own, we cant blame you.</p>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>.<lb/>We will do all we can
                                about<lb/>the blacksmith and about the farming: we<lb/>cant force
                                our young men, but we will try<lb/>all round, all of us will try to
                                get some young<lb/>men to learn this trade, and to learn
                                farming.</p>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>.<lb/>Now we thank you for the
                                pains<lb/>you have taken for poor Indians, and we thank<lb/>you for
                                what you have said to us: and we will<lb/>have council amongst
                                ourselves tomorrow, after<lb/>we have tried what we can do; and then
                                we<lb/>will speak to you again about it.</p>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>.<lb/>This is all we got to say
                                at pres-<lb/>ent.</p>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                    <p>We expressed our satisfaction with<lb/>what they had said, and then the
                        council concluded.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="oneid"/><date when="1798-06-26">26th, 3rd
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q><p>Agreeable to the arrangements of<lb/>7th day last, <persName key="jserg1">John
                            Sergent</persName> in company with<lb/><persName key="jquin2">John
                            Quincy</persName> and <persName key="squan1">Solomon</persName>, from
                            <orgName key="stockbridge">Stockbridge</orgName><lb/>came to <placeName
                            key="oneid">Oneida</placeName>, in order to settle the accounts<lb/>
                        respecting the mill Friends built there,<lb/>which was amicably done.</p>
                    <p>About 5 o'clock this evening the <orgName key="oneida">Oneida</orgName>
                            chiefs<lb/><pb n="104" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_104"/> and a number of
                        their people again assembled in<lb/>council, and after spending more than an
                        hr.<lb/>in conference amongst themselves, they spoke<lb/>to us to the
                        following affect.</p>
                    <floatingText type="speech">
                        <body><dateline><date when="1798-06-26"/><placeName key="oneid"/></dateline>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>.<lb/>You have heard what we
                                said to<lb/>you yesterday, and what is still on our minds.</p>
                            <p>We are very glad you have taken such<lb/>pains to come so far to help
                                poor Indians,<lb/>and we will try to fulfill all that you
                                desire<lb/>of us.</p>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>. We have been trying
                                amongst<lb/>ourselves to do as you proposed yesterday, and
                                we<lb/>find one man that is willing to learn the black<lb/>smith
                                trade, and we find one young lad that will<lb/>come out of his own
                                mind to learn farming:<lb/>He heard what you said yesterday in
                                council, and<lb/>he spoke to his parents, and tell them he wants
                                to<lb/>go and learn farming, and do as you say, and his<lb/>parents
                                are willing, and he will come directly.</p>
                            <p>Brothers,<lb/>Now you must not think hard of<lb/> us because we have
                                not got so many young men<lb/>as you proposed, we have tried to get
                                more, but<lb/>most all our people from tother end of the
                                town<lb/>are gone out a fishing, when they come home, we<lb/>think
                                we shall get some more: and we will do<lb/>the best we can.</p>
                            <pb n="105" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_105"/>
                            <p>
                                <emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>.<lb/> You mentioned about a
                                blacksmith<lb/>shop, and about coal, now we intend to go<lb/>at the
                                shop early tomorrow morning: we<lb/>have got the bark ready to cover
                                it; and we<lb/>shall have it done tomorrow: and some will<lb/>go to
                                drawing wood for coal.</p>
                            <p><emph rend="underline">Brothers</emph>. This is all we got to
                                say.</p>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                    <p>We expressed our satisfaction with what<lb/>they had said, and let them know
                        we were<lb/>very glad to see their chiefs of the same<lb/>mind with us in
                        this business, and we<lb/>were in hopes they would continue to be
                        of<lb/>this mind. We closed with renewedly<lb/>reminding them of the
                        obligations they<lb/>were under to our friends, who remain here<lb/>who have
                        left all their near friends and con-<lb/>nections, to come and live amongst
                        them,<lb/>purely from a desire to do them good: and<lb/>earnestly entreating
                        them to keep this fresh<lb/>in their minds, and then we were certain
                        they<lb/>would be attentive and kind to them at all<lb/>times. The
                        conference ended satisfactorily.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="oneid"/><date when="1798-06-27">27th 4th
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q><p> This morning about 20 <orgName key="oneida">Oneidas</orgName>,<lb/>amongst
                        whom were 4 or 5 of their principal chiefs,<lb/>got early to work at the
                        smith's shop, and some<lb/><pb n="106" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_106"/> to
                        hauling and chopping wood for coal,<lb/>that before noon they had a pretty
                        commodi-<lb/>ous shop covered, and all ready for building<lb/>the fireplace,
                        and a considerable quantity of<lb/> wood ready for the pit.</p>
                    <p>The lad also that proposed engaging in<lb/>farming, entered into work with
                        our friends<lb/>this morning. That things now wear a<lb/>more encouraging
                        appearance: and our friends<lb/><emph rend="underline">here</emph>, sensibly
                        feel it to their relief and<lb/>encouragement.</p>
                    <p>It now looks likely we may set off<lb/>home, to day, which feels <emph
                            rend="underline">very</emph> pleasant.</p></q>
                <p>One says, <q>My mind for the most part<lb/>has been easy <del>for the most
                            part</del> about my<lb/>family and concerns at home ever since I
                        left<lb/> them: but our business appearing to be gone<lb/>through the
                        draught home feels strong.</q></p>
                <q><p>About 1 o'clock took an affection-<lb/>ate farewell of our Friends, having
                        before<lb/>taken leave of the Indians, and set off to <placeName key="newha"
                            >New<lb/>Hartford</placeName> - 17 miles - thence to the <geogName
                            key="mohaw">Mohawk river</geogName><lb/>at <placeName key="fschy">Fort
                            Schuyler</placeName> 4 miles, where we passed through <lb/><pb n="107"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_107"/> another town and crossed the
                        river.</p>
                    <p>
                        <date when="1798-06-23">Last 7th day</date> while we were at <placeName
                            key="stock">Stockbridge</placeName><lb/>a violent hail storm passed
                        through the coun-<lb/>try, a little to the north of us. Its
                        direction<lb/>was nearly east, and its extent twenty miles,<lb/>and from one
                        to two in breadth.</p>
                    <p>As we returned to <placeName key="oneid">Oneida</placeName> next
                        morn-<lb/>ing, we beheld its distructive effects on<lb/>corn, oats, &amp;c.
                        This day for more than 5<lb/>miles it was affecting to see the
                        distruction<lb/>it had made. Whole fields of wheat were en-<lb/>tirely cut
                        off so that we could not see one<lb/>head standing, Corn, flax, and oats
                        fared<lb/>little better. Peas in the gardens and fields,<lb/>(acres being
                        sown here) were entirely destroyed.</p>
                    <p>Large fields of timothy were so broken down,<lb/>that they smelled like fresh
                        hay.</p>
                    <p> Poke bushes, the stalks as thick as rake<lb/>handles, were knocked all to
                        pieces, In short<lb/>all vegetation where the storm reached,<lb/>suffered
                        much: the fences and stumps<lb/>were much marked, and the windows
                        of<lb/>houses were very much destroyed.</p></q>
                <p>This night Our Travellers lodged at<lb/><persName key="ipray1">Isaac
                        Brayton</persName>'s, three miles from <placeName key="fschy">Fort
                        Schuyler</placeName></p>
                <q><p>Here we had good accommodations both<lb/>for our selves and our horses, which
                        is the<lb/>first public inn, we have met with, since <lb/><pb n="108"
                            facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_108"/>we left <placeName key="pitts"
                            >Pittsburgh</placeName> of which this could be<lb/> said.</p></q>
                <p><persName key="jshar1">Joshua Sharpless</persName> says, <q>I have
                        often<lb/>admired since we came on this river, (the<lb/><geogName
                            key="mohaw">Mohawk</geogName>.) to see such large heaps of ashes<lb/>
                        remaining untouched, where potashes<lb/>have been made. It seems to
                        convey<lb/>that the people have no idea, that the<lb/>land would be
                        benefited by spreading<lb/>them over it, or otherwise that they are<lb/>too
                        lazy to do it. Some men were hoe-<lb/>ing very poor corn in a field where,
                        I<lb/>had no doubt there were 300 or 400 loads<lb/> of ashes in a heap. I
                        called aloud to them<lb/>to know why they did not spread that heap of
                        ashes<lb/>over the field, and so have good corn, and not be<lb/>hoeing such
                        poor stuff. They stood like men<lb/>amazed;- made no reply;- and we passed
                        on.</q></p>
                <p>A few miles further we saw large potash<lb/>works works close on the river, so
                    that when<lb/>the ashes were thrown out of the tubs, they<lb/>went into the
                    water and were driven off<lb/>with freshets, <q>Our Travellers</q> kept
                    moving<lb/>on through Oldridges in the <placeName key="gefla">German
                        flats</placeName>,<lb/>to <placeName key="conol">Conoley's
                        Tavern</placeName>, 45 miles where they lodged;<lb/>had good accommodations
                    for themselves, but<lb/>rather poor for their horses, pasture being light.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="conol"/><date when="1798-06-29">29th</date></dateline>
                <p> A ride of 31 1/2 miles took them to the<lb/><pb n="109"
                        facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_109"/>
                    <geogName key="mohaw">Mohawk river</geogName> which they crossed in a
                    boat,<lb/>after which a ride of 5 miles brought them to a<lb/>public house which
                        <persName key="jpier1">J. P.</persName> thus discribes.</p>
                <p><q>This is a poor inn, poor land, poor land-<lb/>lord, poor landlady, poor
                        accommodations;<lb/>may I not be under the necessity of calling<lb/>here
                        often.</q></p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="checkPlace"/><date when="1798-06-30">30th 7th
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <p>Their next stopping place looked dis-<lb/>couraging to weary travellers, but
                        <emph rend="underline">they</emph> fared<lb/>better than they expected,
                    while their horses fared<lb/>
                    <emph rend="underline">well</emph>. This part of <placeName key="newyo">New
                        York</placeName> state at<lb/>that time seemed to have more
                    licenced<lb/>taverns than otherwise, and Our Travellers<lb/>frequently speak of
                    oats being measured in<lb/>rum quarts. One section near 100 miles in
                    length<lb/>almost every house on the road was a Tavern, yet<lb/>the traveller
                    must make long stages to be any<lb/>ways comfortably accommodated. It is
                    relieving<lb/>to note that as they approached <placeName key="alban"
                        >Albany</placeName> there<lb/> seemed to be an improvement in these
                    re-<lb/>spects, and 17 miles beyond that capitol,<lb/> (that is east of it) at
                        <placeName key="leadm">Leadman's inn</placeName>, they had<lb/>good
                    accommodations, both for man and<lb/>beast. Another stage of 19 miles finds
                    them<lb/>at <placeName key="catsk1">Catskill</placeName> Bridge, where is an
                    elegant house<lb/>and good pasture, in other respects nothing<lb/>to boast of.
                        <q>Our oats were measured in rum<lb/>quarts as usual in many places in this
                            <lb/><pb n="110" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_110"/> state. The query is,
                        Is the regulation of public<lb/>inns, a subject unworthy the attention
                        of<lb/>the legislature? must the farmer smart<lb/>for it if he offers a
                        pound of butter for sale<lb/>a few grains too light, and may the
                        tavern<lb/>keeper with impunity trick honest travellers<lb/>out of their
                        money, by selling three quarts<lb/>of oats for four,?</q></p>
                <q><p>From here we proceeded to <placeName key="porre">Porren's
                            ta-<lb/>vern</placeName> 11 miles where we lodged. This ap-<lb/>pears
                        like a full handed Dutchman plenty<lb/>of good wholesome fare, both for man
                        and beast,<lb/>but little attention to please or oblige, At our<lb/>next
                        stop they were obliging, &amp; gentle accommodation</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-07-01">7th Month 1st First day.</date></dateline>
                <q><p> We would have been<lb/>glad to have reached a Friends meeting to<lb/>day, but
                        found it impracticable, therefore<lb/>thought best of travelling. We arrived
                            at<lb/><persName key="sbald1">Samuel Baldwin</persName>'s about 4
                        o'clock, weary and<lb/>glad we were got to a Friends house. The
                        weather<lb/>lately has been very warm, and we having travelled<lb/>hard from
                            <placeName key="oneid">Oneida</placeName>, both we and our
                        horses<lb/>wanted rest, we concluded to lay by here a<lb/>day or two, get
                        them shod, and help their<lb/>backs which were a little sore.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-07-02">2nd, 2nd day.</date></dateline>
                <q><p> This morning concluded to<lb/>pay a visit to our ancient friend <persName
                            key="ehall1">Edward<lb/><pb n="111" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_111"/>
                            Hallock</persName>, about 9 miles east of our present<lb/>quarters,
                        being offered fresh horses for that<lb/> purpose, which we accordingly did
                        to mu-<lb/>tual satisfaction, and riturned in the<lb/>evening. When near the
                            <geogName key="nrive">North River</geogName> about<lb/>a mile before we
                        got to <persName key="ehall1">Edwards</persName>, we hat a<lb/> very
                        beautiful and extensive prospect for<lb/>about 20 miles over the river, and
                        as far<lb/>each way up and down the stream.</p>
                    <p>The face of the country appeared to de-<lb/>scend toward the river, and being
                        mostly<lb/>improved, the wheat and pasture fields, with<lb/>large houses,
                        barns &amp;c. intermingled with<lb/>sheets of the river which presented in
                        places,<lb/>together with the town of <placeName key="pough"
                            >Poughkeepsie</placeName> 4<lb/>miles up the river on its opposite
                        shore,<lb/>made the landscape truly delightful.</p>
                    <p>This is a warm day.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-07-03">3rd 3rd day.</date></dateline>
                <q><p> This morning attended to getting our<lb/>horses shod with a prospect of
                        setting out in<lb/>the afternoon, but were prevented by a thunder<lb/>storm
                        and rain.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-07-04">4th 4th day.</date></dateline>
                <q><p> About 5 this morning set out<lb/>from our agreeable quarters, travelled about
                        18<lb/>miles to --'s tavern where we bated our horses<lb/>and breakfasted,
                        here is a pretty good house, but<lb/>accommodations and attendance
                        indiferent. <lb/><pb n="112" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_112"/>thence through
                            <placeName key="goshe">Geshen</placeName> to --'s 12 miles, where<lb/>we
                        baited; a good house, but rough landlord, then<lb/>on another 12 miles to Dr
                        --'s, a poor place<lb/>both for man and horse, but here we lodged<lb/>having
                        travelled 40 miles. We are now in<lb/><placeName key="newje">New
                            Jersey</placeName>. 3 or 4 miles south of the <placeName key="newyo"
                            >New<lb/>York</placeName> line, having travelled 500 miles
                            in<lb/><placeName key="newyo">New York State</placeName>.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="newje"/><date when="1798-07-05">5th 5th
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q><p> Traveled to <persName key="bscho1">Benjamine Schooley</persName>'s<lb/>11
                        miles where we dined: he and his wife<lb/>are exemplary Friends. Thence to
                            <persName key="jlund1">Jacob<lb/>Lundy</persName>s 16 miles, This has
                        been the worst<lb/>stage for our horses that we have met with<lb/>since we
                        left <placeName key="oneid">Oneida</placeName>, and not very good
                        for<lb/>our selves. We noticed a Dutch plough<lb/>with one handle which
                        stands nearly up-<lb/>right: a very short beam is almost<lb/>the only plough
                        that is used for 200 miles back.<lb/>It appears to work easy both for horse
                        and<lb/>ploughman and does the work pretty neatly.</p></q>
                <p><q>To day we crossed the <geogName key="wallk">Wallkill
                        River</geogName>,<lb/>fifty miles higher up than we crossed<lb/>it last
                        First day: yet the stream is<lb/>so large as to have a bridge erected
                        on<lb/>it a little above the fording place.<lb/>In about 7 miles further, we
                        crossed the<lb/><geogName key="pauli">Paulinskill</geogName> which was the
                        first water<lb/><pb n="113" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_113"/>we met with
                        that ran into the <geogName key="delaw">Delaware</geogName>,<lb/>having gone
                        round the head branches of<lb/>said river as well as those of the <geogName
                            key="susqu">Susque<lb/>hanna</geogName>.</q> This hard days work only
                        brought<lb/><q>our travellers</q> 27 miles nearer their homes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-07-06">6th 6th day.</date><placeName key="kingw"/></dateline>
                <p>
                    <q>Breakfasted at our lodgings, and<lb/>proceeded to <persName key="hclift1"
                            >Henry Clifton</persName>'s where we lodged.<lb/>This days stage, 34
                        miles. We are now at <placeName key="kingw">Kingwood</placeName>.</q></p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="kingw"/><date when="1798-07-07">7th 7th
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q><p> We travelled on, and on, past <placeName key="buckm">Bucking<lb/>ham meeting
                            house</placeName> to our kind Friends<lb/><persName key="jperr1">Jacob
                            Perry</persName>'s 30 miles, where we got our dinners<lb/>and rested a
                        while. Thence to <persName key="ecomf1">Ezra Comfort</persName>'s<lb/>near
                            <placeName key="plymo">Plymouth meeting house</placeName>. 12
                        miles.<lb/>where we lodged, and were kindly entertained.</p></q>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="plymo"/><date when="1798-07-08">8th First
                    day.</date></dateline>
                <q>
                    <p> Breakfasted at our lodging<lb/>and proceed on to <placeName key="willm"
                            >Willistown meeting house</placeName>,<lb/>15 miles, to <persName
                            key="agarr1">Amos Garretts</persName>, before meeting.<lb/>[<persName
                            key="agarr1">Amos</persName> was a brother in law of <persName
                            key="jshar">Joshua Sharpless</persName>.]<lb/>he says, Here I heard from
                        my dear wife and<lb/>family, being the first accound I had from<lb/>them
                        since I left home: and I felt truly<lb/>thankful I was so near my own
                        habitation,<lb/>and among my near relatives and inti-<lb/>mate friends, We
                        returned here from meet-<lb/>ing and got our dinners, then set off home-
                            <lb/><pb n="114" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_114"/> wards. Our roads
                        parting on the way, we<lb/>took an affectionate farewell of each other,
                        hav-<lb/>ing been together 10 weeks, wanting one day:<lb/>and travelled more
                        than 1200 miles, in near<lb/>unity and Christian fellowship, through
                        some<lb/>proving dispensations.</p>
                    <p>Got home in the evening, and found<lb/>my dear wife and family all well, by
                        whom I was<lb/>gladly received, and I felt thankful I was got<lb/>once more
                        among them.</p></q>
                <p><persName key="jpier1">John Pierce</persName> reached his home about 4
                    o'clock<lb/>that evening, and found his wife and family<lb/>well, also.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="115" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_115"/>
            <div type="entry">
                <p> for a moment- and<lb/> Let us imagine our selves in their
                        situation<lb/><del>and</del> reflect that thy have now been from home<lb/>8
                    weeks, and it will be nearly two more before<lb/>thy can meet their beloved
                    families, and they have<lb/>not heard from them since they left them.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="116" facs="HV_IC_1798_1799_Page_116"/>
            <div type="entry">
                <p> It may be well here to remark, though<lb/>not as a part of either of the
                    accounts<lb/>in hand, that the wealth of some, is a<lb/>reward, not only of
                    their honesty and<lb/> persevering industry, but also of their<lb/>economy and
                    endeavors to save their<lb/> earnings as much as may be; only<lb/>spending their
                    money for useful and<lb/>necessary things. Then when they see<lb/>a friend or
                    brother in need, and it seems<lb/><emph rend="underline">right</emph> to help
                    him, they have the means<lb/>to contribute to his relief. </p>
            </div>
        </body>


    </text>
</TEI>
