<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei-print.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="global.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>Joel Swayne Diary: Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Haverford College Quaker Collection</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>FHL staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Journal transcribed by</resp>
                    <name>Crowd-sourced</name>


                </respStmt>

            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 152 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Haverford College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street/>
                    <addrLine>Haverford, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode/>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>This work is the property of Haverford College Special Collections. It may be
                        copied freely by individuals for personal use, research, and teaching
                        (including distribution to classes) as long as this statement of
                        availability is included in the text. It may be linked to freely in Internet
                        editions of all kinds, including for—profit works.</p>
                    <p>Publishers, libraries, and other information providers interested in
                        providing this text in a commercial or non—profit product or from an
                        information server must contact Haverford College for licensing and cost
                        information.</p>
                    <p> Scholars interested in changing or adding to these texts by, for example,
                        creating a new edition of the text (electronically or in print) with
                        substantive editorial changes, may do so only with the permission of
                        Haverford College. This is the case whether the new publication will be made
                        available at a cost or free of charge.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2015">2015</date>
                <idno type="local">hv_swaynej_diary_1798</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Native Americans and Quakers: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Haverford College Quaker and Special Collections</institution>
                        <collection/>
                        <idno/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>86 pp. (1 volume)</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Joel Swayne Diary manuscript is housed in the Haverford College Quaker and
                    Special Collections</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> The transcribers and editor attempted to render the author’s orthography and
                    grammar as they appear on the page of his journal, even when the author’s own
                    spelling and usage are inconsistent. Additionally, many questions remain about
                    spelling the names of his Quaker acquaintances, individual Native Americans who
                    populate his journal, and Indian villages and towns. The transcribers and editor
                    attempted to remain faithful to the author’s Anglicized spellings in all cases. </p>
                <p>The author of the original journal does not include page numbers on his
                    manuscript; the page numbers have been interpolated by the transcribers to
                    correspond with the manuscript sheets.</p>
            </editorialDecl>

        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written in <date when="1809">1809</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Society of Friends</item>


                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>

        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item>
                    <date when="2016"/></item>

            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            
            <div type="undetermined">
                <pb n="1" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_001"/>
                <pb n="2" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_002"/>
                <pb n="3" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_003"/>
                <pb n="4" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_004"/>
            </div>
            
            <div type="narrative">

                <pb n="5" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_005"/>
                <head>Some account of my journey to<lb/> the <orgName key="seneca">Seneca</orgName>
                    Nation of Indians and<lb/> residence amongst that People</head>
                <p>After passing through various exercises on this<lb/> occasion and witnessing a
                    full submision to the Divine<lb/> will in regard to giving up all to follow
                    him<lb/> where ever he might be pleased to lead me; and<lb/> obtaining the
                    aprobation of our Monthly Meet<lb/>ing at <orgName key="meetlondon"
                        >Londongrove</orgName> and a Certificate from<lb/> thence to the Committee
                    on Indian affairs at<lb/> Philadelphia which was accepted and, I left at<lb/>
                    liberty to proceed in company with <persName key="hsimm1">Henry
                        Simmons</persName><lb/> and <persName key="hjack1">Halliday
                        Jackson</persName> who also had prospects of<lb/> going to reside sometime
                    amongst the <orgName key="seneca">Seneca</orgName> In<lb/>dians;</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>Accordingly on the <date when="1798-04-30">30th of 4 mo.
                        1798</date><placeName key="lanca"/></dateline>
                <p>I left the place of my abode in East Marlborough<lb/> and rode about three miles
                    to a friends house<lb/> where according to appointment I met with<lb/>
                    <persName key="hjack1">Halliday Jackson</persName>, and the night following we <lb/>
                    <pb n="6" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_006"/> reached and lodged at the House of
                        <persName key="agibb1">Abraham<lb/> Gibbons</persName> in <placeName
                        key="lanca">Lancaster</placeName> County where <persName key="hsimm1"
                        >Henry<lb/> Simmons</persName> met us, also <persName key="jpier1">John
                        Pierce</persName> and <persName key="jshar1">Joshua<lb/>
                        Sharpless</persName> who had given up to accompany us<lb/> to the <orgName
                        key="seneca">Seneca</orgName> Country.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-05-01">1st of 5 mo.</date><placeName key="wrigh"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> being five in company we all set<lb/> forward on our journey and lodged the
                    night<lb/> following at <persName key="wwrig1">William Wrights</persName> at
                    Wrights<lb/> ferry on <placeName key="susqu">Susquehannah</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-05-02">2nd of the month </date><placeName
                        key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>crossed the River and rode to<lb/>
                    <placeName key="york3">York</placeName>, thence piloted by <persName
                        key="wkirk1">W.Kirk</persName> (a promising<lb/> your Man) to <persName
                        key="jgarr1">John Garritsons</persName> and <persName key="iever1"
                        >Isaac<lb/> Everots</persName> where we lodged that night and believe<lb/>
                    were heartily welcome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-05-03"> 3rd of the month </date><placeName key="redst1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>being now out of the neighbour<lb/>hood of Friends I shall not be particular
                    noteing<lb/> the stages till we crops the Mountains, we<lb/> trailed about 35
                    miles a Day along very rough<lb/> and Mountainous roads still we got to
                        <placeName key="conne">Connell<lb/>Ville</placeName> on the banks of the
                        <placeName key="yough">Yoxhioyany River</placeName> in<lb/> the settlement
                    of <placeName key="redst1">Readstone</placeName>, some of those high<lb/>
                    mountains whose summits seemed to<lb/> mingle with the Clouds afforded a
                    prospect truly<lb/> gratifying to me and displayed the wonderful world<lb/> of
                    Omnipotence <del>more <gap/></del><lb/>
                    <pb n="7" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_007"/><del><gap/></del> the next<lb/> night
                    we lodged at the House of a worthy friend<lb/>
                    <persName key="tgibs1">Thomas Gibson</persName>, and were respectfully
                    entertained,<lb/> having been from home eight Days and traversed<lb/> upwards of
                    250 miles by way of <placeName key="shipp">Shippensburg</placeName><lb/>
                    <placeName key="stras">Strausburg</placeName> and <placeName key="bedfo"
                        >Bedford</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-05-07"> 7th of the month </date><placeName
                        key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>three of our company went to<lb/>
                    <persName key="rcadw1">Reece Cadwalders</persName>, <persName key="hjack1"
                        >halliday jackson</persName> and myself to<lb/>
                    <placeName key="uniont">Union Town</placeName> to see some of our old
                    acquaintance<lb/> that lived thereabouts, <persName key="hjack1"
                        >Halliday</persName> and I parted at<lb/>
                    <persName key="wdix1">William Dixons</persName> and I went to see my
                    brothers<lb/> and Sisters that lived near that place, we<lb/> were much rejoiced
                    to see each other and I had a good<lb/> degree of satisfaction in my visit, yet
                    my stay was<lb/> not as long as would have been desirable, in the course<lb/> of
                    my journey through Readstone I observed that the<lb/> land is of a supervisor
                    quality, abounding with a great<lb/> quantity of excellent timber such as Black
                    Walnut<lb/> Hickory Wild Cherry and Sugar Maple from<lb/> the latter many of the
                    inhabitants supply themselves<lb/> with sugar and molasses of an excellent
                    quality which<lb/> is a great advantage to a new settled county.<lb/> Stone Coal
                    and Iron Ore of an excellent quality<lb/> abounds plentifully in this settlement
                    and<lb/> appears to afford encouraging prospects for Iron <lb/>
                    <pb n="8" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_008"/> works and Blacksmithing. Limestone
                    is also<lb/> plenty here and the whole<lb/> is encouragement for settlers, yet
                    alas, there is one<lb/> abominable practice which the inhabitants<lb/> has got
                    into which I think has been a great hurt<lb/> to them and their Country, that is
                    destroying<lb/> the grain that was given them for the support<lb/> of Life to
                    make an article which tends very<lb/> much to destroy both the lives and Souls
                    of men,<lb/> and set up the Kingdom of Antichrist, I have<lb/> often thought
                    that Spirituous liquors is one of the<lb/> strongest weapons the Adversary has
                    to make<lb/> use of in order for the upholding of his Kingdom,<lb/> for when
                    people are enticed to drink large draughts<lb/> of it, how easy they are lead in
                    to an innumer<lb/>able catalogue of evils such as gambling, lying,
                    swear<lb/>ing, fighting, and sometimes to murder.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-05-09"> 9th of the month </date><placeName
                        key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>set forward again accompanyed<lb/> by my brother and two brothers in law to<lb/>
                    <persName key="rcadw1">Reece Cadwaldies</persName> near <placeName key="brown"
                        >Browns Ville</placeName> where ac<lb/>cording to appointment I met with my
                    travelling<lb/> companions it being friends Meeting Day we<lb/> attended their
                    meeting after which dined at<lb/> our kind friends who heartily approbated
                    us<lb/> in our present undertaking and was very <lb/>
                    <pb n="9" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_009"/> kind and was friendly as was his
                    Wife and Family, after<lb/> Dinner crossed the <placeName key="monon"
                        >Monongahela River</placeName> and<lb/> rode about 13 miles to an Inn where
                    we lodged that<lb/> nigh and had but poor accomodations, tho<lb/> perhaps the
                    best the House could afford.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-05-10"> 10th of the month </date><placeName key="pitts"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>traveled about 24 miles down<lb/> the aforesaid <placeName key="monon">
                        River</placeName> and crossed again at <placeName key="pitts"
                        >Pittsburg</placeName><lb/> and took up our quarters at <persName
                        key="wmorr1">Wm Morrows</persName><lb/> Tavern where we met with good
                    entertainment<lb/> 11th of the month we spent out time in<lb/> procuring some
                    Goods to send by Water<lb/> to the Indian Country, some of our com<lb/>pany went
                    to the Garrison respecting our<lb/> Goods that was sent from Philadelphia
                    and<lb/> upon inquiry found they had arrived a few<lb/> days before and
                        <persName key="gwilk2">General Wilkinson</persName> employed<lb/> a wagon at
                    the States expense to haul them <lb/>to the River and a Boat to <del/> to
                    carry<lb/> them from thence to our intended settlement.<lb/> 12th of the month
                    went again to the Garrison to<lb/> see <persName key="gwilk2">General
                        Wilkinson</persName> who appeared to have<lb/> much good will for us, and
                    the cause in<lb/> which we were engaged, he gave us consider<lb/>able
                    information respecting the Indians <lb/>
                    <pb n="10" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_010"/> and an order on <persName
                        key="cfowl1">George Fowler</persName>, deputy<lb/> Quarter master at
                        <placeName key="ffran">Ft. Franklin</placeName> requesting<lb/> him to
                    furnish us with provisions or any<lb/>thing else we stood in need of at that
                    place, he<lb/> also gave us a written speech addressed to <persName key="cornp2"
                        >Corn<lb/>planter</persName> and other <orgName key="seneca"
                        >Seneca</orgName> Chiefs which is as<lb/> follows</p>
                <floatingText type="letter">
                    <body>
                        <dateline><date when="1798-05-10"/><placeName key="pitts"/></dateline>
                        <opener>To the <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> and the
                            Village<lb/>Chiefs of the <orgName key="seneca">Seneca Nation</orgName>
                            <salute>Friends and Brothers </salute></opener>
                        <p>the bearer one of<lb/> our beloved men from among the People<lb/> called
                            Quakers, Visits you with several good<lb/> Men from the same soceity,
                            who intend to<lb/> set down amongst you, in order to instruct<lb/> our
                            red Brethren in words of usefulness<lb/> and to point out to them the
                            path of<lb/>Virtue which leads to the Blissful mansions<lb/>of the Great
                            Spirit the Father of Light<lb/> and Life-</p>
                        <p>Brothers I charge you to take our beloved man<lb/> and his companions by
                            the hand and treat<lb/> them with kindness and sincerity, open<lb/> your
                            ears and listen to what they say<lb/> open your eyes and follow their footsteps<lb/>
                            <pb n="11" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_011"/> then will your Old Men, your
                            Wives, your<lb/> Children and Childrens Children live in<lb/> security
                            and enjoy the comforts of life</p>
                        <p>Brethren and Children let this admoni<lb/>tion sink deep into your Hearts
                            and may<lb/> you be Blessed with a clear Sky, smooth<lb/> Roads and
                            plentiful harvests to the end<lb/> of your days </p>

                        <closer>I commend you to the care of the Great<lb/> Spirit and am in heart
                            your friend <lb/><signed><persName key="gwilk2">Jas
                                Wilkinson</persName>. <lb/>Commander in Chief of the Troops<lb/> of
                                the United States </signed></closer>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>After spending a short time in conversation with<lb/>
                    <persName key="gwilk2">James Wilkinson</persName> we departed (he
                    accompanying<lb/> us through his Guard) and set forward on<lb/> or journey,
                    crossed the <placeName key="alleg">Allegany</placeName> and tra<lb/>velled about
                    33 Miles to a poor little hut<lb/> where we were obliged to put up for
                    quarters<lb/> or Lodge in the woods, we however tied our<lb/> Horses to Stumps
                    &amp; and fed them with feed<lb/> we carryed with us, our lodging in the
                    House<lb/> being on an earthen floor and very disagree<lb/>able it being the
                    first time we had lodged <lb/>
                    <pb n="12" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_012"/> on the Ground </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-05-13">13th of the Month </date><placeName key="ffran"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>rode about 35 miles to<lb/>
                    <placeName key="ffran">Ft. Franklin</placeName> having a difficult Road and<lb/>
                    horse feed very dear, oats being about two<lb/> Dollars per Bushel; we put up
                    and lodged at<lb/> John Andrews Tavern where we got pretty<lb/> good
                    accomodations tho very dear </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-05-14">14th of the Month </date><placeName key="oilcr"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>went to the Garrison to see<lb/>
                    <persName key="cfowl1">George Fowler</persName> who appeared very oblidging,
                    and<lb/> furnished us with what provender we want<lb/>ed for ourselves and
                    Horses, and expressed a<lb/> willingness to take care of all our Letters
                    and<lb/> Goods that came to his hands, and forward them<lb/> to us if
                    convenient, he also provided us a pilot<lb/> to go to <placeName key="conew"
                        >Conewango</placeName>, through an uninhabited<lb/> wood except by a few
                    families, in the<lb/> afternoon we set forward with our pilot<lb/> and reached
                    the House of James Tite[a?]s on the fertile<lb/> banks of <placeName key="oilcr"
                        >Oil Creek</placeName> where we were kindly en<lb/>tertained without money
                    or price, here we<lb/> put bells on our Horses and let them run<lb/> loose in
                    the woods, the Man of the Hous informed<lb/> us that he had gathered three
                    Barrells of Oil<lb/> in one year off the Waters of <placeName key="oilcr">Oil
                        Creek</placeName>, and <lb/>
                    <pb n="13" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_013"/> sold it at the rate of four Dollars
                    per Gallon it<lb/> being an excellent medicine, a few rods from<lb/> the House
                    was a stream of water which ap<lb/>peared large enough to turn a Saw-mill<lb/>
                    the Man of the House informed us that it<lb/> proceeded from one Spring about
                    20<lb/> rods above </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-05-15">15th of the Month </date><placeName
                        key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>set forward through the<lb/> Woods, and followed the course by marked<lb/> trees,
                    which our pilot had done the Summer<lb/> before, we found the way worse this Day
                    than<lb/> any we had hitherto met with, some places<lb/> very hilly and a
                    multitude of trees and old<lb/> Logs lying in the way, which made it very<lb/>
                    difficult getting along, other places the Ground<lb/> being pared with the roots
                    of large trees with<lb/> many cavities between them, and overgrown<lb/> with
                    moss which made it very dangerous<lb/> crossing, in the evening we arived at the
                    House of<lb/> James Justice on the Waters of Brokenstraw<lb/> where we lodged
                    that night on the floor<lb/> by the fire as we did the night before </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-05-16">16th of the Month </date><placeName key="conew"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>about noon reached the the<lb/> mouth of <placeName key="concr">Conewango
                        Creek</placeName> where a<lb/>
                    <pb n="14" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_014"/> Town is laid out on a piece of Land
                    belonging<lb/> to the State of Pennsylvania at this place<lb/> we met with a
                    company of Indians some<lb/> of whom were much intoxicated and appeared<lb/>
                    miserably dirty and frightfull, having large loops<lb/> cut in their Ears and
                    chunks of lead hanging to them<lb/> to stretch them down, here we stayed all
                    night<lb/> it being the end of our pilots journey and<lb/> about 60 Miles from
                        <placeName key="ffran">Ft. Franklin</placeName>, </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-05-17">17 of the Month </date><placeName key="cornp"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>employed one of the aforsaid<lb/> Indians to pilot us to <persName key="cornp2"
                        >Cornplanter</persName>s Village<lb/> about 15 Miles, found the road
                    extremely difficult<lb/> on account of old longs and trees lying down,<lb/>
                    about 2 o clock in the afternoon we arrived<lb/> at <placeName key="cornp"
                        >Genusshadega</placeName> where we were surrounded<lb/> by a company of
                    Indians who in a friendly man<lb/>ner came and shook hands and appeared to<lb/>
                    give us a hearty welcome, amongst whom<lb/> was <persName key="cornp2"
                        >Cornplanter</persName> the principal Chief, who<lb/> in a friendly manner
                    conducted us to his House<lb/> where we informed him that we were Quakers<lb/>
                    and had come a great distance to see the In<lb/>dians, he made answer and said
                    he had heard<lb/> of our coming and that he was glad and<lb/> thankful to the
                    Great Spirit for our safe <lb/>
                    <pb n="15" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_015"/> arrival and preservation on the way </p>
                <p>After we had unsadled our horses &amp; sat down<lb/> in the House <persName
                        key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> asked us if we could<lb/> eat in his way
                    (being pretty hungry) one of<lb/> our company answered he thought we could<lb/>
                    the old Man then ordered some Victuals to be<lb/> brought which I suppose was
                    the best the House<lb/> could afford, but not being accustomed to their<lb/>
                    sort of diet and cooking, we made a small por<lb/>tion serve at that time, after
                    we had done eat<lb/>ing we informed him something of our business<lb/> and that
                    we desired to have his<lb/> People collected together in Council, to which<lb/>
                    he replyed he was willing and left it to ourselves<lb/> to propose a time,
                    accordingly the next Day<lb/> was agreed on at ten o clock, and runners
                    dis<lb/>patched to notify the Indians under <persName key="cornp2"
                        >Corn<lb/>planters</persName> superintendance, in the evening<lb/> the Old
                    Man brought his Wife and Children<lb/> into the apartment where we were and
                    in<lb/>troduced them to us in a becoming manner,<lb/> after conversing a short
                    time his Wife got<lb/> up in a friendly manner and shook hands<lb/> with us
                    &amp; quitty departed into the other<lb/> end of the House where the family <lb/>
                    <pb n="16" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_016"/> mostly lived; in the evening they
                    brought<lb/> us some milk which with the addition of our small<lb/> stock of
                    provision made us a good supper, our lodging<lb/> was on births on each side of
                    the House raised about<lb/> a foot above the Ground, and overspread with
                    Deer<lb/> Skins on which we spread our Blankets and rested<lb/> pretty
                    comfortably for the first Night in an<lb/> Indian Cabin </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-05-18">18 of the Month </date><placeName key="cornp"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>took a more extensive view of the<lb/> Village and the land about it, the Land
                    appears<lb/> to be very fertile, being a large flat on the West<lb/> side of the
                    River of about 300 Acres inclosed<lb/> with a fence, the most of which has been
                    clear<lb/>ed (I suppose by the Women) about midway<lb/> of this enclosure stands
                    the body of the Village<lb/> which contains about 30 or 40 Houses being<lb/>
                    from ten to thirty feet in length mostly built<lb/> about six feet high and
                    covered with bark,<lb/> along each side are generally two births the up<lb/>per
                    one about five feet high on which they<lb/> throw their lumber and houshold
                    furniture<lb/> the lower one is their place of lodging which<lb/> also answers
                    the purpose of seats to sit on be<lb/>ing about one foot from the Ground.
                    the<lb/> fire they have in the center of the House <lb/>
                    <pb n="17" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_017"/> and a hole in the top of the roof
                    for the<lb/> ascension of the Smoke their Houses, are gene<lb/>rally very open
                    and cold in the Winter season<lb/> and I believe they seldom use more than two
                    Deer skins<lb/> and two or three Blankets to bed and often<lb/> not so much </p>
                <p>This morning <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> and his son <persName
                        key="habee1">Henry</persName><lb/> came into our apartment and desired to
                    hear<lb/> what we had to communicate to the Coun<lb/>cil: one of our company
                    informed them that<lb/> we were not ready to tell all that we expected<lb/> to
                    say when the Council met and that we<lb/> believed it right to wait for the Good
                    Spirit to<lb/> influence our Hearts before we spoke in Council<lb/> but that we
                    were willing to read them a<lb/> Letter that we had from our friends in<lb/>
                    Philadelphia and another from General<lb/>
                    <persName key="gwilk2">James Wilkinson</persName> in <placeName key="pitts"
                        >Pittsburg</placeName> which was<lb/> accordingly done and interpreted by
                        <persName key="habee1">Henry</persName><lb/> to his Father; About eleven o
                    clock they<lb/> blew a horn and the people came in about about<lb/> 40 in number
                    among whom was their<lb/> principal Men and Chief Warriors many of<lb/> them
                    were frightfully painted Black &amp; Red<lb/> their Ears cut in great loops with
                    silver or <lb/>
                    <pb n="18" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_018"/> chunks of led hanging to them to
                    stretch them<lb/> down, They had a multitude of broaches, jewels and<lb/>
                    Breastplates of Silver about their bodies which<lb/> with their belts and straps
                    curiously interwoven<lb/> with beads and their fine Mocasons<lb/> made a
                    splendid appearance to one not acquaint<lb/>ed with Indians; we sat down at one
                    end<lb/> of the House I trust with our minds humblingly<lb/> exercised under the
                    weight of the concern in which<lb/> we were engaged and some of the Indians
                    sat<lb/> pretty quiet, yet the greatest number of them<lb/> manifested much
                    lightness by talking and<lb/> laughing, after siting a short time <persName
                        key="cornp2">Cornplant<lb/>er</persName> got up (<persName key="habee1"
                        >Henry</persName> being interpreter) and spoke<lb/> nearly as follows </p>
                <floatingText type="speech" xml:id="cornp2">
                    <body>
                        <dateline><date when="1798-05-18"/><placeName key="cornp"/></dateline>
                        <p>Brothers when I saw you come out of the<lb/> bushes yesterday I was
                            rejoiced that you were<lb/> come to see your Indian Brothers, I
                            thank<lb/> the Great Spirit for your safe arrival and<lb/> that you were
                            preserved on the way --<lb/> yesterday you told us that you had some
                            talk<lb/> for us and desired that your Indian Brothers<lb/> might be
                            collected to hear you speak, some<lb/> of our Men are hear but our Women
                            could<lb/> not come but we will tell them your <lb/>
                            <pb n="19" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_019"/> talk when we go home,
                            Brothers you see we<lb/> are poor and have bad Houses covered<lb/> with
                            bark and we cant build them better<lb/> We are now ready to hear your
                            talk</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>after<lb/> a short time of silence we informed them<lb/> of the motives of our
                    coming amongst them<lb/> and a little explained the nature of our<lb/> business,
                    then read our Certificate which<lb/> is as follows </p>
                <floatingText type="letter">
                    <body>
                        <opener>To <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> with the chief
                            Men<lb/> and others of the <orgName key="seneca">Seneca</orgName> Tribe
                            of Indians</opener>

                        <p> Brothers <lb/>It has pleased the Great<lb/> Spirit above to dispose the
                            Hearts of the<lb/> Rulers in the United States and of your<lb/> people,
                            to live in Peace and Friendship<lb/> and no longer to hurt and destroy
                            each<lb/> other -- this hath long been the earnest<lb/> desire of the
                            Children of Onas your Breth<lb/>ren the people called Quakers -- The
                            path<lb/> between you and them is now plain and<lb/> open, so that the
                            good will and friendship<lb/> which subsisted between your fathers
                            &amp;<lb/> ours may be renewed and strengthened </p>
                        <pb n="20" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_020"/>

                        <p> Brothers <lb/> Your Friends the Quakers have<lb/> fro many years been
                            desirous you should<lb/> be taught in the ways of hood and honest<lb/>
                            white, that you. your Wives and<lb/> Children might learn to live more
                            com<lb/>fortably, and be relieved from the distresses<lb/> and
                            difficulties to which you have be subjected<lb/> by your old habit and
                            manner of living </p>
                        <p> Brothers <lb/>some of your Counsellors and<lb/> chief Men have told us
                            that you desired<lb/> to follow our advice, and requested our<lb/>
                            assistance in those good ways we should<lb/> recommend to you for your
                            present &amp;<lb/> lasting benefit- now Brothers we have<lb/> been very
                            thoughtfull on your account<lb/> desering to counsel you wisely in all
                            things<lb/> and that you &amp; your children might hear<lb/>ken
                            diligenly to our lasts and lock it up in<lb/> your hearts so that you
                            may often remember</p>
                        <p> Brothers <lb/>We have waited to feel how the<lb/> Good Spirit might lead
                            and direct our mind<lb/> in those things in which we may be helpful<lb/>
                            <pb n="21" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_021"/> to you , and in waiting for
                            right counsel we<lb/> have found much good will toward you, and<lb/>
                            desires for your wellfare to prevail in the<lb/> hearts of many amongst
                            us, and some of<lb/> our young Men from an earnest desire to<lb/> be
                            useful to you, have concluded to leave<lb/> their usual business here
                            and their comfort<lb/>able dwellings and go into your country<lb/> for
                            the purpose of instructing you in the<lb/> cultivation of your land,
                            raisin &amp; managing<lb/> of cattle and to escample you in sobriety
                            and<lb/> industry, for which purpose they expect to re<lb/>main for a
                            time amongst you </p>
                        <p> Brothers <lb/> The names of these three young men<lb/> are <persName
                                key="hsimm1">Henry Simmons</persName>, <persName key="jswai1">Joel
                                Swaiyne</persName>, &amp; <persName key="hjack1">Holliday
                                Jackson</persName>,<lb/> they are true Men and we desire you will
                            re<lb/>ceive them as Brothers, and accept of their<lb/> kind endeavors
                            for your instruction and<lb/> help, and with readings do what they
                            may<lb/> show you to be proper for your improve<lb/>ment </p>
                        <p> Brothers We exhort you to follow the example<lb/> of these sober young
                            Men, that you may learn<lb/>
                            <pb n="22" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_022"/> Industry and to live
                            soberly &amp; peacefully and<lb/> to avoid all evil speaking and in a
                            particular<lb/> manner we entreat you to keep from the<lb/> use of Rum
                            and Strong drink, you know<lb/> it has been the cause of many evils
                            and<lb/> much wickedness amongst you. If you<lb/> follow this counsel we
                            believe the great &amp;<lb/> good Spirit will bless you with many
                            bless<lb/>ings, and fill your Hearts with peace &amp; comfort</p>
                        <p> Brothers <lb/>With these young Men we shall send<lb/> into your country
                            some ploughs and<lb/> other useful articles to assist in
                            cultivating<lb/> your land, which we commit to their<lb/> care in order
                            that they may shew you<lb/> the use and benefit of them, that you<lb/>
                            may be encouraged to procure for your<lb/>selves like necessary tools,
                            and by diligent<lb/> use of them come to reap the plentiful fruits<lb/>
                            of Industy, enjoy with your Families com<lb/>fortable Dwellings, and
                            look on your fields<lb/> your cattle, your fruit trees &amp; woods
                            with<lb/> contentment and pleasure, to enable and<lb/> assist you yo
                            accomplish this is the sole end<lb/> and purpose of our present endeavours.<lb/>
                            <pb n="23" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_023"/> having no desire for any of
                            your lands,<lb/> your skins, your furs, or anything that<lb/> is yours </p>
                        <p> Brothers <lb/>The hearty desire we feel for your<lb/> happy improvements
                            in pursuing a quiet<lb/> peaceful and sober course of life has made<lb/>
                            us very thoughtful about the serious<lb/> undertaking of the
                            aforementioned young<lb/> Men, so that our minds have been
                            ear<lb/>nestly turned to look towards some others<lb/> of our Brethren
                            to accompany them<lb/> on their being introduced among you,<lb/> and to
                            join in endeavours to promote<lb/> their proceeding in a way most likely
                            to be<lb/> helpful to you and satisfactory to themselves.<lb/> and it
                            affords us pleasure to find two friends<lb/> whom we esteem and love
                            have expressed<lb/> a willingness to give themselves up to<lb/> the
                            service; their Names are <persName key="jshar2">Joshua<lb/>
                                Sharpless</persName> and <persName key="jpier1">John
                                Peirce</persName>, Men well<lb/> worthy of the love and regard of
                            our In<lb/>dian Brothers </p>
                        <p>Above all things Brothers forget not that<lb/> when you are still and
                            thoughtful there is <lb/>
                            <pb n="24" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_024"/> something within you which
                            shows you<lb/> what is good and what is bad, for this is<lb/> the Voice
                            of God. Spirit with which you<lb/> as well as all other people in the
                            work may<lb/> be blessed and made to be glad and rejoice if it<lb/>
                            language be sincerely hearkened to and obeyed -<lb/> this will make you
                            a happy people: and with<lb/> out this all the help that Man can
                            afford<lb/> you will be of little service, this it is that can<lb/>
                            preserve you from every thing that is hurtful<lb/> and unkind, and make
                            you rich in the midst<lb/> of Poverty </p>

                        <closer><dateline>We are your friends &amp; Brethren<lb/>
                                <placeName key="phila">Philad. </placeName><date when="1798-06-28"
                                    >June 28 1798</date></dateline>
                            <signed>
                                <persName key="dbaco1">David Bacon</persName>
                                <persName key="eyarn1">Ellis Yarnall</persName>
                                <persName key="jparr1">John Parish</persName>
                                <persName key="nharp1">Nathan Harper</persName>
                                <persName key="hdrin1">Henry Drinker</persName>
                                <persName key="jbidd1">John Biddle</persName>
                                <persName key="jdrin1">John Drinker</persName>
                                <persName key="pbark1">Peter Barker</persName>
                                <persName key="jelli1">John Elliott</persName>
                                <persName key="wgreg1">Wm Gregory</persName>
                                <persName key="tfish1">Thomas Fisher</persName>
                                <persName key="twist1">Thomas Wister</persName>
                                <persName key="tstew1">Thomas
                            Stewwardson</persName></signed></closer>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>After the foregoing and <persName key="gwilk2">Jas Wilkinsons</persName><lb/>
                    address was read and interpreted to them they<lb/> retired into another
                    appartment to con<lb/>sult on the proposials we had made to them <lb/>
                    <pb n="25" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_025"/> and said they would reply to what
                    we had said<lb/> next day; In the evening <persName key="cornp2"
                        >Cornplanter</persName><lb/> came and asked us divers questions relative
                    to<lb/> our qualifications for work if any of us<lb/> were carpenters, to which
                    we gave them such in<lb/>formation as they wanted and told them we had<lb/> a
                    set of carpenter tools and a number of far<lb/>ming utencils coming in a Boat
                    which was<lb/> intended for the use of the Indians </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-05-19">19 of the month </date><placeName key="cornp"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> they spent the most of this<lb/> day in Council among themselves, frequently
                    sending<lb/> one to ask us questions relative to our business<lb/> in the
                    evening about 30 of them came into<lb/> the appartment where we were in order to
                    reply<lb/> to what we had said to them yesterday and <persName key="cornp2"
                        >Corn<lb/>planter</persName> got up and spoke on behalf of the people<lb/>
                    nearly as follows- </p>
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body>
                        <dateline><date when="1798-05-19"/><placeName key="cornp"/></dateline>
                        <p>Brothers the Quakers<lb/> listen now to what I am going to say to
                            you.</p>
                        <p>you know Brothers the Red people are poor<lb/> they are not like the
                            White People, the<lb/> great, Spirit has made them of another
                            lan<lb/>guage so that it is very hard for us to un<lb/>derstand one
                            another plainly, as there is no<lb/> person here that can interpret very
                            well-</p>
                        <p>Brothers we take great pains to settle the <lb/>
                            <pb n="26" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_026"/> proposials you made to us
                            but we differ in<lb/> opinions and we must take great pains to<lb/> have
                            every thing complete.</p>
                        <p>Brothers we suppose the reason you came<lb/> here was to help poor
                            Indians, some way<lb/> or other, and you wish the Chiefs to tell<lb/>
                            their warriors not to go on as bad as they<lb/> have done; and you wish
                            us to take up<lb/> work like the White People. Now</p>
                        <p>Brothers some of our sober Men will take<lb/> up work and do as you say,
                            and if they do<lb/> well then will your young Men stay lon<lb/>ger, but
                            some others will not mind what you<lb/> say. </p>
                        <p>Brothers we cant say a word against<lb/> you it is the best way to call
                            Quaker Brothers<lb/> you never wished our lands therefore we are<lb/>
                            determined to try to learn your ways; and<lb/> there young Men may stay
                            here two years<lb/> to try, by that line we shall know if Morris<lb/>
                            will leave us any land and whether he will<lb/> pay us our Money; for
                            last summer we<lb/> sold our Land and we dont know yet<lb/> whether he
                            shall get our money, but by<lb/> that time we shall know, and then if <lb/>
                            <pb n="27" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_027"/> the young Men likes it and
                            we like it they<lb/> may stay longer. </p>
                        <p>Brothers if your<lb/> young men stay here we want them to<lb/> learn our
                            young men to read and write</p>
                        <p>Brothers two of you are a going home again<lb/> if they hear any thing
                            about our land or<lb/> our money they must write to these young<lb/> men
                            have and they must tell us if we are<lb/> like to cheated</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p> After <persName key="cornp2">Complanter</persName> had closed the foregoing<lb/>
                    speech we informed them that we were satisfied<lb/> with what they had said; and
                    proposed to them<lb/> that they should let us have a good piece of<lb/> land to
                    work in order to set them an exam<lb/>ple and to raise bread for ourselves to
                    eat<lb/> but that the land should still be theirs, and<lb/> all the improvements
                    we had on it would<lb/> also be theirs when we left it; and in order<lb/> to
                    know where would be best for us to settle<lb/> we told them we must look about
                    their Land<lb/> and go to the other village and see the Land<lb/> there, and
                    desired that some of their Chiefs<lb/> would go with us and show us their
                    land<lb/> all which they readily agreed to; we also<lb/> informed them that the
                    carpenters tools <lb/>
                    <pb n="28" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_028"/> and farming utensils that were
                    coming<lb/> forward were intended to lend to our<lb/> Indian Brothers and that
                    they should be<lb/> under the care and notice of our young friends<lb/> while
                    they staid here, for they knew<lb/> that some of their young Men were<lb/> not
                    quite as good as they should be and<lb/> if these things were divided amongst
                    them<lb/> some of them might pawn them away<lb/> for Whisky, and then they would
                    be as<lb/> bad off as they were before they go there<lb/> to this information
                    some of the old Men<lb/> expression their way a hearty approba<lb/>tion, and
                    some of the young Men mani<lb/>fested a sensibility of its perinanaby a<lb/>
                    shamefaced good humoured laugh<lb/> After the above observations had taken<lb/>
                    plave <persName key="cornp2">cornplanter</persName> expressed that as
                    matters<lb/> ware now settled we wouold shake hands as<lb/> Brothers, and
                    directed his people to come to<lb/> us himself first setting them an
                    example<lb/> thus the councel ended late in the evening.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-05-20"> 20 of the Month and first of the weeks
                        above</date><placeName key="cornp"/></dateline>
                <p>nine O clock <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> came into our
                    ap<lb/>artment and said we must not think <lb/>
                    <pb n="29" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_029"/> hard of theirs for not keeping that
                    days we<lb/> told them we did not think hard of it,<lb/> but we mostly kepy that
                    day to wait upon the<lb/> good Spirit, and about ten o clock that day<lb/> we
                    expected to sit down in silence for that<lb/> service, and if any of them had a
                    mind to<lb/> come and sit with us we would be well<lb/> satisfied and desired
                    that we might not be<lb/> interrupted, at the hour appoined we sat<lb/> down in
                    our appartment and were accompa<lb/>nied by <persName key="cornp2"
                        >cornplanter</persName> and several other Indians<lb/> who sat pretty still
                    and quiet a part of the time<lb/> and then all withdrew except <persName
                        key="cornp2">cornplanter</persName><lb/> who conducted himself is a becoming
                    manner<lb/> throughout the opportunity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-05-21"> 21 of the month </date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>made preperations to go<lb/> about nine miles up the river to see where<lb/>
                    would be the most eligible place to settle<lb/> that we might be of the most
                    advantage to the Nation<lb/> in general this land being <persName key="cornp2"
                        >cornplanters</persName><lb/> private property of about 600 acres which<lb/>
                    was given to him by the state of Pennsylva<lb/>nia, and we thought it not best
                    to settle on<lb/> his land, accordngly <persName key="cornp2"
                        >cornplanter</persName>, his son<lb/>
                    <persName key="habee1">Henry</persName>, and there other Indians went with <lb/>
                    <pb n="30" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_030"/> us in a Canoe to <placeName
                        key="genes1">Genesinguhta</placeName> an old Indian<lb/> Village in the
                    State of Newyork about 4<lb/> miles above the Pennsylvania line where we<lb/>
                    explored the Land and found a place<lb/> which we thought most eligible to make
                    the<lb/> settlement near a young Chiefs House<lb/> whose name is John, this man
                        <persName key="cornp2">Cornplan<lb/>ter</persName> said was like ourselves
                    for he would<lb/> drink no whisky, and that he was glad<lb/> we were going to
                    settle so near him,<lb/> after spending some time at the House of<lb/> our
                    intended Neighbour we returned<lb/> again in a canoe to <placeName key="genes1"
                        >Genisatego</placeName> where we at<lb/> that time made our home</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-05-22"> 22 of the Month </date><placeName key="cornp"
                    /></dateline>
                <p><persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> presented<lb/> us with some Corn,
                    Potatoes, Beans and a<lb/> variety of Vine seed which he said was a<lb/>
                    collection brought in by his People as a blessing<lb/> to us in our undertaking,
                    which we thank<lb/>fully accepted, believing they had Hearts of<lb/> good will
                    towards us and our present under<lb/>taking </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-05-23">23rd </date><placeName key="genes1"/></dateline>
                <p>went again to <placeName key="genes1">Genesinguhta</placeName> with<lb/> all our
                    affects and bought a House of an<lb/> Indian woman for 20 Dollars which was <lb/>
                    <pb n="31" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_031"/> on the spot of Land that we
                    intended to im<lb/>prove, after we had paid the Woman for the house<lb/> we
                    assisted her in carrying her goods to another<lb/> so we took possession after
                    clearing<lb/> the Cabbin of some of the filth that is<lb/> mostly to be seen in
                    Indians Houses</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-05-24"> 24th </date><placeName key="genes1"/></dateline>
                <p>made a begining at grubbing which<lb/> business I had never done before
                    there<lb/> appears to be a great deal of it to do before<lb/> the Ground will be
                    ready for the Plough<lb/> and a multitude of old Logs to remove out of<lb/> the
                    way</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-05-27"> 27th of the month and first of the
                        week</date><placeName key="genes1"/></dateline>
                <p>had a meeting in our little Cabin which was<lb/> a very satisfactory one to me,
                    and elderly friends<lb/> being favoured to drop some suitable hints<lb/> of
                    caution and admonition before us which<lb/> I believe was well adapted to the
                    state of our<lb/> minds</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-05-28"> 28 </date><placeName key="cornp"/></dateline>
                <p>we attended another council with the<lb/> Indians, after setting a short time in silence<lb/>
                    <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> got up to open the Council<lb/>
                    and said, -<lb/><said who="cornp2">Brothers I am very<lb/> glad to see you all
                        well, any People are<lb/> also well, many of them are here but <lb/><pb
                            n="32" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_032"/> some of them are gone a
                        hunting, We are<lb/> now ready to hear you speak:</said></p>
                <p>One of our<lb/> company then informed them that we<lb/> had some further
                    proposals to make them<lb/> which we had commited to writing in<lb/> order to
                    help our memories which was<lb/> read and interpreted to them as follows-</p>
                <floatingText type="letter">
                    <body>
                        <opener>To <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> and all our Indian
                            Bro-<lb/> thers of the <orgName key="seneca">Seneca</orgName> Nation now
                            living on<lb/> the <placeName key="alleg">Allegany
                            River</placeName>-</opener>
                        <p>Brothers we have now been several<lb/> Days among you, and have had
                            Coun<lb/>cils with your Chiefs and wise men,<lb/> and we have looked
                            about your Coun<lb/>try and agreed upon a place for our young<lb/> Men
                            to begin on, and we are glad and<lb/> thankful to the Great Spirit that
                            every<lb/> thing we have proposed for your good has<lb/> been so
                            agreeable to your minds, that we<lb/> seem to agree together like
                            Brothers<lb/> having but one mind in every thing<lb/> we do; and we hope
                            Brothers we shall<lb/> continue to be of one mind about all<lb/> the
                            things which we have been speaking<lb/> to you of </p>
                        <pb n="33" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_033"/>
                        <p>Brothers you know the place we have chosen<lb/> for our young Men to
                            settle on up at<lb/>
                            <placeName key="genes1">Genesinguhta</placeName> and we hope some of
                            your<lb/> sober young Men will settle by ours and<lb/> fence off lots
                            for themselves as they see our<lb/> young Men fence of theirs, and our
                            young<lb/> Men will be willing to instruct and assist<lb/> them a little
                            about working their lots, now<lb/> Brothers we think our young Friends
                            will<lb/> not be able to reuse anymore grain this<lb/> year on their lot
                            than what they will<lb/> want to live upon; but we are in hopes<lb/>
                            another year they will have a little to<lb/> spare and we are willing
                            they should give<lb/> to your old People that cannot work for<lb/>
                            themselves one Bushall out of four of<lb/> all the grain &amp;c. they have
                            to spare, the<lb/> rest they must have to buy Salt and<lb/> other things
                            which they cannot raise<lb/> off the ground-<lb/> Brothers, In order to
                            encourage you still<lb/> more to take up work and follow those good<lb/>
                            ways which we pointed out to you; we will<lb/> agree to help you a
                            little more-</p>
                        <p> Brothers We will send you a Smiths <lb/>
                            <pb n="34" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_034"/> tools when our young men
                            shall write us word<lb/> and you stand in need of them</p>
                        <p>Brothers If you are industrious this Summer<lb/> and raise a good deal of
                            Corn and some Wheat<lb/> we will help you build a Grist mill next<lb/>
                            Summer if a suitable place can be found for<lb/> it, you must find half
                            the Money to build<lb/> this Mill and we will find the other half,<lb/>
                            and we hope Brothers you will save some of the Money you get from the
                            white<lb/> people between now and that time so<lb/> that you may have
                            your share ready again<lb/> at next summer, and we think you had<lb/>
                            better choose one of your Chiefs to keep this<lb/> Money for you till
                            the time is is wanted<lb/> or perhaps it will be all gone for
                            whisky<lb/> or something that won't do you so much<lb/> good as a Mill
                            would-</p>
                        <p>Brothers We are also willing to encourage<lb/> you to take up work, and
                            learn farming<lb/> by agreeing to give some small premi-<lb/>ums to such
                            of our Indian brothers who<lb/> are industrious and raise a good deal
                            of<lb/> Grain </p>
                        <pb n="35" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_035"/>
                        <p>Brothers we will give to every Indian Man<lb/> living on this River who
                            shall raise 25 Bushalls<lb/> of wheat or rye in one year on his own
                            Land<lb/> not worked by white people the sum of two<lb/> Dollars</p>
                        <p> 2 For every 50 Bushalls of Indian Corn rai-<lb/> sed by any one Indian
                            Man in like manner<lb/> affor said the sum of two Dollars</p>
                        <p> 3 For every 50 Bushalls of Potatoes raised<lb/> by any one Indian Man in
                            like manner<lb/> affor said the sum of two Dollars</p>
                        <p> 4 For every two tons of hay raised as affor said<lb/> and put into a
                            Stack or Barn not being<lb/> mawed or drawn in by white People the<lb/>
                            sum of two Dollars</p>
                        <p> 5 For every 12 yards of linnen Cloth made<lb/> by any Indian Woman out
                            of flx raised on<lb/> her own or her husbands Land andspun in her<lb/>
                            own House the sum of two Dollars to be<lb/> paid to the Woman</p>
                        <p>6 For every 12 yards of woolen Cloth or lincey<lb/> made by any any
                            Indian Woman out of wool of<lb/> her own or her husbands Sheep and spun
                            in<lb/> her own House the sum of two Dollars to be<lb/> paid to the
                            Woman </p>
                        <pb n="36" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_036"/>
                        <p>Brothers We will give you these premiums<lb/> for Four years from this
                            time if our young Men<lb/> should stay so long, and upon these
                            conditions,<lb/> that the person who applies for the premium<lb/> must
                            produce a Certificate from two of the Chiefs<lb/> certifying the
                            quantity of Grains, Cloth &amp;c. for which<lb/> the premium is demanded and
                            that it was<lb/> raised or made in the manner above mentioned,<lb/> and
                            that the person so applying has not<lb/> been intoxicated with strong
                            Drinks at least<lb/> for the term of six Months before such
                            ap-<lb/>plication; And our Friends <persName key="hsimm1">Henry
                                Simmons</persName><lb/>
                            <persName key="jswai1">Joel Swayne</persName> &amp; <persName
                                key="hjack1">Halliday Jackson</persName> are hereby au-<lb/>thorized
                            and desired to pay the above mentioned<lb/> premiums agreeable to what
                            is herein before<lb/> expressed-</p>

                        <closer><dateline><date when="1798-05-22">5 mo 22nd 1798</date><placeName
                                    key="genes1"/></dateline>
                            <signed><persName key="jshar2">Joshua Sharpless</persName><lb/>
                                <persName key="jpier1">John Pierce</persName><lb/>
                                <persName key="hsimm1">Henry Simmons</persName><lb/>
                                <persName key="jswai1">Joel Swayne</persName><lb/>
                                <persName key="hjack1">Halliday Jackson</persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>After the foregoing was read the Indians re-<lb/>tired into a private apartment
                    in order to con-<lb/>sult each others minds that they might <lb/>
                    <pb n="37" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_037"/> reply to what we had said, and
                    returned<lb/> again in about half and hour and made<lb/> the following reply</p>
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body>
                        <dateline><date when="1798-05-22"/><placeName key="cornp"/></dateline>
                        <p>Brothers We now hear all what you wish<lb/> to do among us, you are come
                            here to see<lb/> us brothers, you wish us well, you wish us<lb/> to
                            become as the White People, the White are rich<lb/> and have every
                            thing, the Indians are poor and<lb/> have nothing,</p>
                        <p>Brothers you told us one thing, it would be good for<lb/> us to build a
                            Mill, we will consult <persName key="ichap1">Cap-<lb/>tain
                                Chapen</persName>, if he thinks we will get our<lb/> Money, and we
                            are able to raise the money<lb/> you propose then we will do it</p>
                        <p>Brothers We know how far you have come to<lb/> see us, it is a great ways
                            to the Sea shore where<lb/> our fore Fathers once lived, the White
                            People<lb/> have cheated us and got our Land from us, and<lb/> now we
                            have but little left, and we will try<lb/> to learn your way-</p>
                        <p>Brothers you know there is some bad People<lb/> among us, and you know we
                            have been cheated<lb/> and that makes us bad, and our minds uneasy,<lb/>
                            if we had not been cheated we should have<lb/> been very rich People,
                            and had plenty of every <lb/><pb n="38" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_038"
                            /> thing, and then our minds would have been<lb/> easy and we could
                            think on the Great Spirit</p>
                        <p>Brothers the reason I mention to you about<lb/> being cheated, some of my
                            Warriors won't<lb/> mind what I say to them, but will have<lb/> their
                            own way, because they know I have often<lb/> been cheated by the White
                            People, if I had never<lb/> been cheated then my warriors would
                            believe<lb/> me and mind what I say to them, but<lb/> now they won't
                            mind</p>
                        <p>Brothers we can't all go to work at once<lb/> some of my warriors will go
                            a hunting to<lb/> get provisions and sometimes they broke a<lb/> Gun and
                            then it takes a great deal of Money<lb/> to buy another, and we have
                            very few Hoes &amp;<lb/> Axes and such things among us and we are
                            not<lb/> able to get them</p>
                        <p>Brothers I will go along with you to <placeName key="canan"
                                >Canadar-<lb/>que</placeName> and then we will get matters settled
                            about<lb/> the Mill and bring it back to your young men<lb/> in
                            Writing</p>
                        <p>Brothers this is all I have to say we will<lb/> now shake hands</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>At the close of the foregoing speech our friends<lb/> exprest a few words,
                    representing among <lb/>
                    <pb n="39" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_039"/> after things the unreasonableness
                    of their present<lb/> practice in suffering their Women to work all Day<lb/> in
                    the fields &amp; Woods with their Hoes &amp; Axes<lb/> whilst they themselves
                    were at the same time<lb/> playing with their Bows &amp; Arrows</p>
                <p> In order for their advancement into the good ways<lb/> and methods of White
                    People, they were recom-<lb/> mended to take their boys to work with their
                    mo-<lb/>thers and Sisters whilst they were young, and<lb/> when they grew older
                    they would not think so<lb/> hard of it, Endeavours were also used seriously
                    to<lb/> impress on their minds the remembrance<lb/> that it was from the Good
                    Spirit they<lb/> received every good thing, and that he could<lb/> hear every
                    thing they said, and see every<lb/> thing they did; and if they were good and
                    in<lb/>dustrious he would love them and bless them<lb/> with many good
                    things-<lb/> After we had one speaking and informed them<lb/> we had said all
                    that we had to say at that<lb/> time, <persName key="cornp2"
                        >Cornplanter</persName> observed that as all thing are<lb/> done and settled
                    we will cover the Council<lb/> fire, the Council ended to pretty good
                    satisfac-<lb/>tion both to us and the Indians tho' a loss was<lb/> sensibly felt
                    by us for want of a good Interpreter </p>

            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="40" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_40"/>
                <dateline><date when="1798-05-30">30 of 5th Mo </date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>While we were sitting in religious re<lb/>tirement (which we continued to do
                    twice a week)<lb/> we were interrupted by our Boatman who had<lb/> arrived at
                    the landing with our goods<lb/> which relieved us of some anxiety of mind as
                    the<lb/> River was geting low and we were doubtful<lb/> of the Boat geting this
                    far at all, the Boat was<lb/> 16 Days coming from <placeName key="pitts"
                        >Pittsburgh</placeName> to this place which after<lb/> a stay of about 2
                    hours returned homewards, the<lb/> arrival of our Boat afforded us a plentiful
                    stock of<lb/> provisions Beding and utensils of various kinds<lb/> to work and
                    instruct the natives with, I now feel<lb/> myself in a good degree happy and
                    contented</p>

            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-06-07">7th of 6th mo.</date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> This morning being the time appoint-<lb/>ed for our friends departure toward
                    their native Land having<lb/> a wilderness journey before them and but
                    little<lb/> prospect of reaching home in less than 5 or 6 weeks<lb/> intending
                    to go a few days journey over <placeName key="niagr">Niagara<lb/>
                        River</placeName> in <placeName key="canad">upper Canada</placeName> thence
                    by way of <placeName key="oneid">Oneida</placeName> and<lb/> New York which
                    would make their route near<lb/> 1200 miles, our neighbour <persName
                        key="ijohn1">Indian John</persName> came<lb/> this morning according to
                    appointment to<lb/> pilot our friends to <placeName key="catta1"
                        >Cataraugus</placeName> about 45 miles<lb/> from this place, our friends
                    being in readiness<lb/> solemnly took leave of us and set forward <lb/>
                    <pb n="41" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_041"/> on their Journey having a very
                    rough and<lb/> disagreeable road as far as <placeName key="catta1"
                        >Cataraugus</placeName></p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-06-11"> 11th of the month </date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>we were visited by <persName key="cornp2">Cornplan-<lb/>ter</persName> and
                    several other Indians being on their<lb/> way to <placeName key="canan"
                        >Canadarque</placeName> in order to settle mat-<lb/>ters about the Land they
                    sold last fall, by<lb/> whom we wrote to our former companions<lb/> which they
                    expected to meet at <placeName key="canan">Canadarque</placeName></p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-06-20"> 20th of the Month </date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>received a letter from <persName key="jpier1">John Pierce</persName><lb/> and
                        <persName key="jshar1">Joshua Sharpless</persName> by the return of our
                    neighbour<lb/> John, informing that they had an affectionate<lb/> parting with
                        <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> at <placeName key="buffc1"
                        >Buffalo Creek</placeName> who<lb/> was pressingly solicitous that they
                    should stay un-<lb/>til the Council met but at length gave it up<lb/> and in
                    their parting conference <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName><lb/>
                    feelingly expressed that he hoped they would<lb/> make their mind perfectly easy
                    about their young<lb/> Men, for altho he could not answer for sickness<lb/> or
                    Death on such things, but as for anything else<lb/> he would look upon it his
                    duty always to be<lb/> their friend and that they might depend upon him<lb/> as
                    such, and that no harm should happen to them<lb/> from his People, he concluded
                    his spech with desi-<lb/>ring the Great Spirit might preserve them on<lb/> their
                    journey, and that he might so order <lb/>
                    <pb n="42" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_042"/> things that they might find their
                    families<lb/> and people well when they got home</p>
                <p>We are now settled and got to work at the old and<lb/> almost deserted Village
                        <placeName key="genes1">Genesinguhta</placeName> which is<lb/> so overgrown
                    with rubbish &amp; bushes as to cause<lb/> a great deal of labour to prepare it
                    for the Plaugh<lb/> which we started a few Days ago and have plan-<lb/>ted a
                    small piece of Corn and also some Vine and<lb/> garden Seeds, The Indians are
                    dayly flocking<lb/> about us and manifest much kindness and respect<lb/> after
                    bringing us Vennison &amp; fish of an excelent<lb/> quality, to the Women we
                    often impart small<lb/> presents which came for that purpose from<lb/> friends
                    in <placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName> for which they returned<lb/>
                    many thanks</p>
                <p> The dress of the Indian men in warm wea-<lb/> ther consists of a short Calico
                    shirt or frock which<lb/> comes a little below the waist over which<lb/> the
                    ware a fine broad Cloth coat of a lively<lb/> coulor mostly Blue or green
                    instead of pantaloons<lb/> they wear a piece of fine cloth, their leggens<lb/>
                    are mostly blue or green, and some times<lb/> superfluously decorated with small
                    beads<lb/> and curious straps about their legs, their<lb/> moccasons are
                    curiously wrought with ribbands <lb/><pb n="43" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_043"
                    /> porcupine quills, and small beads, they are<lb/> latterly getting much in the
                    practice of wearing<lb/> hats, The dress of the Woman is much like<lb/> that of
                    the Men save a short woollen petticoat<lb/> and a broadcloth wrapper instead of
                    a coat.<lb/> The Women about us have a number of<lb/> corn patches interspreed
                    through the bushes<lb/> which they tend with their hoes, they<lb/> plant the
                    hills about 3 feet apart with<lb/> 8 or 10 stalks in a hill, their activity
                    in<lb/> hilling and weeding it is somewhat<lb/> extraordinary</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-06-27">27th of Sixth month</date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p><persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> being at our<lb/> House we enquired
                    of him if he would sell us<lb/> some boards to build a House he replyed
                    that<lb/> we might have as many as we wanted at two<lb/> Dollars per hundred and
                    he would deliver them<lb/> at at our landing, a few days after he<lb/> sent for
                    us to come to the Saw mill and<lb/> see the boards measured out, we
                    immediate-<lb/>ly went and found <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName>
                    and several<lb/> other Indians at the Mill. here we had a<lb/> pretty stricking
                    instance of the generosity<lb/> of <persName key="cornp2"
                    >Cornplanter</persName>, for as we had told the<lb/> Indians in council at our
                    first coming <lb/>
                    <pb n="44" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_044"/> amongst them, that we came not to
                    trade<lb/> with them, nor to use any endeavours to<lb/> to get their land or
                    skins, therefore he<lb/> said he would take no pay of us for<lb/> any thing we
                    got from him, but that we<lb/> might have as many boards as we wanted<lb/>
                    without pay, we got 1000 feet and acknowleged<lb/> the old Mans kindness and
                    offered him the<lb/> Money which he refused taking as pay for<lb/> the boards
                    but as he was in need said he<lb/> would borrow it until he received his<lb/>
                    annuity from government, and then he would<lb/> return it again, which he did
                    accordingly </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-07-07">7th of seventh month</date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p><persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> and one of our<lb/> neighbour being
                    at our house, the latter<lb/> having a short time before erected a sign on
                    the<lb/> bank of the river at his new house with<lb/> an intention of keeping a
                    tavern, which was<lb/> a verry disagreeable circumstance to us, yet
                    cau-<lb/>tion was requisite least we should give offence<lb/> We however
                    manifested our disaprobation to<lb/> to such a practice, in the presence of
                    neighbors<lb/> John and <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName>, the old
                    chief then infor-<lb/>med us that we must not be frightened at it and he<lb/>
                    would try to have matters so ordered that <lb/>
                    <pb n="45" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_045"/> no liquor should be kept for sale
                    near us but still they<lb/> must keep a little to use at times of hard<lb/>
                    labour for some times they worked very hard<lb/> and then a little was
                    necessary, Neighbour<lb/> John said that he could not loose what liquor<lb/> he
                    had on hands for it cost him a great deal<lb/> of money, but when that was all
                    sold he<lb/> gave expectations of declining the practice,<lb/> a few Days after
                    he cut down his new<lb/> sign and told us it was <foreign xml:lang="iro"
                        >tooscoss</foreign>, which in their<lb/> language is, not good</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-07-09">9th of the month</date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> After quiting work in the even-<lb/>ing I and one of my companions went to
                    one<lb/> of our near neighbours who had several<lb/> hand engaged in building a
                    House some<lb/> were a little intoxicated, my companions said<lb/> to one of
                    them who seemed awkward at his words<lb/> that he drunk too much Whisky which
                    the<lb/> Indian understood and immediately his coun-<lb/>tenance changed and
                    looked horrible he<lb/> muttered somthing to himself we did not under-<lb/>stand
                    we then withdrew from the place, when<lb/> we had got a few steps from the House
                    he<lb/> he took up his axe as tho he had a mind to<lb/> follow us, but did not,
                    we expected to <lb/>
                    <pb n="46" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_046"/> have been troubled with drunken
                    Indians<lb/> that night but they came no nearer than<lb/> than their Cabins
                    which were a few rods<lb/> from ours. This was almost the first stri-<lb/>king
                    instance of the bad effects of Spirituous<lb/> liquors that we had seen in our
                    neigh-<lb/>bourhood. A few weeks after the Indian<lb/> brought a large fish and
                    gave to my<lb/> companion and shook hands with him<lb/> as a token of
                    friendship, and appeared<lb/> convicted for his misconduct</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-09-02">2nd of 9th month</date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> A young Man named<lb/><persName key="bshaw1">Benjamin Shaw</persName> who had
                    been employ-<lb/>ed in clearing Land near the waters of <persName key="osway"
                        >Oswaya<lb/> Creek</persName> about 60 miles from this place<lb/> having
                    occasion to return home which was in<lb/> the <placeName key="genes2"
                        >Genesee</placeName> near <placeName key="bath">Bath</placeName>, about 50
                    miles from<lb/> his employment, and on his way thro,<lb/> the woods crossed his
                    path and bewildered<lb/> and after traviling six Days arrived at our house<lb/>
                    and enquired if we could tell him where he<lb/> was said he had lain in the
                    woods 6 nights<lb/> by himself, and 4 of them without fire<lb/> and the last
                    night the wolves killed a deer<lb/> a few rods from him as he was laying without <lb/>
                    <pb n="47" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_047"/> fire, he fortunately had with him a
                    little sugar<lb/> and Cheese on which he subsisted, we let him<lb/> have some
                    provisions and informed him his<lb/> right course homeward</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-09-08">8th of the month</date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> Arrived at our House <persName key="jelic1">Joseph<lb/> Ellicott</persName> head
                    surveyor for the Holland company,<lb/>
                    <persName key="jparr2">Jasper Parrish</persName> States interpreter,
                    Farmers<lb/> Brother the chief Sachom of the <orgName key="seneca"
                        >Seneca</orgName><lb/> Indians, and a large company of Surveyors<lb/> being
                    on their way to <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanters</persName> in<lb/> order to
                    have matters agreed on repecting the<lb/> Indians reservation on this River, the
                    evening<lb/> being wet they stayed with us all<lb/> night which gave us an
                    opportunity of a<lb/> short conference with the <persName key="farme1">Farmers
                        Brother</persName><lb/> in which we informed him of our motives<lb/> in
                    coming amongst these Indians, and<lb/> had our Certificate explained to him<lb/>
                    by <persName key="jparr2">Jasper Parrish</persName>, the old Chief appeared<lb/>
                    to be pretty well satisfied with our proceed-<lb/>ings and said "he was glad to
                    hear of our<lb/> coming among these Indians, and was in hopes<lb/> we would be
                    of use to them, and was<lb/> glad at this time to see us and have<lb/> the
                    opportunity of conversing with us, <lb/>
                    <pb n="48" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_048"/> and said he had somthing to tell
                    us,<lb/> which was, that we had an arduous task<lb/> before us and must have
                    many hardships<lb/> to pass through in the undertaking, he<lb/> also thought
                    that the Indians could not easily<lb/> be brought off from their old habits and
                    cus-<lb/>toms of living, and that the natural disposi-<lb/>tion in them would be
                    hard to change-<lb/> and altho' he observed that many of<lb/> them were very
                    active and with a little<lb/> instruction might learn to work well<lb/> yet they
                    wanted tools to work with-<lb/> And as to teaching their Children to read<lb/>
                    and write it was almost impossible unless<lb/> they understood the English
                    language yet<lb/> he hoped we would be useful to them<lb/> and the tools we
                    brought would be a great<lb/> help toward geting them to work And<lb/> that him
                    and his people would wait to see<lb/> what progress these Indians would make
                    in<lb/> the way of farming, and would be glad to<lb/> hear of our success in the
                    business, and hoped<lb/> we would faithfully discharge our duty and<lb/> often
                    caution the young Men to sobriety <lb/>
                    <pb n="49" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_049"/> and against the use of strong
                    Drink-<lb/> We informed him that we were glad to see<lb/> him and that he used
                    so much freedom<lb/> in telling us his mind, that we expected<lb/> bfore we came
                    to have many hardships to pass through &amp;<lb/> therefore were prepared for
                    them, but we had<lb/> found things much easier than we expected.<lb/> That the
                    Indians were very kind to us and<lb/> as to their learning to work we
                    thought<lb/> there was encouragement and were of the mind that their Children
                    might be learned to<lb/> read and write; but we did not expect a<lb/> great
                    change would take place very soon but<lb/> were willing to wait until the
                    Indians saw<lb/> the advantage of a civilized life-<lb/> Next day they proceeded
                    on to <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanters</persName><lb/> Village where a large
                    council was held &amp;<lb/> all matters agreed on respecting the In-<lb/>dians
                    reservation- A statement of which<lb/> out of <persName key="rmorr1">R
                        Morris</persName>'s purchases as follows</p>
                <floatingText type="account">
                    <body>
                        <p><placeName key="conew">Conewangus</placeName> - 2 square miles </p>
                        <p><placeName key="bigtr">Big Tree</placeName> - 2 square miles </p>
                        <p><placeName>Little birds town</placeName> - 2 square miles </p>
                        <p><placeName key="squaw">Squawky hill</placeName> - 2 square miles </p>
                        <p><placeName>Gardo</placeName> - 4 square miles </p>
                        <p><placeName>Canideer</placeName> - 16 square miles </p>
                        <p><placeName key="alleg1">Allegany</placeName> - 42 square miles </p>
                        <p><placeName key="catta1">Cataraugus</placeName> 42 square miles </p>
                        <p><placeName key="buffa">Buffalo</placeName> and </p>
                        <p><placeName key="tonne">Tonewante</placeName> - 200 square miles</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>

            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="50" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_050"/>
                <dateline><date when="1798-09-24"> 24th of the month </date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p><persName key="habee1">Henry Obeal</persName> and<lb/> several Indians called at
                    our house with<lb/> whom we had some conversation, respect<lb/>ing their going
                    to work and geting a living<lb/> by their industry, one of them said that<lb/>
                    some birds had lately come about and<lb/> told them that we intended to go
                    home<lb/> next Summer and some others were<lb/> coming to take our place. We
                    told them<lb/> we had not yet concluded how long we would<lb/> stay amongst
                    them, but when we went<lb/> away we would let them know our rea<lb/>sons for
                    going, and that it was likely<lb/> some others would come that would be<lb/> of
                    as much benefit to them as ourselves -<lb/> and that they must not believe all
                    that<lb/> these fires told them. -- But still they<lb/> seemed uneasy with their
                    information<lb/> and said <said>you have told us what to do and<lb/> if you go
                        away and some others comes they<lb/> will tell us another story, then
                        how<lb/> shall we know which is right</said>: we reply<lb/> that the Quakers
                    would all tell them<lb/> the same story and that they need<lb/> not be uneasy in
                    that respect. <lb/>
                    <pb n="51" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_051"/> after the foregoing information
                    they<lb/> seemed pretty well reconciled and began<lb/> to enquire if we had
                    wives and children &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1798-11-21">1798 21 of 11th mo.</date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> About this time <persName key="hsimm1">Henry Simmons</persName><lb/> opened a
                    School at <placeName key="genes1">Genisshadego</placeName> which was<lb/>
                    atended by several little boys who seemed very<lb/> anxious to learn the letter
                    and very inquisitive<lb/> for knowing the english names of<lb/> things.
                        <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> bought 50lb. of flower<lb/>
                    and 100lb. of Pork and some Vennison to acco<lb/>midate the School-master --</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1799-01-20">1799 20 of 1st month</date><placeName key="cornp"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> had a visit from H Simmons<lb/> who informed us of the Death of <persName
                        key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName>'s<lb/> Daughter who had been a long time
                    under a<lb/> consumption, the day of burial a few men and<lb/> a great number of
                    Women collected to the house<lb/> of <persName key="cornp2"
                        >Cornplanter</persName>, the Men assisted in carrying the<lb/> corps to the
                    grave, after the internment the<lb/> men withdrew and the Women returned<lb/>
                    again to the House where they exhibited<lb/> a melancholy scene of mourning
                    which lasted<lb/> several days, all kinds of the best provisions<lb/> that they
                    could procure was brought to<lb/> entertain the mourners </p>


            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="52" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_052"/>
                <dateline><date when="1799-02-01">2nd month, first 1799</date><placeName
                        key="genes1"/></dateline>
                <p>We received a letter<lb/> from <persName key="twist1">T.W.</persName> of
                    Philadelphia expressive of a dis-<lb/>pensation of more general health in the
                    City<lb/> than was experienced a few weeks past, but<lb/> that in the course of
                    about three Months<lb/> 3500 of his fellow Citizens were removed<lb/> from works
                    to rewards, and many had<lb/> ended their lives in the adjacent Country<lb/> We
                    also received one from <persName key="jshar1">J. Sharpless</persName> our<lb/>
                    fellow traveler in the commencement of this<lb/> work, in which he expressed
                    much love and<lb/> sympathy with us in our undertaking also<lb/> some pertinent
                    communication concern-<lb/>ing the weighty business in which we<lb/> were
                    ingaged, a circumstantial account of<lb/> the Yearly Meeting and the recent
                    visita-<lb/>tion of sickness in <placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName>
                    and<lb/> parts adjacent-</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1799-02-19">19th of the month</date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>Some Indian traders<lb/> called upon us for lodging, amongst whom<lb/> was the
                    young War Chief of <placeName key="catta1">Catarugus</placeName><lb/> Village,
                    one of the company being a good<lb/> interpreter we informed the Chief that
                    one<lb/> of us had lately passed thro their Village<lb/> and taken a view of the
                    situation of some of <lb/>
                    <pb n="53" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_053"/> of their Land and thought it very
                    good, and<lb/> well situated for cultivating, to which the chief<lb/> replyed,
                    that him and his people<lb/> had it in contemplation for some time<lb/> past and
                    was very desirous of being instructed<lb/> therein, that they had a prospect of
                    building a Sawmill<lb/> and had come to a conclusion, that every young<lb/> man
                    should advance a part of his annuity from<lb/> Government into the hands of a
                    treasurer until<lb/> they had enough to build the Mill, that<lb/> they were very
                    desirous of having some per-<lb/>son amongst them to instruct their
                    children<lb/> but knew not where to apply, for when the<lb/> Quakers came
                    amongst the Indians to settle<lb/>
                    <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> kept us among his people, and<lb/>
                    now they saw and heard what we had done<lb/> here and that made them anxious to
                    go<lb/> to work, but they wanted some tools to<lb/> go on with but ware not able
                    to purchase<lb/> them; and if they should succeed in build-<lb/>ing the Saw Mill
                    they would want some<lb/> instruction how to go on with it</p>
                <p> We then<lb/> informed him of the motives of our society in<lb/> settling amongst
                    Indians, that our prospect<lb/> was not from any lucrative views but from <lb/>
                    <pb n="54" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_054"/> a desire to be useful to them, and
                    instruct them<lb/> in the cultivation of their Land, and wanted<lb/> nothing
                    from them for our trouble. And<lb/> that our prospect was not confined to
                    any<lb/> particular tribe of Indians, but were willing<lb/> (as much as lay in
                    our power) to assist any that made<lb/> application to us, and that we did not
                    wish to<lb/> go amongst them where the Chiefs and<lb/> leading Men were not
                    willing to receive us, and<lb/> the reason we came to <persName key="cornp2"
                        >Cornplanter</persName>'s people was<lb/> that a general circulatory Letter
                    had been<lb/> addressed and sent to these Nations of Indians<lb/> to know if any
                    of them were desirous of having friends<lb/> to instruct their Children in the
                    useful habits of<lb/> good and honest White people, <persName key="cornp2"
                        >Cornplanter</persName><lb/> was the only Chief that consented to
                    receive<lb/> us and therefore we came amongst his people<lb/> but that the way
                    was still open for others to<lb/> make application, and if the Chiefs and<lb/>
                    warriors of <placeName key="catta1">Cataraugus</placeName> Village were
                    desirous<lb/> of having any assistance from our society<lb/> and would send
                    their minds to us in<lb/> writing we would forward it to our friends<lb/> in
                        <placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName>, and perhaps some
                    assistance<lb/> would be given them- <lb/><pb n="55"
                        facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_055"/> we then asked him if they were
                    desirous<lb/> of aplying to our society or to the United States<lb/> To all
                    which he replyed <said>I am very<lb/> thankfull of an opportunity of such
                        information<lb/> there is no people affords such encouragement<lb/> as you
                        do. We have often heard from <persName key="cornp2"
                            >Corn-<lb/>planters</persName> that they had found you punc-<lb/>tual to
                        your words in every thing you<lb/> told them in the begining, and that
                        they<lb/> could not find the least fault with you<lb/> in any one thing. And
                        now I hear<lb/> you with my own ears and believe what<lb/> you say, and am
                        determined to apply<lb/> to you before any other People in the World<lb/>
                        and as soon as I return home we will<lb/> hold a council and send our
                        minds<lb/> to you in Writing for you to forward<lb/> to your Friends, And if
                        any of your<lb/> People should come amongst us, they<lb/> shall have Land to
                        settle on where ever<lb/> they want it, or anything that is ours that<lb/>
                        they stand in need of.</said>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1799-04-16">16th of 4th month</date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> we received the follow<lb/>ing Letter from the <orgName key="seneca">Cataraugus
                        Indians</orgName><lb/> near <placeName key="lakee">Lake Erie</placeName>- </p>
                <pb n="56" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_056"/>
                <floatingText type="letter">
                    <body>
                        <opener><dateline><date when="1799-04-11">April 11th</date>
                                <placeName key="catta1">Cataraugus,</placeName></dateline>
                            <salute>To the Allegany Quakers</salute></opener>
                        <p>This Day we<lb/> have met with our brothers as opportu-<lb/>nity to
                            return thanks to our Maker for<lb/> opportunity to proceed, Our business
                            is to<lb/> desire our friends to take into consideration<lb/> we desire
                            to get the knowledge of farming<lb/> from our friends as one God made
                            us<lb/> both, we have advanced ourselves but<lb/> still think fit to
                            imbrace opportunity, this offer'd<lb/> us by our friends if we have any
                            gift<lb/> that we may have our Eyes opened-<lb/> We first lay our matter
                            before you our<lb/> friends, as you have come forward and off-<lb/>ered
                            to assist in our undertaking, as there<lb/> is three Hundred and sixty
                            one souls in this<lb/> Village that have agreed to receive
                            instruc-<lb/>tion from you, as we desire to be instruced<lb/> in all the
                            various branches of learning<lb/> letters, pen, and tilling the field;
                            as we have<lb/> seen great benefit by <persName key="cornp2"
                                >Captain<lb/> Obeals</persName>, We desire to be instructed in
                            the<lb/> same rules </p>
                        <pb n="57" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_057"/>
                        <p>Brothers, If you will take into consi-<lb/>deration to favour us
                            according to our desire<lb/> and send such Men as you think fit to<lb/>
                            instruct us they shall have House and<lb/> Land to make themselves
                            comfortable,<lb/> and shall not be molested by friend nor foe,<lb/> but
                            be protected according to the best of<lb/> our abilities- and Brothers
                            If you<lb/> conclude to assist us in this time of need<lb/> and
                            necessity we desire you would help<lb/> to a set of Saw mill Irons- </p>
                        <closer>We are your friends<lb/>
                            <signed><persName key="tacono1">Ta con on gee</persName>
                                <persName key="waintaug1">Wain tau guh taugh</persName>
                                <persName key="tenian1">Tenianore</persName> &amp; others</signed>
                            In this Year of our Lord 1799</closer>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>

            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1799-10-05">10th of 5th month</date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> About this time a number<lb/> of Indians arrived from <placeName key="pitts"
                        >Pittsburgh</placeName> where they<lb/> had been to dispose of their Skins
                    furs<lb/> &amp;c. and brought in return a great quantity of<lb/> Whisky which they
                    sold to other Indians<lb/> at home which soon caused much confusion<lb/> and
                    intoxication amongst the Indians at <lb/>
                    <pb n="58" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_058"/>
                    <placeName key="cornp">Cornplanters</placeName> Village insomuch that we<lb/>
                    felt a disposition (or rather a freedom) to have<lb/> the Indians generally
                    collected that we<lb/> might endeavour to make them sensible<lb/> of their
                    misconduct and press upon them<lb/> the bad affects of that pernicious and
                    destruct-<lb/>ive article, accordingly a time was agreed<lb/> on and about 20 of
                    those that were sober<lb/> attended, where we communicated to<lb/> them our
                    concern for their wellfare and<lb/> happiness and also the many bad
                    affects<lb/>that the use of strong drink produced and<lb/> solicited them to lay
                    out their Money<lb/> in future for clothing, farming utensils,<lb/> domestic
                    animals, and such like ne-<lb/>cessary things: and in a short time they<lb/>
                    might become farmers and have<lb/> Milk, meat, and Clothing plenty, instead<lb/>
                    of the Elk they might knock down<lb/> the Cow and instead of the Deer they
                    might<lb/> kill the Sheep, and Swine, which would<lb/> supply them plentifully
                    with good meat<lb/> without exposing themselves to so <lb/><pb n="59"
                        facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_059"/> much toil and hardships wandering<lb/>
                    thro' the Snow when it is 2 or 3 feet<lb/> deep, The Indians sat pretty quiet
                    and some<lb/> of them appeared somewhat convicted, they in-<lb/>formed us that
                    they would consult each other<lb/> and others of their people when they get
                    sober<lb/> and give us an answer another time. A few<lb/> Days after the Indians
                    assembled again and<lb/> made reply to what we had said to them the<lb/>
                    substance is nearly as follows <said>We have made<lb/> enquiry and conversed
                        with each other concern-<lb/>ing you, but can find no faith in all your<lb/>
                        proceedings, but find you just and upright in<lb/> all your ways amongst us,
                        and that the<lb/> fault and bad conduct lies on our own side<lb/> We wish
                        you to make your minds easy<lb/> concerning us, for we intend to take
                        your<lb/> advice and try to do better. And we are<lb/> determined not to let
                        any more Whisky<lb/> be exposed for sale amongst us. We have<lb/> appointed
                        the young Chiefs to have the over-<lb/>sight of those that misconduct in
                        future.<lb/> We will now take up work and assist our<lb/> Women in the labor
                        of the field- </said></p>
                <pb n="60" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_060"/>
                <p>About this time we received a Letter from<lb/> our friends in <placeName
                        key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName> desiring one<lb/> of us to go to
                        <persName key="gwilk1">John Wilkins</persName> farm at<lb/>
                    <placeName key="hicko">Hickory Town</placeName> about 50 miles down this<lb/>
                    River for a yoke of Oxen which journey<lb/> fell upon myself, and I employed
                    an<lb/> Indian lad and embarked in a Canoe<lb/> with several others Indians
                    bound for<lb/>
                    <placeName key="frank">Franklin</placeName>, and arrived at <placeName
                        key="hicko">Hickory Town</placeName> in<lb/> about one Day and having had
                    a<lb/> prospect before I left home of geting a<lb/> Milch Cow at this place and
                    not find-<lb/> ing any here for sale, I concluded to ex-<lb/>tend my enquiries
                    farther and according-<lb/>ly went on foot as far as <placeName key="hicko"
                        >Hickory Town</placeName><lb/> but found none for sale. I then returned
                    again<lb/> to <placeName key="hicko">Hickory Town</placeName> got a yoke of Oxen
                    and<lb/> proceeded homewards, the first days travel<lb/> found the road very
                    rough and Mountain-<lb/>ous and in some places no path to be seen<lb/> at all.
                    The second day about dark got within<lb/> 3 or 4 miles of <persName key="cornp2"
                        >Cornplanters</persName> Town where we<lb/> were oblidged to lodge in the
                    woods without any<lb/> provisions or go home in the dark which <lb/>
                    <pb n="61" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_061"/> would be a very disagreeable
                    journey, however<lb/> we concluded to leave the Oxen in the woods<lb/> and try
                    if we could get to the town, which<lb/> we did with some difficulty being
                    pretty<lb/> tired and hungry, next day the cattle were<lb/> brought home by some
                    Indians</p>
                <p> After my return I was for several days engag<lb/> in the Carpenter-works of a
                    School House about<lb/> half a mile from <placeName key="genes1"
                        >Genisshadego</placeName> where the Indians<lb/> propose building a new
                    Town, while I was thus<lb/> engaged I received information that agreeable to<lb/>
                    <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanters</persName> orders three of his men had
                    ta-<lb/>ken the life of an Indian Woman, who had<lb/> been for some time past
                    strongly suspected<lb/> by the natives for having the art of witchcraft<lb/> and
                    was so despised that her husband put her away<lb/> and took another woman for
                    his wife, (which<lb/> as the story goes) so enraged her, that she<lb/>
                    threatened to take the life of a young child a<lb/> relation to her former
                    husband. This circumstance<lb/> very much agitated the minds of some of the
                    Indians<lb/> insomuch that <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> ordered
                    three of<lb/> his men immediately to take her life, she<lb/> being at that time
                    at work in the cornfield<lb/><pb n="62" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_062"/> with a
                    number of other Women who were<lb/> much alarmed to behold their companion<lb/>
                    stabed with knives</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1799-09-12">12 of 9th month</date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>arrived our beloved Friends<lb/>
                    <persName key="jshar1">Joshua Sharpless</persName>, <persName key="icoat1">Isaac
                        Coates</persName>, <persName key="tstew1">Thomas<lb/> Stewardson</persName>,
                    and <persName key="jcoop1">James Cooper</persName>, the sight<lb/> of which was
                    truly pleasing to me as I<lb/> had not seen any friends since<lb/>
                    <persName key="jpier1">John Pierce</persName> and <persName key="jshar1">Joshua
                        Sharpless</persName> left us<lb/> in the sixth month 1798 they brought
                    with<lb/> them a number of satisfactory letters<lb/> from our friends, and
                    relations, during<lb/> their stay with us they had a council with<lb/> the
                    Indians, admonishing them to useful habits<lb/> of industry, and read to them
                    the following<lb/> address which they committed to paper at<lb/> our House</p>
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body>
                        <dateline><date when="1799-09-12"/><placeName key="cornp"/></dateline>
                        <p> Brothers You have now heard that our<lb/> coming here was to see how you
                            and our<lb/> young men who are living among you<lb/> are getting along.
                            We are glad that the Good<lb/> Spirit has favoured us to meet you in
                            health<lb/> and given us this opportunity of taking<lb/> you by the hand
                            and brighening the <lb/>
                            <pb n="63" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_063"/> Chain of friendship. Now
                            Brothers we should<lb/> like to hear from your own mouths if you are
                            quite satis-<lb/>fied with our young men living amongst you<lb/> they
                            came here with an hope of being useful<lb/> by instructing you in a
                            better way of managing<lb/> your Land and providing for yourselves
                            and<lb/> Cattle, we desire you to speak freely</p>
                        <p>Brothers it has been some satisfaction to us<lb/> in riding thro' your
                            Town to see marks of indu-<lb/>stry taking place, that you are building
                            better<lb/> and warmer Houses to live in and that so much<lb/> of your
                            cleared Land is planted with Corn,<lb/> Potatoes &amp;c. and to see those
                            articles kept in<lb/> good order</p>
                        <p>Brothers We observe where your new houses<lb/> are building that the
                            timber is very much<lb/> cut off a rich flat which we wish you
                            encou-<lb/>raged to clear and make it fit for plow-<lb/>ing we believe
                            it to be very good Land for<lb/> Wheat as well as Corn and as the
                            White<lb/> People are setting around you the Deer and<lb/> other game
                            will grow scarcer and more difficult<lb/> to be taken. We therefore hope
                            that more of your<lb/> Men will assist in clearly Land, fencing it,
                                <lb/><pb n="64" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_064"/> planting it with
                            corn and sowing it with Wheat.<lb/> you will then have a supply of
                            provisions more<lb/> certain to depend upon than hunting</p>
                        <p>Brothers we were pleased to see your stock<lb/> of cattle increased. The
                            rich bottom on the<lb/> river will yield plenty for them to live on<lb/>
                            in the Summer Season, but as your win-<lb/>ters are long and cold it
                            will require some<lb/> thing for them to live on in Winter.<lb/> Now the
                            white people keep thin cattle<lb/> on hay, straw and cornfodder,
                            straw<lb/> you cannot get until you raise wheat or<lb/> other grain, the
                            rich bottoms if they ware<lb/> put in order would produce a great deal
                            of<lb/> hay, but for an immediate supply, we<lb/> think as soon as you
                            gather your corn<lb/> you should cut the stalks close at the<lb/> ground
                            bind them in small bundles<lb/> and put them in stacks as our<lb/> young
                            men do they would keep the<lb/> cattle part of the cold weather</p>
                        <p> Brothers We are pleased to see a<lb/> a quantity of new fence made this
                            sum-<lb/>mer near where our young men live <lb/>
                            <pb n="65" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_065"/> and we would not have you
                            get discouraged<lb/> at the labour it takes for if you will<lb/> clear a
                            little more land every year and<lb/> fence it you will soon get enough
                            to raise<lb/> what Bread you want as well as some<lb/> for grass to make
                            hay for winter</p>
                        <p>Brothers we understand you are desirous to<lb/> discourage whisky from
                            being brought among<lb/> you with which we are much pleased<lb/> and
                            should be glad if you would entirely<lb/> keep it away, for to get it
                            you give your<lb/> money which you should have to buy clothes<lb/> with
                            and to buy Oxen and ploughs with<lb/> to work your land, and it does not
                            do<lb/> you any good</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>After the foregoing writings wore<lb/> read one of our friends was favoured
                    in<lb/> a lively manner to communicate<lb/> some suitable hints of advice to the
                    Na-<lb/>tives well adapted to their present<lb/> state</p>
                <p>Before the council ended <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName><lb/> told
                    our friends that he had made inquiry<lb/> concerning us, but could not find any
                    fault <lb/>
                    <pb n="66" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_066"/> fraud or deception in us at all,
                    but were<lb/> perfectly satisfied with our being am-<lb/>ongst them </p>


            </div>
            <div type="narrative">
                <p>On the first day following<lb/> we had a very satisfactory meeting in our<lb/>
                    house at <placeName key="genes1">Genesinguhta</placeName> which was a<lb/>
                    tendering time to me and I believe our<lb/> little assembly was livingly owned
                    by<lb/> the true sheperd of Israel the silent</p>
                <p> The next day <persName key="jshar1">Joshua Sharpless</persName> fell
                    through<lb/> a trap door in a cellar which stunned<lb/> him, so that he lay for
                    a considerable time<lb/> before he came again to his senses, after he<lb/> had a
                    little recovered we found that he<lb/> was not very badly wounded, tho we<lb/>
                    were doubtful of his being able to tra-<lb/>vel next day which was the time
                    appo-<lb/> inted for their departure, but they got<lb/> themselves in readyness
                        (<persName key="jshar1">Joshua</persName> being anxious<lb/> for going) and
                    took an affectionate farewell<lb/> opportunity with us and set off about
                    noon<lb/> intending to go about 100 miles to the north into<lb/>
                    <placeName key="canad">upper Canada</placeName> in order to pay a visit to<lb/>
                    some of the scattering friends in that<lb/> quarter, they being on a committee
                    appointed<lb/> by the <orgName key="pym">Yearly meeting</orgName> for that
                    purpose </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="67" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_067"/>
                <dateline><date when="1799-10-07">7th of 10 mo</date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p><persName key="hsimm1">Henry Simmons</persName> took his depar-<lb/>ture from
                        <placeName key="genes1">Genesinguhta</placeName> and set out for<lb/> his
                    native land <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> and one of<lb/> his
                    men accompanying him as far as<lb/><persName key="canan">Canadarque</persName>
                    now were are left but two in<lb/> number about this time we killed<lb/> a fat
                    hog and a very fat beef we have a<lb/> pretty plentiful supply of Corn and<lb/>
                    Potatoes and some buckwheat have this<lb/> fall erected a small log barn and a
                    smith<lb/> shop and seem to have things pretty plen-<lb/>tiful about us and we
                    now begin to enjoy<lb/> the fruits of our labour from the field</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1799-12-28">28th of 12 mo</date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> About this time two chiefs<lb/> came from <placeName key="catta1"
                        >Cataraughus</placeName> being on their way<lb/> to <placeName key="cornp"
                        >Cornplanter</placeName>, Village who delivered us<lb/> a letter wrote on
                    behalf of the Chiefs of that<lb/> Village informing that they had received
                    letter<lb/> that was wrote and left at <placeName key="buffc1">Buffalo
                        Creek</placeName> last<lb/> fall by <persName key="jshar1">Joshua
                            Sharpless</persName> &amp;c. which pleased them<lb/> generally, and that they
                    intended to follow<lb/> the advice contained in it for they had<lb/> already
                    swallowed it in their breath and Hearts<lb/> that they were going to lay up
                    several hundred <lb/>
                    <pb n="68" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_068"/> Dollars of their annuity to buy
                    cattle and other<lb/> usefull articles, that they ware very anxious to<lb/> have
                    their friends the Quakers to instruct and<lb/> assist them in building a Saw
                    Mill, that they<lb/> were determined to throw up drinking whisky<lb/> and if any
                    traders brought it amongst them they would<lb/> order them off the ground. We
                    returned them<lb/> the following answer by the aforesaid Chiefs.</p>
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <opener>To the Chiefs and others of <persName key="seneca"
                                >Cataraugus</persName><lb/>
                            <salute>Friends and Brothers</salute></opener>
                        <p>We received your<lb/> letter in company with one to <persName
                                key="cornp2">Captain<lb/> Obeal</persName> and are glad to find that
                            you got a<lb/> good understanding of what our friends<lb/> wrote to you
                            at <placeName key="buffc1">Buffalo Creek</placeName> and that the<lb/>
                            instruction they gave pleased you generally,<lb/> Now Brothers we did
                            not see that speech<lb/> that our friends left at <placeName
                                key="buffc1">Buffalo Creek</placeName> for you<lb/> but as you are
                            determined to take their advice<lb/> and have already swallowed it down
                            in your<lb/> breasts we hope you often remember and con-<lb/>sider
                            it</p>
                        <p> Brothers we are glad to hear that you have <lb/><pb n="69"
                                facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_069"/>come to a resolution to lay up so
                            much of your<lb/> money in order to buy Cattle and other useful<lb/>
                            articles, and that you are determined to quit<lb/> drinking whisky and
                            not to allow any traders to<lb/> sell it on the ground- Now Brothers
                            this<lb/> is a very wise resolution in you and we hope<lb/> you will be
                            sincere and keep to it, we heartily<lb/> wish all the Indian tribes
                            would join you in<lb/> driving Whisky and Rum out of the Land.<lb/> We
                            hope some of you have got you Eyes opened<lb/> to see that Whisky and
                            strong drink has been<lb/> the cause of much evil and wickedness
                            amon-<lb/>gst you, and that it has taken away much of<lb/> your money,
                            your skins, and your furs which<lb/> the Great Spirit has given you to
                            buy blankets,<lb/> clothing, axes, hoes, and other useful articles<lb/>
                            to assist you in tilling the field. And we fear<lb/> in time past it has
                            taken away some of<lb/> the corn your poor Women has worked<lb/> hard at
                            raising with their hoes-<lb/> Brothers you must know that there are
                            many<lb/> white people that love money and they<lb/> know that you love
                            Whisky and this is <lb/>
                            <pb n="70" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_070"/> the way they take to get
                            your money and<lb/> property from you, But if you keep to your<lb/>
                            resolution not to drink it then there will<lb/> be no danger, You will
                            then have money<lb/> to buy Oxen and ploughs to plow your ground<lb/>
                            and raise a great deal of corn, and to buy Axes,<lb/> and hoes, and
                            other useful articles to go to<lb/> farming with; And then when
                            your<lb/> Brothers the Quakers hear that you are<lb/> trying to do good
                            for yourselves and making<lb/> good use of your money it will
                            encourage<lb/> them to help you more</p>
                        <p> Brothers we want you often to think on<lb/> the Great Spirit and to pray
                            to him in your<lb/> Hearts and then he will show you what is<lb/> good
                            and what is evil. And we desire<lb/> you to take up work like the
                            white<lb/> people, for your land we believe is very<lb/> good and will
                            produce a great deal of grain<lb/> if you are industrious; And when you
                            get<lb/> plenty of cattle, Swine and Sheep they will<lb/> afford you
                            plenty of meat and be much<lb/> easier taken than the Elk the Deer and <lb/>
                            <pb n="71" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_071"/> Bear, then will your old
                            men, your wives,<lb/> and your children, be happy and enjoy<lb/> the
                            comforts of life, and you will look<lb/> on your flocks your fields and
                            your fruit<lb/> trees with contentment and pleasure-<lb/> Brothers and
                            Sisters we are young men<lb/> and can't say a grat deal to you but
                            we<lb/> intend to send an account how you<lb/> are coming on to our
                            elder brethren in<lb/> Philadelphia and we can assure you that they<lb/>
                            will be your friends and council you wisely<lb/> in every thing for your
                            good, and we<lb/> hope your ears will always be open to<lb/> listen to
                            their talk</p>
                        <closer>We commend you to the care of the<lb/> Great Spirit and are your
                            friends<lb/> and brothers<lb/>
                            <signed>
                                <persName key="jswai1">Joel Swayne</persName><lb/>
                                <persName key="hjack1">Halliday
                                    Jackson</persName></signed><dateline><date when="1799-12-28"
                                    /><placeName key="genes1"/></dateline></closer>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1800-01-08">8 of the 1st month 1800</date><placeName
                        key="genes1"/></dateline>
                <p><persName key="cornp2">Cornplanters</persName> sis-<lb/>ter brought one of her
                    sons to place him<lb/> with us in order to have him educated in<lb/> school
                    learning and brought up like <lb/>
                    <pb n="72" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_072"/> white children after some
                    consideration we<lb/> complyed with her request and she left<lb/> her son with
                    us-</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1800-02-10">10th of second month</date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> About this time the<lb/> Indians collect'd together to perform their<lb/> half
                    years devotion, at which times they<lb/> are mostly careful to collect all the
                    Silver<lb/> tinkling ornaments, and fine apparel that<lb/> they are master of. I
                    changed to see a broad-<lb/> cloth wrapper that belonged to one of our<lb/>
                    neighbour women the lower end of which<lb/> contained 790 silver broaches which
                    would<lb/> average at about one shilling a piece exclu-<lb/>sive of about 60
                    dols worth of silver crosses, the<lb/> upper end was faced with broad
                    ribones<lb/> which was computed at about 15 dols price<lb/> the whole amount of
                    the wrapper was es-<lb/>timated at 180 Dollars. Yet altho she had<lb/> abundance
                    of superfluous clothing she lived<lb/> in a poor little dirty House. I was
                    afterwards<lb/> informed that she obtained this pro<lb/>perty by selling whisky
                    to other Indians, <lb/>
                    <pb n="73" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_073"/> the Indians continued about 20 Days
                    in their<lb/> usual mode of worship and dancing which<lb/> I shall probably
                    describe at a future time<lb/> when I may have an opportunity of seeing<lb/>
                    them</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1800-03-25">25th of 3rd month</date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> By the arrival of T. King<lb/> from Philad. we this Day received several<lb/>
                    Letters from our Relations and friends, amon-<lb/>gst which was one from the
                        <orgName key="pymind">Committee on<lb/> Indian affairs</orgName> which
                    amongst other things<lb/> contained the fllowing information viz<lb/>
                    <said>Various consideration has induced us to believe it<lb/> right to withdraw
                        our friends from the<lb/>
                        <orgName key="oneida">Oneida</orgName> Nation, several of the Indians
                        have<lb/> been instructed in the best mode of tilling<lb/> this Land, and
                        two or three young men<lb/> have acquired so much knowlage in the<lb/>
                        Smiths Business as to be able to do what<lb/> may be wanted in that line for
                        the use<lb/> of the Nation, so that by a proper applica-<lb/>tion on their
                        part, they will be assenti<lb/>ally benefited by the Labours bestowed on
                        them</said><lb/> and that <persName key="jthom2">Jonathan Thomas</persName>
                    &amp; <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName><lb/> neither of them felt
                    released from further service<lb/> amongst the Nations, and that the Committee <lb/>
                    <pb n="74" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_074"/> expected in a short time they would
                    be<lb/> willing to come to this place with a pros-<lb/>pect of residing some
                    time among the <orgName key="allegany">Allegany<lb/> Indians</orgName></p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1800-05-25">25 of 5th month</date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> This morning arrived the<lb/> above named friends which seemed to<lb/> open the
                    way with cleanness for <persName key="hjack1">Halliday<lb/> Jackson</persName>
                    to return home as he has for some<lb/> time had a prospect of being released
                    from<lb/> his present engagement. They brought<lb/> with them several friendly
                    and sympa-<lb/>thetic Letters from my Friends at home.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1800-06-08">6 mo 8th</date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> an express came from <placeName key="seneca">Cattanaugus</placeName><lb/>
                    requesting some of us to assist them in view-<lb/>ing a seat for a Saw Mill,
                    accordingly <persName key="hjack1">H.<lb/> Jackson</persName> &amp; <persName
                        key="jtayl1">J. Taylor</persName> went for the purpose<lb/> and returned
                    again in six Days informing<lb/> that they had a satisfactory interview<lb/>
                    with the Indians, fixed on a place<lb/> to build the Mill, and were of the
                    mind<lb/> that there was a pretty favourable open-<lb/>ness for a settlement to
                    be made at that<lb/> place. a few Days after their return we<lb/> met the
                    Indians in council at <persName key="cornp2">Corn-<lb/>planters</persName>
                    Village after a certificate of <lb/>
                    <pb n="75" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_075"/> recomendation for <persName
                        key="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName> &amp; <persName key="jthom2"
                        >Jonathan<lb/> Thomas</persName> was read, the Indians expressed much<lb/>
                    satisfaction with the Quakers being among<lb/> them and that they thought the
                    Indians<lb/> and the White People would in a short<lb/> time be all alike, after
                    the Indians had done<lb/> speaking we reminded them of 20 Dollars<lb/> that they
                    had urged us to accept at the<lb/> time of the division of their yearly
                    anuity<lb/> and that we thought it would be best<lb/> to add as much to it, as
                    would buy a<lb/> yoke of oxen for the use of the Town<lb/> which some of them
                    seemed to consent<lb/> too with some reluctance, <persName key="hjack1">H
                        Jackson</persName> next<lb/> informed them of his intentions of
                    re-<lb/>turning to his native Land and <persName key="cornp2"
                        >Corn-<lb/>planter</persName> appointed two Indians to ac-<lb/>company him
                    as far as <placeName key="ceres">Cerestown</placeName>,<lb/> 55 miles up the
                    River </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>accordingly on <date when="1800-06-17">17th of this month</date><placeName
                        key="ceres"/></dateline>
                <p> he bid adieu to old<lb/><persName key="genes1">Genesinguhta</persName> and
                    departed I bore<lb/> him company to <placeName key="ceres">Cerestown</placeName>
                    as I had<lb/> some business there and returned home<lb/> in four Days having
                    lodged comfortably two<lb/> nights in the woods, and partook of a plentiful <lb/>
                    <pb n="76" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_076"/> supply of venison and fish which
                    the Indians<lb/> killed by the way</p>
                <p> An unfortunate circumstance happened among<lb/> a company of Indians that was
                    lately hunting<lb/> on the waters of Beaver and had pitched this<lb/> tent near
                    a white mans house who kept<lb/> Whisky to sell which occasioned some
                    difference<lb/> between the White Man and one of the Indians<lb/> the White at
                    length got other ruffians to assist<lb/> him in taking the lives of the Indians
                    who<lb/> were not aprised of their intentions, in order to<lb/> prosecute their
                    horrid plan they went to<lb/> the Indians camp with Guns and imediately<lb/>
                    shot one of them dead on the spot another<lb/> seeing what was done immediately
                    attem-<lb/>pted to make his escape with a child under<lb/> each arm but was
                    followed by a ball which<lb/> wenet thro' his breast and thro' the
                    shoul-<lb/>der of one of the Children and the wrist of<lb/> the other; one of
                    the murderers is now<lb/> secured in <placeName key="pitts"
                        >Pittsburgh</placeName> in order for tryal-</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1801-01-25">1801 1 mo 25th</date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> About this time considerable<lb/> uneasyness arose in the minds of some of
                    the<lb/> Indians from being informed by a <lb/>
                    <pb n="77" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_077"/> malicious white Man that my motives
                    in<lb/> coming here was to try to get a mile square<lb/> of Land from them as I
                    had been here ever<lb/> since the settlement was first established<lb/> for the
                    improvement of the Natives, two<lb/> Indians came to talk with us on the
                    occasion<lb/> and we endeavoured to convince them<lb/> that the report was
                    intirely groundless and<lb/> that we did not want any of their Land<lb/> nor
                    other property for any of our service<lb/> amongst them</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1801-01-26">26th of the month</date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> we received informa-<lb/> of the Death of Hyute a young indian man<lb/> that had
                    been lately married who after<lb/> about eight days illness died at his
                    hunt-<lb/>ing camp in the woods about 17 miles<lb/> from home. The above
                    information caused<lb/> me some serious reflections, as he was a<lb/> young man
                    in the bloom of life and<lb/> flower of his Days, and in health just a few<lb/>
                    days before, I was led to reflect on the un<lb/>certainty of our existance here
                    in this<lb/> world and how very necessary it is for every<lb/> one to be
                    prepared at any hour to<lb/> meet the messenger of Death</p>
                <pb n="78" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_078"/>
                <p>The death of Hyute led me to enquire<lb/> of one of our neighbours how the
                    Indians<lb/> divided the property of a deceased person.<lb/> I was informed that
                    it is commonly divi-<lb/>ded amongst the brothers and sisters<lb/> of the
                    deceased. the Wife or Children having<lb/> no claim thereto, but in former
                    times<lb/> they buried the apparrel with the corps<lb/> and then burned the
                    House with<lb/> all of its contents</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1801-01-30">30 of the month</date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> 20 or 30 Indians<lb/> called at our house being on their way<lb/> to <placeName
                        key="cornp">Genisatego</placeName> to perform their half<lb/> years worship
                    and notwithstanding I<lb/> have never been to see them I will en-<lb/> deavour,
                    to give a brief account of their<lb/> proceedings which I had by
                    information.<lb/> In the first place they are very zealous<lb/> to have their
                    people generally collected<lb/> some that are not able to walk are hauled<lb/>
                    by two or three of their friends ten or twelve<lb/> miles on the ice or snow
                    wrapped up in Blan-<lb/>kets, buck-skins, when the necessary prepa-<lb/>rations
                    are made they place themselves<lb/> in a circle round a large image which is <lb/>
                    <pb n="79" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_079"/> erected on a pedestal about six
                    feet high<lb/> and having a white Dog skined and dres-<lb/>ed they lay him on a
                    hot fire which is<lb/> previously prepared for the purpose, and<lb/> while he is
                    consuming one of the Chiefs<lb/> on behalf of the people addresses the
                    Great<lb/> Spirit in thanksgivings for the game<lb/> they have been permited to
                    take in their<lb/> hunting hours, after this is done another<lb/> Chief takes
                    about half a pound of Tobacco<lb/> lays it on the fire and addresses the
                    people<lb/> by way of admonition and exhortatin<lb/> During the rendevous they
                    are dressed in their<lb/> best apparrel and many of them have their<lb/> faces
                    painted in many frightful wild looking<lb/> figures and their heads decorated
                    with feathers<lb/> painted different colours and beaded belts &amp;<lb/>
                    Mockasons which altogether forms a very wild ro-<lb/> mantic appearances to one
                    not acquain-<lb/>ted with Indians. They continue their<lb/> dancing and
                    different manuevers about<lb/> six or seven Days with an abundance of
                    rattling<lb/> and tinkling ornaments about their feet<lb/> and legs and their
                    clothes decorated with<lb/> hundreds of silver broaches, breasplates &amp;c. <lb/>
                    <pb n="80" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_080"/> on their way home many of them<lb/>
                    called at our House amongst them was<lb/> an elderly female Chief with whom<lb/>
                    we had considerable conversation, amongst<lb/> other things she observed that
                    the Indian<lb/> Women had too great a burden to labour under<lb/> for the Men
                    would work but little, the Women<lb/> had to cut and carry home all the fire
                    wood,<lb/> plant &amp; raise all the Corn pound it &amp;<lb/> prepare it for
                    eating, and when it was<lb/> ready the Men must eat first, and when<lb/> the Men
                    killed any Deer the Women had to<lb/> carry home the meat and what was
                    worse<lb/> than all the Men often got Drunk and<lb/> then they would beat and
                    abuse the<lb/> Woman and yet they had to bear it all.<lb/> I was a little
                    pleased with the old Womans<lb/> remark as many of them do not seem<lb/> willing
                    their husbands should work.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1801-04-27">4 Mo 27th</date><placeName key="french"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> I set out in company with<lb/> two Indians in a Canoe loaded with wheat<lb/>
                    intending to go to <placeName key="oilcr">Oil Creek</placeName> Mill about <lb/>
                    <pb n="81" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_081"/> eighty miles down the River. but
                    being<lb/> informed on the way that the Mill was<lb/> out of repair, I concluded
                    to go to a mill<lb/> about twenty miles further on the<lb/> waters of <placeName
                        key="french">French Creek</placeName>, after getting the<lb/> grinding done
                    set out homeward<lb/> of the being very rainy and disagree-<lb/>able traveling:
                    the most of the way the Indians had the fortune<lb/> to kill a very large Bear.
                    As he<lb/> was crossing the River, which afforded<lb/> us plenty of good meat on
                    the journey.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1801-05-06">The 6th of 5 mo</date><placeName key="cornp"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> We arrived at <placeName key="cornp">Cornplanters</placeName> Village<lb/>
                    having travelled about 200 miles in the whole<lb/> rout and lodged five or six
                    nights in the woods<lb/> on the banks of the River</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1801-07-18">7th Mo 18th</date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> Received two Letters from friends<lb/> in Philadelphia one directed to the
                        <orgName key="seneca">Seneca</orgName> Indi<lb/>ans of <placeName
                        key="alleg1">Allegany</placeName>, the other to the <orgName key="munseeind"
                        >Munceys</orgName><lb/> at <placeName key="catta1">Cattenaugus</placeName>
                    respecting the late difficulty<lb/> that subsisted between them on account
                    of<lb/> supposed witchcraft also two from the Go-<lb/>verner of Pennsylvania
                    directed to the<lb/> above mentioned Indians on the same<lb/> subjuect. </p>

            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="82" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_082"/>
                <dateline><date when="1801-08-04">8 Mo 4</date><placeName key="genes1"/></dateline>
                <p>78) Received letters from my<lb/> connections in <placeName key="newga">New
                        Garden</placeName> informing of<lb/> a Prospect of a visit this summer of
                    some<lb/> of the <orgName key="pymind">Committee on Indian affairs</orgName>,
                    also<lb/> that a young many by occupation a Black<lb/> smith had given up to
                    come and spend<lb/> some time in this settlement which<lb/> was very
                    satisfactory news to me,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1801-08-17">8 mo 17</date><placeName key="cornp"/></dateline>
                <p> This being the time agreed on<lb/> by some of the Indians to have the
                    Govern<lb/>nors letter explained to them, two of us<lb/> went to <placeName
                        key="cornp">Gineshadago</placeName> for that purpose<lb/> where we found the
                    most of the chiefs<lb/> and a number of others collected for<lb/> also an
                    Ancient man who was<lb/> a very great Speaker belonging to the<lb/>
                    <orgName key="onondaga">Onondago</orgName> Nation, and held in much<lb/> esteem
                    by the <orgName key="seneca">Senecas</orgName>, he having re-<lb/>ceived some
                    previous information of<lb/> the contents of the Governors letter<lb/>
                    <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> having opened it and had<lb/> some
                    parts of it explained before it<lb/> came to our and seemed somewhat<lb/>
                    disaffected towards the Governor, and intimated<lb/> to some of his people that
                    the letter should be burned<lb/> before the letters were read the <orgName
                        key="onondaga">Onondaga</orgName> Chief<lb/> spoke a considerable time
                    requesting them<lb/> to pay attention to the Governors advice said<lb/> he
                    thought none of the letters should be destroyed </p>
                <pb n="83" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_083"/>
                <p>After the aged chief had done speaking the<lb/> Governors letter and one from
                    Friends in<lb/> Philadelphia was read and interpreted<lb/> to them which very
                    much contradicted<lb/> their absurd belief in witchcraft which<lb/> seemed
                    considerably to agitate the mind<lb/> of <persName key="cornp2"
                        >Cornplanter</persName>, yet some others appeared<lb/> to receive it pretty
                    well and appeared to<lb/> be somewhat ashamed for having before<lb/> entertained
                    such foolish notions-<lb/> After the letters directed to the <orgName
                        key="seneca">Senecas</orgName><lb/> were read <persName key="cornp2"
                        >Cornplanter</persName> insisted on having<lb/> those read, which were
                    directed to the <orgName key="munseeind">Mun<lb/>ceys</orgName> we informed him
                    that the Governors<lb/> Letter was sealed and that we did not wish<lb/> to break
                    it open, but if he had a mind<lb/> to open it we would read it at the same<lb/>
                    time cautioning him against it but the<lb/> Governor or the <orgName
                        key="munseeind">Muncys</orgName> might be displeased<lb/> Still the old man
                    insisted upon opening the<lb/> letter and having it read which was done<lb/> he
                    afterward signified that it should be burnt<lb/> for said he, it will do the
                        <orgName key="munseeind">Muncys</orgName> more harm<lb/> than good- another
                    Chief said he was not<lb/> of the same mind and he thought it would<lb/> be best
                    for all the Chiefs to shead their sinti<lb/>ments on the occasion, that it was
                    his mind<lb/> that it would be best for the letter to be<lb/> forwarded to them-
                    it was afterwards agreed<lb/> that all the letters to both parties should<lb/>
                    be explained to all the <orgName key="seneca">Seneca</orgName> Chiefs at<lb/>
                    <placeName key="catta1">Catterangus</placeName> and <placeName key="buffa"
                        >Buffaloe</placeName>, and then the <orgName key="munseeind"
                        >Mun<lb/>ceys</orgName> letter carefully conveyed to them<lb/> the writing
                    were according by forward<lb/>ed by the <orgName key="onondago"
                        >Onondago</orgName> Chief how the matter will<lb/> end is uncertain </p>
                <pb n="84" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_084"/>
                <p>A few days after <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanters</persName> Brother <persName
                        key="conud1">Con<lb/>nudiu</persName> or Handsome Lake collected a num<lb/>
                    ber of Indians and told them he had lately<lb/> needed instructions from Heaven
                    by three<lb/> men whom he stated he had previously seen<lb/> these men had told
                    him many things, that<lb/> the Indians shamed keep up their old prac<lb/>tice
                    and manner of claiming for that was<lb/> right and if they did so the Great
                    Spirit would<lb/> send into their woods great plenty of game<lb/> and cover
                    their ground with a new and rich<lb/> soil whereby the Indians may live
                    plen<lb/>tifully without much labor and that it was<lb/> not right for them to
                    raise wheat and corn<lb/> to sell to one another but they were right<lb/> in
                    wearing old and ragged clothes and in<lb/> painting their skins and tanning
                    often which<lb/> was pleasing to the great spirit. These and<lb/> often such
                    like foolish and supersitious doc<lb/>trines and nations tends very much to
                    obstruct<lb/> the work of civilization being calculated to suit<lb/> the weak
                    ideas of the natives, and retard our<lb/> endeavours for their good - About this
                    time<lb/> while their minds were in much agitation<lb/> some of them gas a
                    little displeased with<lb/> the Quakers being amazed then and as we<lb/> were
                    informed came to a conclusion that<lb/> we should have the plan <persName
                        key="habee1">Henry Obeal</persName>, the<lb/> son of <persName key="cornp2"
                        >Cornplanter</persName> being as far our with us<lb/> had a very warm debate
                    with them<lb/> on the ocassion and told them what we had<lb/> done for them
                    which served to put a<lb/>
                    <pb n="85" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_085"/> stop to their proceedings. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1801-09-15">9 mo 15</date><placeName key="genes1"/></dateline>
                <p>This day <persName key="jpier1">John Pierce</persName>
                    <persName key="tstew1">Tho Stew<lb/>ardson</persName> and Vincent Wiley arrived
                    at<lb/> our house, the sight of whoom was truly<lb/> satisfactory to us
                    particularly to my<lb/> self, I having for a considerable time<lb/> part had a
                    prospect of being released<lb/> from my present engagement &amp; W<lb/> being a
                    Blacksmith will now release<lb/> me I having had to act in that capa<lb/>city in
                    many instances although pre<lb/>viously acquainted with the <gap/><lb/> look
                    forward to a return my<lb/> nation land having been engaged in the<lb/> Indian
                    concern upwards of three years </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1801-09-18">18 of the month</date><placeName key="genes1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> being the time apprai<lb/>sed to have an interview with the<lb/> Indians
                        <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> and several other<lb/> Chiefs
                    attended and about 20 of their<lb/> young men and warriors attended also<lb/>
                    with two of the principal men from <placeName key="buffa"
                        >Buffa<lb/>loe</placeName> and two from <placeName key="tonne"
                        >Tonewanto</placeName>, our friends<lb/> read a certificate from the
                    committee<lb/> on Indian affairs which was inter<lb/>preted to good satisfaction
                    by <persName key="habee1">Henry<lb/> Obeal</persName> also one for V Wiley who
                    intended<lb/> stay my someimte amongst them<lb/> after matters were treated or
                    Friends i<lb/>nformed them of the great satisfaction is<lb/> afforded them to
                    obey over the inform<lb/>
                    <pb n="86" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_086"/> many of them had made in clearing<lb/>
                    <gap/> and farming this land, building<lb/> houses &amp; the unease of their
                    cattle<lb/> since they were among them before, and<lb/> that they had taken up a
                    resolution to grant<lb/> drinking whiskey and of her strong drinks<lb/> it was a
                    very satisfactory conference</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1801-09-22">9 Mo 22</date><placeName key="catta1"/></dateline>
                <p>Took my departure from <placeName key="genes1">Genesh<lb/>ingutla</placeName> in
                    company with the Cornplanter after a solemn leave of those we <lb/>left behind
                    and a number of Indians<lb/> that collected to witness our departure<lb/>
                    travelled about 20 miles through the woods<lb/> having a very rough road and
                    some rain<lb/> encompassed about 4 oclock and rested pret<lb/>ty comfortable
                    next morning set forward<lb/> and found the road find some places upstream<lb/>
                    by bad until we came to <placeName key="catta1">Cattaraugas</placeName>
                    kind<lb/> man which there is abundance of land of<lb/> the best quality and the
                    most beautiful tim<lb/>ber I ever saw chiefly Black Water and Pop<lb/>lar bar
                    after passing about six miles down the<lb/> river we came to the <placeName
                        key="catta1">Cattaraugus</placeName> Village<lb/> and lodged in the house of
                    the Chief Warrior<lb/> and was kindly entertained, his wife en<lb/>deavouring to
                    make us as comfortable as<lb/> possible</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1801-09-24">24</date><placeName key="buffa"/></dateline>
                <p> Left <placeName key="catta1">Catteraugus</placeName> about one oclock,
                    follow<lb/>ed a rough disagreeable path about 7 miles<lb/> to <placeName
                        key="lakee">Lake Erie</placeName> which opened to my view a<lb/> very
                    gratifying and agreeable prospect<lb/> the beach afforded a very good road
                        <lb/><pb n="87" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_087"/> and abandoned with many
                    curiousi<lb/>ties formed by nature and is very<lb/> instructing to a
                    contemplative<lb/> mind we rode at the rate of about<lb/> five miles per hour,
                    until we came<lb/> to a stream of water called Carigua<lb/>ga where we encamped
                    by the side of<lb/> the lake and represented ourselves and<lb/> know with
                    provisions we carried<lb/> with us, we pushed out tent and had<lb/> a pretty
                    comfortable night lodging<lb/> although cattle<lb/> are frequent in these
                    parts<lb/> &amp; fed our horses and took breakfast<lb/> and set forward on our
                    journey about<lb/> six o'clock being pleasingly entertain<lb/>ed by the curious
                    lands of the Lake<lb/> which in some places we thought<lb/> was 80 or 90 feet
                    perpendicular and<lb/> interested with different kinds of<lb/> stone many of the
                    rocks being over<lb/> and by wrong by the waves into coves<lb/> and curls in a
                    fantastic manner<lb/> about 11 we arrived at <placeName key="buffc1">Buffaloe
                        Creek</placeName><lb/> which we crossed in a small flat to<lb/><placeName
                        key="buffa">Buffaloe</placeName> Village on the opposite side<lb/> where we
                    remained till next day hav<lb/>ing about 80 miles from <placeName key="genes1"
                        >Genesingatta</placeName></p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1801-09-27">27</date><placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p> crossed the <placeName key="niagr">Niagara</placeName> at <placeName key="ferie"
                        >Fort Erie</placeName><lb/> about one mile wide and the water<lb/>
                    <pb n="88" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_088"/> run my very rapidly although<lb/>
                    it was thought to be a very favor<lb/>able time to cross on account of the<lb/>
                    wind blowing up the oven which<lb/> prevented all high from the<lb/> lake, after
                    landing in <placeName key="canad">Canada</placeName> we<lb/> travelled about 10
                    miles up the Beach<lb/> thence one mile inland to<lb/> a friend from Jersey
                    where we staid all<lb/> my were kindly entertained<lb/> &amp; went about 2 miles
                    to <persName key="ascho1">Asa Schooleys</persName><lb/> where we met with
                        <persName key="irowl1">Rowland</persName>, <persName key="iwils2">Isaac<lb/>
                        Wilson</persName> on <persName key="rhunt1">Rachel Hunt</persName>
                    <persName key="lshar2">Lydia Sharp<lb/>less</persName> and <persName
                        key="jcros2">Jane Crosson</persName> who were apart<lb/> of the committee
                    appointed to visit<lb/> friends in <placeName key="canad">Canada</placeName>, a
                    meeting was<lb/> held at <persName key="bscho1">B Schooleys</persName> house,
                    where about<lb/> 40 people attended mostly friend<lb/> it appeared to be a
                    satisfactory op<lb/>portunity in the afternoon by William<lb/> &amp; myself took
                    leave of <persName key="jpier1">J Pierce</persName> <persName key="tstew1">T
                        Stew<lb/>ardson</persName> and other friends present<lb/> and departed
                    intending to neturn<lb/> immediately homewards, we lodged<lb/> that night
                        <persName key="dpoun1">Danl Pound</persName>s </p>

            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="89" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_089"/>
                <dateline><date when="1801-09-28">28</date><placeName key="niagf"/></dateline>
                <p> set out for Ng early and rode<lb/> about 20 miles to the falls of <placeName
                        key="niaga">Niagara</placeName><lb/> the greatest Phenomenon and the
                    most<lb/> gratifying sight I had ever beheld<lb/> the water beginning a very
                    rapid de<lb/>scent about three quarters of a mile<lb/> above the cataract,
                    there<lb/> is an Island of 10 or fifteen acres<lb/> just above the precipice
                    which divides<lb/> the sheet of water in its fall at one<lb/> patch of 150 feet,
                    a continual mist<lb/> arises which may be seen for many<lb/> miles and it is
                    thought the roar<lb/>ing of the Cataract may be heard for<lb/> 20 or 30 miles on
                    a still morning, a<lb/> short distance above there are erec<lb/>ted a Grist
                    mill, Saw mill, and Forge<lb/> and excellent seats for that purpose<lb/> there
                    are 17 saws in one frame<lb/> which cuts a log in to boards at<lb/> one through,
                    and would I should sup<lb/>pose cut 10,000 feet of boards in a day,<lb/> several
                    other miles are in contem<lb/>plation at the same place after<lb/> viewing the
                    falls from the top we<lb/> went about half a mile down the<lb/> river, and
                    descended about 35 feet<lb/> by an Indian Ladder that was crea<lb/>ted for the
                    purpose thence down a <lb/>
                    <pb n="90" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_090"/> very steep hill to the water<lb/>
                    and went up to the Cataract<lb/> when the mist is continually fal<lb/>ling, was
                    passed on a little farther<lb/> until we got within the edge of the sheet<lb/>
                    of water, at this time the wind vary<lb/>ing a little blew some of the
                    water<lb/> on us, it was a beautiful yet awful<lb/> sight, we then ascended the
                    bank and<lb/> went on foot to the <placeName key="chipp1">Chippiway</placeName>,
                    where we<lb/> had left our horses, then rode 20 miles<lb/> to an inn near the
                    outlet of the Lake.<lb/> heard the roaring of <placeName key="niagf"
                        >Niagara</placeName> very plain</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1801-09-29">29</date><placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p> Crossed the river and rode about 40 miles<lb/> the most of the way good roads
                    across an<lb/> open Country called the <placeName key="woakp">Whitecoke
                        Plains</placeName><lb/> the two last miles being very muddy &amp;<lb/> deep
                    which we traveled after dark but<lb/> kept the road without much difficulty</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1801-09-30">9 mo 30</date><placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> Left Davison and travelled to the<lb/><geogName key="genes2">Genesee
                        River</geogName> mostly by muddy River<lb/> the land pretty good, on the
                    east side<lb/> of the River we found very good roads<lb/> and the country pretty
                    <gap/> by in<lb/>habited many elegant dwelling house<lb/> mostly farm and some of
                    these<lb/> painted white, the inhabitants<pb n="91"
                        facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_091"/><lb/> living mostly from New England<lb/>
                    and are generally remarked for bei<lb/> a very industrious and
                    enterpri-<lb/>sing people, the land from <placeName key="genes1"
                        >Geneseting</placeName>
                    <placeName key="canan">Cana<lb/>darque</placeName> is g </p>


            </div>
            
            <div type="undetermined">
                <pb n="92" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_092"/>
                <pb n="93" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_093"/>
                <pb n="94" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_094"/>
                <pb n="95" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_095"/>
                <pb n="96" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_096"/>
                <pb n="97" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_097"/>
                <pb n="98" facs="hv_swaynej_diary_1798_098"/>
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
