<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei-print.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="global.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>A series of letters written on a Journey to the Oneida, Onondago, and Cayuga
                    Tribes of the Five Nations, by Joseph Sansom: Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Haverford College Quaker Collection</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>Julian Turner</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Journal transcribed by</resp>
                    <name>Crowd-sourced</name>


                </respStmt>

            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca.98 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Haverford College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street/>
                    <addrLine>Haverford, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode/>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>This work is the property of Haverford College QUaker and Special
                        Collections. It may be copied freely by individuals for personal use,
                        research, and teaching (including distribution to classes) as long as this
                        statement of availability is included in the text. It may be linked to
                        freely in Internet editions of all kinds, including for—profit works.</p>
                    <p>Publishers, libraries, and other information providers interested in
                        providing this text in a commercial or non—profit product or from an
                        information server must contact Haverford College for licensing and cost
                        information.</p>
                    <p> Scholars interested in changing or adding to these texts by, for example,
                        creating a new edition of the text (electronically or in print) with
                        substantive editorial changes, may do so only with the permission of
                        Haverford College. This is the case whether the new publication will be made
                        available at a cost or free of charge.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2016">2016</date>
                <idno type="local">hv_sansomj_letters_1796</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Native Americans and Quakers: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Haverford College Quaker &amp; Special
                            Collections</institution>
                        <collection/>
                        <idno>MC 1008, Box 23, Folder 4</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>48 pp. (1 volume)</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Joseph Sansom manuscript is housed in Haverford College Quaker &amp; Special
                    Collections</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> The transcribers and editor attempted to render the author’s orthography and
                    grammar as they appear on the page of his journal, even when the author’s own
                    spelling and usage are inconsistent. Additionally, many questions remain about
                    spelling the names of his Quaker acquaintances, individual Native Americans who
                    populate his journal, and Indian villages and towns. The transcribers and editor
                    attempted to remain faithful to the author’s Anglicized spellings in all cases. </p>
                <p>The author of the original journal does not include page numbers on his
                    manuscript; the page numbers have been interpolated by the transcribers to
                    correspond with the manuscript sheets.</p>
            </editorialDecl>

        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written in <date when="1796">1796</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Society of Friends</item>


                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>

        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item>
                    <date when="2016"/></item>

            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
        
            <div type="undetermined">
                <pb n="1" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_001"/>
                <pb n="2" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_002"/>
            </div>
            
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="3" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_003"/>
                <head>A Series of letters written on a Journey to the <orgName key="oneida"
                        >Oneida</orgName>, <orgName key="onondaga">Onondago</orgName>, and <orgName
                        key="cayugaind">Cayuga</orgName> Tribes of the <orgName key="sxntns">Five
                        Nations</orgName>, including the <orgName key="brotherton"
                        >Brothertons</orgName>, <orgName key="stockbridge">Stockbridges</orgName>,
                    and some of the <orgName key="tuscarora">Tuscaroras</orgName>, settled upon the
                        <orgName key="oneida">ONEIDA</orgName> RESERVATION; undertaken by <gap/>iah
                    Rowland, James Cooper, <persName key="jpier1">John Pierce</persName>, and
                        <persName key="jsans1">Joseph Sansom</persName>, mainly for the settling of
                    <gap/>Taylor, <persName key="hsimm1">Henry Simmons</persName> Junior, and
                        <persName key="ewalk1">Enoch Walker</persName> at a Tract of Land. the said
                    Reservation originally about twenty miles west north west of <placeName
                        key="alban">Albany</placeName>, in the State of New York; for the purpose of
                    attempting the gradual Improvement and Civilization of the INDIANS: in the
                    Summer of the year 1796. <lb/><gap/>er the Direction of a Committee of the
                    Yearly Meeting of Friends. Pennsylvania, &amp;c. </head>

            </div>
            
            <div type="undetermined">
                <pb n="4" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_004"/>
            </div>
            
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="5" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_005"/>
                <opener><dateline><persName key="ehall2">Edward Halluck</persName>s, on the Banks of
                        the <placeName key="nrive">North<lb/> River</placeName>, 160 miles N. E. of
                        Philad. a<lb/>
                        <date when="1796-06-03"> 7th. day morn.g 6th. Mo. 3rd.
                        1796</date></dateline>
                    <salute>My dear Friends, </salute></opener>

                <p>We reached this Place last evening, and some of<lb/> us, being thoroughly tired
                    of rising early and lying down late, are<lb/> glad to embrace the grateful
                    intermission of first day, among<lb/> Friends, at the expense of to day: so we
                    have put out our<lb/> Cloaths, to be washed' and are mostly employed, in the
                    different<lb/> nooks and corners of an old fashioned house, in opening our<lb/>
                    hearts to the tender Connections we have left behind us, the<lb/> more endeared
                    by distance, difficulty, and solitude. The<lb/> particulars of our Journey are,
                    so far, scarcely interesting<lb/> enough to bear recital: yet I should feel
                    myself wanting to<lb/> the partiality of love and affection if I were to omit
                    what<lb/> I know will be grateful to you, and so shall proceed from<lb/> stage
                    to stage with all the regularities of a Journalist.<lb/> Having all collected at
                        <persName key="chain1">Caspar Haines</persName>'s by 3 o'clock,<lb/> we took
                    leave of the Friends who accompanied us about 5,<lb/> and rode, mostly in the
                    rain, over very muddy road, 10<lb/> miles to <persName key="dcumm1">David
                        Cummings</persName>'s, on the old York Road, where<lb/> we were kindly
                    entertained, two of our Company going to <lb/>
                    <pb n="6" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_006"/> Samuel Gomere's [a friend in the neighborhood] to lodge. Early<lb/>
                    next morning they gave us a breakfast, and bade us good steed<lb/> which we
                    improved by riding 20 miles to <persName key="opaxt1">Oliver Paxson</persName>'s
                    neat<lb/> Carrigells Ferry on Delaware, to dinner; and in the after noon,<lb/>
                    crossing the river a few miles above, 17 to <persName key="hclaf1">Henry
                        Clafton</persName>'s<lb/> in <placeName key="kingw">Kingwood</placeName>, a
                    pleasant village on very high ground where<lb/> we were accommodated for the
                    night as before. Next day<lb/> we rode 40 miles, including 5 wherein we mifed
                    the road, and<lb/> had a grand view of the blue mountains, forming a vast<lb/>
                    amphitheatre of hills and woods around <placeName key="easto"
                    >Easton</placeName>, the sun<lb/> glittering upon its white houses and shine
                    rendering it a most<lb/> beautiful object the 10 miles distant. Dined on bread
                    and<lb/> butter, and honey, about 11 oclock and reached <persName key="jlund1"
                        >Jacob Lundy</persName>'s<lb/> [the husband of <persName key="slunda1">Sarah
                        Lundy</persName>] time enough to see the sun<lb/> shed his last rays with
                    unusual brilliance over the field and<lb/> woods. I was pleased to see his
                    Father and Mother spending<lb/> their last days in ease and quiet in a little
                    hut built for<lb/> them at one end of the house, from which they have the
                    plea<lb/>sure of seeing their Descendants thrive about them, and<lb/> deceiving
                    the lediousness of leisure by chopping a passel of<lb/> mending a stocking to
                    keep up the semblance of wanted utility </p>
                <pb n="7" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_007"/>
                <p>Next morning his so a lad of 15 guided us several miles<lb/> across intricate
                    roads toward <placeName key="susse">Sussex Court House</placeName>, a
                    dismal<lb/> looking place with a jail under it, and a whipping post and<lb/>
                    stocks before, no the almost absolute insignia of<lb/> the cruel system of past
                    times, soon I hope to be every where<lb/> supplanted by the spade and the
                    distaff. Our<lb/> last Host, as we were going out of the Settlements of
                    Friends,<lb/> had directed us to the hospitality of a <persName key="chath1"
                        >Colonel Hathorne</persName>,<lb/><del>for the night</del> at a suitable
                    distance for the night, not<lb/> recollecting that he was a member of Congress,
                    which we dis-<lb/> covered on the road, and as he was not at home went 10
                    miles<lb/> further to a place called <placeName key="chest">Chester</placeName>,
                    and lodged at an Inn. The<lb/> Landlord was old enough to remember old times
                    with an evident<lb/> preference, and with respect to Government in particular
                    he<lb/> thought as somebody else does sometimes that we had got out of the
                    frying pan into the fire. This<lb/> being our first tavern fare we did not take
                    it kindly, and<lb/> started off, <del>before</del> without breakfast, tho' we
                    were glad afterward to<lb/> take it as we could get it, and rejoiced when we
                    came in<lb/> sight of the <placeName key="nrive">North River</placeName> which
                    is here a mile and a half<lb/> wide; but so diminished by comparison with the
                    prodigious<lb/> mountains which surround it, that more of our Company ex <lb/>
                    <pb n="8" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_008"/>(Recollecting the <geogName key="susqu">Susquehannah</geogName> at
                        <placeName key="wrigh">Wright's Ferry</placeName>) thought it<lb/> cept
                    myself more than half of one. Two miles along those<lb/> brought us to <persName
                        key="dburn1">Daniel Byrnes</persName>'s, where we seemed at home<lb/> again,
                    staid through the heat of the day, the weaker now<lb/> growing worser, and rode
                    12 miles in the evening<lb/> to this hospitable mansion, whose venerable Owner
                    now in his<lb/> 79th year, when he crossed the river to settle here 40
                    years<lb/> ago was the only Friend in there part and held a meeting at<lb/> his
                    own house some time, has lived to see ten of his children<lb/> married and
                    settled among Friends so near him that he<lb/> could visit them all in a day.
                    Tomorrow evening we intended<lb/> making a short stage to a Friends house, and
                    expect to reach<lb/>
                    <placeName key="alban">Albany</placeName>, about 80 mile from here, by 3rd day
                    evening from<lb/> whence I shall probably write to you again, </p>
                <closer>with all the<lb/> dutiful affections of Husband, Son and Brother
                        <signed>Joseph Sansom</signed></closer>

            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <pb n="9" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_009"/>
                <opener><dateline>Fourth Day<lb/>
                        <placeName key="alban">Albany</placeName>
                        <date when="1796-06-08">6th. Mo. 8th. 1796</date></dateline>
                    <salute> My dear Friends</salute></opener>
                <p>Agreeably to the expectation given you in my<lb/> last I write again from this
                    low-dutch City, of which you<lb/> will have a tolerable idea when you figure to
                    yourselves<lb/> an old square Church (with a roof almost high enough<lb/> for a
                    steeple, capped with a clumsy belfry) fixed trans-<lb/> versely across the
                    center streets, which wind about it<lb/> in all directions, generally presenting
                    gable ends, scol-<lb/> loped with battlements, and often antiquated with the
                    lead-<lb/> ed casements that have so long given way to the improve-<lb/> ments
                    of modern times elsewhere. But I am un-<lb/> intentionally rambling from
                        <placeName key="ehall1">Edward Hallock</placeName>'s patri-<lb/> archal
                    family; <del>before</del> I have told you that his Fa-<lb/>ther lived to see 140
                    of his Descendants, to the 4th ge-<lb/>nerations; and <persName key="ehall1"
                        >Edward</persName> himself begins to keep count for<lb/> 100 to the third:
                    like somebody else he is still more<lb/> active than either of his sons,
                    abounding with life and<lb/> spirit, anecdote and observation. One
                    circumstance<lb/> of his life deserves particular attention: shortly after<lb/>
                    the British took possession of New York and Long Island,<lb/> I think in 1776,
                    he attended the Yearly Meeting then<lb/>
                    <pb n="10" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_010"/> held at <del>although</del>
                    <orgName key="nyym">Westbury</orgName> tho' all communication was for-<lb/>
                    bidden under pain of death. Being somewhat doubtful<lb/> of the propriety of
                    this risqueing his life, he was confirmed<lb/> by a dream, in which he saw and
                    heard the Persons who<lb/> should trouble him for this act of religious duty
                    threatening<lb/> what they would do to him: but he was assured that they<lb/>
                    should not have power to hurt him, and received directions<lb/> how to conduct
                    himself, and even what to say when<lb/> they should question him. Singular as it
                    may appear<lb/> the latter was couched in the following verses:<lb/>
                    <quote type="poem">O mortal Men! your ways and works consider,<lb/>Sleep not in
                        death least there you be forever<lb/> Awake! and stand upright, that you
                        restor'd maybe<lb/> Both from your sins and evils great, with all
                        iniquity.<lb/> Ye Cedars tall, and Oaks, so strong, tho' towred up on
                        high,<lb/> The fire is kindled at your root, come down before you
                        die.</quote><lb/> When he was afterward had before the Committee of
                    Safety<lb/> he boldly addressed them in these words, <said>If I have done
                        any<lb/> thing worthy of death or of bonds I am ready to an-<lb/>swer for
                        it.</said> They seemed at a loss to begin with him,<lb/> which gave him an
                    opportunity to ask them if he should<lb/> tell them his dream. They said he
                    might, and he re- <lb/>
                    <pb n="11" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_011"/> repeated it to them as above; upon which they seemed as<lb/>
                    tonished, and dismissed him til the next meeting: but they<lb/> did not then
                    make a board; which was the case afterward<lb/> again, and again, till they
                    finally deferred his case for a<lb/> month; saying they should never be able to
                    make a board<lb/> else' and when he attended again there was nobody there<lb/>
                    but the Chairman, and he told him he might go about<lb/> his business. Not
                    feeling perfectly easy to travel thro'<lb/> the Country on first day evening, we
                    started fresh on<lb/> 2.nd day morning, glad to be under way again,
                    feel-<lb/>ing our minds more and more drawn to our object as we<lb/> proceed.
                    Edward set us 5 miles on our way, and we<lb/> rode as usual thro' a rugged and
                    broken Country to<lb/>
                    <placeName key="esopu">Eusopus</placeName>, a town of 80 or a hundred
                    houses<lb/> mostly well built with stone, an inscription on the<lb/> Court House
                    where we dined (for it was also a very<lb/> decent Inn and the County Jail)
                    informed us that<lb/> the town was burnt by the British in the year 1777,<lb/>
                    so completely we were afterward told that just one<lb/> house and one barn
                    escaped the flames. This was done<lb/> under the command of General Vaughan,who
                    was then<lb/> waiting, on board of the Transport in the <placeName key="nrive"
                        >North River</placeName>,<lb/> to facilitate the unsuccessful attempt of
                    General Burgoyne, <lb/>
                    <pb n="12" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_012"/> in revenge for the cruel treatment of the Friends<lb/> to the former
                    Government at this place, and the rash<lb/> conduct of the Townspeople in living
                    upon the Ships<lb/> as they lay at anchor. From this place we rode several<lb/>
                    miles through a deep sand, like that of Jersey covered<lb/> with pines, saw a
                    beautiful waterfall upon our<lb/> left; and crossed a small creek in a Scow, for
                    the first<lb/> time since we left the <placeName key="delaw"
                        >Delaware</placeName>. We did not<lb/> reach <placeName key="catsk1"
                        >Katskill</placeName> the place of our destination for the night<lb/> till
                    dusk, and could not then get over the Creek<lb/> to the town, because the Boat
                    was aground on the other<lb/> side. In this dilemma the Owner of an adjoining
                    House,<lb/> by name <placeName key="jboga1">Jacob Bigordeiss</placeName>,
                    offered us the best accommo-<lb/>dations his house could afford; which we gladly
                    accepted.<lb/> He freely expressed his good will when we<lb/> told him what was
                    our business; and in the morning<lb/> took us out to see a place, near the
                    Creek, where<lb/> the side of a hill had gradually sunk down a few<lb/> days
                    before between 40 and 50 feet. About an acre<lb/> of it has descended
                    perpendicularly; and as much more<lb/> of the lower part had bulged up, and
                    cracked aston-<lb/>ishingly, apparently by the vent of the air confined <lb/>
                    <pb n="13" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_013"/> in the cavern into which the hill had fallen. There was a<lb/> flock
                    of sheep upon it at the time, who were seen to scatter<lb/> with the first
                    fright, but finding themselves hemmed in, they hud<lb/>dled together till the
                    earth settled, and then scudded away for<lb/> terra firma. A large current of
                    muddy water had been long ob<lb/> served to issue from this hill, into the tide
                    way, which had pro<lb/>bably almost worn it thro: but there was no appearance of
                    an<lb/> earthquake. Our Host told us that when he came here 6 years ago,<lb/>
                    there were but Nine Houses in the Town, and now there were<lb/> not less than 20
                    Stores, this being a principal outlet for the Weste<lb/>rn Country. After this
                    however our days ride was very uninter<lb/>resting through broken land, and a
                    tract of Pines extending almost<lb/> to Albany, rendered doubly tedious by the
                    incess and turns and win<lb/>dings of the road, often forming a semicircle
                    instead of a line, and<lb/> sometimes turning three sides of a square. I am just
                    not called to dinner and<lb/> so conclude with our distance from <placeName
                        key="oneid">Oneida</placeName>, (supposed to exceed a<lb/> hundred miles)
                    which we have to make by the end of the week, and<lb/> my love and good wishes
                    for you all, as is named, and other en<lb/>quiring Friends...</p>
                <closer> Your affectionate Kinsman<lb/>
                    <signed><persName key="jsans1">Joseph Samson</persName></signed></closer>

            </div>
            
            <div type="undetermined">
                <pb n="14" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_014"/>
            </div>
            
            <div type="letter">
                <pb n="15" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_015"/>
                <opener><dateline><placeName key="newst">New Stockbridge</placeName>, about 200
                        miles north<lb/> of Philad.a but by the way of New<lb/> York and <placeName
                            key="alban">Albany</placeName> near 400<lb/><date when="1796-06-14">
                            6th. Mo. 14th. 1796</date></dateline><salute>My dear
                    Friends,</salute></opener>
                <p>Dearer, and dearer, as if by the rule of contraries,<lb/> the farther I go from
                    you. We left <placeName key="alban">Albany</placeName> on the<lb/> day of my
                    last letter, glad to turn our backs upon it,<lb/> tho' it is evidently rising
                    into wealth and consequence,<lb/> being likely to become the Seat of Government
                    in a few<lb/> years, and the center of the Western Trade, which has
                    al-<lb/>ready raised the value of property to a comparison<lb/> with the excess
                    of Philadelphia and New York. Its<lb/> Burghers value themselves as the most
                    ancient Corporation<lb/> in the United States: but you will think it an empty
                    one<lb/> when I add that it has only the precedence<lb/> of a single day.
                    Traversed 14 tedious<lb/> miles of sandy road, through a Forest of Hemlock,<lb/>
                    and lodged at Schenectady, a considerable town on the<lb/> banks of the Mohawk,
                    which is here about as large<lb/> as <placeName key="schri"
                        >Schuilkill</placeName>, but preserves a gentle current,<lb/> through a long
                    tract of Country, by being dammed <lb/>
                    <pb n="16" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_016"/> up, near its junction with the <placeName key="nrive">North
                        River</placeName>, at the head<lb/> of the tide, by a solid ledge of Rocks,
                    supposed to be<lb/> from 100 to 150 feet high, over which the water pours<lb/>
                    with amazing violence. The channel is now clearing<lb/> out, and this place is
                    to be rendered passable by<lb/> Locks, which will open a river navigation of
                    300<lb/> miles; and a canal of 5 or 6, now undertaken, will<lb/> give a
                    communication with <placeName key="lakeo">Lake Ontario</placeName>, by
                        <placeName key="woodc">Wood Creek</placeName>,<lb/> and so open a scene of
                    inland connection scarcely<lb/> to be parrallelled, at a comparatively trifling
                    expence.<lb/> Our road lay on both sides of this beautiful river for<lb/> the
                    two next days, several times crossing its windings<lb/> by Ferries, bridges, and
                    often taking up rich<lb/> flats, highly cultivated, yet without partition
                    fences,<lb/> and surrounded on the high land with neat and <lb/>comfortable
                    houses. <note>See the bottom of the 4th page</note> On 6th. day evening we reached<lb/>
                    <persName key="fschy">Fort Schuyler</persName> as the present head of the
                    navigation,<lb/> exhilarated with the sight of the West Country<lb/> Boats,
                    going down the River, with Pos Ash, &amp; and<lb/>
                    <del>surprised</del> agreeably surprised with continued <lb/>
                    <pb n="17" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_017"/> Settlements of the townships of <placeName key="white"
                        >Whitestown</placeName>, first begun<lb/> about 9 years ago by Judge White,
                    in the wild wood,<lb/> tho' now extending 5 or 6 miles along the road, like<lb/>
                    the street of a village, the log hovels intermixed here<lb/> and there with
                    large and handsome frame houses. The<lb/> front lots are already valued at S100
                    an acre,<lb/> and the adjacent farms from 10 to 20, such is<lb/> the fertility
                    of the soil, and the influx of Settlers.<lb/> Here we had the pleasure of
                    meeting with <placeName key="wfloy1">General<lb/> Floyd</placeName>, one of the
                    Commisioners for managing the<lb/> Affairs of the <orgName key="brotherton"
                        >Brotherton Indians</orgName>. He told us that<lb/> he intended to meet them
                    in a few days, to arrange their<lb/> business upon the footing lately prescribed
                    by law, and<lb/> seemed very desirous that one of our Settlers might<lb/> reside
                    among them. <persName key="jwhit1">Judge White</persName>, and the rest<lb/> of
                    the neighboring Gentrs to whom we had an intro-<lb/>ductory letter, being all
                    absent, attending Court, we<lb/> concluded to go on for the Reservations.
                    without<lb/> waiting for their return, and rode through a rugged<lb/> but
                    fertile and populous Country, in the first stages <lb/>
                    <pb n="18" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_018"/> of improvements, you 8 miles; and where the road or<lb/> pathway
                    turned off for <placeName key="newst">New Stockbridge</placeName>, we very
                    opportunely met with<lb/> a drunken Indian, who acknowledged us for
                    Brothers<lb/> with a very good will, and undertook to guide us thro'<lb/> the
                    thick woods with which this Settlement is surround.<lb/> We came to the first
                    houses near night, where the<lb/> Young Men where drawn up in Indian stile,
                    stooting<lb/> at a mark, and Men Women an Children looking<lb/> on received us
                    with stoical indifference. The<lb/> main Settlement being 3 miles further we
                    invited<lb/> ourselves in, asked for supper, and merrily<lb/> helped ourselves,
                    with wooden ladles, and pewter spoons,<lb/> out of a large dish of milk and cold
                    mush baked<lb/> almost to the consistency of bread. This done we<lb/> made our
                    beds upon the floor, and slept till the pigs<lb/> roused us, in the morning, by
                    grunting about us with<lb/> all the familiarity of messmates, impatient for
                        breakfast.<note>Continue at the bottom of the 5th pa.</note>
                    <lb/>20 or 30 miles from <placeName key="schen">Schenectady</placeName>, passed
                    by the old Mansion House<lb/> of <persName key="wjohn3">Sir William
                        Johnson</persName>, remarkable for being flanked with<lb/> wings, one of
                    which has an arched roof. The famous Hall <lb/>
                    <pb n="19" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_019"/> where he afterward resided as a Chief of the <orgName key="mohawk"
                        >Mohawk</orgName> Tribe,<lb/> is a few miles to the north. <del>When</del>
                    he died shortly<lb/> after the late French war. During the Revolution, his<lb/>
                    Son <placeName key="jjohn4">Sir John</placeName> went off with the Tribe, to the
                    British<lb/> in Canada; from whence they made incursions into the<lb/> Country,
                    particularly in 1780, when they came down<lb/> to the number of 600, killed some
                    of the inhabitants, and burnt all the houses for<lb/> many miles round: but it
                    was remarked that they<lb/> did not injure the Women and Children within<lb/>
                    the ancient <orgName key="mohawk">Mohawk</orgName> boundaries, though many
                    were<lb/> murdered without the line. For many miles<lb/> further we were
                    frequently reminded of that, here<lb/> peculiarly, distressing period by small
                    block houses<lb/> or strong log buildings, sometimes square, sometimes octa<lb/>
                    gonal, of two or three stories projecting one over the other<lb/> for the
                    purpose of annoying Assailants before, and pierced<lb/> through with portholes
                    of various sizes, and a look<lb/> out at top. <note>Continue at the bottom of
                        the 2d. page.</note><lb/> In the morning <persName key="haupa1">Hendrick
                        Aupaumut</persName>, one of the Chiefs<lb/> of the <orgName
                        key="stockbridge">Stockbridges</orgName>, and two others came to meet us on <lb/>
                    <pb n="20" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_020"/> horseback, and conducted us to the town, where we were<lb/> very
                    well entertained by his good wife, a managing well-<lb/>disposed Woman. These
                    People settled here by the courters<lb/> of the <orgName key="oneida"
                        >Oneidas</orgName>, about 12 years ago, upon a Tract of excellent land,<lb/>
                    6 miles square, having sold themselves out of house and home, in<lb/> the
                    northern parts of Massachusetts, where they had long resided,<lb/> under the
                    care of a Missionary from the <orgName key="sspck">Scotch Society for the<lb/>
                        propagation of the Gospel.</orgName>
                    <persName key="jserg2">John Sergeant</persName> is their present Pastor.<lb/> He
                    stays with them half his time, two months alternately, and<lb/> appears to have
                    their wellfare at heart, being now here with<lb/> two agreeable Daughters, who
                    make us wellcome. There are<lb/> about 60 Families of them, amounting to about
                    300 persons,<lb/> increasing rapidly, for Indians, as the births exceed the
                    deaths<lb/> as 2 to 1. This is evidently in consequence of their peace<lb/>
                    able, and comparatively, sober and industrious way of living. Every Fa-<lb/>mily
                    has 100 acres in its own right, and as much is divided<lb/> off to every new
                    Beginner; the rest, together with a Saw Mill,<lb/> three yoke of Oxen, some
                    Horses, and an annuity of 250 dollars<lb/> a year, from the United States, being
                    held in common. This<lb/> we learnt from their Chiefs and Councellors in a
                    private con-<lb/>ference; one of the latter, called <gap/> impressing us
                    <lb/>all with respect, by singular meekness, gravity, and decorum.<lb/> On 20.
                    day morning we had a public hearing in their meeting <lb/>
                    <pb n="21" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_021"/> house <del>with</del> 80 to 100 men and women, being present; when
                        <del>in which</del> we explained to them<lb/> our views, with which they
                    appeared satisfied, tho' they had evidently<lb/> expected more from us than it
                    is likely we shall think proper to<lb/> dispense here, as they want nothing but
                    directions to put them<lb/> in a very comfortable way of living, and this Chief
                        <persName key="haupa1">Capt. Hend<lb/> rick</persName> has already set them
                    an encouraging example by raising<lb/> 100 baskets of wheat and as many of
                    Indian Corn in a year.<lb/> I expect to write again before we leave this
                    Reservation,<lb/> as we have yet no accounts of <placeName key="jtayl1">Jacob
                        Taylor</placeName>, and so conclude<lb/> for the present. </p>
                <closer>Your affectionate Kinsman<lb/>
                    <signed><persName key="jsans1">Joseph Sansom</persName></signed></closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>P.S. If my dear Beulah should be from home when this<lb/> reaches <placeName
                            key="phila">Philada</placeName> please to have a copy made out to
                        send<lb/> her, with the inclosed, as it mentions no particulars; and<lb/>
                        inform whoever may call in you for letters from the other<lb/> Friends, that
                        they will be directed to the care of <persName key="jelli1">John<lb/>
                            Elliott</persName> -- It would do our hearts good to have heard
                        from<lb/> our Friends, and if you <del>would</del> write by post to the
                        care<lb/> of <persName key="ichap1">Capt. Israel Chapin</persName> at
                            <placeName key="canan">Canadarquai</placeName>, we may probably<lb/>
                        have the pleasure of taking up the letters ourselves, by<lb/> the end of the
                        month.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
            
            <div type="undetermined">
                <pb n="22" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_022"/>
            </div>
            
            <div type="letter">
                <pb n="23" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_023"/>
                <opener><dateline><placeName key="fschy">Fort Schuyler</placeName>, on the Mohawk,
                            <date when="1796-06-20">6th. Mo. 20th. 1796</date>
                    </dateline><salute>My dear Friends,</salute></opener>
                <p>My last if I recollect right, was dated this day week;<lb/> yet, as I trusted it
                    to an accidental opportunity, I think it very<lb/> probably you will receive
                    this first. It carried us to <persName key="haupa1">Hendrick<lb/>
                        Aupaumuts</persName>, at <placeName key="newst">New Stockbridge</placeName>,
                    and left us under the good keeping of<lb/>
                    <persName key="lquin1">Lydia Quinney</persName> (for the Wife does not here
                    assume the name of her<lb/> Husband) one of the best Housewives, considering
                    circumstances,<lb/> that we have ever known, no offence I hope to Anybody. You
                    may be sure we were not in<lb/> haste to leave her; yet having appointed to meet
                    the <orgName key="oneida">Oneidas</orgName> on<lb/> 3rd. day afternoon we set
                    out, on foot, and in the rain, though<lb/> it cleared up before we had travelled
                    far, through thick woods,<lb/> and marshy bottoms. Two miles brought us to a
                    little remnant<lb/> of the <orgName key="tuscarora">Tuscaroras</orgName>, who
                    fled here 80 or 100 years ago from the banks<lb/> of the Patowmack, and, If I am
                    right, have been ever since incor-<lb/> porated with the ancient <orgName
                        key="sxntns">Five Nations</orgName>, now six. The main<lb/> body of them
                    sided with the British in the late war, and are<lb/> settled on the banks of
                        <placeName key="niaga">Niagara</placeName>. The few that remain<lb/> under
                    the patronage of the <orgName key="oneida">Oneidas</orgName>, appear helpless
                    and forlorn,<lb/> almost without a Chief, and without a Counsellor. Two
                    miles<lb/> further we came across the scattered hamlets of the <orgName
                        key="oneida">Oneidas</orgName>,<lb/> original Proprietors of this fertile
                    spot, who I think at the Treaty of <lb/>
                    <pb n="24" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_024"/> of <placeName key="fstan">Fort Stanwix</placeName>, in 1784,
                    reserved to themselves a Tract of about<lb/> twenty miles square, well watered
                    by several beautiful streams<lb/> upon the border of a charming lake, abounding
                    with Fish. Of<lb/> this however they have since given away one fourth to the
                    different<lb/> Tribes that have claimed <del>that protection</del> kin with
                    them. When they were<lb/> asked to sell they replied: <quote>No, we will not
                        sell our Land,<lb/> to our own Flesh and blood: but we will give you what
                        you<lb/> want.</quote> Another fourth they have lately sold to the State
                    of<lb/> New York, I understand at a dollar an acre (now selling again<lb/> at
                    four and five). The purchase money however is funded, and<lb/> yields them four
                    or five thousand dollars a year, part of which<lb/> is to be vested in Saw
                    Mills, Grist Mills, &amp; &amp; and the remain<lb/>der of in good hands would
                    soon stock their land and enable them <lb/> to live far better than People
                    generally do, even in our happy <lb/> Country. But with all these advantages
                    they drone away their<lb/> lives supinely in idleness and want; their former
                    occupations of fighting<lb/> hunting &amp; naturally ceasing on the White
                    Settlers increase<lb/> and no new plans having been yet adopted.<lb/> about
                    them, they are now about 600, tho continually lessening<lb/> while the other
                    Tribes on this Reservation, who till their land, encrease in a rate<lb/> that
                    would double their numbers in about 30 years. They<lb/> received us kindly, and
                    expressed their willingness to adopt<lb/> our proposals for their gradual
                    civilization, saying <said>the compact<lb/> between our Forefathers was made a
                        great while ago: but now<lb/> it begins to take effect.</said> Here we think
                    to make our first<lb/> Their principal Chief, called <persName key="jsken1"
                        >Seanmadoa</persName>, appears to be a Man in whom the<lb/> utmost
                    confidence may be placed. He is as firm and erect at 78 as our People
                    <lb/>usually are at 60<lb/>
                    <pb n="25" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_025"/> essay upon a piece of level land that has lain common a great<lb/>
                    many years, like a public square, in the centre of their bark huts<lb/> and log
                    houses. Upon which a few of the most tractable Youths<lb/> are to be taught as
                    Apprentices; and the rest will have the<lb/> opportunity of observing the
                    progress, and witnessing the reward<lb/> of their labour. When the business is
                    got under way some of<lb/> our Young Men will occasionally visit the <orgName
                        key="tuscarora">Tuscaroras</orgName>, above-<lb/> mentioned, <orgName
                        key="stockbridge">Stockbridges</orgName>, and <orgName key="brotherton"
                        >Brothertons</orgName>, for the necessary purposes<lb/> of putting forward
                    their work in due season, and improving them<lb/> in the principles of husbandry
                    and good living, in the ru-<lb/>diments of which the two latter are already
                    pretty well grounded.<lb/> On 7th. day morning we visited the <orgName
                        key="brotherton">Brothertons</orgName>, and were sur-<lb/>prised to find
                    them dressed like us, speaking the same<lb/> language, and many of them almost
                    as fair as ourselves.<lb/> Most of the Children having chesnut hair, and some
                    curled.<lb/> They consist of 40 or 50 Families that have been brought<lb/> up in
                    different parts of New England, Long Island, &amp; and<lb/> so naturalized to
                    our language, and customs that<lb/> they now use no other; which has such an
                    effect upon<lb/> persons and principles that I am persuaded they may incorporate
                    with the White<lb/> Inhabitants, in and age or two, upon equal terms. These<lb/>
                    People affairs have been lately put upon an advantageous<lb/> footing by the
                    kind interposition of the Friends of New York,<lb/>
                    <pb n="26" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_026"/> and they appear to us to be in a thriving way, as to
                    spirit-<lb/>uals, as well as temporals. It being their practise to meet for
                    Divine<lb/> Worship twice every first day, under the profession of the
                    Baptists,<lb/> and exercise their own spiritual gift, when no Minister
                    attends<lb/> them. Others of us are now at <placeName key="fschy">Fort
                        Schuyler</placeName>, looking out a little<lb/> impatiently for <persName
                        key="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName>, of whom we have yet heard<lb/> no
                    tidings. Tomorrow we are to introduce ourselves to some more<lb/>
                    <note>I hope to receive letters from you by<lb/> Post at <placeName key="canan"
                            >Canandaigua</placeName> thro' <persName key="ichap1">Captain
                            Chapin</persName></note><lb/> of the principal persons of the
                    neighborhood; and next day to<lb/> rejoin our Friends at <placeName key="oneid"
                        >Oneida</placeName>, from whence I shall probably<lb/> write again, before
                    we set out for the westward, to repeat the <lb/>feelings of my heart, which are
                    continually reminding me <lb/>of the near and dear Relations, Friend, and even
                    Acquaint-<lb/>ance, and Fellow Citizens, that I have left behind me. </p>

                <closer><signed><persName key="jsans1">Joseph Sansom</persName></signed></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <pb n="27" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_027"/>
                <opener><dateline><placeName key="newst">New Stockbridge</placeName>
                        <date when="1796-06-21">6th Mo 21th 1790</date></dateline>
                    <salute>My dear Friends,</salute></opener>

                <p>Little has occurred since my last beside the cus<lb/>tomary disappointment of
                    long expected contingencies, no <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob
                    Taylor</persName><lb/> having yet been heard of, and the usual tediousness and
                    procrastina<lb/>tion of Indian Councils, extraordinarily lengthened out by the
                    novelty<lb/> of our proposals, apparently no less unexpected, than the reply of
                    Her<lb/> Rules to the staff'd Waggoners. "Set thy shoulders to the wheel, and I
                    will<lb/> help thee" We staid at <placeName key="white">Whitestown</placeName> a
                    day or two, and waited upon<lb/>
                    <persName key="jwhit1">Judge White</persName>, and several other persons to whom
                    we were recommended; and<lb/> had the satisfaction to find them all, as well as
                    the Neighborhood in gene<lb/>ral, favorably disposed toward our undertakings;
                    and willing to render<lb/> us any assistance we may be likely to want from them.
                    Here also we<lb/> introduced ourselves to <persName key="jbelk1">Jeremiah
                        Belknap</persName>, Author of the History of New<lb/> Hampshire, and
                        <persName key="jmors1">Jedediah Morse</persName>, who wrote the Geography of
                    the Uni<lb/> ted States; they being on their way to the <orgName key="oneida"
                    />Oneidal Reservation, as Commis<lb/>sioners from the board of Trustees in
                    Boston; for an enquiry into the conduct<lb/> of Missionary Kirkland, of which
                    complaint had been made (principally<lb/> for remissness of duty) to the Scotch
                    Society for propogating the Gospels<lb/> by whom these missions are supported.
                    They seem pleased to<lb/> see us in favour of our errands, of which they
                    expressed a hearty approba<lb/>tion, as the only means of effectually
                    introducing christianity among the <lb/>
                    <pb n="28" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_028"/>
                    <gap/>en. Poor Kirkland is now thought to be dangerously ill, but if<lb/> he
                    should recover he will probably make himself very easy about their<lb/>
                    decision, as he has feathered his nest thoroughly long since. <placeName
                        key="white">Whitestown</placeName><lb/> is the Capital of the Couny of
                        <placeName key="herki">Herkimer</placeName>, which affords an instance of
                    the<lb/> rapid settlement of these parts, scarcely to be parrallelled. Twelve
                    years<lb/> ago <persName key="jwhit1">Judge White</persName> came here the first
                    settler, and lived sometime in a cave,<lb/> Within six years there were 300
                    Familys hearabout; from that<lb/> time as long as it was possible to calculate
                    the numbers doubled every<lb/> year; and now they counted, on a late census,
                    forty three thousand<lb/> Souls. On fourth day morning we all met again at
                        <placeName key="oneid">Oneida</placeName> Dined heartily<lb/> upon excellent
                    Salmon, with which the lake abounds from 10 to 15 lbs;<lb/> and in the afternoon
                    ranged about to view the Country for a suitable<lb/> situation for building:
                    Fixed upon a eligible spot, and returned to<lb/> the <orgName key="stockbridge"
                        >Stockbridges</orgName>, upon occasion of some of their People being
                    desirous<lb/> to sell their share of Land, for which they had requested leave a
                    few<lb/> days before, without the knowledge of their Chiefs, by a string of
                    wampum.<lb/> The <orgName key="oneida">Oneidas</orgName> expressively described
                    their original grant of the Land to the<lb/>
                    <orgName key="stockbridge">Stockbridges</orgName> under the comparison of a
                    steel Dish, which they had given<lb/> to last them forever, expecting they said
                    that they would put a steel spoon into<lb/> it and take care to keep it bright
                    and whole; but they were surprised<lb/> to find that the white People had
                    already got hold of some of their<lb/> hands, and were trying to break the
                    spoon; with all returning the <lb/>
                    <pb n="29" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_029"/> wampum as their manner is when they refuse what is requested
                    by<lb/> telling them that the Dish was given to them, and their Children,
                    and<lb/> that the spoon should never be taken out of their mouths. Having<lb/>
                    sketched out a plan in writing for the settlement at <placeName key="oneid"
                        >Oneida</placeName>, three of<lb/> us went over on 7th day to read it to the
                    Chiefs; that they might have an<lb/> opportunity of considering it before we met
                    the whole Nation in council,<lb/> for a final determination. They then seemed
                    well satisfied tho their expec<lb/>tations had evidently been raised to
                    something more ostensible than<lb/> our present proceedings; but on second Day
                    Morning just as we were set<lb/>ting out, a Runner came in with a note informing
                    us that they were<lb/> gone to <placeName key="fstan">Fort Stanwix</placeName>,
                    to complain of the Surveyors for overrunning the<lb/> boundaries of the last
                    Sale, which will probably delay our business<lb/> some days. Accept my love as
                    usual, dear Father, Mother, Wife,<lb/> Brothers, and Sisters; please to give it
                    freely to all enquiring Friends;<lb/> and remember me particularly to the
                    Families of <persName key="jdrin1">John Drinker</persName>,<lb/>
                    <persName key="jpemb1">James Pemberton</persName>, <persName key="jthom2">John
                        Thomas</persName>, <persName key="obidd1">Owen Biddle</persName>, <persName
                        key="aallm1">Anne Attmore</persName>, <persName key="hdrin1">Henry<lb/>
                        Drinker</persName>, <persName key="jhowe1">Joshua Howell</persName>,
                        <persName key="jparr1">John Parish</persName>, <persName key="ssmit1">Samuel
                        Smith</persName>, Samuel P <unclear>Grief</unclear><lb/>fitts, and the
                    Widows Foulke and Shoemaker. </p>
                <closer><signed><persName key="jsans1">Jos. Sansom</persName></signed></closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>
                        <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName> has just arrived with letters
                        from two of my best<lb/> Friends, they do my heart good. </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
            
            <div type="undetermined">
                <pb n="30" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_030"/>
            </div>   
            
            <div type="letter">
                <pb n="31" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_031"/>
                <opener><dateline><placeName key="oneic">Oneida Castle</placeName>, <date
                            when="1796-07">7th. Mo 1796</date>
                    </dateline><salute>My dear Friends,</salute></opener>
                <p>On the eve of our departure from the <orgName key="oneida">Oneida</orgName>
                    Reservation, which, tho'<lb/> really no more than going on from the main stage
                    of our Journey, feels a little<lb/> like the outset for Home, I sit down to
                    gather up the fragments I may have scattered by trusting to<lb/> memory, from
                    week to week, for the irregular narrative; that no<lb/> thing may be lost,
                    either important or interesting. If the conse<lb/>quence should be a repetition
                    of any thing mentioned before, you will remember the<lb/> motive, and read the
                    faster. Imprimis, The name of the Chief left blank on<lb/> No. 3. is <persName
                        key="dnesho1">David Neshounhut</persName>, the latter received from his
                    Ancestors, who<lb/> it seems were Man that could shoot the birds with one arrow.
                    After the first<lb/> conference with the <orgName key="oneida">Oneidas</orgName>
                    mentioned in No 4 or 5 the Women sent us a<lb/> message, by the Chief Speaker,
                    that they had heard all our words, and hoped their<lb/> Husbands would keep to
                    them as far they were all very good. All the time we<lb/> were at <persName
                        key="haupa1">Hendrick Aupautmut</persName>'s the Indians of the Neighborhood
                    were contin<lb/>ually sending in strawberrys, milk, butter, and sometimes meal,
                    and<lb/> otherwise manifesting their love and regard. One of his Daughters was
                    at a<lb/> conference ten days ago, a mile from her home, and was delivered of a
                    Boy<lb/> that afternoon; which she brought herself the night before last to
                    our<lb/> lodging to tell us she had called him after one of us: I leave you to
                    guess which.<lb/> We have the unexpected satisfaction to find the People of the
                    Neighborhood<lb/> of all Ranks so favorably disposed, both toward us, and the
                    Indians, as to<lb/> bid us good speed in our arduous undertaking, and even the
                    Preiby terrain Cler-<lb/>gy, who have been long labouring among them, assure us
                    they are convinced by<lb/> experience, that the only way to make Christians of
                    them effectually is to<lb/> civilize them, if that be possible. We have agreed
                    to settle <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName>,<lb/>
                    <persName key="ewalk1">Enoch Walker</persName>, and <persName key="hsimm1">Henry
                        Simmons</persName>, near <placeName key="oneic">Oneida Castle</placeName>,
                    and the Indians<lb/> have assigned them an excellent piece of land to go work
                    upon, adjacent to <lb/>
                    <pb n="32" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_032"/>
                    <gap/> frame house of two rooms, which we have rented of one of their Chiefs,
                    for<lb/> the present. They are to take six or eight Apprentices upon the Farm:
                    but, as the<lb/> occasionally do assist those who are disposed to work their own
                    ground; and do<lb/> go among the <orgName key="tuscarora">Tuscaroras</orgName>,
                        <orgName key="stockbridge">Stockbridges</orgName>, and <orgName
                        key="brotherton">Brothertons</orgName>, to rouze them from their<lb/>
                    farming. See the inclosed minutes. On 7th. day evening we had the pleasure<lb/>
                    of hearing that our dear friend <persName key="jevan1">Joshua Evens</persName>
                    was in the neighborhood, and intended to have a meeting at <placeName
                        key="broth">Brotherton</placeName> on first<lb/> day morning and two of us
                    went off with the Chief of the Stockbridges to bid him <lb/>wellcome, the rest
                    of us staying at home to keep up our own meeting, as usual.<lb/> In the evening
                    we collected joyfully at our lodgings, to the number of ten, <persName
                        key="jevan1">Joshua</persName><lb/> having the Companions with him from
                    about the <placeName key="nrive">North River</placeName>; and the Indians
                    ga<lb/> thered round us till bed time, for a sight of the venerable Patriarch.
                    Next<lb/> morning we had our parting Conference with the <orgName
                        key="stockbridge">Stockbridges</orgName>, wherein, after ex-<lb/> plaining
                    our views, We delivered our Proposals to them in writing, and earnestly<lb/>
                    recommended such advice as appeared most necessary for their observance.<lb/>
                    After which an Old Man (baptised many years ago by <persName key="jschm">John
                        Schmitt</persName> a Mo-<lb/>ravian Brother who laboured some years in these
                    parts under great difficulties and discor-<lb/> agements), burst forth very
                    tenderly in the following broken lan-<lb/>guage: <said>Brothers, I glad see you
                        in my heart; and hear your good word.<lb/> You use us just like a Father. I
                        am old, lost all my Family. I can't<lb/> live many days: But all this spring
                        I think Jesus will send me some<lb/> comfort in my trouble; but Nobody say
                        anything to me, till more you are come.<lb/> Wish I was young, then I would
                        do what you say directly: but I go see<lb/> how your People work, every two
                        three days, and tell our Young Men<lb/> what you do.</said> When <persName
                        key="haupa1">Hendrick Aupaumut</persName>, having first rehearsed in
                    Indian<lb/> what he was going to say, replied</p>
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <p>Brothers, We shall speak but a<lb/> few words. We are glad of your
                            company among us, these three weeks, that <lb/>
                            <pb n="33" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_033"/> that, as you told us in the first Council, you might know
                            what was best for all<gap/><lb/> here; and now you tell us what you will
                            do for our nation. We rejoice that the<lb/> Good Spirit has put it into
                            your hearts, and into the hearts of your Brothers at home<lb/> to do us
                            good. We believe it is of the Good Spirit, because your words are
                            weights on<lb/> our minds. Brothers, the offers you make us are great.
                            We did not expect so<lb/> much from Friends. We are thankful to the Good
                            Spirit for putting it into<lb/> your hearts, and for giving you the
                            ability to do it. Brothers, You give us Smith's<lb/> Tools, for which we
                            thank you. We have suffered much for want of them, having been<lb/>
                            obliged to go many miles sometimes, and spend some days, to get on link
                            of a chain mended.</p>
                        <p>Brothers, Your assisting us to build a Grist Mill will be a great thing
                            for us. We have<lb/> suffered many years for want of one, especially our
                            Women, who are obliged to pound over<lb/> corn, they join us to thank
                            you heartily. Brothers, your offer to help us in setting<lb/> up a
                            School is very acceptable to us. Be assured we will do our part towards
                            it. Bro-<lb/>thers, what you propose respecting the money lent us is
                            very agreeable to our minds.<lb/> (It was considered as part of an
                            advance forward building the Mill repayable if ever al<lb/> lowed by
                            Congress) and also the encouragement you offer us by premiums. We
                            hope<lb/> our Young Men will have courage to follow those ways you point
                            out for us. Bro-<lb/> thers, We now freely promise that the Chiefs, and
                            all our orderly Young Men,<lb/> will endeavor to follow your advice, and
                            with the blessing of the Good Spirit we will<lb/> live more than ever as
                            White People do: for we never received such encouragement<lb/> before
                            from any People. We observe what you tell us, that we must be an
                            example<lb/> to other Indians; and we hope to be so more and more.
                            Brothers, We shall not for-<lb/>get what you request for the Young Men
                            you leave behind you. Our minds are<lb/> the same with yours. We will
                            maintain our friendship with them, and will be<lb/> always ready to
                            assist them if they get in trouble. Now Brothers, We spoke<lb/> to you
                            several days ago about the difficulties we are under in not receiving
                            our<lb/> annual income from Government, and we desire that one of your
                            Friends in Phi-<lb/>ladelphia will endeavour to settle that business, so
                            that we can have our<lb/> money punctually, in future</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>In the afternoon <persName key="jevan1">Joshua Evens</persName> had a
                    reli-<lb/>gious meeting with them, after which we parted from them in great love
                    and tenderness. Next <lb/>
                    <pb n="34" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_034"/> Joshua's Companions left him, as he now thinks to return homeward from<lb/>
                    <placeName key="canan">Canandaigua</placeName>, and continue with us so far. We
                    expect to proceed tomorrow afternoon,<lb/> taking <orgName key="onondaga"
                        >Onondago</orgName>, and <orgName key="cayugaind">Cayuga</orgName>, in our
                    way; and begin to promise ourselves the pleasure of<lb/> taking up the letters
                    that have been forwarded to the care of <persName key="ichap1">Captain
                        Chapin</persName>, if all goes well,<lb/> by the middle of the month. Till
                    when you will hardly hear again from </p>
                <closer>Your affectionate <persName key="jsans1">Joseph Sansom</persName></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="undetermined">

                <pb n="35" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_035"/>
                <opener>Minutes of conclusive conferences, and Agreements, between t<gap/><lb/>
                    setling on the <dateline><placeName key="oneid">Oneida</placeName> Reservation,
                        and the Indians there, proposed on<lb/> the 25th and agreed to on the <date
                            when="1796-06-30">30th of the Sixth Month
                    1796</date>.</dateline></opener>
                <floatingText type="letter">
                    <body>
                        <opener>
                            <salute>Brothers of the <orgName key="oneida">Oneida
                                Nation</orgName></salute></opener>
                        <p>You now know that we are sent to you by your old Friends, the People<lb/>
                            called Quakers of Pennsylvania, and parts adjacent not merely to
                            make<lb/> you presents which would soon be spent, leaving you still poor
                            &amp; needy,<lb/> but to show you how we manage, to raise a great deal
                            of food and Clo<lb/>thing, off of a little Land, that you may be able to
                            support yourselves,<lb/> and your Children, comfortably without being
                            beholden to any body,<lb/> and have something to spare for the old and
                            Infirm, as well as to lay<lb/> by against times of scarcity.</p>
                        <p>Brothers <lb/>Remember that we have left all that was dear to us at home,
                            not to get your<lb/> Lands from you or any thing that is yours, but to
                            visit you in love, and<lb/> stay with you, if happily we may put you in
                            a way, to enjoy the manifold<lb/> blessings of the All bountiful
                            Creator. Now we have seen and reflected<lb/> upon your situation &amp;
                            consulted one another, for the future prosperity<lb/> of your whole
                            Nation, and the three tribes, you have kindly permitted to<lb/> settle
                            upon your Land, and we have put our conclusion in Writing,<lb/> that it
                            may be known, what we are willing to undertake for you, and what<lb/> we
                            desire you to do towards it yourselves, for we mean to set before you
                            a<lb/> clear example if you will agree to follow it. </p>
                        <pb n="36" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_036"/>
                        <p>Brothers <lb/>We trust that we have your confidence, unmixed with any
                            jealousies, or fears,<lb/> and we request you to listen patiently, and
                            attentively, to what we are going to<lb/> propose to you, for your own
                            good, yet if any part of it displeases you, tell us so &amp;<lb/> we
                            will reconsider it</p>
                        <p> Brothers<lb/> Three of our Friends intend to say with you for these
                            purposes, namely<lb/>
                            <persName key="ewalk1">Enoch Walker</persName>, <persName key="jtayl1"
                                >Jacob Taylor</persName>, &amp; <persName key="hsimm1">Henry
                                Simmons</persName>, but they are not bound<lb/> to remain by
                            anything but good will, neither are they obliged to work<lb/> more than
                            they think necessary, nor to be altogether among you, as they<lb/> are
                            to go sometimes to <placeName key="stock">Stockbridge</placeName>.
                                <orgName key="tuscarora">Tuscarora</orgName>, and <orgName
                                key="brotherton">Brotherson</orgName>. We earnest<lb/>ly desire that
                            none of you may discourage them, by swearing idleness or<lb/>
                            misbehaviour, for these things are very disagreeable to us, as you know
                            they<lb/> are to the Good Spirit</p>
                        <p>Brothers<lb/> You know we must have some Land to work upon, and we should
                            like<lb/> to begin upon that part of the Common, which lies West of the
                            path<lb/> from Shannandoas to <placeName key="stock"
                                >Stockbridge</placeName>, South of the road to <placeName
                                key="onond">Onandago</placeName>, East<lb/> of the boundaries of the
                                <placeName key="ofsch">old Fort</placeName>, and North of <placeName
                                key="shenr">Shenandoah Creek</placeName>,<lb/> excepting any part
                            thereof now occupied by your Families. </p>
                        <p>Brothers<lb/> If we think there is encouragement to undertake more
                            another Year<lb/> we shall ask you for it reasonably &amp; agree
                            together were it shall be </p>
                        <pb n="37" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_037"/>
                        <p>Brothers<lb/> You know it is hardly practicable for all to learn
                            together, We will begin<lb/> with a few, who must stick to the work, the
                            rest will see how they get<lb/> forward, and be ready to take their turn
                            when it comes round, We want to<lb/> Engage Six or Eight sober young
                            Men, as apprentices, till next Spring.<lb/> Brothers<lb/> We suppose
                            that you will be willing we should graze our Horses, Cattle &amp;C
                            upon,<lb/> the Common, and that you will allow us some grass lots to
                            provide Hay for<lb/> them in the Winter, to cut firewood, railing, and
                            timber for our buildings,<lb/> in your Woods, use your Saw Mill &amp;
                            Smith Shop when we have occasions,<lb/> and sometimes work your Horses
                            &amp; Oxen if you are not using them</p>
                        <p>Brothers<lb/> You will understand that our Friends are to live
                            plentifully as their<lb/> own People do at Home, and their live stock is
                            to be kept upon the pro<lb/>duce of their labours, in the first place.
                            One Eighth part of the remainder<lb/> is to be reserved for the releif
                            of your old and Infirm People, and the rest is to<lb/> be divided among
                            the Indian apprentices, that they may enjoy the<lb/> Fruit of their
                            labours and have something to begin with for themselves<lb/> when others
                            are taken in their stead, provided they behave well,<lb/> but in case of
                            incorrigible idleness, drunkenness, swearing, or misbehavi<lb/>our, in
                            any of them, our Friends must avoid bad company, and we<lb/> request you
                            to appoint three of your Chiefs, to unite with them as judges,<lb/> that
                            if four of them agree the offender may be justly discharged.</p>
                        <p>Finally Brothers<lb/> Our stay among you will depend upon several
                            circumstances but particularly <lb/>
                            <pb n="38" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_038"/>
                            <gap/>encouragement we may have to hope, that you will in time
                            become<lb/> sober industrious, and frugal, laying up something for
                            yourselves, against sick<lb/>ness and old age, Whenever we leave you the
                            improvements we make<lb/> on your Lands, will belong to you, but the
                            Cattle and other things we<lb/> bring with us for our own use, we shall
                            probably take away.</p>
                        <closer><dateline><date when="1796-06-25">Sixth Month 25th</date> the
                                    <gap/><placeName key="oneic"/></dateline></closer>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>


                <p>The Indians replied on the 30th in substance as follows.</p>
                <floatingText type="letter">
                    <body>
                        <p>We find no difficulty in agreeing to your proposals, as to anything
                            but<lb/> the place you choose, (see the 5th article) many of our People
                            are against<lb/> parting with any of the Common, because we have hardly
                            pasture eno<lb/>ugh for our Cattle now, and if we lesson it they will be
                            famish'd, and<lb/> break down the Fences to get at our Corn, besides
                            which we are afraid<lb/> our Young Men will disturb you there sometimes,
                            when they get in<lb/> liquor which we cannot always prevent.<lb/>
                            Brothers<lb/> We think it right to propose another place to you which we
                            believe<lb/> will suit you better will you go and look at it.<lb/> Upon
                            this the spot was viewed and being thought likely to suit as well<lb/>
                            as the others, it was mutually agreed to as follows, beginning at a
                            Gut<lb/>South East of Anthony Shonongleyas House, and running
                            nearly<lb/> South by a <gap/> tree, marked <gap/> to, a <gap/> tree,
                            markd <lb/>
                            <pb n="39" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_039"/> as far as <placeName key="shenr">Shenandoah
                                Creek</placeName>, extending Eastward into the W<gap/><lb/> out
                            limitation, And the said Anthony being willing to leave his<lb/> House
                            and appurtenances, they were engaged for the use of the settlement,<lb/>
                            It was also agreed that the Friends should have liberty to enclose
                            what<lb/> they might want of the Flats, for hay or pasture, agreeable to
                            the<lb/> Eighth article, but the Indians did not choose to engage their
                            Oxen,<lb/> except the young ones to be broke first, or their Horses,
                            because they were<lb/> not good for any thing to Work.</p>
                        <p> And <persName key="jsken1">John Shanandoa</persName>, <persName
                                key="shago1">Anthony Shonongleya</persName>, and <persName
                                key="nshago1">Nicholas Shago<lb/> rohorongo</persName>, were
                            appointed as judges under the 9th Article.</p>
                        <closer>Signed at <dateline><placeName key="oneic">Oneida Castle</placeName>
                                the <gap/>
                                <date when="1796-07">day of the Seventh Month 1796</date>. by
                                <gap/></dateline></closer>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>

            </div>
            
            <div type="undetermined">
                <pb n="40" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_040"/>
            </div>  
            
            <div type="letter">
                <pb n="41" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_041"/>
                <opener><dateline><placeName key="canan">Canadarquai</placeName><date
                            when="1796-07-14"> 7th. Mo. 14th. 17</date></dateline>
                    <salute>My dear Friends,</salute></opener>
                <p>You will be pleased to hear that a hundred and twenty<lb/> miles travelling since
                    my last have carried us very little farther from Phila<lb/>delphia, especially
                    as we reckon it so much toward home, on the Farther<lb/> way round. On 5th. day
                    morning we took an affectionate leave of fifteen<lb/> or twenty of the <orgName
                        key="stockbridge">Stockbridges</orgName>, who had collected at our Lodgings
                    for that purpose,<lb/> and went over to our own House at the <placeName
                        key="oneid">Oneida</placeName> Farm, where we held our<lb/> week day
                    meeting. We dined together at <persName key="jsken1">Shenandoa's</persName>,
                    and<lb/> observing that the Indians were collecting about us we proposed to take
                    our<lb/> leave of them under the trees, and had a seasonable opportunity with
                    some<lb/> hundreds of Men Women and Children, after which the Chiefs observed
                    that<lb/> now they knew we meant what we said for we had only repeated the
                    same<lb/> speech we made to them before, whereas it was the common practise<lb/>
                    of the White People to speak good words to them at first; but when they<lb/>
                    spoke again they always found that they had changed their minds. A
                    respect-<lb/>able old Woman seemed much tendered at parting, and desired the
                    Interpreter<lb/> to tell us that it was not the custom for Women to speak in
                    Council, but that<lb/> their hearts were sensible of our good words though they
                    had nothing to add to<lb/> them. We rose 12 or 15 miles that evening to a
                    wretched tavern, and turning out as early<lb/> as possible next day arrived at
                    Major Danforth's on the <placeName key="onond">Onondago</placeName>
                    Reser-<lb/>vation, by 10 o'clock. <persName key="ewebs1">Ephraim
                        Webster</persName>, a Young Man who had lived with <lb/>
                    <pb n="42" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_042"/>
                    <gap/>seven years, dined with us, and we went in the afternoon to the Town<lb/>
                    consisting of the Council House and 5 or 6 bark cabbins, but the Indians
                    were<lb/> generally out fishing, hunting, &amp; there Corn being already spent.
                    Ten or a<lb/> dozen of them however came together after a while, to whom we
                    opened our<lb/> business, and learned from them that they were about 130 in
                    number and<lb/> received 125 Dollars a year from the Government of New York,
                    which will be<lb/> doubled by a late sale of the greatest part of their Land,
                    leaving them an<lb/> excellent Tract extending four miles by five. They seemed
                    unwilling to<lb/> hear us in the absence of the rest, having evidently formed
                    great expectations<lb/> of something to be done immediately: but we thought it
                    best to proceed so<lb/> they could not readily be got together; and to make them
                    easy left our<lb/> speech in writing, to the effect that they should be
                    furnished with some<lb/> implements of husbandry next Spring, and that we would
                    bring up some<lb/> of their Children to useful learning and trades if they would
                    send<lb/> them down to us. The next afternoon we reached <persName key="fgeer1"
                        >Frederick Gerhart</persName>'s<lb/> near the <orgName key="cayugaind"
                        >Cayuga</orgName> settlement, walked over to one of the hovels in the
                    evening, and appointed<lb/> a Conference for Second day, by sunrise. This Tribe
                    lives principally<lb/> by fishing, the <placeName key="cayug">Cayuga
                        Lake</placeName> 40 miles long, and 2 or 3 wide, abounding in<lb/> Trout,
                    Catfish, and particularly Eels. There are but about eighty of them<lb/> here
                    upon 4000 acres of land, they having lately sold all the rest for<lb/> an
                    annuity of about 1500 Dollars, including 500 they had before. They<lb/> appear
                    to be irreclaimably sunk into the lethargick <lb/>
                    <pb n="43" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_043"/> idleness so common in fishing neighborhoods, for neither gratitude
                    no<gap/><lb/> could move more than three men and as many Women to attend
                    ou<gap/><lb/>ment. They acknowledged their ignorance over and over again, &amp;
                    assented to every<lb/>thing, without answering any thing, except that they would
                    send one or two of<lb/> their Boys among us to learn how to interpret for them,
                    if they could per-<lb/>suade their Mothers to let them go. About 11 oclock we
                    crossed the<lb/>
                    <placeName key="cayuc">Cayuga</placeName> Later in a flat bottomed Sloop, with a
                    stiff sale, in 20 minutes, and, dining<lb/> at the Ferry, I amused myself with
                    looking wistfully after the Sloop till<lb/> she dropped sail again on the other
                    side, in remembrance of the ever shifting<lb/> scenery of Delaware. Who will
                    step into the Jersey View for me<lb/> and count how many Sail are in sight this
                    moment. Here we came<lb/> across a Whitestown News Paper, and were not a little
                    pleased to find<lb/> the following <del>ourselves toasted as the enterprising
                        and benevolent Quaker Missionaries </del><lb/> in a long list of Republican
                    toasts drank there on the celebration of the Anniversary<lb/> of Independence
                        <said>The enterprizing and benevolent Quaker Missionaries,<lb/> May they
                        succeed in civilizing our Indian Brothers at <placeName key="oneid"
                            >Oneida</placeName>,</said> as<lb/> it manifests the favorable
                    disposition of the Neighborhood.<lb/> It rained fast by noon: but as there was
                    Company acquainted with the<lb/> road going on for the next stage, we thought it
                    best to keep with them,<lb/> and rode 12 miles through bad roads and rich land
                    before it ceased, just<lb/> as we came in sight of the <placeName key="senec"
                        >Senneka Lake</placeName>, opposite to <placeName key="genev"
                        >Geneva</placeName>, a thriving<lb/> town of 20 or 10 houses beautifully
                    situated near the outlet of the Lake<lb/> Here we were glad to stop, and dry our
                    cloaths. Next mor-<lb/>
                    <pb n="44" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_044"/>
                    <gap/>de 12 or 14 miles partly through deep mire to this place.<lb/>
                    <gap/>afternoon we called upon <persName key="ichap1">Israel Chapin</persName>
                    the Superintendant<lb/> of Indian Affairs, who informed us that he had received
                    and forwarded<lb/> answers from each of the <orgName key="sxntns">Six
                        Nations</orgName>, excepting only that part of<lb/> the <orgName
                        key="seneca">Sennekas</orgName> living at <placeName key="buffc1">Buffalo
                        Creek</placeName>, who it seems think pro-<lb/>per to see what effect our
                    exertions may have upon others before<lb/> they are tried upon them. I rather
                    expect to write again before<lb/> we leave this place; and an unexpected
                    opportunity now offering<lb/> I am obliged to conclude, in haste, with all
                    respect, and affection</p>
                <closer><signed>
                        <persName key="jsans1">Joseph Sansom</persName></signed></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <pb n="45" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_045"/>
                <opener><dateline><placeName key="canan">Canadarquai</placeName>, <date
                            when="1796-07-12">7th. Mo.<gap/>
                        </date></dateline><salute>My dear Friends, </salute></opener>

                <p>We arrived here on the 12th. and the next day but one I wrote<lb/> you the
                    particulars of our journey from <placeName key="oneid">Oneida</placeName> Farm,
                    in great haste, to go<lb/> by the celebrated Land Jobber <persName key="ophel1"
                        >Phelps</persName>, who was setting out directly, but he is not<lb/> gone
                    yet: for as the Indians say, once he was a light Man, and could go<lb/> over the
                    mountains from <placeName key="canaw">Conewaugus</placeName> to <placeName
                        key="jenuch">Jenuchshadega</placeName> but now he's<lb/> grown so fat and
                    heavy there's no moving him from home. The Country<lb/> surrounding the
                    beautiful Lakes that connect these Parts with the<lb/>
                    <geogName key="mohaw">Mohawk</geogName> and the <geogName key="susqu"
                        >Susquehanna</geogName>, abounds with <del>Sugar</del> Maple <del>and
                    </del>al<lb/>most every Family making sugar <del>supplies itself with ease
                        in</del> early in the Spring with very<lb/> little labour; <del>They are
                        also</del> and is plentifully supplied with salt from a marshy Lake<lb/>
                    near <placeName key="onond">Onondago</placeName>, where several hundred bushels
                    are made in a day, and<lb/> sold at the moderate price of five shillings. It is
                    also remarkable for<lb/> the remains of extensive Fortifications, inclosing
                    several acres with mounds<lb/> of earth, overgrown with the largest timber,
                    which bespeak a de<lb/>gree of labour antiquity and population unaccountable
                    upon the present cir<lb/>cumstances of the Natives, who can give no account of
                    their origin.<lb/> Their mode of carrying on war was by surprise and retreat, in
                    which they often<lb/> suffered <del>amazing</del> extreme hardships to
                        <del>gratify</del> prove their courage, or gratify<lb/> their revenge. The
                        <orgName key="sxntns">Five Nations</orgName> have been in the practice time
                    out of<lb/> mend, untill a few years since, of going almost every summer
                        <del>several</del> many hundred miles against the<lb/>
                    <orgName key="cherokee">Cherokees</orgName>, on the borders of Carolina and
                    Georgia, to signalize their valour<lb/> Some old Men have been pointed out to us
                    who have been on this bloo<gap/><lb/>                  
                    <pb n="46" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_046"/>
                    <gap/>several times, one of whom called <persName key="owhist1"
                        >Owhistonish</persName> (or the Silversines<gap/><lb/>
                    <gap/>he knows the value of money) was once out nine days, without a<lb/>
                    mouthful to eat, upon this senseless errand. Now however they have some<lb/>
                    thing else to do, as they were expressively told by a Chief of the Illinois,
                    who<lb/> invited them all to leave their Country, and go over the Ohio:
                        <said>You are <lb/>growing less and less</said> said he, <said>and Great Eyes
                        will grow bigger and bigge<gap/><lb/> til he gets you in a heap, and then
                        he'll lift up his foot,<lb/> and stamp upon you, as you would upon an Ants
                        nest.</said> A few days ago<lb/> we indulged ourselves in a visit to the
                    Friends about <placeName key="mudcr">Mud Creek</placeName>, who<lb/> were as
                    glad to see us as we were to see them, the good women washing and<lb/> mending
                    for us as if we had been their own Children. <persName key="jevan1">Joshua
                        Evens</persName> has had<lb/> several meetings among them, to good
                    satisfaction, tho' they appear to have<lb/> god into a strange land, and hung
                    their harps upon the willows. Since<lb/> our return we have been much at a
                    stand, one of our Company, <persName key="jpier1">John Pierce</persName>,<lb/>
                    thinking himself clear of the service, and concluding to return home in<lb/>
                    company with <persName key="jevan1">Joshua</persName> through <placeName
                        key="muncy">Muncey</placeName>. But the rest of us are disposed<lb/> to
                    finish the business we came about, though in weakness, and expect to proceed on
                    2nd. day<lb/> for the Indian Settlements on the Genesea, and from there to the
                        <persName key="cornp2">Corn Planters</persName><lb/> Villages on the
                        <placeName key="alleg">Alleghany</placeName>, either by the way of
                        <placeName key="niaga">Niagara</placeName> and <placeName key="buffc1"
                        >Buffaloe<lb/> Creek</placeName>, or more directly across the mountains. We
                    understand he has<lb/> lately made a speech <del>to the President</del>
                    requesting to have some Persons<lb/> removed who have encroached upon his Land,
                    and some Quakers<lb/> sent out as they used to live in peace with them and
                    thinks they could still. We pro- <lb/>
                    <pb n="47" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_047"/> pose to take one or two Indian Guides, from place to place, who
                    ca<gap/><lb/> a fire, or knock up a hut, when we are under the necessity
                    of<gap/><lb/> woods: from which, with submission to Divine disposal, we hope to
                    emerge,<lb/> by way of <placeName key="sunb">Sunbury</placeName>, or <placeName
                        key="pitts">Pittsburgh</placeName>, in two or three weeks; of which I
                    shall<lb/> take the first opportunity to let you know, though we shall
                    probably<lb/> then ride post ourselves to meet again at our greatly endeared
                    homes the loving and be-<lb/>loved Friends we left there</p>
                <closer><signed><persName key="jsans1">Joseph Sansom</persName>
                    </signed></closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p><date when="1796-07-18">Second day the 18th.</date> At a conference yesterday
                            <persName key="jcoop1">James Cooper</persName> expressed
                        himse<gap/><lb/> easy to proceed, without we could all go on together; and this<gap/><lb/>
                        <persName key="irowl1">Isaiah Rowland</persName>, apprehending we could not
                        separate in the unity<lb/> we were directed to preserve, it was concluded
                        that it would be<lb/> unsafe for any of us to go further; and we now intend
                        to<lb/> turn homeward tomorrow morning: So my dear Friends I hope<lb/> we
                        shall meet again much sooner than I expected; probably<lb/> by the end of
                        next week. </p>
                </postscript>

            </div>
            
            <div type="undetermined">
                <pb n="48" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_048"/>
            </div>  
            
            <div type="letter">
                <pb n="49" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_049"/>
                <opener><dateline><placeName key="muncy">Muncey </placeName><date when="1796-07-24">7th. Mo.
                            24th. 7<gap/></date></dateline><salute>My dear
                    Friends,</salute></opener>
                <p>My last, if you have but received it, informed you<gap/><lb/> unexpected return,
                    the present is dated upon the West Branch of <placeName key="susqueh"
                        >Sus-<lb/>quehanna</placeName>, more than half way home, which I hope to
                    reach by<lb/> 6th. or 7th. day next. We left <placeName key="canan"
                        >Canadarquai</placeName> on 3rd. day mor-<lb/>ning the 19th. instead,
                    accompanied by <persName key="alaph1">Abraham Lapham</persName>, one of<lb/> the
                    Friends near <placeName key="mudcr">Mud Creek</placeName>, who attended
                        <persName key="jevan1">Joshua Evens</persName> with a<lb/> fresh horse, to
                    relieve his Mare, whose back was sadly galled soon<lb/> after he left <placeName
                        key="otego">Otego</placeName>. We're shown a small Island, tufted with
                    trees,<lb/> as we rode along the Lake, upon which the Indians<lb/> of this place
                    secreted themselves, drawing up their canoes among<lb/> the bushes, when
                        <persName key="gsull1">General Sullivan</persName> invaded their
                    Country<lb/> in 1778. Reached a new Settlement in the woods, 30 miles<lb/>
                    distant, by 5 o'clock. where, there being no accommodations<lb/> for 12 miles,
                    beyond we spread our blankets on the floor, and slept pretty<lb/> comfortably
                    till day light. Got to Noath the capital of the County<lb/>
                    <gap/>Steuber<gap/> by 10 o'clock, riding <del>with a great deal of
                        pleasure</del>most<lb/> of the way along the banks of the Conhocto,
                    delighted to be once<lb/> more upon running water. The Creek is boatable so
                    high<lb/> in the spring of the year: but the town is more dependant <lb/>
                    <pb n="50" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_050"/>
                    <gap/>crossroads to <placeName key="canan">Canadarquai</placeName> and
                        <placeName key="genes">Genesee</placeName> A mile below<lb/>
                    <gap/>as a Lake of half a mile in diameter, which has no visible<lb/> inlet, yet
                    the water is always fresh, and well stocked wi<gap/><lb/> large and small Fish.
                    It is very deep and has been sounded<lb/> in some places with 40 fathoms of line
                    without finding bottom.<lb/> Lodged at the <placeName key="ppost">Painted
                        Post</placeName>, a small town two miles below the<lb/> spot from which it
                    takes its name, the grave of an Indian<lb/> Sachem, marked by a high post,
                    crudely painted with figur<gap/><lb/> denoting the numbers by him taken captive
                    or killed in battl<gap/><lb/> Riding almost all day through mountainous and
                    barren land<lb/> we were agreeably relieve by the prospect of an extensive
                    and<lb/> well cultivated flat, though still surrounded with mountains
                    resem<lb/>bling green walls of stupendous height. Next moring crossed and
                    recrrossed<lb/> the <placeName key="tioga">Tioga</placeName>, and several of its
                    branches, till about noon, when we<lb/> crossed the Pennsylvania Line, rejoicing
                    at the thoughts of home<lb/> Lodged at the last house on that side of the
                    Wilderness sur<lb/>rounding the <placeName key="allmo">Alleghany
                        Mountains</placeName>, 43 miles across, with<lb/> but one house near the
                    middle, and that inhabited by a Man<lb/> whose general character is fierce and
                    brutal, suspected of having<lb/> killed a Pedlar who lodged here some months ago
                    on his way<lb/> through, and has never been heard of since. This Wretch we<lb/>
                    <pb n="51" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_051"/> determined to avoid, and <persName key="jevan1">Joshua
                        Evens</persName> rouzed us two or three ti<gap/><lb/> o'clock, and finally
                    started in by half after one, the m<gap/><lb/> bright a little past the full.
                    Leaving Ab<gap/><lb/> here, and taking our Landlord for a Guide. We
                    rode<gap/><lb/> day break, along the banks of the <placeName key="tioga"
                        >Tioga</placeName>, through thick woods almost<lb/> impervious to moonshine,
                    silent and slow, every one keeping<lb/> his eye upon the next before, and now
                    and then catching a glimpse<lb/> of <persName key="jevan1">Joshua
                        Evens</persName>'s white coat and horse. Here and there the wood<lb/> opened
                    enough to show the water glistening with moon beams, and<lb/> ever and anon the
                    path way crossed the river to avoid the sidelong<lb/> hills. Stopped to feed
                    about sunrise amidst fog and Gnats and<lb/> gladly turned our backs upon them to
                    encounter the Mountain which continues risi<unclear>g m</unclear>ore<lb/> or less at intervals
                    for 10 or 15 miles the road stony,<lb/> rooty, swampy, and winding to the right
                    and left round fallen<lb/> trees and quagmires. Passed the terrific house before
                    noon,<lb/> and in an hour or two descended the mountain, which is<lb/> here so
                    steep that two miles brings you to the bottom, where<lb/> there is another
                    feeding place, 12 miles from the house we<lb/> put up at for the night, after
                    crossing a branch of Lyconery<lb/> two and thirty times. Next morning reach a
                    Friends House in<lb/> the Settlement of <placeName key="muncy"
                        >Muncey</placeName>, where we seemed at home as soon as we<lb/> sat down,
                    but thought best to proceed for another near the meeting<lb/> house in the
                    afternoon. The Improvements here had been destroyed </p>
                <pb n="52" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_052"/>
                <p><gap/>ans during the last war, and some Person had been killed in the <lb/>
                    <gap/>two families of Friends, remained at their habitations with<lb/>
                    <gap/> untill <del>they were carried away</del> the heads of them were taken <lb/>
                    <gap/>after jail as suspected Person; and the door of another
                    <del>house</del><lb/> was marked in the night with the figure of a tortoise,
                    which was<lb/> afterward understood to have been an indication that they might
                    stay with<lb/> safety like a tortoise covered each in its shell. We expect to
                    leave this Place<lb/> on 2nd. Day by way of Catawissy, and I shall probably be
                        <del>the</del><lb/>myself the bearer of the next intelligence from</p>
                <closer> Your <signed><persName key="jsans1">Joseph
                    Sansom</persName></signed></closer>
            </div>
            
            <div type="undetermined">
                <pb n="53" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_053"/>
                <pb n="54" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_054"/>
                <pb n="55" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_055"/>
                <pb n="56" facs="hv_sansomj_letters_1796_056"/>       
            </div>
            
        </body>


    </text>
</TEI>
