<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei-print.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="global.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>William Allinson Diary, Volume 2: Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Haverford College Quaker Collection</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>FHL staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Journal transcribed by</resp>
                    <name>Crowd-sourced</name>


                </respStmt>

            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 91 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Haverford College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street/>
                    <addrLine>Haverford, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode/>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>This work is the property of Haverford College Special COlleciotn. It may be
                        copied freely by individuals for personal use, research, and teaching
                        (including distribution to classes) as long as this statement of
                        availability is included in the text. It may be linked to freely in Internet
                        editions of all kinds, including for—profit works.</p>
                    <p>Publishers, libraries, and other information providers interested in
                        providing this text in a commercial or non—profit product or from an
                        information server must contact Haverford College for licensing and cost
                        information.</p>
                    <p> Scholars interested in changing or adding to these texts by, for example,
                        creating a new edition of the text (electronically or in print) with
                        substantive editorial changes, may do so only with the permission of
                        Haverford College. This is the case whether the new publication will be made
                        available at a cost or free of charge.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2016">2016</date>
                <idno type="local">HV_WA_1809_v2</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Native Americans and Quakers: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Haverford College Quaker &amp; Special Collections</institution>
                        <collection>Allinson family papers</collection>
                        <idno>Call number: MC 968, Box 11, Folder 4</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>50 pp. (1 volume)</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The William Allinson manuscript journal is housed in the Haverford College Quaker
                    Quaker and Special Collections.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> The transcribers and editor attempted to render the author’s orthography and
                    grammar as they appear on the page of his journal, even when the author’s own
                    spelling and usage are inconsistent. Additionally, many questions remain about
                    spelling the names of his Quaker acquaintances, individual Native Americans who
                    populate his journal, and Indian villages and towns. The transcribers and editor
                    attempted to remain faithful to the author’s Anglicized spellings in all cases. </p>
                <p>The author of the original journal does not include page numbers on his
                    manuscript; the page numbers have been interpolated by the transcribers to
                    correspond with the manuscript sheets.</p>
            </editorialDecl>

        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written in <date when="1809">1809</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Society of Friends</item>


                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>

        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item>
                    <date when="2016"/></item>

            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="narrative">

                <pb n="1"/>
                <p>Poplar Stump at Clock Creek</p>
                <pb n="2"/>
                <p> Longevity, often living to the age of<lb/> about 90 and as they suppose 100
                    years<lb/> or upward, but as they keep no written Re<lb/>cords of Births or
                    other occurrences, nor have<lb/> any regular mode of computing time, other<lb/>
                    than by moons or Winters, or then remem<lb/>brance of remarkable Events the
                    most<lb/> of them can give no correct account<lb/> how old they are. While we
                    were rais<lb/>ing <persName key="jsilv1">Silver Heel</persName>'s house a smart
                    old<lb/> woman, who was sitting on the Ground<lb/> looking on, we were told
                    could call<lb/> her Descendants round her to the 6th<lb/> Generation. Some of
                    them are subject to the Rheuma<lb/>tism which is supposed may be a
                    consequence<lb/> of their traversing the Wood in all weather,<lb/> night and day
                    - wading in the river and Suffering<lb/> their Cloathing to dry on them- and
                    often ly<lb/>ing out exposed with little or no shelter to<lb/> wet and cold- but
                    from the observation I<lb/> have made on the Inhabitants, where we have<lb/>
                    stopd coming along, the Rheumatism is a<lb/> complaint prevailing in this
                    climate<lb/> and therefore not wholly to be imputed<lb/> to the Indian
                    Exposures. </p>
                <pb n="3"/>
                <p>The Children are generally born in the<lb/> woods - where the Woman accompanied
                    by<lb/> her Mother or some other Elderly woman re<lb/>tires on the occasion
                    &amp; of cold builds a<lb/> Fire - The Babe is immediately wrapd in<lb/> a
                    Blanket &amp; in 3 or 4 hours the Mo<lb/>ther returns with it to her own
                    habitation.<lb/> she washes her blanket soon after in Cold<lb/> water &amp;
                    something, on the same Day, with<lb/> out injury to herself &amp; in two or 3
                    Day<lb/> after goes into the Wood, &amp; Collects &amp; car<lb/>ries home heavy
                    Loads, of Wood on her<lb/> Back with the Infant on the Top of<lb/> it tied to a
                    Board. the Boards for this purpose<lb/> are about two feet &amp; a half in
                    length &amp; one<lb/> in breadth with a little Hoop in front to<lb/> protect the
                    Head of the Child or to sus<lb/>pend a curtain to cover it from flies or<lb/>
                    cold. at the bottom a little foot board and<lb/> at the sides are loop holes for
                    the purpose<lb/> of fastening the Child which is placed in<lb/> an erect porting
                    with its hand down<lb/> its sides &amp; then swathed with a piece of<lb/> Cloth
                    from the feet to the Chin so light<lb/> as to be unable to disengage itself- if
                    the<lb/> Weather is Cold &amp; the Child young a Wild<lb/> Cat Skin or some
                    other skin with<lb/> soft Fur is put next to it. &amp; if <lb/>
                    <pb n="4"/> a Female a little block is placed between<lb/> the heels to prie the
                    toes a incli<lb/>nation inwards but if a male the feet<lb/> are left to take the
                    natural direction<lb/> one consequence of this is that the<lb/> track of the
                    different sexes may be<lb/> easily distinguished &amp; the children in<lb/> this
                    situation are carried about at pleasure &amp; if taken into the wood<lb/> are
                    laid down, or set up, against stumps<lb/> on Trees as occasion requires while
                    the<lb/> mother is employed in gathering wood<lb/> or any other service- a few
                    times in<lb/> the day they loosen there but the<lb/> children are so habited to
                    it that-<lb/> they become quiet when uneasy out<lb/> by being placed in again
                    this is<lb/> continued till they are about 9<lb/> months old &amp; anyway the
                    purpose<lb/> of keeping them straight as well<lb/> as lending &amp; carrying
                    them with<lb/> more ease &amp; security - <persName key="jthom2">Jonathan
                        tho<lb/>mas</persName> said he once knew an Indian<lb/> woman who went out
                    pregnant &amp;<lb/> in ten Days returned with the infant<lb/> on her back &amp;
                    two hundred young <lb/>
                    <pb n="5"/> Pidgeons pickd &amp; opened ready for dres<lb/>sing, inclosed in a
                    piece of bark all the<lb/> product of her own labour except that her
                    <lb/>husband fell he trees for her on which the young <gap/><lb/> when the
                    Indians Die the Women <lb/>generally Inter them; having <del>first</del> dug
                    <lb/>the Grave. They lay bark under &amp; above <lb/>the Dead body &amp; their
                    covering all with <lb/>Earth <note>with persons of note they usually bury
                        Cloathing &amp; Provision &amp;c.</note> Since Friends have been here they
                    <lb/>are more in the way of having Coffins <lb/>which the men make, but they
                    rarely at <lb/>tend at the Interment even now and <lb/>formerly not at all -
                    when the Corpse <lb/>is thus interd every moring for Nine <lb/>Days successively
                    the female rela <lb/>tives &amp; Neighbours of the Deceased Col <lb/>lect at the
                    Deceased's Habitation &amp; fall <lb/>into a kind of throbbing Lamentation &amp;
                    <lb/>then to crying &amp; Wailing - for the <lb/>space of Half an hour or more
                    <lb/>after which they disperse &amp; when <lb/>the days of Mourning are thue
                    ended they <lb/>meet &amp; are councild to Dry up their Tears after this
                    <lb/>endeavor to discard all marks of <lb/>lamentation </p>
                <p>They acknowledge One Supreme Being <lb/>whom they call <foreign xml:lang="iro">Ou'wan'nee'o</foreign> - and be
                    <lb/>lieve Him to be the Creator of all<lb/>
                    <pb n="6"/> good things - the author of Happiness<lb/> &amp; the Rewarder, both
                    in this world &amp; the<lb/> next for all good Sections - They be<lb/>lieve also
                    that there is an Evil Spirit<lb/> whom they call <persName key="swhit2"
                        >Neis'she'o'nay</persName> &amp;<lb/> who influences to bad Action &amp; is
                    the<lb/> creator of all that is bad.<lb/> Wolves, &amp; all warlike Bears,
                    Rattlesnakes, Poisonous Weeds,<lb/> bad thoughts &amp; deeds &amp; every thing
                    that<lb/> is productive of unhappiness both in<lb/> man &amp; on the Earth</p>
                <p>They believe there is a place of Happiness<lb/> called <foreign xml:lang="iro">Hight'Caanon gay</foreign> and that
                    when they Die,<lb/>
                    <gap/>their Lives have been regular in this<lb/> World they ascend &amp; are
                    received there among<lb/> the spirits of good Men &amp; Women, where<lb/> the
                    Great Spirit is the Head of all.<lb/> He then presents &amp; hangs about
                    their<lb/> necks a string of Implements for hunt<lb/>ing providing themselves a
                    comfortable livings they are sent to hunt in a Warm<lb/> country where there is
                    plenty of Game.<lb/> &amp; fertile for Corn, Beans &amp; other good things.
                    -</p>
                <p>The place of punishment they call<lb/><foreign xml:lang="iro">Owhon'ga'go'u'nong geeh</foreign> and consider it the
                    reverse of<lb/> that of Happiness being a Cold &amp; Barren Country-<lb/> little
                    Game &amp; nothing to kill it with -<lb/> or to procure other necessaries that
                    the Bad spirit there is Governor of all <lb/>
                    <pb n="7"/> and greatly increases then Distresses<lb/> arrayd in their best
                    Clothing &amp; Ornaments<lb/> They assemble twice in the Year to ren<lb/>der
                    Thanks to the Good Spirit for the<lb/> favours which he hath conferd upon<lb/>
                    them - the first is in the Fall of the Year <lb/>when the Corn, Beans, Squashes
                    &amp;<lb/> Potatoes are ripe &amp; the other about the<lb/> middle of Winter
                    when they return with<lb/> Game &amp; Skins from Hunting - At these<lb/> Times
                    the men, Women, &amp; Children Col<lb/>lect &amp; an examination takes place
                    <lb/>what uneasinesses are among them and<lb/> what evil acts each one has
                    committed<lb/> of there it is also common that they<lb/> make Confession, the
                    design of<lb/> which is that all wrong things should<lb/> be done away &amp;
                    that where Differences<lb/> have existed a reconcilliation take<lb/> place &amp;
                    a promise on the part of<lb/> the Offenders to by to do better for the
                    future<lb/> which done the Council assembled forgive them.<lb/> They then divide
                    into small Companies Men &amp;<lb/> Women apart &amp; dance around &amp; in
                    each<lb/> House in the Town. These Dancing Com<lb/>panies are preceeded by two
                    Men, ap<lb/>pointed for the purpose, who are dressd <lb/>in the most frightful
                    manner they can <lb/>
                    <pb n="8"/> devise, being coverd with Bear Skins &amp;<lb/> a bag of Ashes tied
                    about their middles<lb/> behind them &amp; a hole to admit the Ashes<lb/> to run
                    about as they move- their faces<lb/> are coverd by a Large Painted mask
                    hav<lb/>ing a high mane on the crown made of the<lb/> coarsest long Horse Hair
                    standing al<lb/>most erect &amp; large Eyes encircled<lb/> with a flame coloured
                    ring- the mouth<lb/> is open &amp; shewn their own Teeth with<lb/> which They
                    Grin in a terrific man<lb/>ner &amp; their Hands are blackd so<lb/> as to leave
                    the mark with every<lb/> Person they lay them on- In their<lb/> Hands they carry
                    the Shell of a mud<lb/> Tortoise which has been dried for<lb/> the purpose with
                    a stick thrust<lb/> thro' it which extends the neck<lb/> &amp; large Head to its
                    full extent<lb/> and inside of the Shell are a quan<lb/>tity of Pebbles- Which
                    when shaken<lb/> make a Dismal rattle- these men<lb/> going from House to House
                    rub this<lb/> Rattle on the sides &amp; up &amp; down the <lb/>
                    <pb n="9"/> Door Ports- they also frequently enter<lb/> into the House but say
                    nothing nor<lb/> do any Injury- as they travel about<lb/> if they meet with any
                    Person male<lb/> or female in their way they pursue<lb/> them- those who turn
                    about &amp; receive<lb/> them in a friendly way they shake<lb/> hands with, yet
                    say nothing- but<lb/> it is rather expected that many<lb/> should run as if
                    terrified- these<lb/> before getting into a House<lb/> are pursued &amp; if
                    overtaken are laid<lb/> hold of &amp; blackd with their Hands<lb/> but no other
                    injury is offerd and<lb/> except a frightful yelling noise any things spoken-
                    The design<lb/> of these frightful representations<lb/> is to Personify and
                    imitate the Bad Spirit &amp; to<lb/> remind the Indians of the Necessity<lb/> to
                    amend their Ways &amp; avoid wrong<lb/> things- After these Ceremonies are
                    <lb/>performed they Collect at the Coun<lb/>cil House where they away &amp;<lb/>
                    paint a Dog (a White one is preferd)<lb/> the Poor Dog is then killd &amp;
                    thrown on <lb/>
                    <pb n="10"/> on a Fire prepard for the purpose.<lb/> the Indians, mean while
                    Dancing round<lb/> the Fire and Hooping with a Great noise.<lb/> The Dog is
                    Esteemed by them as approaching<lb/> the nearest to themselves of any other
                    Ani<lb/>mal and therefore is devoted on these occasions as a<lb/> sacrifice to
                    the Great Spirit, and together<lb/> with their Dancing is under a
                    profession<lb/> of pleasing Him- during this ceremony they<lb/> are feasting
                    occasionally on Corn Vegetables &amp; Venison-<lb/> this Venison is taken by
                    encircling a large<lb/> space of Hunting Ground &amp; <lb/>all the Deer <gap/>
                    <lb/> here Killd are Devoted to this Feast.<lb/><gap/> about a Pound of Tobacco,
                    of<lb/> a particular Kind which they consider as peculiarly agree<lb/>able to
                    the Great Spirit is also thrown on the<lb/> Fire while the Dog is burning, in
                    the smoke<lb/> whereof the Spirit of the Dog ascending is<lb/> believed to be
                    received by the Great Spirit<lb/> as a Sacrifice of a Good Savour- during
                    this<lb/> Ascention one of their Chiefs whom they call <lb/>their Minister
                    addresses the Great Spirit<lb/> in a Speech, the purport of which is an<lb/>
                    Acknowledgement for favours received-<lb/> Thanks for His Preservation in times
                    past<lb/> and imploring His continued care &amp; <lb/>
                    <pb n="11"/> protection- he then addresses the People<lb/> advising how they
                    ought to Conduct them<lb/>selves &amp; pointing our some of the promi<lb/>nent
                    Evils which they should avoid- one<lb/> of the greatest of these is stealing and
                    ano<lb/>ther is for the Husband to Desert &amp; Sepa<lb/>rate himself from his
                    Wife during Preg<lb/>nancy- but taking the Life of another<lb/> is not considerd
                    a Crime so Capital, as they<lb/> are left at liberty to revenge it by
                    ta<lb/>king the Life of the Murderer- this may<lb/> be done with impunity by the
                    Nearest<lb/> Relative of the Deceased &amp; they then convey the cries of Blood
                    to be done away. The before<lb/> described feasting &amp; Dancing is
                    continued<lb/> at Intervals &amp; by Companies for <del>the</del> a<lb/> Period
                    of from five to ten Days- &amp;<lb/> Formerly toward the latter part of<lb/> the
                    Time many of them became in<lb/>toxicated, but at present among the<lb/> Indians
                    of this Neighbourhood this is<lb/> entirely disused- and altho the feast<lb/> is
                    conducted with considerable noise<lb/> &amp; apparent Confusion, it also is
                    atten<lb/>ded at Intervals with much Solemnity &amp; on the<lb/> part of many of
                    them purely on <lb/>
                    <pb n="12"/> a religious ground &amp; from sincere &amp; good<lb/> motives-
                    Formerly they<lb/> had Image of a man which at the<lb/> Time of those hearts was
                    decorated in<lb/> the Indian Stile with Wampum &amp;<lb/> Trinkets &amp;c- this
                    was elevated on a<lb/> Pedestal of about 6 feet in heighth &amp;<lb/> their
                    Dance &amp; feasting were performd<lb/> round it &amp; their addresses made
                    to<lb/> it- being considered by them a Repre<lb/>sentative of the Great Spirit-
                    about<lb/> the Year 1802 this Image fell<lb/> down &amp; a council was held what
                    was<lb/> to be done- some were for erecting<lb/> another- others for discarding
                    such<lb/> a Representation entirely- <persName key="habee1">Henry<lb/>
                        Obeal</persName>- Undertook to throw it in the<lb/> River, the Council first
                    Consenting<lb/> that he should do it if he would<lb/> take upon himself &amp; he
                    answerable<lb/> for any Judgement which might<lb/> follow- this <persName
                        key="habee1">Henry</persName> agreed to &amp;<lb/> tumbling it in the River
                    it floated <lb/>
                    <pb n="13"/> down the Stream about Eleven Miles<lb/> &amp; lodged on an Island-
                        <persName key="conud1">Conudiu</persName> was<lb/> appointed successor &amp;
                    Intercessor, to en<lb/>deavour to Keep Peace with the Great Spi<lb/>rit by
                    averting Judments &amp;c- They also<lb/> Esteem him a Great Doctor &amp; a
                    Prophet when<lb/> disposed to communicate any thing to the<lb/> Indians in this
                    Way, he wraps or covers himself<lb/> with his Blanket flying down quite<lb/>
                    still with two little Heaps of Tobacco <lb/>smoaking beside him, he
                    pretends<lb/> leave the Body &amp; Ascend to the upper<lb/> Regions where he
                    says he holds communion<lb/> with the Angels &amp; recieves from them
                    <lb/>information respecting such Things as<lb/> the Great Spirit designs should
                    be<lb/> imparted to the Indians- after he has<lb/> lain about half am Hour he
                    throws <lb/>off his Blanket &amp; opening his Eyes <lb/>sets up- a council is
                    then Calld &amp;<lb/> the subject of his pretended Visions<lb/> communicated
                    these professed Reve<lb/>lations have in some Instances had a<lb/> remarkable
                    effect upon the Indians-<lb/> his first Visions in this way we were<lb/>
                    <pb n="14"/> told was about 10 years ago I was, that<lb/> the Indians should
                    leave off Drinking Rum<lb/> &amp; refrain from Selling their Lands- a<lb/>
                    Reformation accordingly took place, but<lb/> it may be remarked that before
                    this,<lb/> friends had been labouring with them<lb/> much in those respects-
                        <persName key="conud1">Conudiu</persName> Con<lb/>tinued an advocate herein
                    &amp; Some time<lb/> after being desirous of encouraging &amp;<lb/> pleasing his
                    Converts he told them that <lb/>he had another Vission &amp; saw the bad<lb/>
                    Spirit, in a frightful form &amp; having<lb/> Wings alight behind a Certain
                    House<lb/> but that after looking about for some<lb/> time &amp; finding that
                    the Indians had<lb/> declined drinking Rum &amp; he had no<lb/>thing to do
                    there, he flew over to<lb/>
                    <placeName key="buffa">Buffelo</placeName> another Village where the Indians
                    drank<lb/> Rum &amp; where he found plenty of<lb/> Business. The sacrifice of
                    the Dog is now disap<lb/>proved by some of them &amp; <persName key="habee1"
                        >Henry Obeal</persName><lb/> who tho' in some respects he has been a
                    dis<lb/>sipated character &amp; in other is still in the<lb/> commission of
                    wrong things is notwithstanding <lb/>
                    <pb n="15"/> a discerning &amp; enlightened Man) intends<lb/> to open his
                    Objections in Council- he also be<lb/>lieves, with respect to Witchcraft that
                    it<lb/> does not exist &amp; occasionally esperessed this Opinion<lb/> among
                    them, but has to do it with care,<lb/> and thinks he has already incurrd the
                    dis<lb/>pleasure of many whose prejudices in this<lb/> particular are yet
                    strong--</p>
                <p>In Time of War they formerly Roasted<lb/> &amp; Eat their Captives- there are one
                    or two<lb/> among them here who have partaken of<lb/> this inhuman feasting, but
                    of latter time<lb/> this Custom is exploded by this Nation<lb/> The Masks
                    (before described) are some<lb/> times worn as a cure for Diseases which<lb/>
                    cures in this way, are supposed to be<lb/> effected by operating on the
                    Imagination.<lb/> War is considered in its Origin<lb/> to proceed from the Evil
                    Spirit- that<lb/> is the first agressor is instigated by<lb/> him- but when
                    agression has taken<lb/> place they consider is not only justi<lb/>fiable to
                    Revenge the Injury but even<lb/> believe that by so doing they are<lb/> employd
                    in the service of the Good<lb/> Spirit &amp; that if they are killd in<lb/>
                    Battle they are recieved into the place <pb n="16"/> of Happiness<lb/>They have,
                    beside their Public Devotions<lb/> at Hearts &amp; Sacrifices, a Kind of
                    Family<lb/> Worship which is when they are setting<lb/> together particularly in
                    the Evening, if<lb/> one of the Heads of the family feels an<lb/> Impulse to
                    address the Great Spirit<lb/> he or she yield to it with an audible voice,<lb/>
                    and this, among the more serious Class,<lb/> is frequently performed, tho' not
                    many<lb/> stated Days or Times-- They are some<lb/>times exercisd in this Way
                    when their<lb/> Friends are with them &amp; the subject<lb/> of Aspiration is a
                    Thanksgiving for<lb/> preservation of their particular Family<lb/> or Tribe
                    &amp; for supplying the varied<lb/> necessaries &amp; Comforts of Sides-
                    de<lb/>siring their Continuance-</p>
                <p> If an Indian of any particular Tribe<lb/> dreams a remarkable Dream
                    respecting<lb/> a Deceased Relative being Hungry or<lb/> in Need of Sympathy or
                    assistance in<lb/> any way the Indians of his Tribe are<lb/> informed of it
                    &amp; a Hunting takes place<lb/> in consequence- the Game then taken <lb/>
                    <pb n="17"/> is prepared and cooked and a feast and dance<lb/> in a religious
                    way is instituted by the<lb/> partees engaged which continues for a<lb/> day or
                    more.</p>
                <p> Formerly when a stranger or distant friend<lb/> entered an indian habitation it
                    was common<lb/> to set before them such provision as they<lb/> had cooked in the
                    house which the guest<lb/> partook of without ceremony except that<lb/> of
                    thanks, but friends<lb/> have rather advised them not<lb/> to give their
                    provision indiscriminately to<lb/> wondering or idle persons <lb/>
                    <del>but only to</del>
                    <lb/><del>strangers pariicularly Friends they have</del>
                    <lb/><del>old or infirm</del> least it should encourage<lb/> indolence and be a
                    sound of oppressi<lb/>on on to the industirious and frugal- in this<lb/> respect
                    therefore thine is some change -<lb/> when a <orgName key="seneca"
                        >Seneca</orgName> Indian leaves his friend<lb/> he tells him he is done,
                    which amounts<lb/> to farewell - but if any circumstance<lb/> takes place which
                    has given umbrage<lb/> he withdraws and says nothing -this is<lb/> clear
                    evidence that he is offended-</p>
                <p>Notwithstanding stealing in considered<lb/> a great crime, it not unfrequently
                    takes<lb/> place -when the person committing a<lb/> theft is discovered
                    complaint is made to the<lb/> chiefs who dispatch a runner command<lb/>ing
                        <lb/><pb n="18"/> him to appear before the council-<lb/> this mandate he
                    immediately obeys The<lb/> charge is then opend to him &amp; if he is
                    guilty<lb/> confession is made and the Property taken is<lb/> restored if in
                    being -- every Chief or Warri<lb/>or in Council is then at full liberty to<lb/>
                    express what they think, one by one, all<lb/> which he is obliged to hear. Thus
                    is considered<lb/> a severe punishment, but no other is<lb/> inflicted. Should
                    the Person charged de<lb/>ny that he is Guilty, he is considered In<lb/>nocent,
                    for it is remarkable in them that<lb/> they confess when justly Charges.
                        <persName key="jthom2">Jona<lb/>than</persName> told me that on such
                    occasions, he <lb/>had frequently been a Witness, their<lb/> countenance &amp;
                    Eyes betrayd them imme<lb/>diately, &amp; of itself has been suffici<lb/>ent
                    evidence to him that the Gospel<lb/> has been preachd in them, or in other<lb/>
                    Words that the Witness for Truth is<lb/> placed in their Minds--</p>
                <p>The Different Sexes are very jealous &amp; shy of<lb/> each other so that it is
                    rare to see a man<lb/> &amp; Woman, even of the same Tribe, con<lb/>versing
                    together without witnesses, &amp; when<lb/> a Woman has occasion to go abroad it
                    is<lb/> accounted Honourable to take one or more<lb/> Children with her to
                    testify, if needful, <lb/>
                    <pb n="19"/> that she has been orderly - there are<lb/> too many proofs that
                    this is only a preten<lb/>ded shyness, yet being santioned &amp;
                    esta<lb/>blished by custom it is productive of se<lb/>rious Evils - The Indians
                    appear to be as<lb/> well calculated and to possess talents for so<lb/>cial and
                    rational enjoyment as<lb/> any people, but custom putting a nega<lb/>tive on an
                    open friendly acquaintance<lb/> of the sexes, the natural tendency whereof<lb/>
                    would be the improvement of their mind<lb/> and a knowledge of the good
                    qualities one<lb/> of the other, with the undesigned pro<lb/>duction in many
                    instances of permanent<lb/> attachments -they enter into Marie-<lb/> age very
                    early before their judgment<lb/> in ripe for the choice, without affec<lb/>tion
                    &amp; without a knowledge of each<lb/> others dispositions - the
                    consequence<lb/> of which is that separations often<lb/> take place, so that
                    there are many<lb/> instances now here of Men who have<lb/> turned off several
                    wives, and of women<lb/> who have discarded as many hus<lb/>bands - there on
                    both sides marry<lb/>again (in a clandeitine ways to others <lb/>
                    <pb n="20"/> and in some Instances change back<lb/> again, and thus, what ought
                    to be esteem<lb/>ed the most Devious &amp; important Connec<lb/>tion in Life, is
                    lightly formed &amp; dissolved<lb/> and shifted about in a manner unknown<lb/>
                    among a People rightly Civilized -- In these<lb/> separations the Mother takes
                    the Children &amp; uses them Kindly<lb/> They are very fond of Children &amp;
                    indulge them<lb/> in most of their Wishes using little restraint<lb/> or
                    Conection of any Kind, yet sometimes<lb/> if Obstinate, tho' very young, they
                    will<lb/> plunge them in the River &amp; if one Dip is<lb/> not sufficient it is
                    repeated till they be<lb/>come very quiet, which they soon do.<lb/> as the
                    Children get a little older they<lb/> will sometimes talk to them a long
                    time<lb/> in a Kind of harrangue or Speech<lb/> setting forth what the Child
                    should<lb/> do &amp; what leave undone-- this at<lb/> times has such an Effect
                    that the<lb/> Tears will trickle down their Cheeks<lb/> of the Child before the
                    speech is<lb/> ended-- at other times they ridi<lb/>cule them for doing wrong
                    and tell<lb/> them they are not wise in doing so.<lb/> to tell an Indian that he
                    is not wise is a grating stigma.</p>
                <p>When a Person has been Sick for a con<lb/>siderable Time in a lingering condition
                    &amp; <lb/>
                    <pb n="21"/> the appreciation of Roots &amp; Herbs or other<lb/> Medecine proves
                    ineffectual to restore, it<lb/> is common for their Friends to collect<lb/> and
                    dressing two Men with Masks &amp;c <lb/>in the Manner described at times of<lb/>
                    Public Worship, they repair to the Ha<lb/>bitation, which they go round rattling
                    &amp;<lb/> Rubbing the Tortoise Shells &amp; whoping<lb/> in a frightful manner-
                    this altho' it<lb/> is a known Custom &amp; in time of Health does<lb/> not
                    alarm them, yet has considerable af<lb/>fect on the Debilitated Indian
                    whose<lb/> fears being thus previously awakened by<lb/> knowing what is to be
                    endured. the men<lb/> enter the House continuing the noise &amp;<lb/> acting
                    every Wild Contortion &amp; Maneuvre<lb/> which their Imagination Devise-
                    some<lb/> times they pull the sick Person, whe<lb/>ther Male or female, about
                    the Room<lb/> dirtying them with their black Hands<lb/> &amp;rubbing their Heads
                    &amp; Bodies over<lb/> with ashes &amp; handling in such a<lb/> manner that a
                    Person unacquainted<lb/> with their Custom would almost<lb/> suppose they were
                    going to kill the <lb/>Patient-- after this Wild treatment of <lb/>
                    <pb n="22"/> of the sick Person &amp; dirtying the House<lb/> thoroughly with
                    their Ashes they with<lb/>draw &amp; the nurse or some other Indian<lb/>
                    undertakes to Clean after them-- Ab<lb/>surd as this practice appears it is<lb/>
                    said that in many cases it has a<lb/> beneficial Effect by restoring
                    Per<lb/>spiration, working on the Imagin<lb/>ation &amp; rousing the Indisposed
                    Person<lb/> to a Salutary Exertion--- Their Idea is<lb/> they drive away the
                    Evil Spirits in this way. --<lb/> The Ancient Custom when an Indian died<lb/>
                    who was the Head of a Family was to take out<lb/> his Goods &amp; burn the Hut,
                    the Design of thus<lb/> destroying the Habitation was to prevent<lb/> any
                    differences which might arise among<lb/> his Descendents or survivors respecting
                    the<lb/> possesing it that so Peace might be pre<lb/>served--<lb/>
                    <del>on such occasions of <gap/> time <lb/>the husband does <gap/><lb/>the
                        Houses and where both Parents are dead <gap/><lb/></del><lb/><note>This I
                        believe is not correct, but I cannot rectify it.</note></p>
                <p>When an Indian of distinction &amp; property<lb/> dies his Gun, Blanket, Knife,
                    Trinkets &amp; other<lb/> This I believe is not correct, but I cannot rectify
                    it. Property are preserved about 12 &amp; some<lb/> times 18 months, before a
                    Division is made--<lb/> this Delay is in Consequence of an Opinion which
                        <lb/><pb n="23"/>they entertain that it is not decent or<lb/> respectful to
                        <del>take possession or</del> bring<lb/> them into use sooner-- they are
                    then bro.<lb/> into Council &amp; held up to public view, the<lb/> Indians
                    present being informed that here<lb/> are the Goods of such a Deceased
                    Chief.<lb/> on the Articles being thus severally held<lb/> up Any of the Young
                    Men who in<lb/>clince, are at liberty to advance &amp; Snatch<lb/> them away,
                    till the whole are thus dis<lb/>tributed. the Relatives of the Deceased<lb/>
                    making no claim in consequence of Con<lb/>nection. This Custom still
                    prevails<lb/> among some of the Indians in the Southern States<lb/> but some of
                    the more thoughtful among<lb/> the <orgName key="seneca">Senceas</orgName>,
                    since their building of good<lb/> Houses &amp; increase of Property, do not<lb/>
                    seem satisfied with the foregoing Cus<lb/>toms &amp; in two or three Instances
                    they<lb/> have made Wills to divide their<lb/> Possessions &amp; Improvements
                    among<lb/> their Children. this is a Natural Con<lb/>sequence of an advance
                    toward Civilization<lb/> &amp; must obtain more place among them.<lb/> The Gun
                    &amp; other things were formerly buried<lb/> with the Deceased, but latterly
                    this custom is<lb/> much Discontinued. --</p>
                <pb n="24"/>
                <p>They believe in the Ressurection of the Spirit<lb/> but not of the Body &amp;
                    that for some Time<lb/> after Death it is common for it to Ascend &amp;
                    De<lb/>scend. in order therefore for its accommoda<lb/>tion, as altho perhaps
                    from motives of De<lb/>cency &amp; Respect, a Tomb is erected over<lb/> the
                    Graves, sometimes formd with logs<lb/> &amp; having a Roof of Bark -- at others
                    it<lb/> is Constructed with Boards &amp; the Roof of<lb/> the same- it made in
                    this way, a small<lb/> hole, phps the size of a key hole is<lb/> cut at the Head
                    of the Tomb both above<lb/> &amp; below to allow Ingress &amp; Egress to<lb/>
                    the Departed Spirit-- This Custom con<lb/>tinues-- Already in Degree, it is
                    taking place<lb/> when Friends first came among them they<lb/> had one common
                    field &amp; altho' each planted<lb/> his particular spot, there were many
                    Idlers<lb/> who partook the labour of the more Indus<lb/>trious-- They now clear
                    their particular<lb/> spots of land where choice induces them &amp;<lb/> build
                    themselves comfortable Houses.<lb/> these Improvements if they incline to
                    leave<lb/> (as they sometimes do in order to settle else<lb/> where) are sold to
                    such as incline to<lb/> purchase &amp; altho' the Fee in the Soil<lb/> cannot be
                    Conveyd Being the property of<lb/> the Nation yet Improvements so sold are
                    considered the Property of the Purchaser <lb/><pb n="25"/> who without
                    molestation enjoys his prive<lb/>ledge-- The first sale of this Kind was<lb/>
                    considered an innovation &amp; made consider<lb/>able stir but it is now done
                    without<lb/> objection &amp; is no Small stimilus to<lb/> Individual exertion.
                    --</p>
                <p>It sometimes happened formerly that as <lb/><unclear>but</unclear> Indians who
                    were disabled from Hunting by<lb/> Infermity being tird of Life would request
                    to<lb/> be buried alive, a Grave or Hole was then<lb/> dug in which a seat was
                    formed in the Digging<lb/> the Antient Indian was then let down &amp;<lb/>
                    taking his last seat the other Indians be<lb/>gan to fill in the Earth doing it
                    very gently<lb/> &amp; tenderly till it had risen to his Chin.<lb/> a Pause was
                    then made and<lb/> some ceremony used, after which the<lb/> Young Warriors threw
                    in the Dirt very<lb/> hartily so as to prevent their<lb/> being Witnesses to his
                    Struggles &amp; to<lb/>
                    <gap/> terminate his suf<lb/>ferings as speedily as might be.<lb/> The Indian
                    Men formerly pluckd out their<lb/> Beards as also the Hair from their Heads<lb/>
                    except a Tuft on the Crown which was<lb/> left to grow pretty long. In time of
                    War this<lb/> was laid hold of by an Enemy who had the<lb/> Power, &amp; the
                    Skin to which it was attached<lb/> severd with a Knife &amp; this they
                    denominated<lb/> scalping-- The Instrument use in plucking <lb/><pb n="26"/> the
                    Head &amp; Beard was found by twisting a<lb/> Wire of the Common Knitting Needle
                    Size on a<lb/> piece of round hard Wood about 1/2 an Inch in<lb/> Diameter &amp;
                    two Inches in length. On the Wood<lb/> being withdrawn the Wire forms a
                    spring<lb/> or Kind of Pinchers &amp; being applied to the Face<lb/> or Head
                    &amp; then pressd with the thumb &amp;<lb/> Finger at each end, took such fast
                    hold of<lb/> the Hairs which had inserted themselves be<lb/>tween the wires when
                    a little open, they<lb/> were readily extracted by the Roots. This
                    Investment<lb/> is light of carriage &amp; will last an Age.<lb/> Plucking the
                    Hair from their Heads is<lb/> now Discontinued, and in many Instances the
                    Younger Men Shave their Beards.</p>
                <p>Indian Parents commonly give their Children<lb/> names significant of something
                    in Nature, as<lb/>
                    <persName key="cornp2">Corn Planters</persName> name in the Indian Language
                    is<lb/> <foreign xml:lang="iro">Ky ea'twech'Che</foreign>. <persName key="conud1">Conudin</persName>, signifies a<lb/>
                    <foreign xml:lang="iro">handsome Lake</foreign>. <foreign xml:lang="iro">Agish'quat'take</foreign> is Dry<lb/>
                    Much. <foreign xml:lang="iro">Oendo</foreign>, means the first ripe Corn.<lb/> these Names are Changed
                    occasionally<lb/> in Consequence of remarkable Circumstance on<lb/> taking
                    place, or of particular Employments<lb/> or acts of Individuals &amp; latterly
                    some of these<lb/> Class &amp; Children have taken &amp; ap<lb/>pear pleased,
                    with being named after white<lb/> People. They are not Delicate in their Eating,
                    but<lb/> will feast, apparently with a relish, on Meat<lb/> much tainted &amp;
                    even peopled with Inhabi<lb/>tants &amp; sometimes almost rotten. -- </p>
                <pb n="27"/>
                <p>they are very Jealous of encroachments on the<lb/> rights &amp; Priviledges of
                    each other &amp; Offences of this<lb/> Nature have often given occasion for War
                    between<lb/> Nations. When such Offences Occur they hold<lb/> private Councils
                    &amp; if they determine<lb/> to engage, they endeavour to do it by Surprize.
                    Such<lb/> as excel in Artifice &amp; courage are appointed their Chiefs
                    &amp;<lb/> have the management of their War Concerns.<lb/> They generally paint
                    themselves Red, but on<lb/> some occasions streaks of Black are intermixed.<lb/>
                    Painting with Red, tho' expressive of War, is also<lb/> used to denote
                    cheerfulness so &amp; sometimes to hide<lb/> the true expression of the
                    Countenance, &amp; in this<lb/> way, when rubbed round the Eye, it has a
                    Won<lb/>derful Effect. it also makes them look fierce --<lb/> Black mostly
                    denotes Trouble -- In their<lb/> Marches They are as Careful as possible to
                    con<lb/>ceal their Tracks &amp; to make very little Fire<lb/> in order to
                    prevent its being discovered that<lb/> a Multitude has passed. when engaged
                    they<lb/> are very Fierce, scalping those whom they kill,<lb/> &amp; taking
                    Prisoners all they can-- these are taken<lb/> home with them &amp; arranging
                    before the Council<lb/> where it is Determined which should be Put <lb/>to
                    torture &amp; which preserved alive, -- the lat<lb/>ter are sometimes adopted in
                    Families in the<lb/> place of Relatives who have been killd in<lb/> the War-- in
                    such Cases they are treated here<lb/> by &amp; often only in marriage with the
                    nation<lb/> receiving them. --<lb/> They are very fond of ornaments &amp;
                    a<lb/>mong the Woman particularly Silver<lb/> Brouches. TS told us that he once <lb/>
                    <pb n="28"/> saw 700 of these on one Garment.<lb/> When an Indian believes he
                    has received an<lb/> Injury he is never satisfied without Revenge<lb/> and if he
                    cannot obtain it on the aggressor he<lb/> seeks to do it on some of the same
                    tribe<lb/> or family - to illustrate this Disposition,<lb/> I may here relate an
                    Account<lb/> that was given me of an old Indian Man<lb/> on the <placeName
                        key="alleg">Allegany River</placeName> whom I saw<lb/> and shook hand with,
                    who passes<lb/> among them by the name of Stiff<lb/> Arms. In an Indian War
                    many<lb/> years since, when he was young<lb/> he was shot in an Engagement<lb/>
                    thro' both his arms - tho Ball<lb/> passing near the Elbows entirely<lb/>
                    disabled him for resistance he<lb/> thought it necessary to make his re<lb/>peat
                    - in this situation it seems like<lb/>ly he would have perished but some<lb/> of
                    his own Tribe found and took care<lb/> of him feeding him for a long time<lb/>
                    and dressing his Wound. Hostiliies<lb/> between the contending parties
                    being<lb/> by this time over, himself and his Tribe<lb/> returned home, the
                    thoughts of <lb/>
                    <pb n="29"/> the injury he had sustained Rankled<lb/> in his mind &amp; he
                    endeavored for a<lb/> considerable time to prevail with<lb/> some of his friends
                    to go with him<lb/> to there notion by when he was<lb/> wounded to make
                    celabration, but the<lb/> distance was so long (being I think<lb/> about three
                    thousand miles) and<lb/> the danger of the understanding so<lb/> great that they
                    would not join<lb/> him - <gap/> unwilling to relinquish<lb/> his design he set
                    out above &amp; trav<lb/>aild till he reachd the Border<lb/> of his Enemy - he
                    then stripd<lb/> himself naked &amp; for several days<lb/> &amp; night lay in
                    the wood &amp; corn<lb/> field in the vicinity of the Ene<lb/>mies Town,
                    watching to catch<lb/> some of them who might be se<lb/>parated from the next -
                    by obser<lb/>vation he at length found that<lb/> the warriors had gone away on
                    an<lb/> expedition of hunting or war &amp; on <lb/><pb n="30"/>entering the
                    village he killed &amp;<lb/> scalped a woman &amp; two children &amp;<lb/>
                    immediately made his Retreat, tra<lb/>velling into the wilderness night<lb/>
                    &amp; day with the greatest expedition<lb/> he was capable of till almost
                    fam<lb/>ishd -after extreme hardships en<lb/>durd he at length reached home
                    &amp;<lb/> says he then left satisfied, - he<lb/> still relates the circumstance
                    with<lb/> great apparent satisfaction - says he<lb/> thinks he did right &amp;
                    that if he had<lb/> not obtaind revenge he never should<lb/> have felt easy-
                    However despa<lb/>rately cruel this act may appear to<lb/> the Christian, and in
                    a rational view<lb/> however unjust that the innocent<lb/> should be made to
                    suffer for the Guilty,<lb/> yet great allowance is to be made <lb/>for the
                    unfetterd Indian who by Edu<lb/>cation is taught to believe that the<lb/>
                    Revenge for an aggression is a Du<lb/>ty -that the family or the tribe, are<lb/>
                    implicated with the individual aggres<lb/>sor and that if he falls in
                    obtaining<lb/> his desire, he will undoubtedly Die happy- </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="31"/>
                <dateline><date when="1809-09-20"><gap/> mo 20th</date><placeName key="tunes"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>staid about home &amp; employd part of the time<lb/> down five feet deep in a
                    Mound in the Field under an ap<lb/>prehension that it had once been an Indian
                    place of<lb/> internment but in this we were disappointed. we how<lb/>ever found
                    a number of Pebble stones which on break<lb/>ing often presented us the
                    impression of marine<lb/> shells - were also thrown a Flint stone taken<lb/>
                    from the River those involving a shell of their kind -<lb/> and about this House
                    &amp; premises there are large<lb/> rough stones suitable for building which
                    are<lb/> apparently composed entirely of marine shells<lb/> &amp; a kind of
                    Earth or Clay in a Petrified state<lb/> they told in that in the copy of the
                    Mountains, which is<lb/> here near us &amp; in full view, are abundance<lb/> of
                    stone of this description &amp; that Petrifaction<lb/> is very common &amp;
                    discoverable in various ways<lb/> throughout this Mountaneous Country- that<lb/>
                    wherever this Petrification prevails the inhabi<lb/>tants are subject to the
                    complaint before<lb/> mentioned of a Swelling in the Throat, here<lb/>
                    denominated the Guitar -</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1809-09-21">21st &amp; 5th of the Week </date><placeName
                        key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p>- sat with the Fam<lb/>ily in their Week Day meeting - after Din<lb/>ner the
                    Indian Runner who went with our<lb/> Message to <placeName key="catta1"
                        >Cattaraugus</placeName> came in, having<lb/> been quite to <placeName
                        key="buffa">Buffalo</placeName>, calld of 5 miles by<lb/> the Indian Path -
                    he left their town on<lb/> first Day about Eleven oclock &amp; returned<lb/> to
                    it about the same hour having performed<lb/> the journey wholly on foot in 11
                    Days - be<lb/>ing about 150 Miles- he brought a <lb/>
                    <pb n="32"/>short letter from <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName> an
                    Extract<lb/> from which I insert as it shows the place <persName key="jtayl1"
                        >Jacob</persName><lb/> has with the indians and also touches on their
                    im<lb/>provement -- </p>

                <floatingText type="letter">
                    <body>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline><placeName key="buffc">Buffelow creck </placeName><date
                                    when="1809-06-19">June 19th 1809</date></dateline>
                            <salute>Respt Friends </salute></opener>
                        <p>I have now a short oppy to note that<lb/> I arrived here last sixth
                            day at the pressing re<lb/>quest of the <placeName key="allegany"
                                >allegany</placeName> and <orgName key="seneca"
                                >Cattarauguy</orgName> Chiefs, to at<lb/>tend a council of the
                                <orgName key="sxntns">six nations</orgName>. I find the<lb/>
                            principle Business is to adopt some permanent<lb/> measure to prevent
                            any more Sales of their Lands <lb/>&amp;c. The War Department are mostly
                            in favour <lb/>of the Plan, &amp; I rather think it will be car
                            <lb/>ried into effect - they have received their <lb/>presents a few
                            Days since at this place <lb/>from the U.S. &amp; I think I never saw so
                            <lb/>many Indians together that conduct <lb/>ted with so much propriety
                            - the num <lb/>ber could not be well ascertained but it <lb/>was thought
                            there were about One Thou <lb/>sand, and I dont remember to see One
                            <lb/>Drunken Indian amongst them - </p>
                        <p>I believe Wool &amp; other Articles we shall <lb/>want can be obtained at
                            this place - The <lb/>Agents says he will furnish the Cattaragus
                            <lb/>Indians with Wheels, or Unite in any <lb/>Measure proper to forward
                            the Object of <lb/>Improvement - the Chief Warriors wife <lb/>has learnd
                            to spin tolerably well, and <lb/>
                            <pb n="33"/> intends to purchase a Wheel of her own<lb/> &amp; commence
                            Spin'g after Corn Harvest -</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1809-09-22">22d, &amp; 6th Day </date><placeName key="tunes"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>- We have had summer Weather<lb/> since being here &amp; to Day several fine
                    Showers<lb/> being the first Rain of Consequence that we<lb/> have seen since
                    leaving home. In the<lb/> Evening <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName>
                    arrived here having<lb/> rode from <placeName key="catta1"
                        >Cattaraagus</placeName> to Day- he informs<lb/> that the Indians propose
                    being home to<lb/>morow giving us a hearing in<lb/> council on first Day.
                        <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob</persName> was very<lb/> entertaining this
                    Evening in some encou<lb/>raging accounts of Indian Improvement<lb/> &amp;
                    relating some Annecdotes of their Dis<lb/>cernment &amp; Talents. he also read
                    us an<lb/> Indian Letter to the Agent of the US for the <orgName key="sxntns"
                        >six Nations</orgName> on<lb/> Indian Affairs. being as follows- </p>
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <opener><dateline><placeName key="tusca1">TusKarora
                                    Village</placeName> <date>March 8th 1808
                                    </date></dateline><salute><persName key="egran1">Mr
                                    Granger</persName></salute></opener>
                        <p>We Chiefs must inform you, as<lb/> you are superintendant, that bad
                            thing<lb/> happen in our Nation. last Sattarday<lb/> we very Sorry. we
                            hope you will not<lb/> be angry with us about it, when you<lb/> know
                            Truth about it. One William, be<lb/> long <orgName key="oneida">Oneida
                                Nation</orgName>. very bad Man,<lb/> he kill one Wife in <placeName
                                key="oneid">Oneida</placeName>, he then<lb/> run away, come amongst
                            us- take<lb/> Wife in our Nation- he got Drunk very <lb/>
                            <pb n="34"/> 34 very often- beat his Wife very much,<lb/> many times
                            most Kill her- he often say he<lb/> would Kill some our People- Last
                            Saturday<lb/> he come home Drunk- he try to Kill his<lb/> Son, a young
                            Chief,- he knife from his<lb/> Father- his son break it,- run to
                            Bush<lb/> where his Mother &amp; Children make Sugar,<lb/> soon William
                            follow him,- come to camp- all run into Bush but one young<lb/> Man
                            brother to William Wife- he has<lb/> come from <placeName key="grand"
                                >Grand River</placeName> to Visit- he would<lb/> not run,- he think
                            William had Gun<lb/> most Dark- he think he hear Gun<lb/> Snap- William
                            Stand behind Tree,-<lb/> he then shot at William with small<lb/> shot,-
                            William then go away- He lie<lb/> all night in Cold, next Morning
                            was<lb/> found Dead- may be froze more Death<lb/> than Shot Kill him- we
                            do not<lb/> know- Monday we buried him-<lb/> the young Man that Kill him
                            gone<lb/> Grand River- We hope you will ad<lb/>vise what is right- we
                            send Knife<lb/> broke you may see it- we hope you<lb/> will not think
                            Murder- Our whole<lb/> Nation Mourn- We hope our Nation<lb/> will not be
                            blame- we mean to Keep <lb/>
                            <pb n="35"/> Sabath, and hear Gospel, and try to per<lb/>suade all our
                            Nation not Drunk Whiskey.<lb/> we shamed any of our People get
                            Drunk<lb/> - we wish you Send Letter by Young Man<lb/> bring this, and
                            tell when you Come<lb/> see. we want to see you here our<lb/> Fine
                            Place-</p>
                        <closer>We send our Love to you.<lb/> Signd by seven Chiefs- in English but
                            written by<lb/>
                            <persName key="ncusi1">Nicholas Cusick</persName> (one of their
                            number)</closer>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1809-09-23">23 d</date><placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p>Cloudy &amp; some Rain. no account yet of<lb/> the Indians return and we have to
                    exercise Pati<lb/>ence. Ill therefore employ part of the Time in des<lb/>cribing
                    this Farm. Know then whom it may<lb/> concern that it lies on the East side of
                    the <placeName key="alleg">Allegany<lb/> River</placeName> at the Distance of
                    about half a mile. is<lb/> bounded on that side being the West by the Indian
                    Preservation<lb/> &amp; on the East by Sands of the Holland Compy.<lb/> of whom
                    it was purchased about the year 1803.<lb/> for $1.25 cents p Acre and contains
                    692<lb/> Acres- about 60 of which is cleard and per<lb/>haps 22 of the 60 may be
                    Calld Meadow or<lb/> bottom Sand, lying on the <placeName key="tunec">Tunassasa
                        Creek</placeName><lb/> which runs thro' its part of this Meadow is
                    <lb/>considerably Improved &amp; very good (say 12<lb/> Acres) the rest is
                    capable of being made so,<lb/> and will all bear culture with the Plow.<lb/> The
                    Cleard Upland produces well but is not<lb/> the most fertile- the residue mostly
                    well<lb/> Timberd with W Pine, Hemlock, Beech,<lb/> Birch, Sugar Maple &amp;c.
                    The House is <lb/><pb n="36"/> pleasantly situate fronting the South, on an<lb/>
                    agreeable Eminence and commands a view of the<lb/> Meadows, Creek, Race,
                    Tanyard, Saw &amp; Griste Mills<lb/> Cowpen, Piles of Boards &amp;c. these are
                    incom<lb/>passed by Wood, &amp; to the South West is a consi<lb/>derable
                    Mountain containing Petrified curiosities.<lb/> - on the North the Ground is
                    rising, but not<lb/> immediately, and the Pine Trees here rear thin<lb/> lofty
                    Heads. The House is a very comfort<lb/>able one, suited with Judgement for
                    the<lb/> occasion. Its Inhabitants are a very<lb/> clever Company, each filling,
                    or, and believe<lb/> sincerely endeavouring to fill up their<lb/> alotments
                    &amp; several services, &amp; therefore<lb/> there is not one banner or
                    unprofitable<lb/> among them- they appear to be im<lb/>pressed with the
                    Inestimable value of<lb/> Accordance, &amp; Consequently live in Love.<lb/> This
                    Example cannot be last to their Indian<lb/> neighbors who often visit them-
                    indeed<lb/> the seed sown has in many Instances pro<lb/>duced comfortable Fruit.
                    May they be<lb/> presented is my sincere Petition!<lb/> As for us, we are here
                    treated as Prices &amp;<lb/> free on the Fat of the Land. Flesh<lb/> from the
                    Field, &amp; Fish from the Lucid<lb/> Stream;- Butter of Kine, excellent,
                    in<lb/>deed, &amp; vegetables first rate in quality;-<lb/> are prepared by the
                    Representa <lb/><pb n="37"/>tives of Neatness &amp; Good Humour, inviting to the
                    Eye,<lb/> and pleasant to the Taste, -- beside other<lb/> nice sauce, we are
                    favourd with Good ap<lb/>petites as the Diminished Luxuries on the plenteous
                    Board often<lb/> spread, daily bears Witness, Thus are<lb/> we favourd Day by
                    Day from the bounte<lb/>ous Giver of every Good, - to whom with<lb/> propriety,
                    the Aspiration may arise,<lb/>
                    <quote type="bible">What shall we render for all Thy Bene<lb/>fits?</quote>
                </p>
                <p><persName key="cornp2">Corn Planters</persName> Town Calld <placeName key="cornp"
                        >Genuch sha' ta go'</placeName> (or the<lb/> Burnt House) has about 4
                    families who live<lb/> in it &amp; is about 13 Miles from <placeName key="colds"
                        >Cold Spring</placeName>, down<lb/> the River- Genes'ing guh'ta (on amongst
                    the<lb/> Hills) has 3 or 4 families &amp; is 3 Miles from<lb/>
                    <placeName key="colds">Cold Spring</placeName>- all on the West side of the
                        <placeName key="alleg">Alle<lb/>gany</placeName> &amp; on its Banks- from
                        <placeName key="colds">Cold Spring</placeName> to<lb/>
                    <placeName key="pitts">Pittsburg</placeName> by Water is Calld 210 Miles, &amp;
                    by<lb/> sand 150.- The <placeName key="alleg">Allegany River</placeName> is a
                    beau<lb/>tiful stream. There about 90 or 100 yeards<lb/> wide- is fordable when
                    the Waters are low.<lb/> and for about half the Summer season na<lb/>vigable for
                    Boats of 8 to 12 Tons. <placeName key="french">French<lb/> Creek</placeName>
                    puts into the <placeName key="alleg">Allegany</placeName> about 90 miles<lb/>
                    from here &amp; <placeName key="conew">Conowongo</placeName> about 30
                    Miles-<lb/> are both navigable Waters- the 1st<lb/> has 14 Miles sand can get to
                        <placeName key="lakee">Lake Erie</placeName> &amp; the<lb/> other 8 Miles
                    &amp; head in Chintankquasake</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1809-09-24">24th &amp; 1st of the Week, </date><placeName
                        key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p>No Message being re<lb/>cieved from the Indians, Joel set off this Morning
                        <lb/><pb n="38"/>toward the Town to know whether Council was<lb/> to be held
                    to Day, bu on his Way was met<lb/> by J.P. one of the Indian Chiefs who was
                    com<lb/>ing to inform us that it was deferrd till to<lb/>morrow we were
                    therefore at liberty to stay<lb/> at home &amp; sat with the Family in then
                    usu<lb/>al ways. After Dinner a Couple of Indian<lb/> Girls (one of them
                        <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanters</persName> Daughter) came to learn<lb/>
                    respecting the propriety of continuing the Prac<lb/>tice of Grinding for them
                    instructing<lb/> in the various arts of Housewifery on this Day<lb/> of the
                    Week- me own opinion is that it is time to<lb/> shew a discountenance as
                    preparatory to a total<lb/> discontinuance others of the Committee do not<lb/>
                    appear to be like minded supposing the Indians<lb/> to be not yet ripe on
                    account of their prejudices &amp;<lb/> want of Knowledge of Days- some of the
                    Friends<lb/> stationed here have for some time been uneasy.<lb/> &amp; other
                    think the indulging Indians in this re<lb/>spect is unavoidable. I hope
                    eventually all<lb/> will work right. Yesterday the Committee with<lb/> Friends
                    of This Family agreed upon a address to<lb/> the Indians being previously drawn
                    up by TS<lb/> since being here- in substance being- </p>
                <floatingText type="letter">
                    <body>
                        <p>I wish<lb/> to remind them of Frnd continued care toward<lb/> and regard
                            for them. their starting that we had<lb/> from <unclear>vicios</unclear>
                            their Farms &amp; raised improvements<lb/> &amp; had felt desires for
                            their farther advancement<lb/> in every good Work. next that if they men
                            would<lb/> do more Work on their Farms &amp; would en<lb/>courage their
                            Wives &amp; Daughters in learning<lb/> to spin, Weave &amp;c. Our belief
                            was that they<lb/> would devise great advantage from it- </p>
                        <pb n="39"/>
                        <p>That <persName key="jthom2">Jon Thomas</persName> was willing to weave
                            for<lb/> them, free of Cost for one year, provided<lb/> 2 or 3 of their
                            women, in that time, would<lb/> learn to Weave, but if they neglected
                            this<lb/> The benefit designd by his thus instruc<lb/>ting them would
                            not fully answer our<lb/> wishes- Their custom of Husbands<lb/> &amp;
                            Wives separating was next love to<lb/> upon &amp; our sense thereon
                            conveyed that<lb/> such a practice was displeasing to the<lb/> Great
                            Spirit- &amp; often left their Chi<lb/>lden in Poverty &amp; Distress
                            -</p>
                        <p> We also expressd a Desire that they<lb/> would think very seriously
                            indeed be<lb/>fore they condemnd &amp; Killd any for<lb/> supposing them
                            guilty of Witchcraft<lb/> reminding them that about 100 years<lb/> since
                            such a practice prevaild in one<lb/> neighbourhood among White People
                            &amp;<lb/> before put a stop to, some of those who<lb/> had been judges
                            of others, were them<lb/>selves changed with the same often<lb/> is
                            &amp; executed. On these two sub<lb/>jects desiring their Careful
                            Considera<lb/>tion but not wishing a reply at this<lb/> Time </p>
                        <p><pb n="40"/>that they would avail themselves of<lb/> every advantage to
                            be derived from<lb/> our Friends living among them while<lb/> they
                            continued here -</p>
                        <p>That they had seen the bad ef<lb/>fects of playing cards &amp; other
                            games<lb/> &amp; that altho' these was an Impress<lb/>ment these was yet
                            room for more,<lb/> &amp; if their principal Chiefs &amp; wise<lb/> men
                            would discourage the Practice<lb/> we thought a we would arise to
                            <lb/>their Young People -</p>
                        <p>That our friends had lived with<lb/> their many years in Harmony
                            &amp;<lb/> Friendship - if any part of our<lb/> conduct towards them had
                            not<lb/> been quite to their wishes we<lb/> desired they would speak
                            their<lb/> minds freely &amp; let us know -</p>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline><date when="1809-09-25">Dated 9 mo 25th 1809</date> &amp;
                                Signd<lb/> by <persName key="alea1">A Lea</persName>, <persName
                                    key="jbrow1">Jno Brown</persName>, <persName key="tstan1">T
                                    Stew</persName> &amp; WA</dateline></closer>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1809-09-25">25th</date><placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>

                <p>After Breakfast set out to attend the Council<lb/> of <placeName key="colds">Cold
                        Spring</placeName> - I stopd in at several Houses on our<lb/> way to the
                    Town to Shake hands with the Indians<lb/> then went to the Council House with is
                    a Building<lb/> nearby the Centre of the Town about 40 feet in<lb/> length &amp;
                    20 in breadth. having a Door at each End <lb/><pb n="41"/> and two Holes in the
                    Peak of the Roof to admit the<lb/> ascending of the Smoke from Council Fires -
                    which<lb/> are built on the Ground about 12 feet from<lb/> each Door.- These
                    fires are daily used by the In<lb/>habitants for cooking on other purposes,
                    being<lb/> a kind of public Priveledge the Open Doors<lb/> admitting ready
                    Impress &amp; Egress to them at plea<lb/>sure- the floor is laid by nature and
                    on each<lb/> side from one End to the other is a platform laid co<lb/>verd with
                    Board, Skins &amp;c. about 6 feet in width<lb/> &amp; 10 Inches in heighth- over
                    these all the<lb/> heighth of 5 feet under other Platforms which<lb/> serve to
                    throw up skins Corn or any Lumbering<lb/> articles &amp; to the Rafters was
                    suspended a quantity<lb/> of old Corn some of it near the Openings in the<lb/>
                    Roof being as black as smoke Could make<lb/> it - this they dont mind but use it
                    for making<lb/> Bread &amp; other purposes perhaps preferring it<lb/> as I
                    observed in their Houses generally the Corn<lb/> was stored by suspending it
                    with the Husk<lb/> this way - as The Indians were not generally<lb/> collected
                    it afforded opportunity to make some<lb/> observations. <placeName key="conud1"
                        >Conudius</placeName> House stand the nearest<lb/> to the Council House
                    &amp; within a few Yards- Our at<lb/>tention was here averted by the sound of
                    mu<lb/>sic &amp; Dancing &amp; feeling some inclination to be<lb/> witnesses we
                    were informed that it would give<lb/> no offence &amp; so went inside of the
                    Door - In the<lb/> Middle of the Room lay the Hommany Block<lb/> &amp; an Old
                    Bench apparently designd to prevent an<lb/> encroachment on that part of the
                    floor &amp; to<lb/> preserve regularity of Circuit sound them <lb/>those rude
                    Regulators were encompassd by<lb/> 18 <lb/>&amp; 20 Females (occasionally more)
                    some Elder <lb/>
                    <pb n="42"/> Elderly Women &amp; down to Girls about 10 years<lb/> of age- these
                    forming a Circle were Dancing (or<lb/> shuffling) round sideways with a slow
                    &amp; solemn<lb/> motion, &amp; Heads uniformly reclining to the<lb/> sound of
                    Musick performd by a Man in one<lb/> corner of the Room. this was done by
                    beating<lb/> slowly on a Drum made by a Dried Deer or<lb/> some other Kind of
                    Skin dressd a little in the<lb/> manner of Parchment &amp; tightly strechd
                    over<lb/> the Top of a Churn. or sometimes we were<lb/> told an Iron Pot- they
                    said he bent with<lb/> two sticks &amp; the sound of one of them put me<lb/> in
                    mind of tinkling symbols, being, either hol<lb/>low &amp; enclosing something of
                    the trikling kind<lb/> or else havg some small bells attachd to<lb/> it. but it
                    was so dark where he sat that I<lb/> could not see- this sound he
                    accompa<lb/>nied with a vocal Time or perhaps a song,<lb/> but if the latter his
                    articulation was very<lb/> indistinct - it however appeard to be in<lb/> stanza
                    at the end of which the female<lb/> circle would cease their Dancing &amp;
                    walk<lb/> round with a quicker motion &amp; some ap<lb/>pearance of Hilarity
                    till after a circle or<lb/> two, another Stanza began. this Dance &amp;
                    music<lb/> continued for abt 2 Hours after we were there<lb/> &amp; the Dancers
                    would step out occasionally drip<lb/>ping with Perspiration (apparently to cool
                    &amp; get<lb/>air) &amp; then return again- they were much in<lb/> then usual
                    Dress except the Children several<lb/> of whom lookd clean &amp; Dressed for the
                    occasion<lb/> one in white Cloth- another Green a third<lb/> Blue &amp;c.- and
                    there had each a bunch of <lb/>
                    <pb n="43"/> small Bells hung to the Knee &amp; made a noise<lb/> as they Danced
                    not much unlike the singing of Secrets- a few<lb/> of them were a little touchd
                    with Paint- when<lb/> the Dance was over they had a Feast being a<lb/> kind of
                    soup or <unclear>sand-compon</unclear> we were told of<lb/> new corn shelld from
                    the Cob- a little meat, su<lb/>gar &amp;c. &amp; was boild in the Council House
                    in a<lb/> large Kettle. this being carried into <persName key="conud1"
                        >Coundius</persName><lb/> one of each family engagd in the Dance &amp; who
                    had pre<lb/>viously (we were told) contributed, refraind<lb/> with their small
                    kettles or Wooden Bowls to<lb/> receive their shares-. After waiting for
                    some<lb/> Time an Antient Indian blew a Trumpet to no<lb/>tify the Inhabitants
                    of Council &amp; they began to<lb/> assemble- They were dressd of ornamented
                    various<lb/>ly many were painted with red streaks about<lb/> the face Head &amp;
                    Eyes as fancy inclined- some<lb/> had Bandages of Indian Workmanship round<lb/>
                    their Heads &amp; tufts of Feathers of different co<lb/>lumns. Sometimes Furs.
                    The Hair of some<lb/> was shorn round the Crown &amp; left long round<lb/> the
                    Temples &amp; on the Top of the Head- others<lb/> had it left long in little
                    Tufts over the Head<lb/> &amp; those Tufts plaited - many had Breast<lb/> plates
                    of Different fancies- others back Or<lb/>naments &amp; Ear Bobbs all of
                    silver-<lb/> One had one Red Legging &amp; the other Blue- some<lb/> Caps of Fur
                    with Tufts of Dyed Freathers<lb/> or Caps of Feathers &amp; <gap/> &amp; Tips of
                    Fur<lb/> other tails of long Hair like Horse Hair Dyed<lb/> Red hanging down
                    their Backs or erected<lb/> or suspended from their Ears- <persName key="conud1"
                        >Old Conidin</persName>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="44"/> has a blaze of vermillion from the Corner<lb/> of each Eye- his
                    Ears were cut round in<lb/> their manner &amp; extended to a considerable<lb/>
                    length on each Ear were two silver<lb/> Quills- one about 3 1/2 &amp; the other
                    2 Inches<lb/> the erect one having a Tuft of Red Feathers<lb/> stuck in at the
                    lower End- part of his<lb/> Forehead &amp; on his Crown were also painted
                    red<lb/> &amp; being nearly bald &amp; a very grave countenance<lb/> he lookd
                    venerable- On his arms were wider<lb/> silver Bracelets- his Leggings were of
                    Red Cloth<lb/> &amp; his Covering a Blanket over all which he<lb/> threw off in
                    Council &amp; look up his long Pipe-<lb/> They had a very great variety of other
                    orna<lb/>ments &amp; trinkets such as Nose Bobs &amp; Plates re<lb/>sembling
                    Furniture for Drawers- silver band<lb/> round their Arms wrists or Ankles
                    &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp; yet in<lb/> a general way very Dirty &amp; careless in
                    their<lb/> Persons- One of the Chiefs was Dressd in a<lb/> Wood Rangeres Frock
                    &amp; many of them had<lb/> no ornaments- <persName key="jpier2">John
                        Peirce</persName> (who is a Chief)<lb/> was the only one among them who
                    thought<lb/> it worth while to appear on this occasion<lb/> in a Full Dress- He
                    is Tall &amp; a good Per<lb/>son- Had a new White Hat on with a high<lb/> crown
                    which was coverd from the Brim to<lb/> the top with a bandage of Green
                    Flowred<lb/> silk- in front were two bunches or Knots of<lb/> Green Ribbons
                    displayd with taste one above<lb/> the other &amp; on one side of them a Tuft of
                    <lb/>Dyed Feathers of Different Colours- He wore<lb/> a new Coat of a neatly
                    figured green Calico <lb/>
                    <pb n="45"/> made a little in the manner of a Frock &amp;<lb/> the Boson Raffled
                    with the same. his Leg<lb/> coverings or Pantaloons were in the Indian<lb/>
                    manner with a seam sewed out leaving a ship<lb/> of about am Inch &amp; Quarter.
                    this strip or Edging<lb/> on each Leg was faced with blue Silk, neatly<lb/>
                    wrought with needlework of Blue ornamen<lb/>ted with Red twines or Curls- and
                    edged with<lb/> Beads in the Indian Stile- Instead of a Blanket<lb/> his Outer
                    Covering was about a yard &amp; half of<lb/> super fine White Cloth which in
                    Council<lb/> he threw off from his Shoulders at pleasure.<lb/>
                    <persName key="ylatt1">young Fatty</persName>. another Chief was pretty Dirty -
                    the<lb/> Hair was shorn on the sides of his Head but from<lb/> the crown down
                    the neck was left to grow in<lb/> the antie quite long &amp; was pleated down
                    his<lb/> Back in a large Plait- on each side of this the<lb/> Hear was left
                    about 4 Inches long &amp; being soft<lb/> course &amp; glossy resembled a ship
                    of black<lb/> Feathers- The Council having at length taken<lb/> their seats we
                    were introduced &amp; seated near<lb/> the centre- The Chiefs present were
                        <persName key="cornp2">Cornplan<lb/>ter</persName>- <persName key="gblac1"
                        >Tekiando</persName> (his Nephew) <persName key="jsilv1">Johnson Silver<lb/>
                        heels</persName>- <persName key="jpier2">John Peirce</persName>, Tusenda
                    quit (or <persName key="ylatt1">young<lb/> fatty)</persName>or Tockewassee (or
                    go to War) <persName key="jsnow1">Jacob Snow</persName>
                    <lb/> &amp; Old <persName key="conud1">Conudin</persName>- several of them are
                    hand<lb/>some Men- <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> has an
                    Expressive<lb/> countenance &amp; penetrating Eyes, but owing to some<lb/> cause
                    either habit or Injury, he keeps one of<lb/> them about half shut - after a
                    little Time of<lb/> silvence &amp; then a Conference between the Chiefs
                        <persName key="conud1">Conudiu</persName><lb/> opend the Business for which
                    we had met &amp; that<lb/> they were now ready to hear;- Our communications <lb/>
                    <pb n="46"/> were then read &amp; interpretted to them, &amp; after<lb/> a
                    little further conference among themselves<lb/>
                    <persName key="cornp2">cornplanter</persName> made a Reply first to us &amp;
                    then<lb/> an address to the Indians in a methodical &amp;<lb/> sensible manner-
                    when our Business was<lb/> got this base their farewell &amp; returnd home.</p>

            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1809-09-26">26th</date><placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>26th Left the settlement of our Friends at<lb/>
                    <placeName key="tunes">Tunasassa</placeName> about 10 oClock <persName
                        key="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName><lb/> accompanying us- J B Moses &amp;
                    myself keeps<lb/> with [hemion?] the West side of the <placeName key="alleg"
                        >Allegany</placeName> in<lb/> order to go by the Indians Saw Mill which<lb/>
                    in about 10 miles from their Town- On our<lb/> way passd several Indian
                    Plantations as good<lb/> we thought as any we had seen, particularly<lb/> an
                    Indian named Kah'Shun'Lee' on the<lb/> Fiery flying Dragon- his Wife was
                    Dressd<lb/> in a Silk Short Gown wearing a large silver<lb/> cross at her
                    Breast- these the Indians have<lb/> got from the Roman Catholics originally<lb/>
                    but are now worn only by way or ornament<lb/> Kah shun dee was hawlg oats of
                    which<lb/> we saw a considerable Crop standing in the<lb/> build in a neat
                    shock. He had a large Barn<lb/> (which <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob</persName>
                    told us was maid with his own<lb/> Hands). &amp; in it is considerable
                    quantity<lb/> of Old Corn &amp; Grain of Different Kinds a<lb/> part of which we
                    saw- on passing pay- he<lb/> is Industrious &amp; Wealthy- not fond of<lb/>
                    attending their feasts &amp; Councils and de<lb/>clines the appointment of a
                    Chief-<lb/> our course after leaving Peter Snyders was <lb/>
                    <pb n="47"/> nearly N West. here we bid adieu to the <placeName key="alleg"
                        >Al<lb/>legany</placeName> &amp; passg this a Rich Country, reachd<lb/>
                    Stephen Hazeltines before 4 oClock calld<lb/> 20 miles from <placeName
                        key="tunes">Tunasassa</placeName>, Road Rough &amp; mud</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1809-09-27">27th</date><placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p> 27th our Bed, last night not being calculated<lb/> to Induce a morning
                    Indulgence we rose before<lb/> Day eat our Breakfasts &amp; set off before
                    it<lb/> was light- in a little way Riding fell into<lb/> the Indian Path which
                    we pursued upwd<lb/> of 20 miles &amp; take it all together perhaps<lb/> the
                    worst Road we have passd over any Day<lb/> before- Moses concluded that after
                    this he<lb/> should not be afraid of any sort of Road<lb/> &amp; I thought while
                    riding on a long sideling Hill<lb/> which really seemd Dangerous I should be
                    wis<lb/>hing our Friends at home should have a peep<lb/> at us, could they have
                    also had an assurance<lb/> that we should get thro this safely, as was the
                    care<lb/> not by our own might or management but<lb/> under the protecting care
                    of the Omnipotent<lb/> Arm for which may our acknowledgements<lb/> were as
                    acceptable Incence to Him.<lb/> -- part of our Way was up the <placeName
                        key="lvall">little Valley</placeName>-<lb/> then across the <placeName
                        key="broam">Broad Mountain</placeName> 5 miles<lb/> over &amp; next the Hog
                    back Mountain 6<lb/> miles over- on this for miles our path lay<lb/> on the
                    Crown of the Hill &amp; the descent<lb/> immediately &amp; in some places steep,
                    on<lb/> either hand- We also several times forded<lb/>
                    <placeName key="catta2">Cattarangus Creek</placeName> in its Different
                    branches<lb/> &amp; then the main Creek- The soil rode even<lb/> to Day has been
                    generally good &amp; the Timber <lb/>
                    <pb n="48"/> fine even on the Mountains- here we saw<lb/> Chestnut Trees which
                    we supposed 6 &amp; of feet<lb/> over (perhaps more)- also Poplars,
                    Hemlock,<lb/> Sugar Maples, Ash, Cucumber Trees, Beech &amp;c.<lb/> very large-
                    near the main Catt. Creek lay a<lb/> body of sand much coverd with Black
                    Walnut<lb/> &amp; as rich as Bank Meadow- about the mid<lb/>dle of our Journey
                    we fed our Horses &amp; eat a<lb/> biscuit at a place of Indian Encampment
                    &amp;<lb/> before this had passd as Grave enclosd in<lb/> the Indian manner
                    where <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob</persName> told us<lb/> a man was buried who
                    perished in the<lb/> Woods about 4 years ago on his way from<lb/>
                    <placeName key="buffa">Buffaloe</placeName> to <placeName key="colds">Cold
                        Spring</placeName>- his Horse first Died<lb/> &amp; himself about 8 miles
                    further- was warnd<lb/> before setg out of the Danger of Perishing<lb/> but said
                    he was so much like Iron <lb/>there was no Danger- We also met<lb/> an Indian on
                    Horseback from <placeName key="grand">Grand Ri<lb/>ver</placeName> going to see
                    the <orgName key="allegany">Allegany Indians</orgName>, to<lb/> some of whom he
                    was related- <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob</persName><lb/> talkd with him,
                    informg our Bu<lb/>siness &amp;c. - He replied in substance<lb/> that he was
                    pleasd with meeting us- &amp; with <lb/>the Business we were engagd in, and
                    wish<lb/>ing us preservation &amp; safety on our <lb/>
                    <pb n="49"/> Journey bade us favourable- a few miles<lb/> further we met another
                    man on Horseback<lb/> named <persName key="polla1">Pollard</persName>) from
                        <placeName key="buffa">Buffaloe</placeName>. he had a<lb/> small Child
                    before him &amp; his Wife (we sup<lb/>posed) on another Horse behind. she
                    was<lb/> well dressd &amp; her neck ornamented with sil<lb/>ver Broaches so as
                    to give it the appearance<lb/> at a little Distance of a richly silverd
                    Shawl<lb/> It had not felt quite pleasant to me<lb/> that we made no return to
                    the Saluta<lb/>tion &amp; friendly wish of the first Indian<lb/> &amp; this one
                    also Greeting us in a sim<lb/>ilar way. I desired <persName key="jtayl1"
                        >Jacob</persName> to tell him that<lb/> we were pleasd with meeting him on
                    his<lb/> Way to visit his Friends at <placeName key="alleg">Allegany</placeName>
                    and<lb/> brighten the Chain of Friendship- if<lb/> he could also encourage them
                    in useful<lb/> Industry it would be a good Work- he<lb/> recieved it Cordially
                    &amp; we passd on- <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob</persName><lb/> told us he was
                    an Industrious Man &amp; one<lb/> of the greatest Farmers among the Indians<lb/>
                    in that Country. before 4 oclock reachd<lb/> the settlements of our Friends at
                        <placeName key="clearc">Clear Creek </placeName><lb/> calld 25 Miles from
                    Hazeltines &amp; after takg<lb/> some Refreshment spent the Eveng in viewg<lb/>
                    the Farm &amp; Improvements</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1809-09-28">28th</date><placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>went to see the Indians Improvements. <unclear>our</unclear><lb/> way, except
                    about a Quarter of a mile being <lb/>
                    <pb n="50"/> 50 on their Reservation which is very Rich Land<lb/> &amp; well
                    Timberd but (as if it were designd for<lb/> Indians who have not yet learnd to
                    labour there<lb/> are many hundred Acres of Flats without a Tree,<lb/> being
                    coverd with Fern, Wild Grass, Strawbery<lb/> vines (which in their season
                    [been?] abundantly) and<lb/> rich herbage in some place as high as our
                    heads<lb/> on Horseback- the soil is black when wet &amp;<lb/> new when Dry
                    resembling Ashes- the Timber ad<lb/>joining &amp; bordering on it White &amp;
                    blk oak- black<lb/> Walnut, Sugar Maple &amp;c. - on the open Plains<lb/> were
                    many Houses feeding, belonging to the Indians<lb/> in about 5 miles riding we
                    came to the Village<lb/> of the <orgName key="munseeind">Muncy
                    Indians</orgName>, who are a part of the<lb/>
                    <orgName key="delaware">Delaware Tribe</orgName> &amp; about 152 in number<lb/>
                    the <placeName key="catta1">Cataraagas</placeName> settlement of Senecas is
                    about<lb/> one mile further &amp; they are about 250 Persons<lb/> We stopd at
                    the House of the Chief Warrior<lb/> named Wyundegohta whose store House we<lb/>
                    found pretty well supplied with wheat, oats,<lb/>old corn&amp;some of his
                    Warrior employed in shilg<lb/> new corn which they had previously parched-<lb/>
                    this is to be dried in the sun &amp; as wanted for<lb/> use, to be pounded &amp;
                    mixed with sugar, and is<lb/> an excellent nutritious &amp; portable food for
                    tra<lb/>velling- We here saw many Ornaments in<lb/> their Way. One Head Dress
                    made with long Fea<lb/>thers wrapd on the sides of the Head with white<lb/> skin
                    of some animal ornamented with the<lb/> skin of a Drakes Head in spots. the
                    Feather<lb/> part stuck out behind being highly coloured,<lb/> &amp; over the
                    Forehead was the Head &amp; beak of<lb/> a Bird (perhaps a Raven) on each side
                    of<lb/> which from the Eye was a Tuft of long Crim<lb/>
                    <pb n="51"/> son coloured Feathers. At the side of the Room<lb/> being a string
                    of Half Moons of 4 in Number, all of Sil<lb/>ver, the largest (wh they said cost
                    6 Dollars) being on the<lb/> Top &amp; so regularly becoming [On after?] as they
                    went to<lb/> the bottom- on each was an ingraving of some bird<lb/> or animal-
                    One pt of Musical Leg Ornaments com<lb/>posd of Dyed Feathers &amp; worn in
                    these Dances- a pair<lb/> of Mockasins richly wrought with Porcupine Quills<lb/>
                    &amp; tipd with a very great number of silver Quills<lb/> many other things rich
                    in their way- The Sand<lb/> on which these two villages stand, perhaps 15<lb/>
                    or 20 Acres in each is beautifully coverd<lb/> with white Clover, Green Grass
                    &amp;c. &amp; if it<lb/> were inclosed &amp; Kept up for Mowing we thought<lb/>
                    would cut the first crop near two Tons per<lb/> acre. After stageing here a
                    while &amp; leaving it<lb/> with them to fix a time when to receive us<lb/> in
                    Council we rode about two miles further<lb/> down the <placeName key="catta2"
                        >Cataraugus Creek</placeName> to see the Indians <lb/>corn &amp; oats
                    &amp;c. the Crops are not very good<lb/> owing to several causes the principal
                    are<lb/> poor cultivation, yet the Sand is superlatively<lb/> good- those
                    Flatts, containing many Thou<lb/>sand Acres contain in their Bowels strong<lb/>
                    months of being made Ground- as we rode<lb/> along the <placeName key="catta2"
                        >Creek</placeName> on the opposite side an Island<lb/> is now forming, while
                    the bank on which we were<lb/> is washing away &amp; as the Depth of 10 or 12
                    feet<lb/> the Logs are sticking out of the Bank into the Creek<lb/> bearing the
                    marks of having been there buried<lb/> for a long series of years- On returning
                    to the <lb/><pb n="52"/> village we rode about half a mile &amp; forded the<lb/>
                    <placeName key="catta2">Catarinugus Creek</placeName> to the Indians saw mill -
                    here we<lb/> rode out of the main creek into the Bed of the<lb/> small creek
                    which the mill is built on - the<lb/> bottom of which is a slate rock -on about
                    80 or<lb/> 100 yards we came to the spring mentd the 18th Ult<lb/> an indian had
                    a accompanied us with a fire brand<lb/> on the application of whichto the
                    Effluvium<lb/> arising it immediately burnt into a Blasett<lb/> burned with
                    considerable heat as long as we in<lb/>clined to view it &amp; would have
                    continued to burn<lb/> as we were told till extinguished by a sudden<lb/> Dash
                    of water or blow of wind - I dashed afraid<lb/> of it out with water pour the
                    creek but al<lb/>most as soon as I had done the air caught again<lb/>
                    <gap/> then took his hat &amp; blew it quite out.</p>
                <p>The Rock in this place is cracked across in<lb/> several directions &amp; the
                    Babbling appears in <lb/>the centre, where is the largest opening, at<lb/> this
                    place is first caught but soon exten<lb/>ded itself for several feet along<lb/>
                    the other cracks the flame emitting a<lb/> sulpherous Effluvia, mixed with
                    some<lb/> other smell- the Water in the Creek was<lb/> now very low, but
                        <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob</persName> told us that when the<lb/> Spring
                    was coverd with the Creek as it often<lb/> was it produced a much larger
                    Flame<lb/> than we saw- At a small Distances<lb/> from this Spring <persName
                        key="jtayl1">Jacob</persName> told us there was<lb/> an Antient
                    Fortification containing <lb/>about </p>
            </div>
        </body>


    </text>
</TEI>
