<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei-print.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="global.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>William Allinson Diary, Volume 3: Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Haverford College Quaker Collection</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>FHL staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Journal transcribed by</resp>
                    <name>Crowd-sourced</name>


                </respStmt>

            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 63 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Haverford College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street/>
                    <addrLine>Haverford, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode/>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>This work is the property of Haverford College Special COlleciotn. It may be
                        copied freely by individuals for personal use, research, and teaching
                        (including distribution to classes) as long as this statement of
                        availability is included in the text. It may be linked to freely in Internet
                        editions of all kinds, including for—profit works.</p>
                    <p>Publishers, libraries, and other information providers interested in
                        providing this text in a commercial or non—profit product or from an
                        information server must contact Haverford College for licensing and cost
                        information.</p>
                    <p> Scholars interested in changing or adding to these texts by, for example,
                        creating a new edition of the text (electronically or in print) with
                        substantive editorial changes, may do so only with the permission of
                        Haverford College. This is the case whether the new publication will be made
                        available at a cost or free of charge.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2015">2015</date>
                <idno type="local">HV_WA_1809_v3</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Native Americans and Quakers: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Haverford College Quaker &amp; Special Collections</institution>
                        <collection>Allinson family papers</collection>
                        <idno>Call number: MC 968, Box 11, Folder 4</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>34 pp. (1 volume)</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The William Allinson Diary manuscript is housed in the Quaker &amp; Special
                    Collections, Haverford College</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> The transcribers and editor attempted to render the author’s orthography and
                    grammar as they appear on the page of his journal, even when the author’s own
                    spelling and usage are inconsistent. Additionally, many questions remain about
                    spelling the names of his Quaker acquaintances, individual Native Americans who
                    populate his journal, and Indian villages and towns. The transcribers and editor
                    attempted to remain faithful to the author’s Anglicized spellings in all cases. </p>
                <p>The author of the original journal does not include page numbers on his
                    manuscript; the page numbers have been interpolated by the transcribers to
                    correspond with the manuscript sheets.</p>
            </editorialDecl>

        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written in <date when="1809">1809</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Society of Friends</item>


                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>

        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item>
                    <date when="2016"/></item>

            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="entry">

                <pb n="1"/>
                <dateline><date when="1809-09-28"/><placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>about 3 Quarters of an Acre being encompassd by <unclear>which</unclear><lb/>
                    entrenchment apparently intended for Pikes and having a <lb/> level Gateway on
                    the back side. It occupies a consider<lb/>able Entrance or open up the
                    mountains, laying behind which<lb/> puts down to the main creek, and is now
                    overgrown w/<lb/> heavy Timber of at least an Hundred Years growth.<lb/> On our
                    way to the saw mill we passd thro' some very good<lb/> corn, where the large
                    Walnut Trees, killd by Girdling, are<lb/> standing. As we returnd home stopd at
                    the Village of the<lb/>
                    <orgName key="munseeind">Muncy Indians</orgName> &amp; talkd with several,
                    particularly the Chief<lb/> Warrior who was informed that we intended a Council
                    to<lb/>morrow with the <orgName key="seneca">Cattaraugus Indians</orgName> &amp;
                    if they had any<lb/> thing to communicate to us, they might do it as we
                    passd<lb/> thro' their settlement. when we got into the Woods on<lb/> the Indian
                    Reservation, curiosity induced us to measure<lb/> of the Walnut Trees there
                    growing. One of them appeared by<lb/> our Measurement to be 15 Feet 8 Inches in
                    Circumference<lb/> another 16 ft 2 Inches &amp; a third 16 ft 5 Inches. at 2 ft
                    6 In<lb/> from the level of the Ground. They were also very straight<lb/> &amp;
                    tall, we unitedly concluded 60 feet without a [?]<lb/> &amp; held their
                    thickness remarkably well. there is little<lb/> Doubt but we could have found
                    larger had we gone to<lb/> hunt them but these all stood close by our Road.
                    On<lb/> getting to the House we also measured several<lb/> Poplar stumps all
                    within about 60 yards of it--on<lb/> being 5 Feet 4 1/2 Inches in Diameter at
                    the heighth of<lb/> 4 ft 4 Inches over, at the same heighth <lb/>4 Feet, 4 &amp;
                    5 Inches over, at near the same heighth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1809-09-29">9 mo. 29th</date><placeName key="catta1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> Met the Indians in Council at the <placeName key="catta1"
                    >Cataraugus</placeName><lb/> Village, about 30 being present. It was Announced
                    <gap/><lb/> at <placeName key="colds">Cold Spring</placeName> by the Blowing of
                    a Trumpet &amp; when they <lb/><pb n="2"/>were Convened a Messenger was sent to
                    inform us that<lb/> they were ready, &amp; we accordingly went, <persName
                        key="egran1">Erasmus<lb/> Granger</persName>, the Agent of the United States
                    for the <orgName key="sxntns">Six<lb/> Nations</orgName> of Indians bearing us
                    Company--he had<lb/> unexpectedly met us here being on a Visit to the<lb/>
                    several settlements of Indians for the purpose of<lb/> enquiring into their
                    Improvements &amp; wants, so as to be<lb/> enabled to make Report of their
                    situation to the Pre<lb/>sident of the U.S. He is a sensible, well informed<lb/>
                    &amp; discreet Man, his Person tall &amp; handsome &amp; Eye<lb/> penetrating
                    but his Countenance wearing the marks<lb/> of Care &amp; poor Health.</p>
                <p> About noon the Council opend &amp; after sitting a while<lb/> in respectful
                    silence, a Conversation, in a low voice<lb/> took place among the Chiefs--when
                    the Business was<lb/> introduced to the following import by of them named
                        <persName key="thomp1">Thomson</persName></p>
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body>
                        <dateline><date when="1809-09-29"/><placeName key="catta1"/></dateline>
                        <p>Brothers We heard you were coming to see us. we are<lb/> happy you have
                            now arrivd, and thank the Great<lb/> Spirit that He has preserved you
                            thro' a Long Journey<lb/> Brothers--We think it is Consistent with His
                            Will<lb/> that we should be favoured all to meet here this day<lb/> in
                            Council. We are also pleased that <persName key="egran1">Mr.
                                Granger</persName><lb/> the Agent of the US for the <orgName
                                key="sxntns">Six Nations</orgName> is present<lb/> with us, and we
                            are now ready to hear what you<lb/> have to say.</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>Our Addresses being being read &amp; interpretted to them<lb/> by Henry York were
                    well rec'd. The Indians again<lb/> sat for a few minutes entirely silent
                    smokeing their<lb/> Pipes, which was succeeded by a Whisper among the <lb/><pb
                        n="3"/> Chiefs <del>for some minutes</del> when the same speaker<lb/>
                    (sitting) addressd the Agent, inform'g that they understood<lb/> he was going to
                        <placeName key="alleg1">Allegany</placeName> &amp; were desirous to know his
                    par<lb/>ticular business. <persName key="egran1">Granger</persName> informd him
                    that he would<lb/> do it when they had answerd our Communication.<lb/> Another
                    silence &amp; whisper ensued. The Chief<lb/> Warrior <persName key="wyund1"
                        >Wyundegohta</persName> then rose &amp; holding our<lb/> Addresses in his
                    Hand folded as delivered to him, some<lb/> times looking on them attentively
                    &amp; then casting his<lb/> Eyes round over us &amp; the Council, replied nearly
                    as<lb/> follows </p>
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body>
                        <dateline><date when="1809-09-29"/><placeName key="catta1"/></dateline>
                        <p>Brothers attend. We have heard the<lb/> speech of our Friends at Phila.
                            by which we un<lb/>derstand that you still continue to speak the<lb/>
                            same Language to our Nation &amp; we believe your<lb/> views towards us
                            are the effect of Pure Friendship<lb/> &amp; a desire for our
                            Welfare--and altho' we have<lb/> fallen short of your former advices we
                            are<lb/> still encouraged to follow your Council &amp; pursue<lb/> the
                            Path you have set before us. You remain<lb/> anxious we should improve
                            in Habits of Industry<lb/> by which we might render our Lives more
                            com<lb/>fortable. Brothers we hope you will continue to have<lb/>
                            Patience towards us, as Indians cannot adopt<lb/> all those Habits at
                            once but we are fully Con<lb/>vinced that Industry in Cultivating our
                            Lands is<lb/> the only method by which we can receive lasting<lb/>
                            Benefits, and we are determined to pursue it <lb/><pb n="4"/> and hope
                            we will still continue to make<lb/> a gradual Advancement.<lb/> Brothers
                            We understand you wish us to be bene<lb/>fitted by the Example of our
                            Friends who are setled<lb/> beside us, and wish our Firnds in
                            Philad.<lb/> to know we have rec'd considerable satisfac<lb/>tion &amp;
                            advantage from them. We all re<lb/>joice that they are setled so near,
                            and it<lb/> is our intention to treat them with Kindness<lb/> &amp;
                            consider them as our Friends.</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>The Day before the council we had prepared our<lb/> Address to them, touching on
                    various subjects<lb/> in which we thought it needful they should
                    im<lb/>prove--to which <persName key="wyund1">Wyundegohta</persName>
                    replied,</p>
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body>
                        <dateline><date when="1809-09-29"/><placeName key="catta1"/></dateline>
                        <p>Brothers, <lb/>you that are now here have<lb/> also told us that on
                            looking over our Corn<lb/>fields you find we have not made as much<lb/>
                            use of the Plow as you could wish. We<lb/> find that your Eye sight is
                            straight. We<lb/> acknowledge we have been deficient in<lb/> this
                            respect, &amp; the fault is our own.<lb/> Brothers--A long time ago we
                            requested<lb/> you to send us a sett of Mill Irons, you ac<lb/>cordingly
                            sent them as you promised--you <lb/><pb n="5"/>also sent us a sett of
                            Smiths Tools--you<lb/> have fulfilld all your Engagements with<lb/> us.
                            We have not received the advantage<lb/> from the saw mill we
                            expected--one rea<lb/>son is our People are Deficient in knowing<lb/>
                            how to work it--another Reason--the Water<lb/> is not sufficient to saw
                            more than one<lb/> Quarter of the Year. We have not re<lb/>ceived the
                            advantage from the Smith<lb/> Tools that we might have done, yet we<lb/>
                            have used them more than the Saw Mill-<lb/> Some of our people have
                            learned to do<lb/> a number of small matters, yet we<lb/> acknowledge we
                            have been too neg<lb/>lectful of both.<lb/> Brothers--You say if our
                            Minds were<lb/> more strong to Labour--it would give our<lb/> Women more
                            time to learn to spin.<lb/> We think this would be a great
                            ad<lb/>vantage to us, for if our Women would<lb/> learn to spin &amp;
                            make their own Cloth,<lb/> the Money which they now use to buy<lb/>
                            Cloathes would be saved for other <lb/><pb n="6"/>purposes. We think
                            this would make us<lb/> more Independent &amp; Happy, and when we<lb/>
                            are Dead our Children will have reason<lb/> to rejoice that we have
                            followed your<lb/> Instructions.<lb/> Brothers--The Reason we have not
                            made more<lb/> use of the Plow Irons you sent us is--we have<lb/> not
                            had a sufficient number of Oxen, but we<lb/> are thankful you have sent
                            them, as we<lb/> have now got a number of young oxen<lb/> growing up,
                            &amp; hope we shall be able<lb/> to use them more.<lb/> You observe we
                            have got a great many<lb/> Horses &amp; you think it will be better
                            to<lb/> have more Cattle &amp; Oxen. Your Remarks<lb/> on this subject
                            are just, we have found<lb/> inconvenience from so many Horses, for<lb/>
                            all the use they seem to be to us is to ride<lb/> about home, but when
                            we have occasion<lb/> to go amongst White People, we find them<lb/> only
                            a Bill of Expence.<lb/> Brothers--We are thankful for your<lb/> friendly
                            advice. Our Hearts rejoice <lb/><pb n="7"/> for the Good Council you
                            have given<lb/> us, and we wish you to keep your Minds<lb/> strong
                            towards us.</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>Thos Stewardson made a short verbal reply &amp;<lb/> when he had done, Old
                        <persName key="halft1">Half Town</persName> told<lb/> us that they had done
                    with the use of Spi<lb/>rituous Liquors, every Man, but there were<lb/> yet
                    three Women who would sometimes<lb/> become Intoxicated, yet they did not<lb/>
                    intend to cease Labouring with them till<lb/> they became reformd. This old
                        <persName key="halft1">Half Town</persName><lb/> some years back was much in
                    the Practice of<lb/> getting Drunk &amp; when the <orgName key="allegany"
                        >Allegany Indians</orgName><lb/> Banishd the Poison, he said there was
                    no<lb/> get Drunk at <orgName key="allegany">Allegany </orgName>--he would
                    not<lb/> stay there but would go to <placeName key="buffa"
                    >Buffaloe</placeName>--he<lb/> accordingly went, but did not stay long<lb/>
                    before he came to <placeName key="catta1">Cattaraugus</placeName> where he<lb/>
                    now lives &amp; is so far reformd that Friends<lb/> dont know of his having one
                    frolic this sea<lb/>son, yet they suspected him once. He<lb/> is a very stout
                    Indian &amp; has been a Chief<lb/> of great Influence. <persName key="wyund1"
                        >Wyundegohta</persName> (which<lb/> signifies, he has gone by) is a very
                    respectable <lb/><pb n="8"/> serious &amp; Worthy Character--his Person<lb/>
                    tall--Countenance modest &amp; appearance<lb/> Plain--he is industrious &amp;
                    very hospitable<lb/> which character he has sustaind for ma<lb/>ny years. His
                    Wife is also a Worthy Wo<lb/>man but not very nice. <persName key="halft1">Half
                        Town</persName>s<lb/> Indian Name is Codjeyate --or to put a<lb/> cork in a
                    Bottle. <persName key="thomp1">Thomsons</persName> Name is<lb/> Kys wyd twa--or
                    the whole side of a Hog<lb/> There were also several other Chiefs of low<lb/>er
                    Grade present at Council.<lb/> After our Business with them was gone thro'<lb/>
                    <persName key="egran2">Granger</persName> informd them of the Object of his
                    Visit<lb/> &amp; concluded with some very suitable advice,<lb/> all
                    correspondent with ours &amp; tending to enforce<lb/> it. On breaking up, our
                    Comp't with <persName key="egran2">E Granger</persName><lb/> went to the House
                    of <persName key="wyund1">Wyundegohta</persName> where we found<lb/> his Wife
                    had been preparing us a Repast &amp;<lb/> was just bringing it into the Store
                    House where<lb/> we had been received--it consisted of a Bowl<lb/> of Soup made
                    of Wild Pidgeons &amp;c--the Pidge<lb/>ons being left in--and some Indian
                    [Cakes?]<lb/> one kind made of Old Corn Pounded &amp; baked<lb/> in the
                    Ashes--the other of new shelld off corn which<lb/> it was said had been tied up
                    in a Corn Husk<lb/> and Boild--but I think it had also been <lb/><pb n="9"/>
                    baked a little in the Ashes--the Cakes I<lb/> tasted with some reluctance but
                    was afraid<lb/> of giving offence if I did not--&amp; the kind made<lb/> of the
                    New Corn I should have thought re<lb/>ally good had some of my White Friends
                    been<lb/> the Cooks--the other Cakes tasted of the<lb/> smoke with which their
                    old Corn is ge<lb/>nerally seasoned. The Pidgeons were taken<lb/> in the Fingers
                    &amp; eaten with little ceremony<lb/> &amp; the soup was obtaind by the aid of
                    an Old<lb/> black Wooden Ladle which each person inclining<lb/> to partake took
                    hold of and supd till he was satis<lb/>fied &amp; then left it in the Dish for
                    his successor<lb/> &amp; so it went round to many of the Company<lb/> who
                    pronounced it very good--I however felt<lb/> satisfied to take their Word for it
                    &amp; therefore it<lb/> will not be safe to contradict them.<lb/> On Our Way
                    home stopd at the <placeName key="muncy">Muncy</placeName> Village<lb/> but they
                    had nothing material to say to us--they<lb/> appear more Dirty &amp; Idolent
                    than the <orgName key="seneca">Seneca</orgName> In<lb/>dians &amp; are
                    considered by them as their Inferiors<lb/> yet they permit them to live on their
                    Land on suf<lb/>ferance as they the <orgName key="munseeind">Munceys</orgName>
                    have no Land of their own,<lb/> &amp; this may in part account for their
                    degraded<lb/> state--they have little stimilus to exert them<lb/>selves in
                    Improving Lands while only Tenants<lb/> at Will of the <orgName key="seneca"
                        >Senecas</orgName>, who do not respect<lb/><pb n="10"/> &amp; Esteem them.
                    They are a part of the<lb/>
                    <orgName key="delaware">Delaware Nation</orgName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1809-09-30">9 mo. 30th</date><placeName key="tunes"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>30th. Some of our Co. spent part of the Day<lb/> in Walking over the Farm &amp;
                    Viewing the Land<lb/> situation for a Grist Mill &amp;c. It is a beauti<gap/>ful
                    kindly<lb/> soil the greater part of it high land &amp; well<lb/> Timberd--as is
                    also the Valley or Bottom Land,<lb/> of which there is about 100 Acres.
                    This<lb/> Valley or bottom, which runs from here to<lb/>
                    <placeName key="lakee">Lake Erie</placeName> (about 9 or 10 miles distant North
                    West)<lb/> it looks very probable was once a part of the<lb/> Lake &amp; is very
                    rich. Our Friends have near<lb/> 30 Acres Cleard &amp; Clearing &amp; the Oats,
                    Wheat,<lb/> &amp; Vegetables grow very fine--to the West of<lb/> the House about
                    60 yards is a beautiful spring on the Edge of<lb/> the Hill about 110 feet from
                    the surface<lb/> of the Valley, <del>which</del> this spring is con<lb/>ducted
                    into a bark Spring House--into a<lb/> Water Trough &amp;c. in a very convenient
                    &amp;<lb/> simple manner. Part of the Dwelling<lb/> House is made of logs--about
                    13 feet square<lb/> a second addition is constructed of the<lb/> Bark of the
                    Black Ash, sewed with the<lb/> inside Bark of the <gap/> Wood<lb/> The Frame or
                    skeleton of the Building <lb/><pb n="11"/> is first made with small poles set in
                    the<lb/> Ground &amp; Rafters of the same lyed on them--<lb/> the Bark is then
                    placed edge ways by way<lb/> of Weather boarding &amp; Roofd of the same<lb/>
                    Material--each piece of Bark being well<lb/> tyed to the Poles with the [B?]
                    wood Bark<lb/> before mentioned--the Doors are each made of<lb/> a single Bark
                    Board &amp; the floor is composd<lb/> of about 4 or 5 some of them being<lb/>
                    between 5 &amp; 6 feet in Width--about 9<lb/> or 10 in length &amp; an inch in
                    thickness. The<lb/> cost of this Fabric was $1.75 cents, and was<lb/> built by
                    the Indians by agreement for that<lb/> sum. It was our Lodging &amp; Eating Room
                    while<lb/> there--containd two Beds--a Large Table--two<lb/> Benches--several
                    Chairs--Chest--Corn Mill--<lb/> &amp; sundry other Furniture too tedious to
                    enu<lb/>merate. <persName key="egran2">Erastus Granger</persName> came home with
                    us from<lb/> the Treaty last Evening &amp; was my Bedfellow<lb/> we had
                    considerable conversation relative to<lb/> the Indians &amp; among other things
                    got on the sub<lb/>ject of their Qualifications for Orratory--he<lb/> said one
                    of the most pathetic communications<lb/> he had ever heard was from a Young
                    Warrior<lb/> of the <orgName key="tuscarora">Tuscarora</orgName> Nation about
                    four years <lb/><pb n="12"/> ago. The Indians had taken up a couple<lb/> of
                    Women for the supposed crime of Witch<lb/> Craft--one of these Women they had
                    put to<lb/> Death, &amp; the other to extreme Torture to extort<lb/> from her a
                    Confession of her Guilt. The<lb/> young Warrior was the son of this Woman.<lb/>
                    <persName key="egran2">Granger</persName> having by some means heard what<lb/>
                    was going forward among them went to the Wo<lb/>mans Relief and remonstrated
                    with them on the<lb/> evil &amp; impropriety of such acts--they however<lb/>
                    plead with him on the Necessity of taking<lb/> the Womans Life &amp; when the
                    found he<lb/> continued firm in his Objection, her own<lb/> son stepd forth,
                    first lookd to the Ground &amp; then<lb/> raising his Eyes in a moving manner a'
                    said<lb/> My Friend I hope you will listen to<lb/> what I have to say. I am the
                    son of that<lb/> Woman--she is my Mother!--She<lb/> nursed me when I was a
                    Child, and I<lb/> love my Mother!--Her Arms were ex<lb/>tended for my
                    protection--she laboured<lb/> for my support &amp; Comfort!--how can I<lb/> help
                    but love my Mother? She<lb/> clothed me &amp; kept me from all harm<lb/> both in
                    sickness &amp; in Health, and you<lb/> cannot doubt that I still love my
                        Mo<lb/><pb n="13"/>Mother, yet notwithstanding my strong<lb/> attachment to
                    her, I an convinced that<lb/> she is a bad Woman &amp; has been the<lb/> means
                    of taking the Lives of some of our<lb/> People by Witchcraft. I think
                    there<lb/>fore she ought to Die, and desire <persName key="egran2">Mr.<lb/>
                        Granger</persName> that you will not oppose<lb/> her being put to Death. As
                    to my<lb/>self &amp; my Brothers we have given<lb/> her up for the Good of the Nation.<lb/>
                    <persName key="egran2">Granger</persName> said that the young man (who<lb/> was
                    unaccustomed to speaking in public) deli<lb/>vered this Expostulatory
                    address<lb/> with much emotion, appearing greatly af<lb/>fected--&amp; with
                    respect to himself he<lb/> said, as nearly as I remember his own lan<lb/>guage,
                    that if he was to have had the World<lb/> he could not have avoided shedding
                    Tears--<lb/> the Life of the Woman however was pre<lb/>served &amp; said to be
                    still living <gap/><lb/> &amp; supported by that Son, but much<lb/> deformed by
                    the Tortures they used upon<lb/> her. The Chief Warriors Wife paid us a Visit
                    to<lb/>day &amp; spent a considerable part of the Time in Spinning<lb/> with
                    which she seems much pleasd &amp; performs cleverly.</p>
               
            </div>
            <div type="entry"> <pb n="14"/>
                <dateline><date when="1809-10-01">1st of 10 month.</date><placeName key="tunes"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>1st Day. A shower in the<lb/> Night from which our Bark Habitation en<lb/>tirely
                    sheltered us. Intending to prosecute our<lb/> Journey after an Early Dinner, we
                    prepard<lb/> ourselves soon after Breakfast &amp; sat down<lb/> together with
                    the Family (consisting of <persName key="bcoop1">Benjn.<lb/>
                        Cope</persName>--<persName key="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName>--<persName
                        key="stwin1">Stephen Twining</persName> &amp; Hank<lb/> Jackson) about 9
                    oClock. Our Minds, I trust<lb/> being disposed to offer an Acknowledgment<lb/>
                    of Gratitude to Him Who hath thus far<lb/> preserved us &amp; Comfortably shed
                    the Light<lb/> of his Countenance on our present Under<lb/>taking &amp;
                    Embassy--with Denies also that<lb/> He may continue His protecting Care,<lb/>
                    both to us on our Return, and to our<lb/> Friends here stationed--that He
                    may<lb/> Dispence to them a portion of His Wisdom<lb/> to go in and out &amp;
                    hold intercourse with<lb/> the Natives promotive of their Improve<lb/>ment and
                    of His Praise. With<lb/> respect to the Concern of Friends in this<lb/>
                    Important Work, the Pious Poets Petition<lb/> occurd to me (and I hope, with
                    propriety<lb/> it may here be prefer'd) <lb/><pb n="15"/><quote type="poem">Prosper,
                        We press Thee with a powerful Plea<lb/> A Task we've Venturd on, impelld by
                        Thee.</quote><lb/> Our Opportunity together was a favourd<lb/> one--the
                    Overshadowing Wing of Antient<lb/> Kindness accompanying our Minds,<lb/> under
                    which a renewed Confirmation of<lb/> the Promise was afforded, That<lb/> where
                    two or three are met &amp; gathered<lb/> in the Almighty Name--there He
                    would<lb/> be in the midst of them. <persName key="alea1">Amos
                    Lea</persName><lb/> had a comfortable yet solemn Com<lb/>munication, reviving
                    the scripture that<lb/> here we have no continuing City &amp; there<lb/>fore
                    should seek one to come &amp;c--but<lb/> that if we were in our proper places
                    it<lb/> matterd not where our Exit as to sub<lb/>limary Things took place. The
                    Text<lb/> which had several times run<lb/> thro' my own Mind, he also
                    repeated.<lb/> Where Two or Three &amp;ca. I can ac<lb/>knowledge that in this
                    Opportunity<lb/> I felt abundantly satisfied--it seemd<lb/> like a seal of our
                    being rightly put <lb/><pb n="16"/> forth &amp; evidence that we are still<lb/>
                    cared for.<lb/> After rising from an Early Dinner, mounted<lb/> our Horses for
                    Home, <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName><lb/> accompanying us,
                    having Business as <placeName key="batav">Batavia</placeName><lb/> our Road was
                    across the Wilderness for about<lb/> 12 or 14 Miles a single Horse Path. In<lb/>
                    this afternoons Ride I met with several Dis<lb/>asters--but the Last &amp; Worst
                    was from a<lb/> Hemlock Knot sharp at one End &amp; laying<lb/> in the
                    Road--which my Horse stuck into his<lb/> Near Hind Foot an Inch &amp; 1/8th in
                    Depth the<lb/> effect of which was to lame him so much<lb/> as almost to Disable
                    him from travelling--<lb/> in this situation I travelld ab. 5 or 6 miles<lb/>
                    thro' an Extremely bad Road--perhaps<lb/> the worst, some part of it, that I
                    ever saw<lb/> my Comp'y leavg me behind I had some very<lb/> unpleasant
                    sensations, principally arising<lb/> from the Pain which my Horse evidently<lb/>
                    traveld in--they at length came to <placeName key="lakee">Lake<lb/>
                        Erie</placeName> &amp; there stopd for me after which<lb/> about one mile
                    along Its Shore brought<lb/> us to a poor forlorn House kept by one <lb/>Enos
                        <lb/><pb n="17"/> Enos (a new Comer there)--have rode this af<lb/>ternoon
                    about 21 miles--&amp; it now being night<lb/> we with considerable Difficulty
                    extracted the Snag<lb/> from my poor Horses Foot &amp; without any other<lb/>
                    application than a little Black Alder Spirit which<lb/> I had with me turnd him
                    out with the rest in<lb/> a bare field, with a priveledge to go to a Hay<lb/>
                    stack if they inclind, which stood a good way<lb/> off. The land lady provided
                    us a supper of Tea<lb/> &amp;c. as good as she was able &amp; we were then
                    told<lb/> that they would leave us the Two Beds &amp; the<lb/> Room were we eat,
                    to lodge in--being 5 in num<lb/>ber, I told my Co. that I intended to be
                    the<lb/> one who should take the Floor against this<lb/> several of them
                    objected, but I told them I<lb/> did not intend returning home without once<lb/>
                    making trial of such a mode of Lodging. I<lb/> accordingly inverted a
                    Chair--placed my<lb/> Saddle &amp; Bags upon it for a Pillow, &amp;<lb/> spread
                        <persName key="tstew1">T Stewardson</persName>s Blanket on the floor<lb/>
                    for a Bed--then puting on my Great Coat<lb/> &amp; wrapg myself in my own
                    Blanket I<lb/> lay down, Boots &amp; all, with my feet to the<lb/> fire &amp;
                    had a very comfortable Sleep &amp; some<lb/> pleasant Dreams. Towards Day
                        <persName key="jbrow1">Jn. Brown</persName>
                    <lb/><pb n="18"/> getting up to look after our Horses, awoke<lb/> me &amp; several
                    Poetical extracts presenting<lb/> as appropriate to my situation, I had
                    some<lb/> very Instructive Reflections relative to the<lb/> protecting care
                    &amp; paternal Regard of an Al<lb/>mighty Father, whose Dispensations whether
                    plea<lb/>sant or Afflictive, are all in Mercy &amp; unerving Wisdom. I then had
                    another<lb/> sweet sleep. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1809-10-02"/><placeName key="buffa"/></dateline>
                <p>In the Morning rose<lb/> early--fed our Horses &amp; rode about 9 Miles<lb/>
                    along the Lake Shore to Breakfast at<lb/>
                    <placeName key="buffa">Buffaloe</placeName>--calld now <placeName key="amst"
                        >Amsterdam</placeName>--my<lb/> Horse very Lame, travelling
                    consequently<lb/> painful both to him &amp; myself yet it did<lb/> not entirely
                    prevent me from enjoying the<lb/> Grandeiur of the Scenes presented by the<lb/>
                    foaming Billows which lashd the shore,<lb/> expressing in Accents Rude, yet
                    awful<lb/> &amp; Sublime, the Omnipotence of Him who <lb/>marks their
                    Boundaries.<lb/> The Lake appears to be supplied, not only<lb/> by the larger
                    Waters which empty into it.<lb/> The Mouths of several of which we crossd,<lb/>
                    viz. Smoke &amp; <placeName key="buffc1">Buffaloe Creek</placeName>s, but
                        <lb/><pb n="19"/>innumerable springs weep from its Banks<lb/> &amp; loose
                    themselves in its hungry Sands<lb/> which are so calculated to absorb small<lb/>
                    supplies that the returning Billow<lb/> is lost to the View, before the Welling
                    is<lb/> renewed by its speedy Successor.<lb/> The Shore for the most part is
                    coverd with a<lb/> Beautiful fine Gravel &amp; small Shells--but in<lb/> some
                    places Sand &amp; others mud--in some<lb/> places it is receeding &amp; in
                    others forming<lb/> &amp; we were told that when there is much<lb/> Wind the
                    Breakers exceed their Banks &amp;<lb/> dash over the adjacent Country,
                    covering<lb/> many Acres like a sea.<lb/> Now Amsterdam is situate near the
                    Mouth<lb/> of <placeName key="buffc1">Buffaloe Creek</placeName> about a Quarter
                    of a<lb/> Mile from the Lake and commands a<lb/> View <placeName key="point"
                        >Point Abineau</placeName>, about 14 Miles<lb/> distant, and a considerable
                    extent of the<lb/>
                    <placeName key="canad">upper Canada</placeName> Shore about the Mouth<lb/>
                    of <placeName key="blacc">Black Creek</placeName>, where a number of
                    Friends<lb/> are setled. <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>, where
                    there is<lb/> a British Garrison, stands opposite, yet<lb/> the View is
                    obstructed from the Town by <lb/><pb n="20"/> a skirt of Woods on this Bank,
                    but<lb/> when we cast our Eyes up this Lake<lb/> it looks like a mighty sea, and
                    Vission is<lb/> too short to scan its extent. The Town<lb/> contains about 40 or
                    50 Houses &amp; is in<lb/>creasing in Population &amp; handsome Buildings<lb/>
                    it seems to be a place of much intercourse<lb/> &amp; is about 22 Miles from
                        <placeName key="niagf">Niagara<lb/> Falls</placeName>. There are several
                    Indian Towns<lb/> within a few miles &amp; the Indians are too<lb/> often here
                    to give hope, on national Ground,<lb/> of their general reformation from
                    their<lb/> use of Spirituous Liquors, &amp; yet we were<lb/> told that many of
                    them have abandoned<lb/> this Destroyer &amp; stand firm against
                    Temp<lb/>tation. <placeName key="buffc1">Buffaloe Creek</placeName> is
                    navigable<lb/> for shallops several miles up yet<lb/> subject to a Changeing Bar
                    at its<lb/> mouth, in which we forded it about 2<lb/> feet Deep &amp; 10 Yards
                    wide.<lb/> The Lake where we first struck it is<lb/> calld 12 Miles wide--at
                        <placeName key="buffa">Buffaloe</placeName> 3 Miles<lb/> &amp; 3 miles lower
                    down, at <placeName key="blacr">black Rock</placeName>--One <lb/><pb n="21"
                    />Mile &amp; here there is a Ferry kept over<lb/> into Canada.<lb/> At
                        <placeName key="buffa">Buffaloe</placeName> we saw a great many Indians<lb/>
                    among which were <placeName key="redja1">Red Jacket</placeName> &amp; the
                    Farmers<lb/> Brother, but all appeard to be sober.<lb/> After Dining &amp;
                    getting our Horses shod we<lb/> mounted them &amp; proceeded over the <placeName
                        key="woakp">White Oak<lb/> Plains</placeName>, which appear to be composd of
                    a large<lb/> proportion of small Lime Stone &amp; an intermix<lb/>ture of pretty
                    good soil--there are very few<lb/> Trees, but fern &amp; some scrubby Bushes
                    &amp; abun<lb/>dance of strawberry Vines. <persName key="egran2">Erastus
                        Grangers</persName><lb/> House--a Neat Building, lay to our Left hand<lb/>
                    &amp; 14 Miles from <placeName key="buffa">Buffaloe</placeName> we stopd for
                    the<lb/> Night at <persName key="aharr1">Asa Harris</persName>'s Tavern--my
                    Horse<lb/> had traveld in much pain &amp; </p> </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1809-10-03"/><placeName key="batav"
                /></dateline>
                <p>next morning the<lb/> 3d. I with Difficulty got him to move, he<lb/> had also
                    left his oats (for the first time since<lb/> leaving home). Our Comp'y intending
                    Breakfast<lb/> at <placeName key="vande">Vandeventers Tavern</placeName> 8 Miles
                    distant, I<lb/> got along with them, but neither myself<lb/> or Horse being in
                    Eating Mood we passd on<lb/> over a Rough Road much of it being log
                    causeway<lb/> 18 Miles to <placeName key="batav">Batavia</placeName>. I had
                    drove him before<lb/> me a Considerable part of this Distance &amp; felt<lb/>
                    spent &amp; unwell on reach'g there--when my Co.<lb/> came up a pretty good
                    Dinner &amp; Glass of Wine <lb/><pb n="22"/>refreshd me but did not relieve my mind
                    [?]<lb/> felt in a great straight what was best to be<lb/> done--my Co. were
                    intent on proceeding home<lb/>ward &amp; could not bear to a
                    Detention--they<lb/> therefore advised me to change my Horse<lb/> for another,
                    or sell him &amp; take the stage<lb/> via <placeName key="alban"
                        >Albany</placeName> &amp; New York, but to neither plan<lb/> could I feel
                    reconcild--&amp; to be left behind among<lb/> strangers at such a Distance
                    looked very gloomy,<lb/> yet seemd the most satisfactory provided I could<lb/>
                    not keep along. <placeName key="batav">Batavia</placeName> is in <placeName
                        key="genec">Gennessee<lb/> County</placeName> &amp; the County Town has a
                    fine Court<lb/> House &amp; prhps 30 Houses -- is situate on<lb/> the <placeName
                        key="toncr">Tonawanda</placeName> which we crossd<lb/> some miles before
                    getting here, and a<lb/> little before <placeName key="murder">Murder
                        Creek</placeName>.<lb/> having Dind I went on with my Co. 12 Miles<lb/> to
                        <placeName key="ganson">Gansons Tavern</placeName>, where I nursd poor
                    Snip<lb/> as well as I could, &amp; </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1809-10-04">next Morn'g the 4th</date><placeName key="danv"/></dateline>
                <p>Rose before Day &amp; rode over a poor Dry<lb/> Country till we came to the
                    Indian Reser<lb/>vation on the <placeName key="genes2">Gennessee
                        River</placeName>, which we<lb/> Crossd, perhaps a mile thro' the
                    enclosd<lb/> Flats, a very excellent soil coverd with<lb/> rich Pasture, with
                    Horses, Cattle &amp; Swine <lb/><pb n="23"/> belonging to the Indians, feeding on
                    it.<lb/> there are two settlements of Indians<lb/> near here, one of which we
                    passd thro.<lb/> We passd also by a very large spring,<lb/> which of itself was
                    a mill but in<lb/> general this <placeName key="genec">Gennessee
                        County</placeName> is badly<lb/> Waterd &amp; Water is bad--much of the<lb/>
                    soil is coverd with poor scattering scrubbly<lb/> Oaks &amp; full of Lime Stone.
                    At a little<lb/> place calld <placeName key="hartf2">Hartford</placeName> we
                    crossd the<lb/>
                    <placeName key="genes2">Gennessee River</placeName> 13 Miles from <placeName
                        key="ganson">Gansons</placeName> &amp; breakfasted at<lb/> a Good Inn kept
                    by Maria Berry--<lb/> after Breakfast submitted to my Friends<lb/> whether they
                    would advise me to go on<lb/> with them or take my route alone<lb/> Via
                        <placeName key="alban">Albany</placeName> (the Road to which they<lb/> were
                    now going to leave)--they encouraged<lb/> me to proceed with them as my
                    Horse<lb/> seemd rather better, so passing over a barren<lb/> country for some
                    miles, coverd principally with<lb/> scattering Oaks, we came to a better soil
                    &amp; a<lb/> number of Settlements--also passd thro' the<lb/> noted Farm on
                    which live two Brothers by<lb/> the Name of<persName key="wwads1">Wadsworth,
                        Wm</persName> &amp; <persName key="jwads1">James</persName><lb/>
                    <pb n="24"/> and is a part of the Big-Tree Reservation,<lb/> principally Flats,
                    very fine &amp; bounding on the<lb/>
                    <placeName key="genes2">Gennessee River</placeName>--they here keep a very
                    lrg<lb/> stock &amp; we were told 1200 head of sheep.<lb/> At <placeName
                        key="willi">Williamsburg</placeName> (a Wretched place, formerly<lb/> noted
                    for Horseracing &amp;c, now only three In<lb/>habited Houses) we fed our
                    Horses--eat a<lb/> few poor red Plumbs &amp; piece of Gingerbread<lb/> &amp;
                    then mounted again coming pretty soon<lb/> to a Stream of Water calld <placeName
                        key="canas">Canneseraga</placeName><lb/> being a Fork of the <placeName
                        key="genes2">Gennessee River</placeName><lb/> which here is about 8 Miles
                    from us--<lb/> along this Stream is a body of valuable<lb/> Flatts which lay to
                    our Right &amp; a Moun<lb/>tain to our left--this is a rich soil if rightly<lb/>
                    managed but the Farms are in poor Culture<lb/> &amp; many of the Houses are
                    deserted--partly<lb/> owing (we were told) to the badness of the<lb/> Water
                    &amp; partly, I suspect, from the use<lb/> of Whisky which is sadly common
                    here<lb/> --a little before Night reachd <placeName key="danv"
                        >Danville</placeName><lb/> which makes our Days ride 40 Miles--<lb/> stopd
                    at a Tavern kept by a <placeName key="jrowl1">Jonathan Rowley</placeName>--<lb/>
                    here we met with Colonel Troop &amp; a young man<lb/> from <placeName
                        key="alban">Albany</placeName> &amp; <placeName key="jwads1">James
                        Wadsworth</placeName>, one of the <lb/><pb n="25"/> Brothers before mentioned--he
                    told us, on our<lb/> enquiry, that they had about 1600 sheep &amp; be<lb/>tween
                    1 &amp; 200 Cattle--this <placeName key="danv">Daville</placeName> is a
                    poor<lb/> little place, but the Landlady seemd disposd<lb/> to entertain us
                    according t the best of her abi<lb/>lity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1809-10-05"> Next Morning the 5th.</date><placeName key="danv"/></dateline>
                <p>rose about Day Break &amp; rode 12 1/2 miles<lb/> to Breakfast at <persName
                        key="churl1">Christian Hurlburts</persName> Tavern<lb/> a Good House near
                    the <placeName key="canis">Canisteo</placeName> Creek--our<lb/> ride this
                    Morning chiefly over a spur of the<lb/>
                    <placeName key="allmo">Allegany Mountains</placeName>--then passing a
                    large<lb/> Body of uninclosd Marshy Ground--then<lb/> after Breakfast about 11
                    o'Clock took our<lb/> Way up the <placeName key="canis">Canisteo</placeName>
                    Creek, pretty much<lb/> following its courses in the Valley which<lb/> is rich
                    &amp; affords many fine Farms--the<lb/> Hills on either hand appeared like<lb/>
                    Chains of Mountains, yet we were told<lb/> that the Country on the Top is
                    pretty<lb/> level &amp; well Timberd--after making<lb/> our Days ride 32 Miles
                    put in at the<lb/> House of <persName key="jlough1">Joseph Loughrey</persName>,
                    a poor place<lb/> but the only one then attainable--here</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1809-10-06">6</date> <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>they gave us our Breakfast about Day<lb/> Break and keeping down the Valley 18<lb/>
                        <pb n="26"/> Miles we fed at Jones's Tavern &amp; in 5<lb/> more came to the
                        <placeName key="tioga">Tioga River</placeName> where<lb/> the <placeName
                        key="canis">Canisteo</placeName> emptied into it--we were all<lb/> told that
                    the <placeName key="tioga">Tiogo</placeName> empties into the North<lb/> Branch
                    of <placeName key="susqueh">Susquehanna</placeName> about 50 Miles<lb/> from
                    here--after fording the <placeName key="canis">Canisteo</placeName> &amp;<lb/>
                    <placeName key="tioga">Teoga</placeName> stopd &amp; Dind at <placeName
                        key="fords">Fords Tavern</placeName> just as<lb/> it began to Rain, which
                    Continuing we<lb/> unbent on Great Coats for he first time<lb/> that Rain had
                    made them necessary, &amp;<lb/> in about 3/4 of a mile riding cross'd<lb/> the
                        <placeName key="cowan">Cowawneskee</placeName> &amp; tak'g the left<lb/>
                    hand road of three forded the <placeName key="tioga">Tioga</placeName><lb/>
                    twice got in to a Tavern kept by another<lb/> Widow Berry, being a little West.
                    Our<lb/> Days ride computed 41 Miles--my Horse thi<lb/>s afternoon much better
                    of his Lameness &amp;<lb/> in good spirits. We are now in the State<lb/> of
                        <placeName key="penns">Pennsylvania</placeName> hav'g crossd the Line
                    of<lb/> Pens'a &amp; N York this afternoon between the<lb/>
                    <placeName key="cowan">Cowawneskee</placeName> &amp; <placeName key="tioga"
                        >Tioga</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1809-10-07">7th</date> <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>Took an Early start again &amp; rode Eleven<lb/> Miles to Breakfast at a
                    poor Tavern kept<lb/> by one Greno. Our Road worse than we <lb/><pb n="27"/> have
                    lately had it, the mud being<lb/> increasd by last nights Rain. The Land<lb/>
                    here is Good--well Timberd &amp; many setlers<lb/> our Course is up the
                        <placeName key="tioga">Tioga</placeName>--here has been<lb/> no Frost of
                    Consequence, nor have we seen<lb/> any since crossing the <placeName
                        key="genes2">Gennessee River</placeName><lb/> --after Breakfast pursued our
                    route up<lb/> the <placeName key="tioga">Tioga</placeName> about 7 Miles further
                    when its<lb/> increasing Murmers &amp; Rapidity reminded us<lb/> of a greater
                    Elevation ahead--we accordingly<lb/> soon began to ascend the savage
                    Mountain<lb/> being calld 10 Miles across &amp; the Worst<lb/> Travelling we
                    have had since leaving <placeName key="lakee">Lake<lb/> Erie</placeName>--yet
                    even on this Wild &amp; Stony Height<lb/> I was not destitute of Enjoyment. The
                    falling<lb/> Beech &amp; Sugar Maple Leaves mingling their<lb/> sweets with the
                    Mountain Air, after the Noc<lb/>turnal shower, emitted a fragrance regaling<lb/>
                    to the senses &amp; cheering to the Mind--at the<lb/> foot of this Mountain
                    (sometimes calld Briar<lb/> Hill) we put in at the <placeName key="block">Block
                        House</placeName>, now<lb/> kept by S Hisley. We are now said to be<lb/>
                    opposite <persName key="rmoor1">Richard Moore</persName>s where we lodgd in<lb/>
                    our Route up--being about 8 Miles off on a<lb/> North Course. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1809-10-08">8th</date><placeName key="newbe1"></placeName></dateline>
                <p>Rose before Day &amp; crossd the <placeName key="allegany"
                        >Allegany</placeName>
                    <pb n="28"/> Mountain, <lb/>9 Miles over--then Descended into<lb/> a Valley, the Bed
                    of <placeName key="trout">Trout River</placeName>, which in<lb/> about 3 Miles
                    we forded 30 times &amp; put in<lb/> about 10 o'Clock at <persName key="dreyn1"
                        >David Reynolds</persName> Tavern,<lb/> having rode 15 Miles over a very
                    rough,<lb/> Muddy &amp; bad Road, being considerably wet by<lb/> a heavy
                    Drizzle, amounting to a fine Rain--<lb/> here we found Peaches in abundance
                    &amp;<lb/> for the first time since leaving home, I feas<lb/>ted luxuriously
                    upon them, both before &amp;<lb/> after Breakfast--we are here again on<lb/> the
                        <placeName key="lycom3">Lycoming Creek</placeName> which runs before
                    the<lb/> Door--about 1/2 past Eleven following its<lb/> courses &amp; fording it
                    many times, with Moun<lb/>tains high on either hand we reachd<lb/>
                    <placeName key="newbe1">Newberry</placeName> in about 11 Miles riding--and<lb/>
                    <persName key="melli2">Mercy Ellis</persName>'s before Dark having rode<lb/> 41
                    Miles.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1809-10-09">9th</date><placeName key="catta"/></dateline>
                <p>Breakfasted at <persName key="melli2">Mercy Ellis</persName>'s &amp;
                    then<lb/> proceeded--from the Top of Muncy Hill the<lb/>
                    <placeName key="catta">Cattawissa</placeName> &amp; other Mountains before
                    us<lb/> with the intervening Vale, thro which<lb/> the <placeName key="susqu"
                        >Susquehanna</placeName> runs, our Prospect was<lb/> very fine--then passing
                    Hard Scrabble Town <lb/><pb n="29"/> we fed again at <placeName key="jtown2">Jersey
                        Town</placeName> &amp; Dind on our<lb/> own Provision--the appearance of
                    Things being<lb/> no temptation to call for Dinner. In a few<lb/> Miles riding
                    we got another feast of Peaches<lb/> which are here very plenty--when we<lb/>
                    came to the <placeName key="susqu">Susquehanna</placeName>, no ferryman<lb/>
                    appearing at our call &amp; the Water being<lb/> lower than when we went up, we
                    ven<lb/>tured to ford it &amp; got to <placeName key="catta"
                        >Cattawessa</placeName> before<lb/> Dark. <persName key="tamos1">Tho.
                        Amos</persName> &amp; myself put up<lb/> our Horses &amp; supd at <persName
                        key="bshar1">Benj. Sharplesses</persName><lb/> but lodged at <persName
                        key="telli1">Tho. Ellis</persName>'s very comfort<lb/>ably, &amp;</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1809-10-10">before 5
                    o'Clock next morn'g the 10th, </date> <placeName key="benst"/></dateline>
                <p>they gave us Breakfast so as to en<lb/>able us to set out with the first
                    appear<lb/>ance of Day--as we left the Town<lb/> &amp; for a Considerable
                    Distance up the<lb/> Mountain the Fog was so great as to<lb/> make it very Damp
                    riding--but when<lb/> we had nearly reachd the Mountains<lb/> top we found
                    ourselves entirely above<lb/> it--on getting to the Top of the Little<lb/>
                    Mountain 10 Miles off we saw the Fog <lb/><pb n="30"/> still hanging over the
                        <placeName key="susqu">Susquehanna</placeName><lb/> very heavy for along
                    Distance--after<lb/> Xg this &amp; the <placeName key="mahan">Moehanoy
                        Mountains</placeName><lb/> fed our Horses about noon at <persName
                        key="mkett1">Michael<lb/> Ketteras</persName> 23 miles from <placeName
                        key="catta">Cattawessey</placeName>--<lb/> the Weather very Warm, as it has
                    been<lb/> nearly ever since we have been on our<lb/> return. Our next stage was at<lb/>
                    <placeName key="benst">Bensingers</placeName> which we reachd about sun<lb/>
                    set--tird--&amp;</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1809-10-11"> next morng the 11th</date> <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>rose before Day &amp; rode to Breakfast<lb/> 16 long Miles over a stony
                    mountainous<lb/> Road, at <persName key="mlee1">Mordicai Lea's</persName>--and
                    went with<lb/> them to <orgName key="maidem">Maiden Creek Meeting</orgName>
                    about one<lb/> mile from there--after Meetg Dind at <persName key="tligh1"
                        >Tho.<lb/> Lightfoots</persName> where we Draughted a Report<lb/> to the
                    Indian Coun. and <persName key="tstew1">T. Stewardson</persName> havg<lb/> sold
                    his Mare to <persName key="alea1">A Lea</persName> we here parted<lb/> with him
                    &amp; went home with Amos 10<lb/> Miles, part of the Way in the Rain.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1809-10-12">12th</date> <placeName key="byber">byber</placeName></dateline>
                <p>Rose again before Day--took Break<lb/>fast by Candle Light &amp; makg a
                    small <lb/><pb n="31"/> stop at <persName key="bwrig1">Benjamin Wrights</persName>
                    passd thro <placeName key="potts">Potts<lb/>Grove</placeName> &amp; over
                        <placeName key="perki">Perkioming</placeName> &amp; Skippack Bridges<lb/>
                    &amp; stopd to Dine at a Tavern on the Turnpike<lb/> Road, near the 18 Mile
                    stone &amp; the 2d.<lb/> Gate having rode since Breakfast &amp; feedg<lb/> 33
                    miles--soon after getting in here<lb/> it began to Raise. Dinner over we<lb/>
                    left the Turnpike &amp; passing by <persName key="jfoul1">Jesse<lb/>
                        Foulkes</persName> House &amp; Mill--thro North Wals<lb/>and by <orgName
                        key="meethorsh">Horseham Meetg House</orgName> &amp; the<lb/> Billet I
                    parted with <persName key="jbrow1">Jn. Brown</persName> near<lb/> Byberry just
                    at Dark &amp; got in to <persName key="hyarn1">Han<lb/> Yarnall</persName>s soon
                    after. <persName key="jbrow1">John</persName> intending home <lb/>that
                    night--found that HY had gone<lb/> to Baltimore YM &amp; Jas <unclear>Suter</unclear> to
                    Phila.<lb/> but I spent a pleasant Eveng with<lb/> the Caretakers left at
                    home -- my<lb/> ride this Day is computed 54 Miles.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1809-10-13">13th</date><placeName key="burli"/></dateline>
                <p> 13th My Desire to reach home induced<lb/> me to rise early before the Family
                    but<lb/> found the stable Lockd which produced a<lb/> little Detention--on
                    getting to Dunks <lb/><pb n="32"/>Ferry, the Hands had gone a <gap/> &amp;<lb/> I was
                    again Detaind near an Hour--but<lb/> reachd <placeName key="burli"
                        >Burlington</placeName> at latish Break<lb/>fast time--having been absent
                    about<lb/> three Days short of Six Weeks &amp;<lb/> rode, or traveld, 816 Miles.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="accounts">
                <p>9 mo 26 2 [Fish?] presented to us [?] .50cts <lb/>Lodgd at Stephen [Hazeltines?] 20
                    Miles  <lb/>27 Lodgdg Feed &amp;c. for 4 Persons $2.91 1/2  <lb/>rode to <placeName
                        key="catta1">Cataraugus</placeName> Clear Creek 25 Ms.  <lb/>28th Went to view
                    the Ind. Town &amp; Impr.  <lb/>bing 8 miles out &amp;  <lb/>8 in  <lb/>16 10 mo 1st. rode to
                    Enos's on <placeName key="lakee">Lake Erie</placeName> Lodgd  <lb/>21 M 21st-- 23 2d.
                    SUp. &amp; Horses a Enos's $2.94 "  <lb/>Breakfast Dinner &amp; Horses at <placeName
                        key="buffa">Buffaloe</placeName>, called New Amsterdam 9 M $4. <lb/>-- shoeing
                    Horses--my own $2.  <lb/>Lodgd at [name?] Harris's 14. $4.69 8 3d.  <lb/>Breakfast at
                    Vanderslice Td pd.8.  <lb/>-- <placeName key="batav">Batavia</placeName> Keyes Tavern
                    18  <lb/>[D?] &amp; fed $1.88  <lb/>Garrisons Tavern Supd &amp; Lodgd 12. 2.25  <lb/>40  <lb/>4
                    Breakfast at McBerrys (Hartford) 13.-- 2.--  <lb/>" fed at <placeName key="willi"
                        >Williamsburg</placeName> 12.-- .37 1/2  <lb/>" Lodgd at Dansville Inn a <gap/>
                    Rowley 15. 2.87 1/2 32  <lb/>5. Breakfast at Chris Hulberts Tavn. Canisted 2 1/2 1.25
                    Creek  <lb/>" Lodgd at Joseph Lugtneys &amp; Breakfastd 19 1/2 2.75 41  <lb/>6th Fed at
                    Jones Tavern 18 --.50  <lb/>" Dind &amp; fed at Forks Tavn. formerly <placeName
                        key="linds">Linsleys</placeName> 13. 1.87 1/2  <lb/>" Lodgd &amp; supd at a Q
                    Widow Berrys 10. 3.--  <lb/>28  <lb/>7th. Breakfasted &amp; fed at Greno's Tavern 11.
                    1.12 1/2  <lb/>" Supd &amp; Lodgd at the <placeName key="block">Block
                        House</placeName> 17. 3.12 1/2  <lb/>41  <lb/>8th. 1st. Day Breakfasted &amp; fed at
                    <persName key="dreyn1">David Reynolds</persName> Tavern 15. 1.50  <lb/>" To
                        <placeName key="newbe1">Newberry</placeName> 11 Miles &amp; to <persName
                            key="melli2">Mercy Ellis</persName>'s 15 in  <lb/>26. <lb/> --.50 28 9th. Breakfasted
                    [Millers?]-- <lb/>Fed at <placeName key="jtown2">Jersey Town</placeName> X Keys 16.
                    --.46  <lb/>Lodgd at <persName key="telli1">Thomas Ellis</persName>'s--<placeName
                        key="catta1">Cattawassey</placeName> 12. $40.51 </p>
           
                <p>10 mo. 9th. Amo. of Exp. bro. over $40.57 41 10th.  <lb/>Breakfast at <persName
                    key="telli1">Tho. Ellis</persName>'s  <lb/>" Fed ab. 12 at Michael [name?] 23
                    Miles $--.59  <lb/>" Lodgd at <placeName key="benst">Bensingers</placeName> supd feed
                    &amp;c. 18 2.87 1/2 27</p>
          
                <p> 11th. Breakfasted at <persName key="mlee1">Mordicai Lees</persName> 16.  <lb/>Dind at
                    <persName key="tligh1">T Lightfoots</persName> 1 Mile  <lb/>Lodgd at <persName
                        key="alea1">Amos Leas</persName> 10m 11 Miles 4 $43.97 1/2 &amp;  <lb/>Breakfast
                    next morng. each 10.99 1/2  <lb/>Rec'd of TS 7.87 1/2 3.12 $10.99  <lb/>rec'd of TS 11.--
                    <lb/>rec'd of <persName key="alea1">A Lea</persName> 11  <lb/>rec'd of <persName
                        key="jbrow1">Jn. Brown</persName>  <lb/>12th Toll at <placeName key="potts">Potts
                            Grove</placeName>--12 1/2--2d Gate 9cts--3d. D. 8. --.29 1/2  <lb/>Dind &amp; fed
                    at Thomas's Tavern near the 18 miles 54 stone on the Road S Road from <persName
                        key="alea1">A Leas</persName> 33 Ms. .87 1/2 2 117 X Rec'd 58 1/2 cts of
                        <persName key="jbrow1">Jn. Brown</persName> each . 58 1/2 after Dinner rode
                    to <persName key="hyarn1">H Yarnells</persName> [?] 21 Ms.  <lb/>13th Reachd home to
                    Breakfast 8 Ms. [?] 37 1/2 122 291 </p>
            </div>
        </body>


    </text>
</TEI>
