<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei-print.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="global.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>A Brief Account of the Proceedings of the Committee Appointed by the Yearly
                    Meeting of Friends, Held in Baltimore for Promoting the Improvement and
                    Civilization of the Indian Natives: Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>NAME</name>
                </respStmt>


            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 5 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>This work is the property of the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore
                        College. It may be copied freely by individuals for personal use, research,
                        and teaching (including distribution to classes) as long as this statement
                        of availability is included in the text. It may be linked to freely in
                        Internet editions of all kinds, including for—profit works.</p>
                    <p>Publishers, libraries, and other information providers interested in
                        providing this text in a commercial or non—profit product or from an
                        information server must contact Swarthmore College for licensing and cost
                        information.</p>
                    <p> Scholars interested in changing or adding to these texts by, for example,
                        creating a new edition of the text (electronically or in print) with
                        substantive editorial changes, may do so with the permission of Swarthmore
                        College. This is the case whether the new publication will be made available
                        at a cost or free of charge.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2015">2015</date>
                <idno type="local">SW_BYM1806</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Native Americans and Quakers: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
            </seriesStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="book">

                    <monogr>
                        <title>A Brief Account of the Proceedings of the Committee Appointed by the
                            Yearly Meeting of Friends, Held in Baltimore for Promoting the
                            Improvement and Civilization of the Indian Natives</title>

                        <idno>BX7747.3.A1B1 c.2</idno>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Phillips and Fardon</publisher>
                            <date when="1862">1806</date>

                        </imprint>

                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>


        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p> Native Americans and Quakers </p>
            </projectDesc>

        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Wyandot Indians</item>
                        <item>Indians of North America -- Indiana</item>
                        <item>Baltimore Yearly Meeting of the Religious Society of Friends</item>
                        <item>Indians of North America -- Ohio</item>
                        <item>Society of Friends - Indian Affairs</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item>
                    <date when="2015"/>POD edit</item>

            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            
            <div type="undetermined">
                <pb n="1" facs="SW_BYM1806_001"/> 
                <pb n="2" facs="SW_BYM1806_002"/> 
            </div>
            
            <div type="preface">
                 <pb n="3" facs="SW_BYM1806_003"/>
                <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
                <p>Since putting to press a London Edition of<lb/>"A brief Account of the
                    Proceedings of the<lb/>"Committee appointed in the Year <date when="1795"
                        >1795</date>, by<lb/>"the Yearly Meeting of Friends of Pennsyl-<lb/>"vania,
                    New Jersey, &amp;c. for promoting the<lb/>"Improvement and gradual Civilization
                    of the<lb/>"Indian Natives," an account of the proceed-<lb/>ings of a committee,
                    appointed by another<lb/>Yearly Meeting in North America, has been<lb/>received.
                    In presenting it to the English reader,<lb/>a few remarks may be useful.</p>

                <p>The <orgName key="bym">Yearly Meeting held at <placeName key="balti1"
                            >Baltimore</placeName></orgName>, in<lb/><placeName key="maryl"
                        >Maryland</placeName>, is quite distinct from <orgName key="pym">that held
                            at<lb/><placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName></orgName>; yet it
                    represents a considerable<lb/>part of the body of Friends in the western
                    part<lb/>of <placeName key="penns">Pennsylvania</placeName>. The objects of the
                    concern of<lb/>the two Yearly Meetings are equally distinct.<lb/>The Indian
                    nations to which the Maryland com-<lb/>mittee has directed its attention, lie in
                    general<lb/>farther west, than those under the notice of the<lb/>Pennsylvanians.
                    They are situated in that vast<lb/>district which is comprehended between
                    the<lb/>rivers <geogName key="ohior">Ohio</geogName> and <geogName key="missi"
                        >Mississippi</geogName>, and bounded to<lb/>the north by the lakes <geogName
                        key="lakes">Superior</geogName>, <geogName key="lakeh">Huron</geogName>,
                        and<lb/><geogName key="lakee">Erie</geogName>. <geogName key="lakem">Lake
                        Michigan</geogName> penetrates this district,<lb/>and may be said to be
                    wholly within it. It has<lb/><pb n="4" facs="SW_BYM1806_004"/>been called the North-Western
                    Territory; and<lb/>was not long ago the scene of an Indian war; but<lb/>peace
                    was established by a treaty at <placeName key="greenv"
                    >Greeneville</placeName><lb/>in <date when="1795">1795</date>; when a part of
                    the territory was ceded<lb/>to the United States, together with some
                    posts,<lb/>or trading stations, within the Indian part. Of<lb/>these <placeName
                        key="fwayn">Fort-Wayne</placeName> is one. It is in the unceded<lb/>parts
                    that the experiments have been made,<lb/>which are recorded in the following
                    pages.</p>
                <p>Both the Yearly Meetings seem to have lost<lb/>no time in beginning their work of
                    brotherly<lb/>kindness to the Indians. The war had been<lb/>an obstruction; but
                    we find the date of the<lb/>peace, and of the appointment of their
                    com-<lb/>mittens, to be in the same year, <date when="1795">1795</date>.</p>
                <p>In the letter which forms the Appendix to<lb/>the Pennsylvanian account, an
                    Indian chief, named<lb/><persName key="lturt1">Little Turtle</persName>, is
                    spoken of in terms of great ap-<lb/>probation. It may therefore be particularly
                    ac-<lb/>ceptable to see a speech of his in this narrative.</p>
                <p>In the advertisement prefixed to the Penn-<lb/>sylvanian account, an apology is
                    made for the<lb/>apparent absence of religious instruction as a<lb/>part of the
                    plan. The concluding paragraph<lb/>of this account confirms the apology; but
                    fu-<lb/>pressed the necessity of repeating it.</p>
                <p>Probably, a slight geographical description,<lb/>may render the narrative more
                    interesting to<lb/>some readers; and though maps are not always<lb/><pb n="5" facs="SW_BYM1806_005"/>
                    />to be depended on, especially with respect to a<lb/>country so uncivilized,
                    the following sketch,<lb/>taken from maps, may convey no bad notion of<lb/>the
                    locality of the committee’s labours.</p>
                <p><geogName key="muskr">Muskingum river</geogName> runs from N. to S. and
                    falls<lb/>into the Ohio in about 81.40 West longitude.</p>
                <p><geogName key="tuscr">Tuskarawas</geogName> (supposing it to be the
                    Tuscaroras<lb/>of the maps), is a small stream in the limits
                    of<lb/>Pennsylvania, which falls into the <geogName key="junia"
                        >Junietta</geogName>, a<lb/>branch of the <geogName key="susqu"
                        >Susquehannah</geogName>.</p>
                <p><placeName key="sand">Sandusky</placeName> is an Indian settlement, on a
                        <geogName key="sandr">river</geogName><lb/>of the same name that has a N.E.
                    course, and<lb/>empties itself into a small arm of <geogName key="lakee">lake
                        Erie</geogName>, near<lb/>its western end, about 82.50 W. lon.</p>
                <p><geogName key="miamr">Miami</geogName> is the name of three rivers in
                    this<lb/>country. That which concerns the account is<lb/><geogName key="miamr"
                        >Miami</geogName> of the lakes, which running nearly from S.<lb/>to N. a
                    course of apparently 150 miles, falls into<lb/><geogName key="lakee">lake
                        Erie</geogName>, about 50 miles W. of <placeName key="sand"
                        >Sandusky</placeName>.<lb/>On this river, where, as the term is, it
                    forks,<lb/>is <placeName key="fwayn">Fort-Wayne</placeName>.</p>
                <p>The <geogName key="wabas">Wabash</geogName> seems a long and crooked
                    river.<lb/>One of its sources is S. of <placeName key="fwayn"
                        >Fort-Wayne</placeName>; the<lb/>stream from which is doubtless the Wabash,
                    near<lb/>which the agricultural examples have been felt,<lb/>as related in the
                    account. The Ohio receives<lb/>the waters the <geogName key="wabas"
                        >Wabash</geogName>, not far from the 88th<lb/>degree of W. longitude.</p>
                <pb n="6" facs="SW_BYM1806_006"/>
                <p>The <geogName key="eelr">Eel-River</geogName> appears to be one of the
                    streams<lb/>which run into the <geogName key="wabas">Wabash</geogName>. It seems
                    to rise<lb/>in the neighbourhood of <placeName key="fwayn"
                        >Fort-Wayne</placeName>.</p>
                <p>The <orgName key="miami">Miami</orgName> nation, is no doubt connected
                    with<lb/>the <geogName key="miamr">river</geogName>, or rivers of that name. The
                    place of<lb/>the <orgName key="wyandot">Wyandots</orgName> is given in the
                    account. The <orgName key="shawnee">Sha-<lb/>wanees</orgName> and <orgName
                        key="delaware">Delawares</orgName> are marked in one map<lb/>as occupying
                    the neighborhood of the Ohio.<lb/>The <orgName key="wea">Weas</orgName> are
                    mentioned in the account as con-<lb/>nested with <geogName key="eelr"
                        >Eel-River</geogName>.</p>
                <p><placeName key="fwayn">Fort-Wayne</placeName> in a strait line seems not less
                    than <lb/>350 miles from <placeName key="balti1">Baltimore</placeName>; but
                    probably a great<lb/>deal more by any practicable road.</p>
                <p>Humanity may venture to rejoice at these at-<lb/>tempts. Though, as was observed
                    in the former<lb/>account, not on a grand scale, they are attended<lb/>with
                    considerable expence; and a labour, not<lb/>easily appreciated by the
                    inhabitants of highly<lb/>cultivated and civilized countries. But, to
                    adopt<lb/>a metaphor from the work, they are attempts<lb/>to cultivate the
                    large, and inexhaustible field<lb/>of Christian benevolence: for no less is
                    every<lb/>extension of brotherly kindness to our fellow-<lb/>men, which springs
                    from Christian principles.</p>
                <pb n="7" facs="SW_BYM1806_007"/>
                <p>THE Editor regrets that, in the letter<lb/>from the American General, printed at
                    the close<lb/>of the Account from <placeName key="penns"
                        >Pennsylvania</placeName>, a few lines<lb/>were suffered to remain, which
                    convey a cen-<lb/>sure on some former American missionaries. It<lb/>may have not
                    been perfectly easy for a person in<lb/>a very different walk of life to feel
                    exactly the<lb/>difficulties of their situation. Whoever duly<lb/>weighs the
                    state of the Indians, may account for<lb/>their want of success without thinking
                    them<lb/>much to blame. At any rate the Editor is dis-<lb/>posed to call it an
                    oversight, that in a work<lb/>intended to show the successful diligence of
                    one<lb/>set of men, there should have slipped in a need-<lb/>less censure of
                    another.</p>
                <pb n="8" facs="SW_BYM1806_008"/>
                <p>Extract from the Minutes of the <orgName key="bym">Yearly Meeting<lb/>held in
                        Baltimore</orgName>, <date when="1805-10">10th Mo. 1805</date>.</p>
                <p>A Report from our <orgName key="bymindian">Committee on
                        Indian<lb/>concerns</orgName> was produced, which being read
                    and<lb/>considered, much satisfaction with their pro-<lb/>ceding was expressed:
                    inasmuch as it very<lb/>evidently appears that considerable benefits to<lb/>our
                    Red Brethren have already resulted, since<lb/>the care of the <orgName key="bym"
                        >Yearly Meeting</orgName> towards them.<lb/>The <orgName key="bymindian"
                        >Committee</orgName> were encouraged to continue<lb/>such exertions, in the
                    prosecution of this im-<lb/>portent concern, as may be in their power
                    to<lb/>extend: they were also left at liberty to have<lb/>printed, for the more
                    general information of<lb/>Friends, as many copies of their report,
                    con-<lb/>nected with a narrative of their previous pro-<lb/>ceedings, as they
                    apprehend may be usefully<lb/>distributed amongst our members.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>


            <div type="narrative">
                <pb n="9" facs="SW_BYM1806_009"/>
                <head>A BRIEF ACCOUNT<lb/>OF THE<lb/>PROCEEDINGS OF THE <orgName key="bymindian"
                        >COMMITTEE</orgName><lb/>APPOINTED BY THE<lb/><orgName key="bym">YEARLY
                        MEEITNG OF FRIENDS<lb/>HELD IN BALTIMORE</orgName>,<lb/>For Promoting the
                    Improvement and Civilization<lb/>of Indian Natives.</head>
                <p>A weighty concern having been opened in<lb/>the year <date when="1795"
                        >1795</date> in our <orgName key="bym">Yearly Meeting</orgName>,
                    re-<lb/>specting the difficulties and distresses to which<lb/>the Indian natives
                    of this land were subject, it<lb/>obtained the serious attention of Friends;
                    and<lb/>many observations were made, relative to the<lb/>kindness of their
                    ancestors to ours in the early<lb/>settlement of this country; exciting a deep
                    con-<lb/>sideration and enquiry, whether, under the in-<lb/>fluence of that
                    exalted benevolence and good<lb/><pb n="10" facs="SW_BYM1806_010"/>will to men, which our holy
                    profession incul-<lb/>cates, there was not something for us, as a<lb/>Society,
                    to do for them; towards their promoting their<lb/>religious instruction, and
                    knowledge of agricul-<lb/>ture, and useful mechanic arts.</p>
                <p>A solemnity prevailing, the sentiments of<lb/>many were expressed, evidencing a
                    near sym-<lb/>pathy with them. The meeting therefore united<lb/>in recommending
                    to our Quarterly and Monthly<lb/>Meetings, to open subscriptions amongst
                    our<lb/>members for their relief; and appointed a <orgName key="bymindian"
                        >com-<lb/>mittee</orgName>, to pay such attention to the
                    interesting<lb/>concern, as they might be enabled to render.</p>
                <p>The <orgName key="bymindian">committee</orgName>, after having fully
                    considered<lb/>the subject of their appointment, concluded, as<lb/>the most
                    effectual way of obtaining correct in-<lb/>formation of the situation and
                    disposition of the<lb/>Indians, to appoint a deputation from
                    amongst<lb/>themselves, to visit the <orgName key="shawnee">Shawnees</orgName>,
                        <orgName key="delaware">Delawares</orgName>,<lb/><orgName key="wyandot"
                        >Wyandots</orgName>, or other such nations, north-west of<lb/>the <geogName
                        key="ohior">river Ohio</geogName>, as they might find practicable.<lb/>The
                    friends who were nominated to this service,<lb/>having first obtained the
                    approbation of Govern-<lb/>ment, proceeded in the summer of <date when="1796"
                        >1796</date>, as far<lb/>as the forks of the <geogName key="muski">Muskingum
                        river</geogName>, at which<lb/>place, they had been informed that a
                    consider-<lb/>able number of Indians were collected; but<lb/><pb n="11" facs="SW_BYM1806_011"/>upon
                    their arrival there, they found that all the<lb/>chiefs, and most of the
                    hunters, had dispersed.<lb/>And, it not appearing practicable to
                    convene<lb/>them in a suitable manner for a conference at<lb/>that time, they
                    returned without accomplishing<lb/>the object of their visit. They however
                    saw<lb/>divers hunters and others, who appeared to be<lb/>well disposed to
                    receive the instruction and<lb/>assistance, with which Friends proposed to
                    fur-<lb/>nish them.</p>
                <p>The <orgName key="bymindian">committee</orgName> being still deficient in
                    the<lb/>information necessary to enable them to pro-<lb/>ceed with safety, in so
                    important an undertaking,<lb/>one of their number offered, in the fall of
                    this<lb/>year, to undertake a visit to the Indians, for the<lb/>purpose of
                    obtaining a more satisfactory know-<lb/>ledge respecting them; and his proposal
                    being<lb/>approved, he was encouraged to proceed as<lb/>soon as might be
                    practicable. Accordingly, in<lb/>the spring of <date when="1797">1797</date>,
                    he, with two others of the<lb/>committee, who became concerned to unite<lb/>with
                    him, made them a visit; in the course of<lb/>which, having passed by a number of
                    their<lb/>hunting camps, and several of their towns, they<lb/>had large
                    opportunity of discovering their situ-<lb/>ation. Often exposed to the
                    inclemency of the<lb/>seasons, with a very precarious, and often a<lb/>very
                    scanty supply of food and clothing, they<lb/><pb n="12" facs="SW_BYM1806_012"/>suffered all the
                    miseries of extreme poverty; in a<lb/>country, which, from its great fertility,
                    would,<lb/>with but little cultivation, abundantly supply<lb/>them with all the
                    necessaries of life.</p>
                <p>These friends had an opportunity with some<lb/>of they chiefs and hunters of the
                        <orgName key="wyandot">Wyandot</orgName>, and<lb/><orgName key="delaware"
                        >Delaware</orgName> nations, in which they informed them<lb/>of the concern
                    of Friends relative to them; and<lb/>endeavoured to impress on their minds, the
                    ad-<lb/>vantages they would derive, from permitting a<lb/>knowledge of
                    agriculture, and some of the most<lb/>useful mechanic arts, to be introduced
                    amongst<lb/>their people. The Indians appeared to give close<lb/>attention to
                    the communication, and promised<lb/>to lay the matter before their grand
                    council, and<lb/>inform us of their conclusion upon the subject.</p>
                <p>No way opened during the year <date when="1798">1798</date>, to<lb/>proceed in
                    carrying the concern of the <orgName key="bym">Yearly<lb/>Meeting</orgName> into
                    effect; except that the committee<lb/>furnished a few implements of husbandry,
                    and<lb/>other assistance to some Indian families, which<lb/>were situated upon
                    the branches of the <geogName key="tuscr">Tus-<lb/>karawas</geogName> river.</p>
                <p>In the <date when="1799-02">Second Month, 1799</date>, the <orgName
                        key="bymindian">committee</orgName><lb/>received a speech, and a belt of the
                    Wampum, from<lb/><persName key="tarh1">Tarhie</persName>, the principal chief of
                    the <orgName key="wyandot">Wyandot</orgName> nation,<lb/><pb n="13" facs="SW_BYM1806_013"/>delivered
                    at <placeName key="detro">Detroit</placeName>, in the <date when="1798-09">Ninth
                        Month</date> pre-<lb/>ceding; of which the following is an extract:</p>
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body><dateline><date when="1798-09"/></dateline>
                        <p>Brethren Quakers,<lb/>You remember that we once met a cer-<lb/>tain
                            place. When we had there met, a great<lb/>many good things were said,
                            and much friend-<lb/>ship was professed between us.</p>
                        <p>Brothers,<lb/>You told us that at the time, that you not only<lb/>took us
                            by the hand, but that you held us fast<lb/>by the arm: that you then
                            formed a chain of<lb/>friendship. You said, that it was not a chain
                            of<lb/>iron; but that it was a chain of precious metal,<lb/>a chain of
                            silver, that would never get rusty; and<lb/>that this chain, would bind
                            us in brotherly affec-<lb/>tion for ever.</p>
                        <p>Brethren, listen:<lb/>We have often heard that you were a good<lb/>and a
                            faithful people, ever ready to do justice,<lb/>and good to all men,
                            without distinction of co-<lb/>lour; therefore we love you the more
                            sincerely,<lb/>because of the goodness of your hearts, which<lb/>has
                            been talked of amongst our nations, long<lb/>since.</p>
                        <p>Brethren, listen:<lb/>You have informed us, that you intend to<lb/><pb n="14" facs="SW_BYM1806_014"/>
                            visit us; yes, that, even in our tents and cabins,<lb/>you
                            will take us by the hand. You, brethren,<lb/>cannot admit a doubt that
                            we should be very<lb/>happy to see you.</p>
                        <p>Brethren, listen:<lb/>It is but proper to inform you at this
                            time,<lb/>that when you do come forward to see us, you<lb/>will, no
                            doubt, pass by my place of residence<lb/>at <placeName key="sand"
                                >Sandusky</placeName>. I will then take you, not only<lb/>by the
                            hand, but by the arm, and will conduct<lb/>you safely to the grand
                            council-fire of our great<lb/>Sasteretsey; where all good things are
                            trans-<lb/>acted, and where nothing bad is permitted to<lb/>appear. When
                            in the grand council of our<lb/>Sasteretsey, we will then sit down
                            together, in<lb/>peace and friendship, as brethren are accus-<lb/>tomed
                            to do, after a long absence; and remind<lb/>each other, and talk of
                            those things that were<lb/>done between our Good Grand-Fathers,
                            when<lb/>they first met upon our lands, upon this great<lb/>island.</p>
                        <p>Brethren,<lb/>May the Great Spirit, the master of light<lb/>and life, so
                            dispose the hearts and minds of all<lb/>our nations and people, that the
                            calamities of<lb/>war may never more be felt, or known by any<lb/><pb n="15" facs="SW_BYM1806_015"/>
                               of them; that our roads and paths may never<lb/>more be
                            stained with the blood of our young<lb/>warriors; and that our helpless
                            women and chil-<lb/>dren may live in peace and happiness.</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>After a consideration of the foregoing com-<lb/>munication, from the <orgName
                        key="wyandot">Wyandot</orgName> Nation of Indians,<lb/>the <orgName
                        key="bymindian">committee</orgName> concluded to appoint a few<lb/>friends
                    to make them a visit, agreeably to their<lb/>request. These were directed to
                    cultivate a<lb/>friendly correspondence with them, and afford<lb/>them such
                    assistance as they might be enabled<lb/>to render. They accordingly proceeded in
                    the<lb/>visit; with an intention of being at the General<lb/>Council; and after
                    passing through several of<lb/>their towns, arrived on the <date
                        when="1799-06-03">Third of the Sixth<lb/>Month</date> at <placeName
                        key="usand">Upper Sandusky</placeName>, the principal vil-<lb/>lage of the
                        <orgName key="wyandot">Wyandots</orgName>, where they were received<lb/>in a
                    friendly manner, by <persName key="tarh1">Tarhie (the Crane)</persName>,<lb/>and
                    others of that nation.</p>
                <p> Upon conferring with these Indians, it was<lb/>found, that a mistake had been
                    made in the<lb/>translation of the speech, which they had sent<lb/>to friends,
                    respecting the time of opening their<lb/>great Council, to which Friends had
                    been invited:<lb/>who were now informed, that it began annually<lb/>at the full
                    moon, in the Sixth Month. Finding<lb/><pb n="16" facs="SW_BYM1806_016"/>it would be difficult to
                    procure food for them-<lb/>selves and horses there, until that time, the
                        <orgName key="bymindian">com-<lb/>mittee</orgName> concluded it was best,
                    under their present<lb/>circumstances, to propose to <persName key="tarh1"
                        >Tarhie</persName>, a con-<lb/>terence with him and the other chiefs,
                    who<lb/>were then at, and in the neighborhood of, <placeName key="sand"
                        >San-<lb/>dusky</placeName>: which was accordingly agreed to; and<lb/>at the
                    time appointed, they met him and several<lb/>other chiefs, together with a
                    number of their<lb/>hunters, at his own house; when they had a<lb/>full
                    opportunity with them on the subject of<lb/>their visit.</p>
                <p>Their communication appeared to be received<lb/>with great satisfaction by the
                    Indians; who<lb/>in their answer, delivered on some strings of<lb/>Wampum,
                    expressed the gratitude they felt, for<lb/>the care and friendship which their
                    beloved<lb/>brethren, the Quakers, had always manifested<lb/>for the Indians;
                    and promised, as soon as the<lb/>grand Council met, that they would
                    communi-<lb/>cate fully to it, the concern which our Society<lb/>felt for their
                    improvement, and inform us by a<lb/>written speech of their conclusion
                    thereon.</p>
                <p>Whilst these friends were at <placeName key="sand">Sandusky</placeName>
                    and<lb/>other villages, their minds were often deeply<lb/>affected, under the
                    sorrowful consideration of<lb/>the baneful effects of spirituous liquor
                    upon<lb/><pb n="17" facs="SW_BYM1806_017"/>the Indians, at that time supplied with it, in
                    al-<lb/><lb/>most every village, by Canadian traders residing<lb/>amongst them:
                    and they were confirmed in the<lb/>opinion, that unless these traders could be
                    res-<lb/>trained from furnishing them with this destruc-<lb/>tive article, in
                    exchange for their skins and furs,<lb/>they would not easily be persuade to turn
                    their<lb/>minds towards agriculture and the useful arts.</p>
                <p>Notwithstanding which discouragement, the<lb/>great affection they have for our
                    Society, mani-<lb/>fested on all occasions whilst the <orgName key="bymindian"
                        >committee</orgName> were<lb/> amongst them, induced a hope, that
                    Friends<lb/> would endeavour to keep under the weight of<lb/>the concern; and be
                    prepared to proceed in the<lb/>benevolent work, whenever way might open
                    for<lb/>further service amongst them.</p>
                <p>There was not any communication between<lb/>the <orgName key="bymindian"
                        >committee</orgName> and the Indians during the year<lb/><date when="1800"
                        >1800</date>. In the spring of <date when="1801">1801</date>, they addressed
                    a<lb/>letter to them, which was forwarded to <placeName key="sand"
                        >San-<lb/>dusky</placeName>; but the person to whose care it
                    was<lb/>directed, and who was requested to communi-<lb/>cate it to their council
                    in the Sixth Month, not<lb/>being at home, it was returned to the <orgName
                        key="bymindian">committee</orgName>.</p>
                <p>In the <date when="1802-06">Sixth Month, 1802</date>, the <persName key="lturt1"
                        >Little Turtle</persName>,<lb/><persName key="fmeda1">Five
                            Medals</persName>, and several other principal chiefs,<lb/><pb n="18" facs="SW_BYM1806_018"/>of the
                        <orgName key="miami">Miami</orgName> and <orgName key="potaw"
                        >Pottowattomi</orgName> nations of Indians,<lb/>passed through <placeName
                        key="balt1">Baltimore</placeName>, on their way to visit<lb/>the President
                    of the United States; at which<lb/>time the <orgName key="bymindian"
                        >committee</orgName> took the opportunity of<lb/>holding a conference with
                    them; in which the<lb/>concern of Friends was fully opened; when<lb/>they
                    informed them, of the great discouragement<lb/>Friends had met with, in carrying
                    their views<lb/>into effect, from the intemperate and destructive<lb/>use of
                    spirituous liquors amongst the Indians:<lb/>which was found to be the greatest
                    obstacle in<lb/>the way of their profiting by the aid which<lb/>Friends had been
                    desirous of giving them.</p>
                <p>This opened the way for free communica-<lb/>tion, on the subject of the
                    introduction of ardent<lb/>spirits into their country; in which its
                    baneful<lb/>and pernicious effects were strongly pointed out.<lb/>The <persName
                        key="lturt1">Little Turtle</persName>, in reply, made a very
                    pathe-<lb/>ticand impressive speech upon this subject, from<lb/>which the
                    following in extracted.</p>
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body><dateline><date when="1802-06"/></dateline>
                        <p>Brothers and Friends,<lb/>When our forefathers first met on
                            this<lb/>island, your Red Brethren were very numerous.<lb/>But since the
                            introduction amongst us, of what<lb/>you call spirituous liquors, and
                            what we think<lb/>may justly be called Poison, our numbers
                            are<lb/>greatly diminished. It has destroyed a great<lb/>part of your
                            Red Brethren.</p>
                        <pb n="19" facs="SW_BYM1806_019"/>
                        <p>My Brothers and Friends,<lb/>We plainly perceive, that you see the
                            very<lb/>evil which destroys your Red Brethren. It is<lb/>not an evil of
                            our own making. We have not<lb/>placed it amongst ourselves. It is an
                            evil placed<lb/>amongst us by the white people. We look to<lb/>them to
                            remove it out of our country. We tell<lb/>them, Brethren, fetch us
                            useful things; bring<lb/>goods that will clothe us, our women, and
                            our<lb/>children; and not this evil liquor, that destroys<lb/>our
                            reason, that destroys our health, that de-<lb/>stroys our lives. But all
                            we can say on this<lb/>subject, is of no service, nor gives relief to
                            your<lb/>Red Brethren.</p>
                        <p>My Brothers and Friends,<lb/>I rejoice to find, that you agree in
                            opinion<lb/>with us, and express an anxiety to be, if pos-<lb/>sible, of
                            service to us, in removing this great<lb/>evil out of our country: an
                            evil which has had<lb/>so much room in it, and has destroyed so
                            many<lb/>of our lives, that it causes our young men to<lb/>say, <said>We
                                had better be at war with the white<lb/>people. This liquor, which
                                they introduce into<lb/>our country, is more to be feared than the
                                gun<lb/>and the tomahawk. There are more of us dead<lb/>since the
                                treaty of <placeName key="greenv">Greenville</placeName>, than we
                                lost by<lb/>the six years of war before. It is all owing to
                                the<lb/>introduction of this liquor amongst us.</said></p>
                        <pb n="20" facs="SW_BYM1806_020"/>
                        <p>Brothers,<lb/>When our young men have been out hunt-<lb/>ing, and are
                            returning home loaded with skins<lb/>and furs; on their way, if it
                            happens that they<lb/>come where some of this whiskey is
                            deposited,<lb/>the white man who sells it, tells them to take
                            a<lb/>little drink. Some of them will say No, I do<lb/>not want it. They
                            go on till they come to ano-<lb/>ther house, where they find more of the
                            same<lb/>kind of drink. It is there offered again; they<lb/>refuse; and
                            again the third time; but finally,<lb/>the fourth or fifth time, one
                            accepts of it, and<lb/>takes a drink; and getting one, he wants
                            ano-<lb/>ther; and then a third, and fourth, till his senses<lb/>have
                            left him. After his reason comes back<lb/>again to him; when he gets up,
                            and finds where<lb/>he is, he asks for his peltry. The answer
                                is,<lb/><said>You have drunk them.</said>
                            <said>Where is my gun?</said><lb/><said>It is gone.</said>
                            <said>Where is my blanket?</said>
                            <said>It is<lb/>gone.</said>
                            <said>Where is my shirt?</said>
                            <said>You have sold<lb/>it for whiskey!!</said> Now, Brothers, figure to
                            your-<lb/>selves what condition this man must be in. He<lb/>has a family
                            at home; a wife and children, who<lb/>stand in need of the profits of
                            his hunting. What<lb/>must be their wants, when he himself is
                            even<lb/>without a shirt!</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <pb n="21" facs="SW_BYM1806_021"/>
                <p>These chiefs appeared to be much rejoiced at<lb/>the assistance, Friends proposed
                    to render them;<lb/>and, in reply to that part of our
                    communication,<lb/>observed, <said>That it was their anxious wish, to<lb/>engage
                        in the culture of their lands; for although<lb/>the game was not so scarce,
                        but that they could<lb/>get enough to eat; yet they were sensible it
                        was<lb/>daily diminishing, and that the time was not far<lb/>distant, when
                        they should be compelled to take<lb/>hold of such tools, as they saw in the
                        hands<lb/>of the white people.</said></p>
                <p>The <orgName key="bymindian">committee</orgName>, on a weighty consideration
                    of<lb/>the subject, being from their former experience<lb/>united in judgment,
                    that no great progress could<lb/>be made in the civilization of the Indians,
                    while<lb/>they were so abundantly supplied with distilled<lb/>spirits, concluded
                    to address Congress on the<lb/>subject. Their memorial was favourably
                    re-<lb/>ceived, and a law passed, which in some mea-<lb/>sure provided a remedy
                    for the evil.</p>
                <p>As it now appeared to the <orgName key="bymindian">committee</orgName>, that
                    the<lb/>principal obstruction to the introduction of agri-<lb/>culture amongst
                    the Indians was removed, they<lb/>felt themselves encouraged to proceed in
                    their<lb/>undertaking; and accordingly provided a con-<lb/>siderable number of
                    implements of husbandry;<lb/>such as ploughs, hoes, axes &amp;c. which were
                    for-<lb/><pb n="22" facs="SW_BYM1806_022"/>warded to <placeName key="fwayn"
                    >Fort-Wayne</placeName>, where they were imme-<lb/>diately distributed, as a
                    present from the society<lb/>of Friends, and thankfully received by
                    the<lb/>Indians.</p>
                <p>A letter was received in the summer of <date when="1803">1803</date>,<lb/>from
                    the agent for Indian affairs at <placeName key="fwayn"
                    >Fort-Wayne</placeName>,<lb/>in which he says:—</p>
                <p><said>Since there have been no spirituous liquors<lb/>in the Indian country, they
                        appear very indus-<lb/>trious, and are fond of raising stock.</said> He
                    also<lb/>expressed, as his opinion, that <said>the suppression<lb/>of spirituous
                        liquors in that country is the most<lb/>beneficial thing which has ever been
                        done for<lb/>them by the United States; that there had not<lb/>been one
                        Indian killed in that neighbourhood for<lb/>a year; and that in no preceding
                        year, since the<lb/>treaty of <placeName key="greenv"
                        >Greenville</placeName>, had there been less than<lb/>ten, and in some
                        years, as many as thirty, killed.</said><lb/>The agent further added, that
                        <said>the Indians<lb/>appeared to be very desirous of procuring
                        for<lb/>themselves the necessaries of life, in our way;<lb/>but say they do
                        not know how to begin. Some<lb/>of their old men say, <q>The white people
                            want<lb/>for nothing. We wish them to shew us how<lb/>to provide the
                            many good things we see amongst<lb/>them. If it is their wish to
                            instruct us in their<lb/>way of living, as they tell us it is, we
                            wish<lb/><pb n="23" facs="SW_BYM1806_023"/>them to make haste and do it, for we are
                            old,<lb/>and must die soon; but we wish to see our<lb/>women and
                            children in that path, that will lead<lb/>them to happiness, before we
                            die.</q></said></p>
                <p>At the same time a letter was received from<lb/>the <persName key="lturt1">Little
                        Turtle</persName> and <persName key="fmeda1">Five Medals</persName>, in
                    which<lb/>they expressed a wish, that some of the <orgName key="bymindian"
                        >com-<lb/>mittee</orgName> would visit their country; which
                    being<lb/>considered, the <orgName key="bymindian">committee</orgName> appointed
                    a depu-<lb/>tation for that purpose; who were authorized<lb/>to take one or more
                    suitable persons with them,<lb/>to reside amongst the Indians, for the
                    purpose<lb/>of teaching them agriculture, and other useful<lb/>knowledge; as far
                    as such an establishment<lb/>should appear practicable.</p>
                <p>In the <date when="1804-02">Second Month, 1804</date>, two of the<lb/>deputation
                    proceeded to <placeName key="fwayn">Fort-Wayne</placeName>, accom-<lb/>panied by
                        <persName key="pdeni1">Philip Dennis</persName>; who had offered
                    his<lb/>services to go with them, to remain with the<lb/>Indians during the
                    summer; for the purpose of<lb/>instructing them in husbandry; taking with
                    him<lb/>two horses to be employed in ploughing, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>They arrived at <placeName key="fwayn">Fort-Wayne</placeName> the <date
                        when="1804-03-31">last day<lb/>of the Third Month</date>, and soon after
                    convened<lb/>several of the principal chiefs; in a council with<lb/><pb n="24" facs="SW_BYM1806_024"/>whom, a future day was fixed upon for the<lb/><orgName key="bymindian"
                        >committee</orgName> to meet them, together with as many<lb/>of their old
                    men, their young men, and their<lb/>women and children, as could be assembled.
                    The<lb/>attendance of the latter was particularly re-<lb/>quested by our
                    deputation; and these chiefs<lb/>having previously requested, that whatever
                    mat-<lb/>ter Friends might have to communicate to the<lb/>Indians should be
                    written, in order that they<lb/>might lay it before the Grand Council,
                    in<lb/>the <date when="1804-06">Sixth Month</date> following (to the
                    attendance<lb/>of which they very pressingly invited the com-<lb/>mittee), on
                    the day appointed, the committee<lb/>being met by a considerable number of the
                    na-<lb/>tives, the following written address was read<lb/>and interpreted to
                    them.</p>
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body><dateline><date when="1804-06"/></dateline>
                        <p>Brothers and Friends,<lb/>When we were together, eight days ago,<lb/>with
                            the <persName key="lturt1">Little Turtle</persName> and the <persName
                                key="fmeda1">Five Medals</persName>, the<lb/>letter was read to them
                            which has just been<lb/>read. That letter, you observe, says, that
                            we<lb/>were appointed by the people called <orgName key="bym"
                                >Quakers<lb/>of Baltimore</orgName>, to visit you, and to take you
                            by<lb/>the hand on their behalf, desiring that you<lb/>would receive any
                            communications from us, as<lb/>coming immediately from them.</p>
                        <pb n="25" facs="SW_BYM1806_025"/>
                        <p>Brothers,<lb/>After that letter was read, our hearts were<lb/>filled with
                            so much love for our Red Brethren,<lb/>that, on looking over and
                            considering the busi-<lb/>ness upon which we had come, we felt a
                            desire<lb/>to see as many of you together as could be<lb/>convened: and
                            this day was then agreed upon,<lb/>for us to meet you.</p>
                        <p>Brothers,<lb/>We believed, that the things we had to<lb/>say, were of
                            great importance to our Red Bre-<lb/>thren; and therefore it was that we
                            requested to<lb/>see you together; that you all might have
                            an<lb/>opportunity of hearing what we have to say.</p>
                        <p>Brothers,<lb/>Our hearts are filled with thankfulness to<lb/>the Great
                            Spirit, that he has brought us safely<lb/>to the country of our Red
                            Brethren, and pro-<lb/>tected us through our journey. We also
                            rejoice<lb/>that he has given us this opportunity of seeing<lb/>you, and
                            of taking you by the hand.</p>
                        <p>Brothers,<lb/>It is now a little more than two years since<lb/>your
                            brothers of <placeName key="balt1">Baltimore</placeName> had an
                            opportunity<lb/>of becoming acquainted with the <persName key="fmeda1"
                                >Five Medals</persName>, the<lb/><persName key="lturt1">Little
                                Turtle</persName>, <persName key="topin1">Tuthinipee</persName>, and
                            some other chiefs.<lb/><pb n="26" facs="SW_BYM1806_026"/>They were glad of that opportunity of
                            having a<lb/>talking with them, and of enquiring after the<lb/>situation
                            of their Red Brethren.</p>
                        <p>Brothers,<lb/>We had for some time entertained appre-<lb/>hensions, that
                            the many changes, which were<lb/>taking place in circumstances, must
                            greatly<lb/>change the situation of our Red Brethren; and<lb/>that the
                            time was fast approaching, in which it<lb/>would be necessary for them
                            to alter their mode<lb/>of living.</p>
                        <p>Brothers,<lb/>After our talk with the chiefs whom we<lb/>have just
                            mentioned, we are fully convinced<lb/>that the time was come, in which
                            our Red Bre-<lb/>thren ought to begin to cultivate their lands.<lb/>That
                            they ought to raise corn, and other grain,<lb/>also horses, cows, sheep,
                            hogs, and other ani-<lb/>mal. We then proposed to afford them
                            some<lb/>assistance. They appeared to be glad of the<lb/>proposal, and
                            informed us that many of their<lb/>people were disposed to turn their
                            attention to<lb/>the cultivation of the earth. They also ex-<lb/>pressed
                            a desire to be assisted by their brothers<lb/>of <placeName key="balt1"
                                >Baltimore</placeName>.</p>
                        <pb n="27" facs="SW_BYM1806_027"/>
                        <p>Brothers,<lb/>Having been encouraged by the opportu-<lb/>nity which we
                            then had, we sent to the care of<lb/>the agent for Indian affairs, some
                            ploughs, har-<lb/>ness for horses, axes, hoes, and other
                            imple-<lb/>ments of husbandry, which were made for the<lb/>use of our
                            Red Brethren; and desired that they<lb/>might be distributed amongst
                            them, as tokens<lb/>of our friendship.</p>
                        <p>Brothers,<lb/>We received last fall, through the hands<lb/>of the agent
                            for Indian affairs, a talk from the<lb/><persName key="lturt1">Little
                                Turtle</persName>, the <persName key="fmeda1">Five
                            Medals</persName>, and others, in-<lb/>forming us that they had received
                            the imple-<lb/>ments of husbandry; and requesting that
                            their<lb/>brothers of <placeName key="balt1">Baltimore</placeName> would
                            send some of their<lb/>people into the country of their Red
                            Brethren;<lb/>for the purpose of seeing their situation, and<lb/>shewing
                            them how to make use of the tools:<lb/>saying, they did not know how to
                            begin.</p>
                        <p>Brothers,<lb/>It is for these purposes, that we have now<lb/>come; and we
                            again repeat, that we rejoice we<lb/>have this opportunity of seeing
                            you, and of<lb/>taking you by the hand.</p>
                        <pb n="28" facs="SW_BYM1806_028"/>
                        <p>Brothers,<lb/>In coming into the country of our Red<lb/>Brethren, we have
                            come with our eyes open.<lb/>And although we are affected with sorrow,
                            in<lb/>believing, that many of the red people suffer<lb/>much, for the
                            want of food, and for the want<lb/>of clothing; yet our hearts have been
                            made<lb/>glad, in seeing, that it has pleased the Great<lb/>Spirit, to
                            give you a rich and valuable country.<lb/>Because we know, that it is
                            out of the earth, that<lb/>food and clothing come. We are sure,
                            bro-<lb/>thers, that, with but little labour and attention,<lb/>you may
                            raise much more corn, and other grain,<lb/>than will be necessary for
                            yourselves, your wo-<lb/>men, and children; and may also, with
                            great<lb/>ease, raise many more horses, cows, sheep,<lb/>hogs, and other
                            valuable animals, than will be<lb/>necessary for your own use. We are
                            also con-<lb/>fident, that if you will pursue our method, in<lb/>the
                            cultivation of your land, you will live in<lb/>much greater ease and
                            plenty, and with much<lb/>less fatigue and toil, than attend hunting for
                            a<lb/>subsistence.</p>
                        <p>Brothers,<lb/>We are fully convinced, that if you will<lb/>adopt our mode
                            of cultivating the earth, and of<lb/>raising useful animals, you will
                            find it to be a<lb/>mode of living not only far more plentiful
                            and<lb/><pb n="29" facs="SW_BYM1806_029"/>much less fatiguing; but also much more
                            cer-<lb/>tain, and which will expose your bodies less, to<lb/>the
                            inclemencies of the weather, than hunting.<lb/>It will lead you,
                            brothers, to have fixed homes.<lb/>You will build comfortable
                            dwelling-houses for<lb/>yourselves, you women, and children,
                            where<lb/>you may be sheltered from the rain, from the<lb/>frost, and
                            from the snow; and where you may<lb/>enjoy in plenty the rewards of your
                            labours.</p>
                        <p>Brothers,<lb/>In laying these things before you, we have<lb/>no other
                            motive, than a desire of heart for the<lb/>improvement, the benefit, and
                            the welfare of<lb/>our Red Brethren; and therefore it is, that
                            we<lb/>speak with freedom; and we hope that what we<lb/>have to say,
                            will go in at one ear, and not come<lb/>out at the other; but that it
                            will be remembered<lb/>by our Red Brethren. For we know,
                            brothers,<lb/>that we shall not be ashamed of what we say,<lb/>when in
                            time to come, you compare the things<lb/>we are saying to you, with your
                            experience in<lb/>practising them.</p>
                        <p>Brothers,<lb/>We will here mention, that the time was,<lb/>when the
                            forefathers of your brothers, the white<lb/>people, lived beyond the
                            great water, in the<lb/>same manner that our Red Brethren now
                            live.<lb/><pb n="30" facs="SW_BYM1806_030"/>The winters can yet be counted, when they
                            went<lb/>almost naked, when they procured their living<lb/>by fishing,
                            and by the bow and arrow in hunt-<lb/>ing; and when they lived in houses
                            no better<lb/>than yours. They were encouraged by some,<lb/>who came
                            from towards the sun-rising, and<lb/>lived amongst them, to change their
                            mode<lb/>of living. They did change; they cultivated the<lb/>earth; and
                            we are sure the change was a happy<lb/>one.</p>
                        <p>Brothers and Friends,<lb/>We are not ashamed to acknowledge, that<lb/>the
                            time was, when our forefathers rejoiced at<lb/>finding a wild plum-tree,
                            or at killing a little<lb/>game, and that they wandered up and
                            down,<lb/>living on the uncertain supplies of fishing and<lb/>hunting.
                            But, brothers, for your encourage-<lb/>ment, we now mention, that by
                            turning their<lb/>attention to the cultivation of the earth,
                            instead<lb/>of the plum-tree, they soon had orchards, of<lb/>many kinds
                            of good fruit; instead of the wild<lb/>game, they soon had large numbers
                            of cattle,<lb/>horses, sheep, hogs, and other valuable ani-<lb/>mal; an
                            in many places, instead of their fo-<lb/>rests, they had large fields of
                            corn and of other<lb/>grain, as also of many other valuable
                            produc-<lb/>tions of the earth.</p>
                        <pb n="31" facs="SW_BYM1806_031"/>
                        <p>Brothers,<lb/>We hope your eyes will be open, to see<lb/>clearly the
                            things which are best for you; and<lb/>that you will desire to pursue
                            them. We be-<lb/>lieve, brothers, that it is in the heart of
                            your<lb/>father, the President of the United States, to<lb/>assist his
                            Red children, in the cultivation of the<lb/>earth; and to render them
                            services, which will<lb/>be greatly for their benefit and welfare.
                            We<lb/>hope that your exertions to change your present<lb/>mode of
                            living, will be so plain to him, that he<lb/>will see them. This will
                            encourage him to con-<lb/>tinue to aid you, in your endeavours.</p>
                        <p>Brothers,<lb/>We have spoken plainly; we desire to<lb/>speak plain. We
                            will now tell you, that we<lb/>have not come merely to talk with you.
                            We<lb/>have come prepared to render you a little assist-<lb/>ance. Our
                            believed brother, <persName key="pdeni1">Philip Dennis</persName>,
                            <lb/>who is now present, has come along with us.<lb/>His desire to
                            cultivate for you, a field of corn;<lb/>also to show you how to raise
                            some of the other<lb/>productions of the earth. He knows how to<lb/>use
                            the plough, the hoe, the axe, and other<lb/>implements of husbandry.</p>
                        <p>Brothers,<lb/>We will here ask you, Are you still desi-<lb/><pb n="32" facs="SW_BYM1806_032"/>rous to be instructed by us, in the cultivation of<lb/>your lands? If
                            you say, you are; our brother,<lb/>whom we have just mentioned, will
                            continue<lb/>with you, during the summer. We shall leave<lb/>it to you,
                            to shew him the spot where to begin<lb/>to work.</p>
                        <p>Brothers,<lb/>He has left a farm; he has left a wife, and<lb/>five small
                            children, who are very dear to him;<lb/>he has come from a sincere
                            desire to be useful<lb/>to our Red Brethren. His motives are pure;
                            he<lb/>will ask no reward from you, for his services;<lb/>his greatest
                            reward will be, in the satisfaction he<lb/>will feel, in finding you
                            inclined to take hold of<lb/>the same tools which he takes hold of; to
                            re-<lb/>chive from him instruction in the cultivation of<lb/>your lands,
                            and to pursue the example he will<lb/>set you.</p>
                        <p>Brothers,<lb/>We hope, you will make the situation of<lb/>our brother as
                            comfortable as circumstances<lb/>will admit. We hope, also, that many of
                            your<lb/>young men will be willing to be taught by him,<lb/>to use the
                            plough, the hoe, and other imple-<lb/>mets of husbandry. For we are
                            sure, brothers,<lb/>that as you take hold of such tools, as are
                            in<lb/>the hands of the white people, you will find<lb/><pb n="33" facs="SW_BYM1806_033"/>them
                            to be to you, like having additional hands.<lb/>You will also find, that
                            by using them, they<lb/>will enable you to do many things, which,
                            with-<lb/>out them, cannot be performed.</p>
                        <p>Brothers,<lb/>There is one thing more, which we wish to<lb/>add. The
                            white people, in order to get their<lb/>land cultivated, find it
                            necessary, that their<lb/>young men should be employed in it, and
                            not<lb/>their women. Women are less than men. They<lb/>are not as strong
                            as men. They are not as<lb/>able to endure fatigue and toil as men. It
                            is<lb/>the business of our women, to be employed in<lb/>our houses, to
                            keep them clean, to sew, knit,<lb/>spin, and weave; to dress food for
                            themselves<lb/>and families; to make clothes for the men and<lb/>the
                            rest of their families, to keep the clothing<lb/>of their families
                            clean, and to take care of their<lb/>children.</p>
                        <p>Brothers,<lb/>We desire not to mention too many things<lb/>to you; but we
                            must add a little further. We<lb/>are fully convinced, that if you will
                            turn your<lb/>attention to the cultivation of the earth, to<lb/>raising
                            the different kinds of grain, to erecting<lb/>mills for grinding grain,
                            to building comfortable<lb/>dwelling-houses for your families, to
                            raising<lb/><pb n="34" facs="SW_BYM1806_034"/>useful animals; amongst others, sheep, for
                            the<lb/>advantage of the wool, in making clothing; and to<lb/>raising
                            flax and hemp, for your linen; and if<lb/>your young women learn to
                            spin, and weave;<lb/>that your lives will be much easier, and
                            hap-<lb/>pier, than at present; and that your numbers<lb/>will increase,
                            and not continue to diminish. As<lb/>we before observed, brothers, your
                            land is<lb/>good. It is far better than the land, the white<lb/>people
                            near the great water cultivate. We are<lb/>persuaded, that your land
                            will produce double<lb/>the quantity of any kind of grain, or of flax,
                            or<lb/>hemp, with the same labour necessary near<lb/>the great
                            water.</p>
                        <p>Brothers and Friends,<lb/>We shall now end what we have to say,
                            with<lb/>informing you, that all the corn, and other pro-<lb/>ductions
                            of the earth, which <persName key="pdeni1">Philip
                            Dennis</persName>,<lb/>may raise, we wish our Red Brethren to
                            accept<lb/>of, as a token of our friendship. And it is our<lb/>desire
                            that the chiefs of the <orgName key="potaw">Pottowattomi</orgName>
                                and<lb/><orgName key="miami">Miami</orgName> nations, who are now
                            present, added to<lb/>our brothers, the <persName key="fmeda1">Five
                                Medals</persName>, <persName key="topin1"
                            >Tuthinipee</persName>,<lb/>and <persName key="pdeni1">Philip
                                Dennis</persName>, make such a distribution<lb/>thereof, as they may
                            think proper.</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>The Indians observed great decorum, and<lb/>gave close attention during the
                    delivery of this<lb/><pb n="35" facs="SW_BYM1806_035"/>address. They respectfully manifested their
                    ap-<lb/>probation of the sentiments it contained, by re-<lb/>iterated
                    exclamations of applause, and the most<lb/>evident demonstrations of
                    satisfaction. In re-<lb/>ply, the <persName key="lturt1">Little
                        Turtle</persName> delivered a speech on be-<lb/>half of the council, from
                    which the following<lb/>is extracted.</p>
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body><dateline><date when="1804-06"/></dateline>
                        <p>Brothers and Friends,<lb/>We rejoice, that the Great Spirit has
                            ap-<lb/>pointed that we should meet this day; for we<lb/>believe, this
                            meeting will be of the utmost con-<lb/>sequence to your Red
                            Brethren.</p>
                        <p>Brothres,<lb/>The things you have said to us, require our<lb/>greatest
                            attention: it is really necessary, that we<lb/> should deliberate upon
                            them. In order to do<lb/> so, we must beg you to leave the paper,
                            upon<lb/>which they are written, that we may communi- <lb/>cate them to
                            our chiefs, when they assemble in<lb/>Grand Council.</p>
                        <p>Brothers,<lb/>You have been very particular in pointing<lb/>out to us,
                            the duties of our women; and you<lb/>have told us, that in adoptting
                            your mode of<lb/>living, our numbers would increase, and not<lb/><pb n="36" facs="SW_BYM1806_036"/>continue to diminish. In all this, I certainly<lb/>agree
                            with you, and I hope my brother chiefs<lb/>will also agree with you.</p>
                        <p>Brothers,<lb/>Assure your people who sent you here,<lb/>tell your old
                            chiefs, that we are obliged to<lb/>them, for their friendly offers to
                            assist us, in<lb/>changing our present mode of living. Tell them,<lb/>it
                            is a great work, that cannot be done immedi-<lb/>ately; but that we are
                            the way disposed, and<lb/>hope it will take place gradually.</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>The <orgName key="bymindian">committee</orgName> remained several weeks
                    a-<lb/>mongst the Indians, during which time, they<lb/>visited a number of their
                    towns and villages, at<lb/>all of which they were received in the
                    most<lb/>friendly and hospitable manner.</p>
                <p>In the course of their journey, they passed<lb/>by a settlement of the <orgName
                        key="wyandot">Wyandots</orgName>, at <placeName key="browt"
                        >Brown’s<lb/>Town</placeName>, or the Rock. They found that the
                    In-<lb/>dians at this place, had, since the visit made by<lb/>Friends to their
                    nation, in the year <date when="1799">1799</date>, ad-<lb/>vanced considerably
                    in agriculture: many of<lb/>them having built comfortable houses, and
                    ac-<lb/>queried a considerable number of cattle, hogs,<lb/>and other domestic
                    animals. And they were in-<lb/>formed from good authority, that the <orgName
                        key="wyandot">Wyandots</orgName>,<lb/>residing at <placeName key="sand"
                        >Sandusky</placeName>, as well as the <orgName key="shawnee"
                            >Shawanees</orgName>,<lb/><pb n="37" facs="SW_BYM1806_037"/>on the <geogName key="augl"
                        >Auglaize</geogName> river, and also since the visit,<lb/>turned their
                    attention very much towards the<lb/>cultivation of their lands. They had
                    therefore<lb/>the satisfaction to remark, that the communi-<lb/>cations from the
                        <orgName key="bymindian">committee</orgName> to these nations;<lb/>and the
                    exertions which had been made, to<lb/>turn their minds to agriculture; although
                    we<lb/>had not been in a situation to extend much<lb/>assistance to them, had
                    not been altogether<lb/>unavailing.</p>
                <p>They also visited the place fixed upon for the<lb/>settlement of <persName
                        key="pdeni1">Philip Dennis</persName>, on the <geogName key="wabas"
                        >Wabash<lb/>river</geogName>, about forty miles south-west of <placeName
                        key="fwayn">Fort-<lb/>Wayne</placeName>; and found its situation to be very
                    ad-<lb/>vantages for farming; the soil appearing to<lb/>be equal in fertility,
                    to any land in the western<lb/>country. To this place there are also two
                    good<lb/>mill-seats adjacent; one on the <geogName key="wabas"
                    >Wabash</geogName>, which<lb/>may be improved without injuring its
                    navigation,<lb/>and the other on a stream which falls into that<lb/>river, about
                    half a mile below</p>
                <p>Soon after their return home, a letter was re-<lb/>ceived by the committee, from
                    the Indian agent<lb/>at <placeName key="fwayn">Fort-Wayne</placeName>, informing
                    them that the Indians<lb/>had held their council in the Sixth
                    Month,<lb/>agreeably to expectation; at which 874 of<lb/>them attended;
                    <said>when the written address of<lb/><pb n="38" facs="SW_BYM1806_038"/><persName key="gelli1"
                            >George Ellicott</persName> and <persName key="ghopk1">Gerard T.
                            Hopkins</persName>, (who<lb/>it appeared had been appointed to visit the
                        In-<lb/>dians on behalf of the Society of Friends,) was<lb/>produced, read,
                        and interpreted to all the diffe-<lb/>rent nations present.</said> In reply
                    to which, divers<lb/>of their chiefs expressed great satisfaction;
                    and<lb/>amongst others <persName key="toeth1">Toethteboxie</persName>, on behalf
                    of the<lb/><orgName key="delaware">Delawares</orgName>, said, <said>For many
                        years before I<lb/>came into the world, the white people have<lb/>been
                        offering to do for us, what is now men-<lb/>tioned; and it appears, that our
                        eyes were never<lb/>opened, until this time. We will now take hold<lb/>of
                        it, and receive it. I am an old man, and<lb/>want to see it before I die. If
                        I once see it,<lb/>I shall die in peace, to think I have left my<lb/>women
                        and children in comfort.</said></p>
                <p>On the return of the friend*, <note resp="author" rend="asterisk">[* <persName key="pdeni1">P.
                            Dennis</persName>, probably.]</note> who went out<lb/>with the <orgName
                        key="bymindian">committee</orgName>, and remained in the Indian<lb/>country,
                    during most of the year <date when="1804">1804</date>, he re-<lb/>ported that he
                    spent the time agreeably with<lb/>them; and was favoured to enjoy a good
                    portion<lb/>of health whilst there. He raised about 400<lb/>bushels of corn,
                    besides a quantity of turnips,<lb/>potatoes, cucumbers, water-melons,
                    pumpkins,<lb/>beans, parsnips, and other garden-vegetables;<lb/>which he
                    directed to be divided amongst the <lb/><pb n="39" facs="SW_BYM1806_039"/> Indians on their return
                    from their hunting<lb/>camps;and left with the family of Indians,<lb/>with whom
                    he resided, upon the farm he had<lb/>cultivated, 23 hogs and pigs, seven of
                    which<lb/>were in good order to kill, and he expected<lb/>would weigh 1500 lb.
                    These he engaged the<lb/>agent to attend to the killing and salting of.<lb/>They
                    were small when brought to the farm in<lb/>the spring, and had no other food
                    than what they<lb/>gathered in the woods.</p>
                <p>With some assistance, which he obtained<lb/>from <placeName key="fwayn"
                        >Fort-Wayne</placeName>, he cleared and enclosed un-<lb/>der a substantial
                    fence twenty acres of ground,<lb/>and built a house, thirty-two feet long and
                    se-<lb/>venteen feet wide, a story and a half high, with<lb/>floors and
                    partition.</p>
                <p>He further reported that the Indians, who<lb/>remained with him, were very
                    industrious, and<lb/>attended to his directions. The young women<lb/>wished to
                    work in preparing the ground and<lb/>attending the corn. From this he dissuaded
                    them;<lb/>and as some spinning-wheels had just arrived at<lb/><placeName
                        key="fwayn">Fort-Wayne</placeName>, which had been sent by Govern-<lb/>ment,
                    he encouraged them to go there, and<lb/>learn to spin and knit, of a white woman
                    who<lb/>happened to be at that place. This they did,<lb/>and soon learned both
                    to spin and knit ; and he<lb/><pb n="40" facs="SW_BYM1806_040"/>left them knitting yarn of their own
                    spinning, when<lb/>he came away.</p>
                <p>He also reported, that a considerable number<lb/>of <orgName key="eel"
                        >Eel-River</orgName> and <orgName key="wea">Weas</orgName> Indians were
                    about to<lb/>settle near the place he cultivated; and that<lb/>previously to his
                    departure, he was with several<lb/>of their principal chiefs; who requested him
                    to<lb/>tell Friends, that they, and the Indians gene-<lb/>rally, were much
                    obliged to them for the assis-<lb/>tance they had given them; and hoped
                    we<lb/>would continue our friendship towards them,<lb/>and that nothing might
                    happen to discourage<lb/>us.</p>
                <p>All the Indians he was amongst, were very<lb/>friendly; as was also the agent and
                    other officers<lb/>of the Government.</p>
                <p>As it appeared that the Indians were very<lb/>desirous of Friends continuing
                    their care to-<lb/>wards them; and sending a person to take the<lb/>place of
                        <persName key="pdeni1">Philip Dennis</persName>. After weightily
                    consider-<lb/>ing the subject, it was concluded to endeavour<lb/>to procure a
                    suitable friend for that purpose;<lb/>but none offering to engage in service,
                    and<lb/>the committee taking into consideration the low<lb/>state of their
                    funds, and the advanced season of<lb/><pb n="41" facs="SW_BYM1806_041"/>the year; together with the
                    dissatisfied and unset-<lb/>tled situation of the Indians at the time, on
                    ac-<lb/>count of a sale of land made by some of the tribes<lb/>to the United
                    States*; <note rend="asterix">*The uneasiness, which this circumstance
                        occasioned<lb/>amongst the Indians has since been entirely removed.</note>
                    thought it might, for the<lb/>present season, be best to write to the
                    agent,<lb/>and request him, to procure for us, the most<lb/>suitable character
                    in his power; who, under his<lb/>direction, should plough the land which
                        <persName key="pdeni1">Philip<lb/>Dennis</persName> cultivated the last
                    season, and plant it<lb/>with corn: in the performance of which it was<lb/>hoped
                    he would be assisted by the Indians.<lb/>We also observed, that after their corn
                    was<lb/>planted, we were willing to believe they would<lb/>be able to manage it
                    themselves. Should a<lb/>second ploughing however be necessary, we<lb/>directed
                    this also to be done. This person was<lb/>also desired to prepare for them a
                    garden of the<lb/>most useful vegetables, which they might after-<lb/>wards
                    easily manage.</p>
                <p>The <orgName key="bymindian">committee</orgName> have since received his
                    answer<lb/>to this letter, in which he says, he will lose no<lb/>time in
                    complying with their request, and that<lb/>he will at all times be ready to put
                    the benevo-<lb/>lent concern of Friends, towards the Indians, in<lb/>execution.
                    He also says, that at this time, a<lb/>spirit of industry exists among the
                    Indians<lb/>generally; and that, as several of the tribes,<lb/>had requested of
                    Government, to have a part<lb/><pb n="42" facs="SW_BYM1806_042"/> of their annuities expended in the
                    employment<lb/>of men, to split rails, and make fences for them,<lb/>the
                        <orgName key="delaware">Delawares</orgName> had twenty-three
                    thousand<lb/>rails put up into fences, the last winter; and<lb/>that forty
                    thousand more would be made into<lb/>fences for the <orgName key="miami"
                        >Miami</orgName> and <orgName key="eel">Eel-River Indians</orgName>,
                    by<lb/>the first of the Sixth Month. He adds, that ten<lb/>families of the
                        <orgName key="miami">Miami</orgName> have settled adjoining the<lb/>place
                    cultivated by <persName key="pdeni1">Philip Dennis</persName>; and that<lb/>four
                    men were employed in making rails to<lb/>fence forty acres for them; also, that
                    three<lb/>persons more were at work for the <orgName key="eel"
                        >Eel-River</orgName><lb/>Indians, half a mile below <persName key="pdeni1"
                        >Dennis’s</persName> station;<lb/>that they had twenty-five acres cleared
                    and<lb/>ready for the plough, and he expected would<lb/>have fifty or sixty
                    acres fenced in by the first<lb/>of the Sixth Month. He further adds,
                    that<lb/>he expects at least twenty five families of In-<lb/>dians will remove
                    to reside at that place the<lb/>present season, and he is confident the
                    settlement<lb/>will increase very fast. The Indian who worked<lb/>during the
                    last season with <persName key="pdeni1">Philip Dennis</persName> was<lb/>about
                    building himself a comfortable house, had<lb/>cleared two acres more of ground,
                    and was<lb/>ploughing the field previously cleared by <persName key="pdeni1"
                        >Philip<lb/>Dennis</persName>. The hogs which were left there with<lb/>him,
                    had increased to one hundred in number.</p>
                <p>The agent further says, that there would be<lb/><pb n="43" facs="SW_BYM1806_043"/>one hundred acres of
                    land under good fence, at<lb/>the <placeName key="lturtown">Little Turtle’s
                        Town</placeName> (eighteen miles north<lb/>of <persName key="pdeni1"
                        >Dennis</persName>’s station), by the first of the Sixth<lb/>Month; where
                    they had also obtained a large<lb/>number of hogs, and some cows; and he
                    doubts<lb/>not, but that the Indians will soon see, that it is<lb/>easier to
                    raise food, than to procure it by hunt-<lb/>ing; and adds, Friends may see, from
                    the great<lb/>progress they have made in civilization, since<lb/><persName
                        key="pdeni1">Philip Dennis</persName> was with them, that they only<lb/>want
                    good and suitable men to reside amongst<lb/>them, and teach them how to
                    work.</p>
                <p>Notwithstanding there are several other na-<lb/>tons, who appear desirous of the
                    assistance and<lb/>care of Friends; yet from the limited state of<lb/>our funds,
                    we have heretofore been under the<lb/>necessity of confining our aid,
                    principally, to<lb/>the <orgName key="miami">Miami</orgName>, <orgName key="eel"
                        >Eel-River</orgName>, and <orgName key="wea">Weas</orgName> Indians.</p>
                <p>It will be perceived, that during several years<lb/>of the first labours of the
                        <orgName key="bymindian">committee</orgName>, but little<lb/>progress was
                    made. This may be attributed, in<lb/>a great measure, to the pernicious effects
                    of<lb/>ardent spirits amongst them. As soon as the<lb/>introduction of this
                    great evil into their country<lb/>was restrained, there was an immediate
                    im-<lb/>provement discoverable; and an almost univer-<lb/>sal disposition seemed
                    to pervade them, to aban-<lb/><pb n="44" facs="SW_BYM1806_044"/>don their former habits of living, and
                    turn to<lb/>the cultivation of their lands. Their progress<lb/>in civilization
                    has, since then, been much more<lb/>rapid, than the most sanguine could have
                    ex<lb/>pected; and on comparing the condition of these<lb/>Indian tribes, at the
                    time the last deputation from<lb/>our committee visited them, with their
                    present<lb/>situation, we are of opinion, that there is great<lb/>cause of
                    encouragement for Friends to persevere<lb/>in the benevolent work they have
                    undertaken;<lb/>and strong ground to hope, that our labours<lb/>will, in the
                    end, be crowned with the desired<lb/>success.</p>
                <p>When we reflect on the gradual, but con-<lb/>tinued decrease of these people,
                    from the time<lb/>the Europeans first visited this continent, until<lb/>the
                    present; and the many whole tribes, of<lb/>which not any trace now remains,
                    except their<lb/>names; there is every reason to believe, that<lb/>should the
                    Indians continue to pursue their<lb/>former mode of life, a few centuries
                    more,<lb/>many other whole nations of them will become<lb/>entirely extinct.</p>
                <p>Impressed with this melancholy consideration,<lb/>it must be a prospect truly
                    gladdening to the en-<lb/>lightened Christian mind, to survey the
                    hasten-<lb/>ing of that day, when this part of the human fa-<lb/><pb n="45" facs="SW_BYM1806_045"/>mily, weaned from savage habits, and allured by<lb/>the superior advantages of
                    civil life, shall ex-<lb/>change the tomahawk and scalping knife for
                    the<lb/>plough and the hoe; and instead of ranging the<lb/>forests in seeming
                    affinity to the wild beasts of desert,<lb/>shall peacefully and rationally
                    enjoy<lb/>the productions of the fruitful field!—Nor is<lb/>this all. Added to
                    the cultivation of the earth,<lb/>the first step in the view of the
                    committee,<lb/>the first step in the view of the committee,<lb/>towards many
                    other important temporal advan-<lb/>tages, to be derived o this people from
                    civil<lb/>life; may not the promotion of this concern,<lb/>which has thus far
                    evidently prospered, prepare<lb/>for, and prove the means under the DIVINE
                    BLES-<lb/>SING, through which, may finally spread and<lb/>prevail amongst these,
                    our fellow-men, that<lb/>LIGHT and KNOWLEDGE, which so eminently<lb/>distinguish
                    the true CHRISTIAN?</p>
                <closer><dateline><placeName key="balt1">Baltimore</placeName>, <date when="1805-11"
                            >Eleventh Mo. 1805</date></dateline>.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="epilogue">
                <pb n="46" facs="SW_BYM1806_046"/>
                <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
                <opener>SINCE this narrative was prepared for<lb/>publication, a letter has been
                    received from the<lb/>agent at <dateline><placeName key="fwayn"
                            >Fort-Wayne</placeName>, dated the <date when="1805-10-05">5th of
                            the<lb/>Tenth Month, 1805</date></dateline>, in which he says,</opener>
                <floatingText type="letter">
                    <body><dateline><date when="1805-10-05"/></dateline>
                        <p>Agreeably to the directions of the commit-<lb/>tee, I have employed a man
                            to assist the Indians<lb/>in cultivating the field on the <geogName
                                key="wabas">Wabash</geogName>, which<lb/>was cleared and cultivated
                            by <persName key="pdeni1">Philip Dennis</persName>
                            <date when="1804">last<lb/>year</date>. The Indians with the man’s
                            assistance<lb/>have raised, it is supposed, at least six
                            hundred<lb/>bushels of good corn from this one field, ex-<lb/>clusive of
                            what they have raised from ground<lb/>of their own clearing.</p>
                        <p>Many of the oldest of the <orgName key="eel">Eel-River</orgName>
                                and<lb/><orgName key="wea">Weas</orgName> Indians have removed and
                            settled at that<lb/>place, where they will be followed by
                            the<lb/>younger branches of their tribes in the ensuing<lb/>spring.</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>He adds, <floatingText type="letter">
                        <body>
                            <p>Believing as I do, that the Society<lb/>of Friends are desirous of a
                                meliorating the situa-<lb/>tion of their Red Brethren in this
                                country, I will<lb/><pb n="47" facs="SW_BYM1806_047"/>take the liberty to observe, that
                                the present is<lb/>a very favourable time, to put in execution
                                their<lb/>benevolent views, towards the distressed natives<lb/>of
                                this land; and that much good may be done<lb/>on the <geogName
                                    key="wabas">Wabash</geogName>, by sending one or two
                                suit-<lb/>able men to reside amongst the Indians, and<lb/>teach them
                                how to raise stock, and cultivate the<lb/>earth. Witness what
                                    <persName key="pdeni1">Philip Dennis</persName>
                                effected<lb/>amongst them the last year. At a station where<lb/>he
                                had every thing to begin, there are now at<lb/>least four hundred
                                hogs and twenty cows; and<lb/>the Indians at no village in this
                                country live so<lb/>comfortably, as those at that place. If this
                                spirit<lb/>of industry is kept alive for a few years, it
                                will<lb/>certainly have a powerful influence upon the<lb/>minds of
                                the Indians at many of the neighbour-<lb/>ing villages. The Indians
                                have lately concluded<lb/>a treaty with the United States, which
                                has<lb/>settled all their jarring interests.</p>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText></p>

                <p>Printed by Phillips &amp; Fardon, George Yard, Lombard Street, London.</p>
            </div>


        </body>


    </text>
</TEI>
