<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei-print.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="global.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sketch of the Customs, Religion and Government of the Seneca Indians, in
                    1800: Electronic Version</title>

                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by</resp>
                    <persName>Cara Ehlenfeldt</persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 102 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>This work is the property of the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore
                        College. It may be copied freely by individuals for personal use, research,
                        and teaching (including distribution to classes) as long as this statement
                        of availability is included in the text. It may be linked to freely in
                        Internet editions of all kinds, including for—profit works.</p>
                    <p>Publishers, libraries, and other information providers interested in
                        providing this text in a commercial or non—profit product or from an
                        information server must contact Swarthmore College for licensing and cost
                        information.</p>
                    <p> Scholars interested in changing or adding to these texts by, for example,
                        creating a new edition of the text (electronically or in print) with
                        substantive editorial changes, may do so with the permission of Swarthmore
                        College. This is the case whether the new publication will be made available
                        at a cost or free of charge.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2014">2014</date>
                <idno type="local">SW_HJ1830</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Native Americans and Quakers: Electronic
                    Collection</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="book">

                    <monogr>
                        <author>Jackson, Halliday, 1771-1835</author>
                        <title level="m">Sketch of the Customs, Religion and Government of the
                            Seneca Indians, in 1800</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Marcus T. C. Gould</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Isaac T. Hopper</publisher>
                            <date when="1830">1830</date>

                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>


        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p> The Halliday Jackson book is housed at Friends Historical Library, on the campus
                    of Swarthmore College. Beginning in the fall semester of 2010, Swarthmore
                    students have transcribed a number of Quaker journals that document contact
                    interaction between Quakers and Native Americans, mostly in the area of upstate
                    New York and northern Ohio.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written in <date when="1830">1830</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Society of Friends -- Indian Affairs</item>

                        <item>Cornplanter, Seneca chief, 1732?-1836</item>
                        <item>Indian reservations</item>
                        <item>Indians of North America--Missions</item>
                        <item>New York (State)--Description and travel</item>
                        <item>Pennsylvania--Description and travel</item>

                        <item>Philadelphia Yearly Meeting of the Religious Society of Friends</item>
                        <item>Quakers--Pennsylvania--Diaries</item>
                        <item>Quakers--Political activity</item>
                        <item>Seneca Indians</item>
                        <item>Society of Friends--Missions</item>
                        <item>Voyages and Travels</item>

                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            
            <div type="undetermined">
                <pb n="Title page" facs="SW_HJ1830_001"/>
            </div>   
            
            <div type="preface">
                <pb n="Preface" facs="SW_HJ1830_002"/>
                <head>PREFACE.</head>
                <p>The following account of the <orgName key="seneca">Seneca Indians</orgName>, was
                    published some<lb/> months since, in the columns of The Friend, or Advocate of
                    Truth;<lb/> but is now presented to the public, on a larger type, to be sold
                    sepa-<lb/>rately, or bound up with an original work upon the <q>Civilization
                        of<lb/> the Indian Natives,</q> recently published from the pen of the
                    same<lb/> author.</p>
                <p>A number of corrections have been made in the original essays, and<lb/> some
                    interesting extracts added, from the speeches of the celebrated<lb/> Chief,
                        <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName>, during an interview with
                    President <persName key="gwash1">Washington</persName>.</p>
                <p>Those who feel an interest in the welfare of these Aborigines of our<lb/>
                    country, have now an opportunity to rescue from oblivion this sketch<lb/> of
                    their history, at a very cheap rate, and in a form much more satis-<lb/>factory
                    than that of detached fragments, interspersed with various<lb/> other matter,
                    and scattered through several numbers of a periodical in<lb/> fine type.</p>
                <p>It may not be out of place to insert the following explanatory note,<lb/> from
                    the proprietor of the Friend or Advocate of Truth, formerly an<lb/> inhabitant
                    of the state of New York:-</p>
                <note>When the interior of the state of New York was first explored by Europeans, it
                    was found in the posses-<lb/> ion of five distinct and powerful Indian nations,
                    viz.-the <orgName key="mohawk">Mohawks</orgName>, <orgName key="oneida"
                        >Oneidas</orgName>, <orgName key="onondaga">Onondagas</orgName>, <orgName
                        key="cayugaind">Cayugas</orgName>, and<lb/>
                    <orgName key="seneca">Senecas</orgName>. These five nations, though independent,
                    like the individual states of the present American union,<lb/> had formed
                    themselves into a confederated government, for the purpose of general defence,
                    and held their<lb/> grand national councils at <placeName key="onond"
                        >Onondaga</placeName>, the centre point of the five separate sovereignties.
                    <lb/>In the early part of the last century, the <orgName key="tuscarora"
                        >Tuscaroras</orgName> removed from the south to the western part of the<lb/>
                    state of New York, and were received into the confederacy, from which time the
                    term 'Six Nations' has<lb/> been used for general distinction.</note>

            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="narrative">

                <pb n="5" facs="SW_HJ1830_003"/>
                <head>An Account of the Seneca Indians</head>
                <p>As the present seems to be an interesting crisis respecting the abori-<lb/>gines
                    of our country, and particularly some of the southern tribes,<lb/> whose
                    precarious situation has awakened the feeling, and excited the<lb/> sympathies
                    of an enlightened public; and as memorials have been pre-<lb/>sented to
                    congress, with a view of protecting this much injured race of<lb/> mankind in
                    their rightful possessions, it may, perhaps, be a means of<lb/> increasing our
                    sympathies for the Indian tribes, to bring into view the<lb/> situation of those
                    more contiguous to our borders. For if the faith of<lb/> the United States is
                    once broken, to favour the claim of any individual<lb/> state, and the solemn
                    pledges, made by President <persName key="gwash1">Washington</persName>, to
                    pro-<lb/>tect the Indians in the possession of their land, are violated, to the
                    ex-<lb/>pulsion of one nation or tribe, then the fate of the Indian is sealed.
                    He<lb/> is no longer secure within the boundaries of this great republic.
                    As<lb/> he becomes obnoxious to those of a fairer skin, and the little land
                    he<lb/> posesses, like Naboth's vineyard, is convenient for his master's use,
                    he<lb/> is then to be extirpated from the inheritance of his fathers, and
                    dri-<lb/>ven from valley to mountain, and from mountain to hill, until his
                    feeble<lb/> voice is scarcely heard even among the western wilds.</p>
                <p>Although we hope better things of the legislators of our country, and<lb/>
                    indulge a glimmering hope, that they will still continue their protection<lb/>
                    to the aboriginal lords of the soil who kindly received and made room<lb/> for
                    our forefathers when they first landed on their shores; and minis-<lb/>tered to
                    their necessities, when they were strangers in a strange land;<lb/> yet, from
                    the measures in operation by some of the southern and west-<lb/>ern states, with
                    regard to the Indian tribes within their limits, we can-<lb/>not but entertain
                    fears for their safety. It is therefore desirable, at<lb/> least, to retain a
                    history of those sons of the forest, who have made<lb/> some progress in the
                    civilized arts, and with a view of developing their<lb/> native character, as
                    well as their progress in civilization, the writer of<lb/> this article designs
                    to offer, through the medium of the Friend, or Ad-<lb/>vocate of Truth, some
                    account of the <orgName key="seneca">Seneca Nation</orgName>, whose
                    situation,<lb/> perhaps, above all others, would entitle them to the strongest
                    claims of<lb/> protection from the general government.</p>
                <p>At a treaty held at <placeName key="canan">Canandaigua</placeName>, under the
                    authority of the United <lb/>States, with the <orgName key="Six Nations">Six
                        Nations</orgName>, dated the <date when="1794-11-11">eleventh of November,
                        1794</date>, 
                    <lb/>after describing the boundaries of the lands belonging to the <orgName
                        key="seneca">Seneca <lb/> Nation</orgName>, the treaty further states- Now
                    the United States acknowledge <lb/>
                    <pb n="6" facs="SW_HJ1830_004"/> all land within the afore-mentioned
                    boundaries to be the property of<lb/> the <orgName key="seneca">Seneca
                        nation</orgName>; and the United States will never claim the same,<lb/> nor
                    disturb the <orgName key="seneca">Seneca nation</orgName>, nor any of the
                        <orgName key="Six Nations">Six Nations</orgName>, or any of<lb/> their
                    Indian friends residing thereon, and united with them in the free<lb/> use and
                    enjoyment thereof; but it shall remain their's until they choose<lb/> to sell
                    the same to the people of the United States, who have the right<lb/> to
                    purchase.</p>
                <p>The <orgName key="seneca">Seneca nation</orgName> of Indians, previous to a sale
                    they made in the<lb/> year 1797, were the proprietors of the greater part of the
                    land west<lb/> of the <geogName key="genes2">Genesee river</geogName>, in the
                    state of New York. </p>
                <p>By an indenture, bearing date the <date when="1797-09-15">fifteenth of
                        Ninth-month, 1797</date>,<lb/> they sold to <persName key="rmorr1">Robert
                        Morris</persName>, in consideration of one hundred thousand<lb/> dollars, to
                    be by the said Robert Morris vested in the stock of the<lb/> bank of the United
                    States, and held in the name of the president of<lb/> the United States, for the
                    use and behoof of the <orgName key="seneca">Seneca nation</orgName> of<lb/>
                    Indians, they bargained and sold a large tract of cuintry mentioned in<lb/> said
                    indenture, to the said Robert Morris, excepting, nevertheless, and<lb/> always
                    reserving out of this grant and conveyance, all such pieces<lb/> and parcels of
                    the aforesaid tract, and such privileges thereunto be-<lb/>longing, as is
                    therein afterwards particularly mentioned, which said<lb/> pieces or parcels of
                    land so excepted, are, by the parties to the presents<lb/> clearly understood to
                    remain the property of the said <orgName key="seneca">Seneca
                    nation</orgName><lb/> of Indians, in as full and ample a manner as if the said
                    presents<lb/> had not been executed.</p>
                <p>Agreeably to the provisions made by the treaty, these reservations<lb/> were
                    located to the Indians in such places and manner as were desired<lb/> by the
                    sachems and chiefs. The principal reservations were, the <placeName key="alleg1"
                        >Alle-<lb/>ghany</placeName>, the <placeName key="catta1"
                        >Cattaraugus</placeName>, the <placeName key="buffa">Buffalo</placeName>,
                    and the <placeName key="tonne">Tonnewonta</placeName>, with several<lb/> smaller
                    reservations near the <geogName key="genes2">Genesee river</geogName>,
                    containing in all three<lb/> hundred and twelve square miles, or nearly two
                    hundred thousand<lb/> acres.</p>
                <p>The noted Chief <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName>, and his family or
                    tribe, resided in<lb/> Pennsylvania, a little south of the state of New York, on
                    a tract of<lb/> land secured to him and his heirs forever, by a special act of
                    the state.</p>
                <p>This Chief (whose Indian name is Ki-on-twogh-ky,) was much<lb/> esteemed for his
                    wisdom and superior skill, in directing the great coun-<lb/>cils of the nation;
                    and finer specimens of pathetic eloquence are scarcely<lb/> to be met with in
                    the annals of history, either amongst savage or civil-<lb/>ized nations, than
                    are displayed in his speeches to President <persName key="gwash1"
                        >Washing-<lb/>ton</persName>, in the year 1790, when he, with several other
                    noted chiefs, visited<lb/>
                    <placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName>. These speeches, with the
                    President's answers, the famous<lb/> Chief had recorded in a book, of which the
                    writer obtained a copy in<lb/> the year 1800. They were printed some years since
                    by the committee<lb/>
                    <pb n="7" facs="SW_HJ1830_005"/> who had the charge of promoting civilized
                    habits among the Indians-<lb/> but are rarely to be met with at present. Our
                    limits will not admit<lb/> their republication here, but to give the reader some
                    specimens of the<lb/> superior powers of mind with which this native son of the
                    forest was<lb/> endowed, we will here give a few extracts from them, as also of
                    the<lb/> President's replies.</p>
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body><dateline><date when="1790"/><placeName key="phila"/></dateline>
                        <opener>To the Great Counsellor of the Thirteen Fires, the Speech of
                                <persName key="cornp2">Corn-<lb/>planter</persName>, <persName
                                key="halft1">Halftown</persName> and <persName key="great1">Great
                                Tree</persName>, Chiefs and Counsellors of the <orgName key="seneca"
                                >Seneca Nation</orgName>.</opener>
                        <p>Father, The voice of the <orgName key="seneca">Seneca Nation</orgName>
                            speaks to you, the Great<lb/> Counsellor in whose heart the wise men of
                            all the Thirteen Fires have<lb/> placed their wisdom. It may be very
                            small in your ears, and we,<lb/> therefore, entreat you to hearken with
                            attention, for we are about to<lb/> speak of things which are to us very
                            great.</p>
                        <p>When you gave us peace, we called you Father, because you pro-<lb/>mised
                            to secure us in the possession of our land; do this, and so long<lb/> as
                            our land shall remain, that beloved name will live in the heart of<lb/>
                            every Seneca.</p>
                        <p>Father, when you kindled your Thirteen Fires separately, the<lb/> wise
                            men who assembled at them, told us that you were all brothers -<lb/> the
                            children of one great Father, who regards also the red people as<lb/>
                            his children. They called us brothers, and invited us to his
                            protection.<lb/> They told us that he resided beyond the great waters,
                            where the sun<lb/> first rises - that he was a king, whose power no
                            people could resist - <lb/> and that his goodness was as bright as that
                            sun. What they said went<lb/> to our hearts. We accepted the invitation,
                            and promised to obey him.<lb/> What the <orgName key="seneca">Seneca
                                nation</orgName> promise, they faithfully perform - and when<lb/>
                            you refused obedience to that king, he commanded us to assist his
                            be-<lb/>loved men in making you sober. We obeyed him - we did no
                            more<lb/> than yourselves had led us to promise. The men who claimed
                            this pro-<lb/>mise, told us that you were children, and had no guns,
                            that when they<lb/> had shaken you, you would submit - we hearkened to
                            them, and were<lb/> deceived, until your army approached our towns. We
                            were deceived;<lb/> but your people, in teaching us to confide in that
                            king, had helped to<lb/> deceive us, and now we appeal to your heart -
                            is all the blame ours?</p>
                        <p>Father, When we saw that we had been deceived, and heard the<lb/>
                            invitation you gave us to draw nigh to the fire which you had
                            kindled,<lb/> and talk with you concerning peace, we made haste towards
                            it. You<lb/> then told us that we were in your hand, and that by closing
                            it, you<lb/> could crush us to nothing-and you demanded from us a great
                            country<lb/> as the price of that peace you had offered to us, as if our
                            want of <lb/>
                            <pb n="8" facs="SW_HJ1830_006"/> strength had destroyed our rights.
                            Our chiefs had felt your power, and<lb/> were unable to contend against
                            you, and they, therefore, gave up that<lb/> country. What they agreed
                            to, has bound our nation; but by this time<lb/> your anger against u
                            must be cooled, and although our strength has<lb/> not increased, nor
                            your power become less, we ask you to consider<lb/> calmly - were the
                            terms dictated to us by your commissioners reasona-<lb/>ble and
                                just?<note resp="author">[After setting forth, in a plaintive
                                strain, the many wrongs they had<lb/> suffered, and the difficulties
                                they had been led into by subsequent<lb/> treaties with individuals,
                                they go on, and say,]</note> Father, We could<lb/> bear this
                            confusion no longer, and determined to lift up our voice, so<lb/> that
                            you might hear us, and to claim that security in possession of our<lb/>
                            lands, which your commissioners so solemnly promised us, and we now<lb/>
                            entreat you to inquire into our complaints, and redress our wrongs.<lb/>
                            We have already said how we came to join against you: - we saw that<lb/>
                            we were wrong - we wished for peace - you demanded a great country<lb/>
                            to be given up to you as the price of peace; and we ought to have<lb/>
                            peace, and possession of the little land you then left us.</p>
                        <p>Father, We will not conceal from you that the great God, and not<lb/>
                            man, has preserved the <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName>
                            from the hands of his own nation,<lb/> for they ask continually, 'where
                            is the land on which our children, and<lb/> their children after them,
                            are to lay down upon?' 'You told us,' say<lb/> they, 'that the line
                            drawn from Pennsylvania to <geogName key="lakeo">Lake
                            Ontario</geogName>, would<lb/> mark it forever on the east, and the line
                            running from <geogName key="beave">Beaver Creek</geogName><lb/> to
                            Pennsylvania would mark it on the west; and we see that it has not<lb/>
                            been so - for first one, and then another, comes and takes it away,
                            by<lb/> order of that people who you tell us promised it to us.' He is
                            silent,<lb/> for he has nothing to say. When the sun goes down, he opens
                            his heart<lb/> before God, and earlier than the sun appears again upon
                            the hill , he<lb/> gives thanks for his protection during the night
                            season - for he feels that<lb/> when men become desperate by their
                            danger, it is God only that can<lb/> preserve him. He loves peace, and
                            all that he had in store he has<lb/> given to those who have been robbed
                            by your people, lest they should<lb/> plunder the innocent to repay
                            themselves. The whole season which<lb/> others have employed in
                            providing for their families, he has spent in en-<lb/>deavouring to
                            preserve peace, and at this moment his wife and children<lb/> are lying
                            on the ground in want of food - his heart is in pain for them<lb/> - but
                            he perceives that the Great Spirit will try his firmness in doing<lb/>
                            what is right. </p>
                        <p>Father, All the land we have been speaking of, belonged to the<lb/>
                            <orgName key="Six Nations">Six Nations</orgName>. No part of it ever
                            belonged to the King of England, and<lb/> he could not give it to you.
                            The land we live on, our fathers received<lb/>
                            <pb n="9" facs="SW_HJ1830_007"/> from God, and they transmitted it
                            to us for our children, and we cannot<lb/> part with it.</p>
                        <p>Father, These are to us very great things - we know that you are<lb/>
                            very strong - and we have heard that you are wise - and we shall
                            now<lb/> wait to hear your answer to what we have said, that we may
                            know<lb/> that you are just.</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>

                <p>The foregoing speech was signed by <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName>,
                        <persName key="halft1">Half-town</persName>, and<lb/>
                    <persName key="great1">Great Tree</persName>, in the presence of <persName
                        key="jnich1">Joseph Nicholson</persName>, interpreter, and <persName
                        key="tmatl1">Timo-<lb/>thy Matlack</persName>.</p>
                <p>President <persName key="gwash1">Washington</persName> answered them in a style
                    adapted to the<lb/> Indian mode of speech. In reply to their embarrassments
                    respecting<lb/> the sale of their lands, he says, </p>
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body><dateline><date when="1790"/><placeName key="phila"/></dateline>
                        <p>I am not uninformed that the <orgName key="Six Nations">Six<lb/>
                                Nations</orgName> have been led into some difficulty with respect to
                            the sale of<lb/> their lands, since the peace - but I must inform you
                            that these evils<lb/> arose before the present government of the United
                            States was esta-<lb/>blished, when the separate states and individuals
                            under their authority<lb/> undertook to treat with the Indian tribes
                            respecting the sale of their<lb/> lands. But the case is now entirely
                            altered - the general government,<lb/> only, has the power to treat with
                            the Indian nations, and any treaty<lb/> formed and held without its
                            authority, will not be binding.</p>
                        <p>Here, then, is the security for the remainder of your lands - no<lb/>
                            state or person can purchase your lands, unless at some public
                            treaty<lb/> held under the authority of the United States. The general
                            govern-<lb/>ment will never consent to your being defrauded, but will
                            protect<lb/> you in all your rights.</p>
                        <p>Hear well, and let it be heard by every person in your nation, that<lb/>
                            the President of the United States declares that the general
                            govern-<lb/>ment considers itself bound to protect you in all the land
                            secured to<lb/> you by the treaty at <placeName key="fstan">Fort
                                Stanwix</placeName>, <date when="1784-10-22">the twenty-second of
                                October,<lb/> 1784</date>, except such parts as you may since have
                            fairly sold to persons<lb/> properly authorized to purchase of you.</p>
                        <p>Your great object seems to be the security of your remaining lands,<lb/>
                            and I have, therefore, upon this point, meant to be sufficiently
                            strong<lb/> and clear, that in future you cannot be defrauded of your
                            lands - that<lb/> you possess the right to sell, and the right of
                            refusing to sell your lands<lb/> - that, therefore, the sale of your
                            lands in future, will depend entirely<lb/> upon yourselves.</p>

                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>In the conclusion of his speech, the President assures them the<lb/> United
                    States will be true and faithful to their agreement.</p>

            </div>
            <div type="narrative">
                <pb n="10" facs="SW_HJ1830_008"/>
                <p>The Second Speech of <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName>, <persName
                        key="halft1">Half-town</persName>, and <persName key="great1">Big
                        Tree</persName>.</p>
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body><dateline><date when="1790"/><placeName key="phila"/></dateline>
                        <p>Father, Your speech, written on the great paper, is to us like the<lb/>
                            first light of the morning to a sick man, whose pulse beats too
                            strongly<lb/> in his temples - he sees it, and rejoices, but is not
                            cured.</p>
                        <p>You have spoken plainly on the great point, that you will protect<lb/> us
                            in the land secured to us at <placeName key="fstan">Fort
                                Stanwix</placeName>, and that we have a right<lb/> to sell, or
                            refuse to sell-this is very good. But our nation complain<lb/> that you
                            compelled us at that treaty to give up too much of our lands<lb/> - we
                            confess that our nation is bound by what was there done, and<lb/>
                            acknowledge your power - we have now appealed to yourselves against<lb/>
                            that treaty, as made while you were too angry at us - and,
                            therefore,<lb/> unreasonable and unjust - to this you have given us no
                            answer.</p>
                        <p>Father, That treaty was not with a single state - it was the
                            thir-<lb/>teen states. We should never have given all that land to one
                            state -<lb/> we know that it was before you had the great authority -
                            and as you<lb/> have more wisdom than the commissioners who forced us
                            into that treaty,<lb/> we expect you have more regard to justice, and
                            will now, at our re-<lb/>quest, reconsider the treaty, and restore to us
                            part of that land.</p>
                        <p>Father, The land which lies between the line running south from<lb/>
                            <geogName key="lakee">Lake Erie</geogName> to the boundary of
                            Pennsylvania, as mentioned in the treaty<lb/> of <placeName key="fstan"
                                >Fort Stanwix</placeName>, and the eastern boundary of that land
                            which you sold<lb/> and the <orgName key="seneca">Senecas</orgName>
                            confirmed to Pennsylvania, is the land on which <persName key="halft1"
                                >Half-<lb/>town</persName> and all his people live, with other
                            chiefs, who always were, and<lb/> still are, dissatisfied with the
                            treaty of <placeName key="fstan">Fort Stanwix</placeName>. They grew
                            out<lb/> of this land, and their fathers grew out of it, and they cannot
                            be per-<lb/>suaded to part with it. We therefore entreat you to restore
                            us this<lb/> little piece.</p>
                        <p>Father, Look at the land which we gave to you at that treaty, and<lb/>
                            then cast your eyes upon what we now ask you to restore us, and you<lb/>
                            will see that what we now ask is a very little piece. By giving it
                            back<lb/> again you will satisfy the whole of our nation. The chiefs who
                            signed<lb/> that treaty will be in safety - and peace between your
                            children and<lb/> our children will continue so long as your land shall
                            continue to join<lb/> our's.</p>
                        <p>Every man in our nation will then turn his eyes away from all the<lb/>
                            other land that we then gave up to you, and forget that our fathers<lb/>
                            ever said that it belonged to them.</p>
                        <p>Father, We see that you ought to have the path at the carrying-<lb/>place
                            from <geogName key="lakee">Lake Erie</geogName> to <geogName key="niaga"
                                >Niagara</geogName>, as it was marked down at <placeName key="fstan"
                                >Fort Stan-<lb/>wix</placeName>, and we are willing it should remain
                            to be yours. And if you de-<lb/>sire to reserve a passage through the
                                <geogName key="conew">Conewango</geogName>, and through the <lb/>
                            <pb n="11" facs="SW_HJ1830_009"/>
                            <geogName key="chaut"> Chautauque Lake</geogName>, and land for a path
                            from that Lake to <geogName key="lakee">Lake Erie</geogName>,<lb/> take
                            it where you like best. Our nation will rejoice to see it an open<lb/>
                            path for you and your children, while the land and water remain:
                            But<lb/> let us pass along the same way, and continue to take the fish
                            of these<lb/> waters in common with you.</p>
                        <p>Father, You say that you will appoint an agent to take care of<lb/> us -
                            let him come and take care of our trade, but we desire he may<lb/> have
                            nothing to do with our land; for the agents who have come among<lb/> us,
                            and pretended to take care of us, have always deceived us when-<lb/>ever
                            we sold lands: both when the King and when the separate states<lb/> have
                            bargained with us: They have, by this means, occasioned many<lb/> wars,
                            and we are, therefore, unwilling to trust them again.</p>
                        <p>Father, When we return home, we will call a great council, and<lb/>
                            consider well how lands may be hereafter sold by our nation, and
                            when<lb/> we have agreed upon it, we will send you notice thereof-but we
                            de-<lb/> sire that you will not depend upon your agent for information
                            concern-<lb/>ing lands; for after the abuses which we have received from
                            such men,<lb/> we will not trust them with anything concerning
                            lands.</p>
                        <p>Father, We will not hear lies concerning you, and we desire you<lb/> will
                            not hear lies concerning us, and then we shall certainly live in<lb/>
                            peace with you.</p>
                        <p>Father, Our nation has long looked round for a father, but they<lb/>
                            found none that would own them for his children, until you now tell
                            us<lb/> that your courts are open for us as to your own people. The joy
                            that<lb/> we feel on this great news so mixes with the sorrows that are
                            past, that<lb/> we cannot express our gladness, nor conceal the
                            remembrance of our<lb/> affliction - we will speak of it at another
                            time.</p>
                        <p>Father, We are ashamed that we have listened to L-----n's lies,<lb/> or
                            been influenced by threats of war from P-----s, and would hide that<lb/>
                            whole transaction from the world and from ourselves, by quietly
                            re-<lb/>ceiving what P-----s promised to give us for the land he cheated
                            us of.<lb/> But as P-----s will not pay us according to that fraudulent
                            bargain, we<lb/> must lay the whole proceeding before your court. When
                            the evidence<lb/> which we can produce is heard, we think it will appear
                            that the whole<lb/> bargain was founded upon lies which he placed one
                            upon another - that<lb/> the goods which he had charged to us, as part
                            payment, were plunder-<lb/>ed from us - and that if P-----s was not
                            directly concerned in the theft,<lb/> he knew of it at the time, and
                            concealed it from us, and that the per-<lb/>sons we confided in were
                            bribed by him to deceive us in the bargain -<lb/> and if these facts
                            appear, your courts will not say that such bargains<lb/> are just, but
                            set the whole aside.</p>
                        <p>Father, the blood that was spilt near <geogName key="pinec">Pine
                                Creek</geogName>, is covered, and<lb/> we shall never look where it
                            lies. We know that Pennsylvania will<lb/>
                            <pb n="12" facs="SW_HJ1830_010"/> satisfy us for that which we speak
                            to them, wherefore we speak to you.<lb/> The chain of friendship will
                            now, we hope, be made strong, as you desire<lb/> it to be - we will hold
                            it fast - our end of it shall never rust in our hands.</p>
                        <p>Father, we told you what advice we gave to the people you are<lb/> now at
                            war with, and we now tell you that they have promised to come<lb/> again
                            next spring to our towns. We shall not wait for their coming,<lb/> but
                            set out very early in the season, and how them what you have<lb/> done
                            for us, which must convince them that you will do for them every<lb/>
                            thing that they ought to ask. We think they will hear us and
                            forward<lb/> our advice.</p>
                        <p>Father, you gave us leave to speak our minds concerning the till-<lb/>ing
                            of the ground - we ask you to teach us to plough and to grind corn,<lb/>
                            and supply us with broad axes, saws, augers, and other tools to assist
                            us<lb/> in building a saw mill, that we may make our houses more
                            comfortable<lb/> and more durable. That you will send smiths among us,
                            and above all<lb/> that you will teach our children to read and write,
                            and our women to<lb/> spin and weave. The manner of doing these things
                            for us we leave to<lb/> you who understand them, but we assure you that
                            we will follow your<lb/> advice as far as we are able.</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>

                <p>To this second speech the President made them a written reply, stat-<lb/>ing,
                    among other things, that he could not disannul treaties made with<lb/> the
                    United States before his administration, and that, therefore, the<lb/>
                    boundaries marked by the treaty of <placeName key="fstan">Fort
                        Stanwix</placeName> must remain esta-<lb/>blished. He assured them an agent
                    should be appointed who would not<lb/> be suffered to defraud them, or assist in
                    defrauding them of their land;<lb/> and concluded, by saying -</p>
                <p><said who="gwash">You may, when you return from this city to your own
                        country,<lb/> mention to your nation my desire for their prosperity by
                        teaching them<lb/> the use of domestic animals, and the manner that the
                        white people<lb/> plough and raise so much corn, and if, upon consideration,
                        it would be<lb/> agreeable to the nation at large to learn these valuable
                        arts, I will find<lb/> such means of teaching them, at such a place within
                        their country as<lb/> shall be agreed upon.</said></p>

                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body>
                        <opener>To the great counsellor of the Thirteen Fires. The speech of
                                <persName key="cornp2">Corn-<lb/>planter</persName>, <persName
                                key="halft1">Half-town</persName>, and <persName key="great1">Big
                                Tree</persName>.</opener>
                        <p>Father, no Seneca ever goes from the fire of his friend until he has<lb/>
                            said to him I am going. We therefore tell you that we are now
                            set-<lb/>ting out for our own country.</p>
                        <p>Father, we thank you from our hearts that we now know there is<lb/> a
                            country we may call our own, and on which we may lay down in<lb/> peace.
                            We see that there will be peace between your children and<lb/> our
                            children, and our hearts are very glad. We will persuade the<lb/>
                            <orgName key="wyandot">Wyandots</orgName> and other western nations to
                            open their eyes, and look to-<lb/>
                            <pb n="13" facs="SW_HJ1830_011"/> wards the bed which you have made
                            for us, and to ask of you a bed for<lb/> themselves and their children,
                            that will not slide from under them.</p>
                        <p>Father, we thank you for your presents to us, and rely on your
                            pro-<lb/>mise to instruct us in raising corn as the white people do. The
                            sooner<lb/> you do this the better for us, and we thank you for the care
                            which you<lb/> have taken to prevent bad people from coming to trade
                            among us. If<lb/> any come without your license, we will turn them back,
                            and we hope<lb/> our nation will determine to spill all the rum that
                            shall hereafter be<lb/> brought to our towns.</p>
                        <p>Father, you have not asked of us any surety for peace on our part,<lb/>
                            but we have agreed to send nine <orgName key="seneca">Seneca</orgName>
                            boys to be under your care for<lb/> education - tell us at what time you
                            will receive them, and they shall<lb/> be sent at that time. This will
                            assure you that we are indeed at peace<lb/> with you, and determined to
                            continue so. If you can teach them to be<lb/> wise and good men, we will
                            take care that our nation shall be willing<lb/> to be instructed by
                            them.</p>
                        <closer>Signed in the presence of <persName key="jnich1">Joseph
                                Nicholson</persName>, interpreter.<lb/> Attest, <signed><list>
                                    <item><persName key="tproc1">Thomas Proctor</persName>,</item>
                                    <item><persName key="tmatl1">Timothy Matlack</persName>.</item>
                                </list></signed>
                            <dateline><placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName>,<emph/><date
                                    when="1791-02-07">February 7th, 1791</date>.</dateline></closer>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>


                <p>The foregoing extracts may serve to show the strong point of view<lb/> in which
                    the faith of the United States was pledged to protect the In-<lb/>dians in their
                    rightful possessions. And this interview with the Presi-<lb/>dent opened the way
                    for the introduction of civilized habits among the<lb/>
                    <orgName key="seneca">Seneca nation</orgName> of Indians, subsequently commenced
                    and prosecuted by<lb/> the society of Friends. Some account of their proceedings
                    may here-<lb/>after be given, in which the writer of this was for many years
                    actively<lb/> engaged. It is, in the first place, his design to give a sketch of
                    their<lb/> manners and customs, at the time these operations were commenced
                    -<lb/> being the result of observation, during his residence and frequent
                    visits<lb/> among the <orgName key="seneca">Seneca nation</orgName>, as well as
                    from the most authentic infor-<lb/>mation collected from other well acquainted
                    with their habits and<lb/> manners.</p>
                <p>This sketch, written many years ago, will consist in a brief view of<lb/> their
                    persons, dress, houses, provisions - hardships imposed upon the fe-<lb/>males,
                    economy, intercourse with one another, treatment of their chil-<lb/>dren,
                    employment of the men - hunting, their belief in the Great Spirit,<lb/> opinion
                    of the evil spirit, place of happiness after death, place of punish-<lb/>ment,
                    religious ceremonies, sacrifices, mourning for the dead, supersti-<lb/>tious
                    notions, banquets, marriages, government, mode of appointing<lb/> chiefs,
                    punishments, hyeroglyphics, idea of the globe, &amp;c.</p>

            </div>
            <div type="narrative">
                <pb n="14" facs="SW_HJ1830_012"/>
                <head>Manners and Customs of the <orgName key="seneca">Seneca Nation</orgName> of
                    Indians, in the year 1800.</head>
                <p>In their persons, the <orgName key="seneca">Senecas</orgName> are generally of a
                    moderate stature<lb/> and well proportioned, though instances of dwarfishness
                    and deformity<lb/> are sometimes to be seen among them. Their complexion is of a
                    cop-<lb/>per colour, and the hair black - that of the men being generally
                    cut<lb/> close, excepting a small tuft on the crown of the head, which is
                    suf-<lb/>fered to grow long, and is tied in a small roll on the top, on which
                    they<lb/> frequently wear a silver tube, about three inches in length.
                    Some,<lb/> also, let small locks grow obliquely projecting over their
                    shoulders.<lb/> They very generally extract their beards by means of a spiral
                    spring<lb/> ring made of wire, about the common knitting needle size, and
                    about<lb/> two inches in length; this being applied to the face, and pressed
                    be-<lb/>tween the thumb and finger, forms a kind of pincers, and takes so
                    fast<lb/> hold of the beard as readily to extract it. This is also frequently
                    made<lb/> use of to extract the hair from the head instead of cutting, and
                    some-<lb/>times the operation is performed between their thumb and the
                    blunt<lb/> edge of a knife.</p>
                <p>Their eyes are black, keen, and penetrating - their countenance open<lb/> and
                    engaging in general, and a great object of their vanity is, to give<lb/> every
                    possible decoration to their persons, by painting their faces a <lb/> variety of
                    colours, among which vermilion and charcoal are their<lb/> favourites.</p>
                <p>They most generally use the red, but streaks of black are occasion-<lb/>ally
                    intermixed. Black mostly denotes trouble; but the red, though it<lb/> makes them
                    look fierce, as in time of disturbance, is expressive of war – <lb/> so it is
                    also used to denote cheerfulness, and sometimes to hide the true<lb/> expression
                    of the countenance - and in this way, when rubbed round<lb/> the eyes, it has a
                    wonderful effect.</p>
                <p>Their dress is simple and commodious. It consists of tight leggings<lb/> reaching
                    above the knee, made of cloth or flannel - a strip of cloth<lb/> about a foot
                    wide and three or four feet long, according to the size of<lb/> the person, is
                    drawn inwards at each end, and hangs down behind and<lb/> before, over a belt
                    tied round the waist for that purpose - the outward<lb/> ends of this are
                    frequently ornamented with silver brooches. A close<lb/> vest or shirt reaching
                    somewhat below the waist, made of linen or<lb/> calico, and in some instances a
                    short waistcoat, with an overcoat of cloth,<lb/> or blanketing, (which they call
                    match-coat,) clumsily made, and the<lb/>
                    <pb n="15" facs="SW_HJ1830_013"/> addition of moccasins on their feet, and a
                    cap on their head, mostly<lb/>/ complete their apparel. The materials of their
                    dress, however, vary<lb/> according to the season. In warm weather they are very
                    thinly<lb/> clad, and in the winter they generally wrap their blanket round
                    them,<lb/> in addition to their other clothing. At times, their head dress is
                    cu-<lb/>riously ornamented with large feathers, and the tails of wild
                    animals,<lb/> projecting from their ears sideways, some erect, and others
                    flowing be-<lb/>hind them. These habiliments are put on, however, as their
                    caprice<lb/> suggests, and are generally worn at their feasts and sacrifices, or
                    on ex-<lb/>peditions to distant parts, when they make the most antic
                    appearance.</p>
                <p>The female dress is formed of much the same material as that of<lb/> the other
                    sex, but of somewhat different make and arrangement. They<lb/> wear moccasins on
                    their feet, and their leggings are fastened<lb/> below the knee. An open garment
                    descending about half down the leg, is fastened<lb/> round them by a belt at the
                    waist, and the upper part turned down-<lb/>wards, reaching near to the knee,
                    which part is often covered with ri-<lb/>bands or embellished with silver
                    brooches, with a considerable degree<lb/> of skill and taste.</p>
                <p>They wear a short frock or vest, reaching to the waist, flowing<lb/> loose about
                    them, and when their business will admit, their blanket is<lb/> spread over the
                    whole, and serves them both night and day. Divers<lb/> of their garments are
                    fancifully fringed and ornamented with needle<lb/> work, set in with beads and
                    porcupine quills, variegated and disposed<lb/> with much skill and ingenuity.
                    Their hair is left to grow at full length,<lb/> generally falls back, and is
                    tied up in a knot behind, care being taken<lb/> to apply to it plentifully of
                    the fat of the bear. Their head-dress con-<lb/>sists principally of a simple
                    cap, or hood, made of cloth, or old blanket-<lb/>ing, secured together, at one
                    end, and flowing round their neck and<lb/> shoulders; but these are seldom worn
                    by the females, except in cold<lb/> weather.</p>
                <p>Their houses are of different dimensions, from ten to thirty feet<lb/> in length,
                    but narrow in proportion. They are built of poles, or small<lb/> logs, being
                    about six feet to the square of the eve, and covered with a<lb/> very steep roof
                    of bark, which they take off the tree in very broad<lb/> pieces, five or six
                    feet long, mostly chestnut, hemlock, or cucumber.<lb/> They generally take it
                    from the tree, shave the outside off, and lay it in<lb/> a horizontal pile to
                    press, some time before they use it.</p>
                <p>The rafters are made of round poles, the lower end dovetailed in the<lb/> top log
                    - tied together at the top, and crossed again at smaller dis-<lb/>tances by
                    other poles, on which are laid the bark, which is tied to the<lb/> poles with
                    the inside rind of hickory or other strong bark.</p>
                <p>Two courses thus laid on, generally cover one side of the house, and<lb/> the
                    ridge of the roof is made tight by laying broad pieces lengthways,<lb/>
                    <pb n="16" facs="SW_HJ1830_014"/> and tying them down as aforesaid. A roof
                    of good bark, thus put on,<lb/> will stand water proof for several years, and
                    the labour of renewing it<lb/> is not very considerable in a country where
                    timber abounds. In a long<lb/> house, the logs are joined together at the ends
                    by means of a gutter<lb/> post, which stands perpendicular about midway on each
                    side of the<lb/> building, and are neatly notched down at the corners. Some<lb/>
                    who wish to live more secure from the cold winds, stop the interme-<lb/>diate
                    spaces with moss. The door is almost invariably at one end of<lb/> the house,
                    the logs being all cut off except the top and bottom ones,<lb/> and fitted into
                    gutter posts, which serve for door cheeks. Two births<lb/> or shelvings are made
                    on each side of the house, the lower one about<lb/> one foot from the ground, on
                    which they lodge, and the other about five<lb/> feet high, on which they throw
                    their household furniture, provisions,<lb/> &amp;c. The fire is built in the
                    centre of the house, and a hole left in the<lb/> roof directly over it to vent
                    the smoke. There are girders supported by<lb/> upright timbers, on which they
                    hang up their corn to dry; a cross-<lb/>piece of timber again rests on these,
                    from which withs and wooden<lb/> hooks are suspended to hang their kettles on,
                    over the fire, wherein they<lb/> cook their provisions.</p>
                <p>Some had wigwams,* the walls as well as roofs of which were con-<lb/>structed of
                    bark, supported by small poles stuck in the ground, to which<lb/> the bark was
                    fastened - the inside of the house much on the same con-<lb/>struction as the
                    former. These were not very common in their villages,<lb/> but more generally
                    occupied as a temporary residence, when in the<lb/> woods making sugar, or as a
                    hunting encampment.</p>
                <p>The third month, is generally their season for making sugar, when<lb/> whole
                    families retire into the woods contiguous to a grove of sugar<lb/> maple, the
                    sap of which they extract, by making an incision into the<lb/> trunk near the
                    ground, and convey it, by means of a small tube, into<lb/> troughs set for the
                    purpose. This is collected and taken to the camp,<lb/> where it is boiled in
                    large kettles till reduced to sugar, and when clean-<lb/>liness is observed in
                    the operation, they will make this valuable article<lb/> of an excellent flavour
                    and quality. The sap runs most plentifully in<lb/> a clear sunshine, after a
                    cold frosty night - but a damp wind from the<lb/> southward checks the flowing
                    of the sap immediately.</p>
                <p>At this season the Indians remain several weeks in the woods, and<lb/> the men
                    assist the women in the labour of making sugar, besides at-<lb/>tending to their
                    hunting, to procure supplies of meat. They also trap<lb/> those amphibious and
                    other animals, which furnish furs, and especially<lb/> the beaver, the meat of
                    which they esteem a luxury.</p>
                <note resp="author">*The Delaware word for house.</note>
                <pb n="17" facs="SW_HJ1830_015"/>
                <p>The females, who are subject, (as amongst other uncivilized nation)<lb/> to
                    almost every kind of domestic drudgery, are industrious in the culture<lb/> of
                    Indian corn, beans, squashes, melons, potatoes, and many other vege-<lb/>tables.
                    And although each family have their separate piece of ground<lb/> to cultivate
                    with the hoe, and hold the fruit of their industry as distinct<lb/> property,
                    yet they frequently join in large companies to assist each<lb/> other, on which
                    occasions they are remarkably loquacious and lively,<lb/> as also expert in
                    using the hoe, each patiently assisting her neighbour,<lb/> till her own turn
                    comes in rotation. Thus they enjoy a kind of con-<lb/>vivial intercourse, which
                    greatly tends to ameliorate the weight of la-<lb/>bour assigned them, and in
                    many instances no doubt, affords them a<lb/> satisfaction equal to, if not
                    surpaaaing that enjoyed by many of the white<lb/> female in their most social
                    entertainments.</p>
                <p>The vegetables which they raise with the hoe, with some fish caught<lb/> in the
                    river, generally compose a great part of their provision in the<lb/> summer
                    season. Venison was not at all time to be procured plentifully,<lb/> and even
                    when obtained, by hunting, they had no way of preserving it,<lb/> in the warm
                    weather, except by drying it over the fire, into what they<lb/> call jerk. This
                    is sometimes done in the woods, at their hunting camps<lb/> - by means of a kind
                    of rack made of small sticks, over the fire, or by<lb/> sharpening the sticks at
                    both ends and setting them in the ground, near<lb/> the fire, with the meat
                    stuck on the upper end. Salt at this time was<lb/> a scarce article among them,
                    and not to be procured but at an ex-<lb/>travagant price, yet it is an article
                    of which they are very fond, and<lb/> what little they were enabled to obtain
                    was frequently carried with<lb/> them, carefully tied up in one corner of their
                    clothes, and used sparing-<lb/>ly. Their venison was often eaten without salt,
                    bread, or vegetables;<lb/> and as they are not delicate in their palate, they
                    often feast, apparently<lb/> with a relish, on meat highly tainted. They were
                    not observed to be<lb/> early risers in the morning; they seldom eat more than
                    two meals a<lb/> day, and those morning and evening. Their meals principally
                    consist<lb/> of soups, made of squashes, beans, hominy, and other vegetables;
                    also<lb/> of meat cut in small pieces, when it can be procured. This dish is
                    then<lb/> served up in wooden bowls, and supped with wooden ladles; the
                    eldest<lb/> of the male part of the family being generally served first, and
                    thus in<lb/> rotation, to the youngest - afterwards the females partake in a
                    similar<lb/> manner. On some extraordinary occasions, they sweeten their
                    soups<lb/> with sugar. This article they are very fond of; and as they make
                    it<lb/> in cakes of near a pound weight, they frequently carry it with
                    them,<lb/> and eat it like cheese, with bread, or sweeten water to drink. </p>
                <p>When their new corn becomes fit for use, which is generally in the<lb/>
                    ninth-month, they feast plentifully on it, sometimes boiling it, as usual<lb/>
                    among white people, and also make soup or dumplings of it, while in a<lb/>
                    <pb n="18" facs="SW_HJ1830_016"/> milky state. The process of the latter is,
                    to cut it off the cob and tie<lb/> it up in small cakes, in the corn husks,
                    mixed with whortleberries or<lb/> dried blackberries, and boiled like a pudding.
                    This when seasoned<lb/> with a little salt, makes a palatable food, and with the
                    addition of some<lb/> bear's fat, is to them a luxury.</p>
                <p>Their bread is made of corn meal, into which they put bean, mix<lb/> it up with
                    hot water, and bake it in the embers. They also parch<lb/> their corn, pound it
                    fine, and mix sugar with it. This is a delicacy<lb/> even with white people, and
                    frequently forms a part of the Indian's<lb/> travelling provisions; wanting no
                    other preparation for eating, than<lb/> wetting it with water. They raise a kind
                    of small round squash, which<lb/> they boil or roast in the embers, and which,
                    in taste, resembles a sweet<lb/> potato; and these they not only use in the
                    autumn, but preserve nearly<lb/> through the winter. In times of scarcity, they
                    are often reduced to the<lb/> necessity of gathering wild roots and herbs, on
                    which they subsist. In<lb/> short, a great variety, prepared in the most simple
                    manner, composed<lb/> their provisions. Almost every kind of fowl, fish, and
                    flesh are eaten<lb/> by them; even some amphibious animals - and the beaver,
                    especially<lb/> - as before stated, was esteemed a luxury.</p>
                <p>Having no mills in their country, the women reduced their corn to<lb/> meal, by
                    pounding it in wooden mortars, and sifting it in a sieve made<lb/> of wooden
                    splints. The pounders were made of hard wood, and of dif-<lb/>ferent weights,
                    according to the size and strength of the woman; and<lb/> frequently three of
                    them would be engaged in one block at the same<lb/> time, and regulate their
                    strokes in alternation.</p>
                <p>The females also cut their firewood and carry it home on their<lb/> backs; and
                    about some of their ancient villages, oftentimes from a quar-<lb/>ter to a half
                    mile distance. This being an arduous part of the task as-<lb/>signed them, they
                    frequently join in large companies to assist each other;<lb/> and to those who
                    have not been eye-witnesses, it might appear incredi-<lb/>ble to relate the size
                    and weight of the burthens they carry tied up in<lb/> a belt, which bears on the
                    forehead; the wood being suspended across<lb/> the back, as the females incline
                    forward. The young girls are not ex-<lb/>empted from this service, but carry
                    small burthens in proportion to<lb/> their strength; and these female labourers
                    knowing the task assigned<lb/> them, are economical in procuring their wood in
                    the summer, or early<lb/> in the fall; having it split up small, carried home,
                    and piled round the<lb/> house, or often under a shed made for the purpose. This
                    would be<lb/> thought insupportable, by the females of some, if not all
                    civilized na-<lb/>tions; but custom and necessity have made it quite familiar to
                    these<lb/> sprightly inhabitants of the wilderness.</p>
                <p>The economy of the women in procuring sustenance, far exceeds that<lb/> of the
                    men, as they carefully collect almost every natural or sponta-<lb/>
                    <pb n="19" facs="SW_HJ1830_017"/> neous production of their country,
                    suitable for the support of human<lb/> life, and lay up against times of
                    scarcity, which sometimes occur, and<lb/> more frequently in the fore part of
                    summer. For though many of them<lb/> raise a competence of corn, to serve, with
                    frugality, the year round, yet<lb/> others fall short - using their supply so
                    liberally, it is exhausted before<lb/> the new corn is fit for use; still
                    trusting to the hazard of procuring food<lb/> from their native forests.</p>
                <p>When an Indian entered the house of his friend, it was common to<lb/> set before
                    him such provisions as were cooked, and if while he was<lb/> eating, several of
                    his associates came in, he divided it in equal parts<lb/> amongst them;
                    reserving his own proportion. When he is about to<lb/> leave his friend, he
                    tells him he is going, which amounts to farewell;<lb/> but if any circumstance
                    takes place which has given umbrage, he with-<lb/>draws, and says nothing. This
                    is clear evidence that he is offended.</p>
                <p>They appear to be naturally as well calculated for social and rational<lb/>
                    enjoyment, as any people. --They frequently visit each other in their<lb/>
                    houses, and spend much of their time in friendly intercourse.</p>
                <p>They are also mild and hospitable, not only among themselves, but<lb/> to
                    strangers, and good natured in the extreme, except when their na-<lb/>ture are
                    perverted by the inflammatory influence of spirituous liquors.<lb/> In their
                    social interviews, as well as public council, they are careful<lb/> not to
                    interrupt one another in conversation, and generally make short<lb/> speeches.
                    This truly laudable mark of good manners, enables them to<lb/> transact all
                    their public business with decorum and regularity, and more<lb/> strongly
                    impresses on their mind and memory, the result of their delibe-<lb/>rations.
                    Probably it is from this circumstance that they are enabled,<lb/> without the
                    aid of literature, to retain in their memory, and transmit<lb/> their
                    transactions from one generation to another; thus one of their<lb/> chiefs,
                    speaking in public council , will relate with precision, circum-<lb/>stances
                    that have taken place among their ancestors for several gene-<lb/>rations
                    past.</p>
                <p>Although they appear to possess tender feelings for their children,<lb/> they
                    inure them to hardships, while in an infant state, by frequently<lb/> immersing
                    them in cold water. Being indulged in most of their wishes,<lb/> as they grow
                    up, liberty, in its fullest extent, becomes their ruling pas-<lb/>sion. They are
                    seldom chastened with blows, or treated with restraint<lb/> or correction. Their
                    faults are mostly left for their own reason to cor-<lb/>rect when they are grown
                    up - which faults, they say, cannot be very<lb/> great, before reason arrives at
                    some degree of maturity. If, however,<lb/> they prove too obstinate, they
                    sometimes plunge them in the river; and<lb/> if one dip is not sufficient to
                    conquer or quiet them, it is repeated, till<lb/> the end is effected. As the
                    child gets a little older, they will sometimes<lb/> talk to it a long while,
                    endeavouring to impress on its mind what it<lb/>
                    <pb n="20" facs="SW_HJ1830_018"/> ought to do, and what to leave undone. At
                    other times, they ridicule<lb/> their children for doing wrong, and tell them
                    they are not wise in doing<lb/> so.</p>
                <p>And one remarkable trait in the character of the children, is, that<lb/> they are
                    generally good humoured among themselves, and children of<lb/> the same family
                    show strong attachments to each other, and are less<lb/> liable to quarrel in
                    their youthful days than is generally the case with<lb/> white children.</p>
                <p>The father, although he assumes little command over his sons, is<lb/>
                    nevertheless anxious to instruct them in the necessary qualifications for<lb/>
                    hunting, &amp;c. while the mothers are equally attentive to their
                    daugh-<lb/>ters, in teaching them every thing that is considered necessary to
                    their<lb/> character and mode of living.</p>
                <p>On taking a view of their situation, one would naturally suppose the<lb/> life of
                    these women was an uninterrupted scene of toil and pain, which,<lb/> indeed, in
                    a great measure, it really is; for, besides attending to the<lb/> usual labours
                    of the field, and every culinary service, the duties of ma-<lb/>ternal care are
                    added, and require a considerable part of their atten-<lb/>tion - the men
                    assuming very little of the parental trust.</p>
                <p>Providence seems, in a remarkable manner, to have furnished these<lb/> females
                    with strength and fortitude adequate to their situation; for, at<lb/> those
                    times when the females of civilized nations require the most ten-<lb/>der care
                    and solicitude, these hardy daughters of the forest have little<lb/> or no
                    respite from their usual labours.</p>
                <p>Their children are frequently born in the woods, where the woman,<lb/>
                    accompanied by an elderly female, retires on the occasion, and if in<lb/> cold
                    weather a fire is made. The babe is immediately wrapt in a blan-<lb/>ket, and
                    generally, in a few hours, the mother returns with it to her<lb/> own
                    habitation, and engages in her usual employment, without any ap-<lb/>parent
                    injury to her health, or constitution.</p>
                <p>In the nursing of their children, a very considerable degree of inge-<lb/>nuity
                    is manifested; and for convenience of carrying, as also to keep<lb/> the limbs
                    of the young child straight, they confine it with it back to a<lb/> board, made
                    for the purpose; and often fancifully decorated with va-<lb/>rious trinkets, and
                    embroidery. This board is about two feet and a<lb/> half in length, and one in
                    breadth, with a little hoop in front, to protect<lb/> the head and face of the
                    child, from which also they suspend a curtain<lb/> to cover it from flies or
                    cold. At the bottom is a small foot-board, on<lb/> which the child is placed in
                    an erect posture, with its hand down its<lb/> sides. It is then swathed with a
                    bandage of cloth, from the feet to the<lb/> chin, so tight as to be unable to
                    disengage itself. If the weather is cold,<lb/> the skin of some animal, with
                    soft fur on it, is put next to it; and if a<lb/> female, a small block is placed
                    between the heels to give the toes an<lb/>
                    <pb n="21" facs="SW_HJ1830_019"/> inclination inwards, but if a male, they
                    endeavour to keep the feet in<lb/> a direction straight forward. One consequence
                    of this is, that the<lb/> track of the different sexes may easily be
                    distinguished. In this vehi-<lb/>cle, their children are carried about at
                    pleasure, suspended down the<lb/> back by a belt, which comes round the forehead
                    of the mother. When<lb/> taken to the woods, or fields, they are occasionally
                    set up against trees<lb/> or stumps, while the mother is employed in her
                    customary labours.<lb/> Sometimes they are suspended by the four corners to
                    poles laid hori-<lb/>zontally on forks stuck in the ground. In this position
                    they are drawn<lb/> backwards and forward, a little similar to rocking in a
                    cradle, and on<lb/> all occasions they are careful to prevent their children, as
                    much as may<lb/> be, from crying. They are loosened from the board a few times
                    in the<lb/> day; but being so accustomed to this confinement, and so perfectly
                    at<lb/> ease in it, they become uneasy when taken out, and their
                    tranquillity<lb/> is restored when replaced. This mode of confinement is
                    continued<lb/> about nine months, and is not only advantageous in the nursery,
                    but<lb/> also in carrying them with more ease and security.</p>
                <p>The chief employment of the men was hunting and fishing, making<lb/> canoes,
                    building their houses, dressing deer skin, making bowl, &amp;c.<lb/> in all
                    which they were ingenious, considering the tools they had to work<lb/> with. In
                    their hunting excursions, they generally take their wives and<lb/> families with
                    them, and remain several weeks in the woods, sometimes<lb/> twenty, forty, or
                    even one hundred miles from their villages, and gene-<lb/>rally up or down a
                    river, or some large stream of water, where they<lb/> can go in canoes. And
                    their household furniture being mostly porta-<lb/>ble, they carry as much with
                    them as answers their purpose during<lb/> their hunting tour. On getting to the
                    place they have chosen for a<lb/> hunting ground, they erect a temporary shed,
                    generally so situated as<lb/> to command an extensive view of the river, or some
                    smaller stream,<lb/> where they may have a favourable opportunity of seeing the
                    deer, or<lb/> other wild animals pass and repass, and thus it frequently
                    happens, that<lb/> they have an opportunity of shooting them from the door of
                    their cabin.</p>
                <p>The man sets out in the morning, generally taking his course along<lb/> some
                    stream of water, making, as he travels on, a kind of a way mark,<lb/> by once in
                    a while breaking down a bush; and in this way traverses<lb/> the country for
                    many miles in the course of the day, exploring the<lb/> haunts of the deer or
                    elk, as these animals resort to certain places called<lb/> deer licks, with
                    which the country abounds, where the water issuing<lb/> from them is somewhat
                    impregnated with salt. When the huntsman<lb/> kills a deer, or other animal, he
                    takes off the skin, which he generally<lb/> carries with him; and, dividing the
                    carcass in quarters, he hangs it<lb/> up in a tree, and then makes his way to
                    the path along the water<lb/> course, breaking down the bushes from the deer,
                    till he reaches it,<lb/>
                    <pb n="22" facs="SW_HJ1830_020"/> where he scrapes with his feet in the
                    leaves or snow, or otherwise in<lb/> case of snow falling to cover his marks on
                    the ground; he cuts down a<lb/> bush, and sharpening a stick, sets it in a
                    position pointing in a direct<lb/> line to the deer he has killed; this
                    furnishes a mark for his wife to find<lb/> the game he has killed, whose
                    business it is to carry it home to their<lb/> camp. He then pursues his hunting
                    again, and if he kills several deer<lb/> in the course of the day, he marks the
                    way from each in the same man-<lb/>ner to the main path by the water; and in the
                    evening returns to his<lb/> cabin tired with his day's toil, where his wife
                    furnishes him with a sup-<lb/>per of such as she has to prepare. He then relates
                    the success that<lb/> has attended him through the day, regales himself with the
                    fumes of<lb/> tobacco, and retires to rest on a deer skin, in his native
                    dignity, as abo-<lb/>riginal lord of the soil. If too late in the evening when
                    he returns, his<lb/> wife goes off next morning, directed by his marks where to
                    find the<lb/> deer he has killed, and brings them home on her back, one at a
                    time,<lb/> often from a great distance; but in the winter time, when they
                    have<lb/> great success in hunting, they leave much of the flesh in the
                    woods,<lb/> which is devoured by wolves, or other animals of prey.</p>
                <p>They sometimes watch the deer licks in the night season, where those<lb/> animals
                    more frequently resort than they do in the day time, and some-<lb/>times in
                    great numbers.</p>
                <p>The huntsman take his station in the evening at a proper distance,<lb/> and
                    kindles a small fire, which he is careful to conceal, until he hears<lb/> some
                    deer in the lick, and then having some torches, or dry wood, pre-<lb/>sently
                    makes the light shine round about, by which he can discover his<lb/> prey, and
                    the poor animals will stand gazing at the light, while he dis-<lb/>charges his
                    gun at them. In this manner, they frequently kill several<lb/> deer in a
                    night.</p>
                <p>As the snow falls deep in their country, frequently from one to three<lb/> feet,
                    it renders travelling difficult in the winter. The Indians, there-<lb/>fore,
                    have recourse to snow shoes, on which they can travel with much<lb/> facility,
                    and sometimes catch the deer by running them down, without<lb/> either dog or
                    gun.</p>
                <p>These snow shoes are made of a tough piece of wood curved before,<lb/> and
                    somewhat of an oval form, making a span of about two feet long,<lb/> and perhaps
                    one foot wide, in the middle. Two straight braces cross<lb/> this again at
                    proper distances to support the foot, and the intermediate<lb/> spaces are laced
                    with great neatness, with thongs of deer or elk skin.<lb/> They vary in size
                    according to the person wearing them. On these,<lb/> the huntsman wanders over
                    mountain, hill, and dale, in pursuit of the<lb/> wild animals of the wood, and
                    should he get benighted at too great a<lb/> distance to reach his cabin, and has
                    killed any deer, he strikes up a fire<lb/> in the woods, and roasts a ham or
                    shoulder of venison on a sharp stick<lb/>
                    <pb n="23" facs="SW_HJ1830_021"/> stuck in the ground before it; beginning
                    to eat as soon as one side is<lb/> done, and sometimes continuing to eat, as his
                    venison cooks, until he is<lb/> satisfied or the whole is consumed. It is said
                    that some of the hunters<lb/> when very hungry, will eat a ham of venison
                    without much difficulty.<lb/> This, in part, may be accounted for, from their
                    sometimes starving a<lb/> long time - for in general they are moderate
                    eaters.</p>
                
            </div>
            <div type="narrative">
                <head>Religious Ceremonies, Government, &amp;c. </head>
                
                <p>THE Indians believe in one all-wise, Supreme Being, who governs<lb/> the
                    universe; and that they will be made happy or miserable in a fu-<lb/>ture state,
                    according as their conduct pleases or displeases him, in this<lb/> state of
                    existence. This all-wise being they call How-wa-neeo, or<lb/> Great Spirit, and
                    believe him to be the creator of all good things, the<lb/> author of happiness,
                    and the rewarder of all good actions, both in this<lb/> world and in the
                    next.</p>
                <p>They believe, also, that there is an evil spirit, which they call
                    Nish-<lb/>shee-o-nee, who influences to bad actions, and who is the creator of
                    all<lb/> that is bad - such as venomous serpents, wolves, and all warlike
                    beasts,<lb/> poisonous weeds, bad thoughts and deeds, and every thing that is
                    pro-<lb/>ductive of unhappiness, both in man and on the earth.</p>
                <p>They believe there is a place of happiness called in their language<lb/>
                    Hight-ca-a-nongay, and that, when they die, if their conduct has been<lb/>
                    orderly, and pleasing to the Great Spirit in this world, they are ad-<lb/>mitted
                    into this happy region, among the spirits of good men and wo-<lb/>men, where the
                    Great Spirit is their comforter and chief ruler - and<lb/> that he there hangs
                    about their necks a string of implements for hunt-<lb/>ing, and for providing
                    themselves a comfortable living, and that they<lb/> are sent to hunt in a warm
                    country, where game is plenty, and the<lb/> land fertile for corn, beans, and
                    other vegetables.</p>
                <p>Twice in the year, arrayed in their best clothing, and decked with<lb/>
                    ornaments, they assemble at the town where their Chief lives, in order<lb/> to
                    render thanks to the Great Spirit for the favours which he hath con-<lb/>ferred
                    upon them. Their stated period for these ceremonies are in<lb/> the beginning of
                    autumn, when their new corn, beans, squashes, pota-<lb/>toes, &amp;c. are fit
                    for use, and again about the middle of winter, when<lb/> they generally return
                    to their villages with the produce of their hunt-<lb/>ing expeditions.</p>
                <p>After they are generally collected, both men and women, with the<lb/> children,
                    an examination takes place, whether any uneasiness or dis-<lb/>satisfaction
                    exist among them, and whether any have committed offences<lb/> or evil acts. Of
                    these it is often the case that the offender makes con-<lb/>fession, the design
                    of which is, that all wrong things may be done away,<lb/>
                    <pb n="24" facs="SW_HJ1830_022"/> and reconciliation take place, where any
                    differences have occurred,<lb/> and a promise on the part of the aggressor or to
                    try to do better for the<lb/> future; which done, the council then assembled
                    forgive them.</p>
                <p>They then institute a dance round or near a wooden image, which<lb/> stands a
                    little distance from the Chief's door, being formed of a huge<lb/> block of wood
                    into the similitude of a man, and artfully painted; em-<lb/>bellished with skin,
                    handkerchiefs, fine ribands, and feathers of a va-<lb/>riety of colours. Both
                    sexes join promiscuously in the dance - two<lb/> men being seated near the feet
                    of the image, make music by pounding<lb/> on a skin drawn over the mouth of a
                    kettle, or some other vessel, the<lb/> sound of which has some resemblance to
                    that of a drum. As they<lb/> move round in a circle, each one has a spoon,
                    ladle, or some other in-<lb/>strument in the left hand, and frequently give a
                    frightful halloo or<lb/> scream. The men are all naked from the waist up, and
                    their bodies<lb/> painted a variety of hues. They have also various kind of
                    trinkets<lb/> suspended from their ears and noses, and abundance of ornaments,
                    such<lb/> as belt and deer's hoofs strung like beads, fastened about their
                    legs,<lb/> which make a great rattle during the process of the dance.</p>
                <p>After a day pent at this general rendezvous, they divide into smaller<lb/>
                    companies, men and women apart, and keep up the dance in each<lb/> house in the
                    town. These dancing companies are preceded by two<lb/> men appointed for the
                    purpose, who are dressed in the most frightful<lb/> manner imaginable, being
                    covered with bear skins, and a bag of ashes<lb/> tied round their middle, behind
                    them, with a hole to suffer the ashes to<lb/> fly about as they move. Their
                    faces are covered with a large painted<lb/> mask, having a high mane on the
                    crown, made of long coarse horse<lb/> hair standing almost erect, and large eyes
                    encircled with a flame-co-<lb/>loured ring. The mouth is open, and shows their
                    own teeth, with<lb/> which they grin in a terrific manner, and their hands are
                    blackened so<lb/> as to leave the marks on every person they lay them on. They
                    carry<lb/> the shell of a mud tortoise, which has been dried for the purpose,
                    with<lb/> a stick thrust through it, which stretches the neck and large head
                    to<lb/> their full extent, and inside of the shell are a quantity of pebbles,
                    with<lb/> which they make a wonderful rattle.</p>
                <p>These men go from house to house, and rub this shell on the sides<lb/> and up and
                    down the door posts. They also frequently enter into the<lb/> house, but say
                    nothing, nor do any injury. As they travel about, if<lb/> they meet with any
                    person, male or female, in their way, they pursue<lb/> them - those who turn and
                    receive them in a friendly way, they shake<lb/> hands with, but say nothing -
                    but it is rather expected that many<lb/> should run as if terrified; these are
                    pursued, and if overtaken before<lb/> they get into a house, are laid hold of,
                    and blackened with their hands,<lb/>
                    <pb n="25" facs="SW_HJ1830_023"/> but no other injury is offered, and,
                    except a frightful yelling noise, no-<lb/>thing is spoken.</p>
                <p>The design of these frightful representations is, to personify and imi-<lb/> tate
                    the bad spirit, and to remind the Indians of the necessity to amend<lb/> their
                    ways, and avoid all wrong things.</p>
                <p>After this concert of heathenish superstition has continued for seve-<lb/>ral
                    days, they assemble again round the wooden image* near the coun-<lb/> cil house,
                    and sacrifice a dog, first decorating him with strings of wam-<lb/> pum, fine
                    ribands, and some paintings; and after hanging him on the<lb/> image, burn him
                    to ashes, on a fire kindled near him for the purpose.<lb/> On some extraordinary
                    occasions, they eat the flesh of the dog, and a<lb/> white dog is always
                    preferred, as being deemed a more acceptable of-<lb/> fering.</p>
                <p>While the dog is consuming, they dance round the fire, making a<lb/> dreadful
                    yelling and whooping, and during the process of the dance,<lb/> about one pound
                    of tobacco, of a particular kind, rubbed fine, which<lb/> they consider as
                    peculiarly agreeable to the Great Spirit, is thrown on<lb/> the fire, in the
                    smoke whereof, their aspirations, as they suppose, as-<lb/> cending, they
                    believe are heard by the Great Spirit, and are offered,<lb/> together with their
                    dancing, under a profession of pleasing him.</p>
                <p>During this ascension of the smoke, a Chief whom they call their<lb/> minister,
                    and who appears to have the command and superintendence<lb/> of this ceremony,
                    addresses the Great Spirit in a speech, the purport<lb/> of which is an
                    acknowledgment for favours received, thanks for pre-<lb/> servation in times
                    past, and imploring his continued care and protection.</p>
                <note resp="author">
                    <p>*About the year 1802 this image, decaying at the ground, fell down. This
                        circum-<lb/>stance occasioned very considerable agitation among them, to
                        know in what manner to<lb/> dispose of it, without giving offence to the
                        Great Spirit; as they considered it to be his<lb/> representative. Some were
                        for taking it into the woods, and leaving plenty of provi-<lb/>sions beside
                        it. Others were for erecting another in its stead, and some were for
                        dis-<lb/>carding such a representation entirely. </p>
                    <p>A <persName key="habee1">son</persName> of <persName key="cornp2"
                            >Cornplanter</persName>, the Chief, who had got his ideas a little
                        expanded by an edu-<lb/>cation among white people, reasoned with them on the
                        subject, and told them that it<lb/> had grown up in the woods like other
                        trees of the forest; that they had cut it down,<lb/> and made it into the
                        form of a man, but it was still nothing but a block of wood, and<lb/> had no
                        power or sense, and, therefore, could not represent the Great Spirit, as
                        they<lb/> imagined; and if they would give it up to him, he would dispose of
                        it. To this they<lb/> reluctantly consented, and on conditions only, that he
                        would take all the responsibility<lb/> of any harm happening the nation in
                        consequence thereof. Accordingly he tumbled<lb/> it into the river, and let
                        it swim down, the Indians carefully viewing the process, to see<lb/> whether
                        any evil would befall him.</p>
                    <p>Some time after, several of them passing along the river, discovered it
                        lodged on an<lb/> island, about eleven miles below its former station, at
                        which they appeared struck with<lb/> astonishment, and considerably alarmed,
                        but let it remain as they found it.</p>
                </note>
                <pb n="26" facs="SW_HJ1830_024"/>
                <p>He then addresses the people, advising them how they ought to con-<lb/>duct, and
                    pointing out some of the prominent evils which they ought to<lb/> avoid; one of
                    the greatest of these is stealing, and another is, for the<lb/> husband to
                    desert and separate himself from his wife during pregnancy;<lb/> but taking the
                    life of another is not considered a crime so capital, as<lb/> they are left at
                    liberty to revenge it, by taking the life of the murder-<lb/>er. This may be
                    done with impunity by the nearest relative of the<lb/> deceased, and they then
                    consider the cries of blood to be done away.<lb/> Preparatory to these
                    sacrifices they are careful to procure a sufficien-<lb/>cy of provisions.</p>
                <p>This is done by deputing a certain number of their warriors to hunt,<lb/> who
                    encircle a large space of hunting ground, and all the game taken<lb/> thereon is
                    devoted to this feast. Previously to that which was held in<lb/> the summer of
                    1799, thirty men were sent out, who returned the day<lb/> following with
                    seventeen deer. Great attention is paid to the cooking,<lb/> and certain places
                    are appointed where the entertainment shall be<lb/> given. Spirituous liquors
                    are not allowed on these occasions, although<lb/> near the conclusion there are
                    instances, at times, of some of them get-<lb/>ting intoxicated.</p>
                <p>Their stated time, according to ancient custom, for holding these
                    sa-<lb/>crifices, is four days at a time, twice in the year; but they
                    frequently<lb/> continue their feasting and dancing at intervals and by
                    companies, for<lb/> eight or ten days; and, after the last day being spent in
                    playing at<lb/> games of chance, they generally conclude by the firing of
                    guns.</p>
                <p>Their reason for performing these ceremonious rites, at these two<lb/> seasons of
                    the year, they say, is to return thanks to the Great Spirit,<lb/> for sending
                    them plenty of bread and meat - that it was the way their<lb/> forefathers had
                    taught them, and they knew of no better; and although<lb/> the feast is
                    conducted with considerable noise, and apparent confusion,<lb/> it is also
                    attended at intervals with much solemnity, and on the part of<lb/> many of them,
                    purely on a religious ground, and from sincere and good<lb/> motives. But, at
                    the same time, they are willing to acknowledge that<lb/> their worship was not
                    performed with so much solemnity as their fore-<lb/>fathers practised.</p>
                <p>Besides their public devotional feasts and sacrifices, the Indians ex-<lb/>ercise
                    a kind of family worship, at times, when they are sitting together,<lb/>
                    particularly in the evening. If one of the heads of the family feels an<lb/>
                    impulse to address the Great Spirit, he, or she, yields to it with an
                    au-<lb/>dible voice, and this, among the more serious class, is frequently
                    per-<lb/>formed, though not on any stated days or times. They are sometimes<lb/>
                    exercised in this way when their friends are with them, and the subject<lb/> of
                    aspiration is a thanksgiving for the preservation of their particular<lb/>
                    family or tribe, and for supplying the varied necessaries and comforts<lb/>
                    <pb n="27" facs="SW_HJ1830_025"/> of life, desiring their continuance; an
                    evidence, this, that among all<lb/> their superstition and ignorance, they are
                    not destitute of the divine<lb/> principle operating within them, and raising in
                    their minds a sense of<lb/> their dependent state, the obligations they are
                    under to their great pre-<lb/> server and benefactor, and the necessity of
                    prayer for the continua-<lb/> tion of his blessings and favours.</p>
                <p>Though much reserved in expression, with regard to abstruse subjects,<lb/> they
                    nevertheless at times manifest an inquisitive disposition respecting<lb/> the
                    creation of the world, the formation of man, and whether Indians<lb/> and white
                    people go to the same place after death, or whether they<lb/> will be all of one
                    language in a future state.</p>
                <p>Their funeral rites are observed with great solemnity, and succeeded<lb/> by deep
                    mourning. Whatever might have been their ancient custom,<lb/> as stated by some
                    writers with respect to a place of general deposit of<lb/> the bones of their
                    dead, I find no such tradition among them at the pre-<lb/>sent day. A spot of
                    ground contiguous to each village is occupied as a<lb/> place of interment, and
                    each grave has a separate covering of boards,<lb/> or clefts of wood. The corpse
                    dressed in the best apparel is put into a<lb/> coffin made of boards, when they
                    can be procured, or otherwise bark<lb/> laid beneath and over it in the grave,
                    and sometimes a new blanket<lb/> and small kettle is enclosed with it, and
                    frequently other articles, to<lb/> which the deceased was attached while
                    living.</p>
                <p> As they believe in the resurrection of the spirit, and that for some<lb/> time
                    after death it is common for it to ascend and descend, in order,<lb/> therefore,
                    to afford it more easy access to its former tabernacle, a hole<lb/> is cut in
                    both the head of the coffin and the covering of the tomb, the<lb/> ground not
                    being considered as any obstruction to its entrance or egress.</p>
                <p>At these mourning processions, the women, who more generally at-<lb/>tend than
                    the men, and have the task of burial assigned them, give<lb/> every possible
                    vent to their passions, as also when they return to the<lb/> house of the
                    deceased, where they indulge in feasting, and extremity of<lb/> grief; and this
                    is renewed by the female relatives, and neighbours meet-<lb/>ing at the same
                    house every morning, for nine days, and kept up by<lb/> doleful noises and
                    lamentable cries, for about the space of half an hour.<lb/> When the days of
                    mourning are thus ended, they meet together, and<lb/> are consoled to dry up
                    their tears, from which time they endeavour to<lb/> discard all marks of
                    lamentation.</p>
                <p>They relate circumstances that happened formerly, of ancient In-<lb/>dians, who
                    were disabled from hunting, by infirmity, and becoming tired<lb/> of life, would
                    request to be buried alive. A grave or hole was then<lb/> dug, in which a seat
                    was formed in digging, the ancient Indian was then<lb/> let down, and taking his
                    last seat, the other Indians began to fill in the<lb/> earth, doing it very
                    gently and tenderly till it had risen to his chin. A<lb/>
                    <pb n="28" facs="SW_HJ1830_026"/> pause was then made, and some ceremony
                    used, after which the young<lb/> warriors threw in the dirt very hastily, so as
                    to prevent their being<lb/> witnesses to his struggles, and to terminate his
                    sufferings as speedily as<lb/> possible. Happily there exists no such barbarous
                    custom among them<lb/> at the present day. They are superstitious in the
                    extreme, with re-<lb/> spect to dreams, and witchcraft, and councils are often
                    called, on the<lb/> most trifling occurrences of this nature. To elucidate this
                    - in the win-<lb/>ter of 1799, while one of the Friends was engaged in
                    instructing the<lb/> children in school learning, a message carne from a
                    confederate tribe,<lb/> eighty miles distant, stating that one of their little
                    girls had dreamed<lb/> that “the devil was in all white people alike, and that
                    they ought not<lb/> to receive instruction from the Quakers, neither was it
                    right for their<lb/> children to learn to read and write.” In consequence of
                    this circum-<lb/>stance, a council was called, the matter was deliberated on,
                    and divers<lb/> of them became so much alarmed, as to prevent their children
                    from<lb/> attending the school for some time.</p>
                <p>They are also in the practice of collecting together and making feasts<lb/> in
                    remembrance of their dead, some months after the interment, under<lb/> an
                    apprehension that the deceased will receive some benefit thereby.<lb/> And if an
                    Indian of any particular tribe dreams a remarkable dream,<lb/> respecting a
                    deceased relative being hungry, or in need of sympathy,<lb/> or assistance in
                    any way, the Indians of the deceased's particular tribe<lb/> are informed of it,
                    and a deputation is sent out to hunt. The game<lb/> thus taken, is prepared and
                    cooked, and a feast and dance in a religious<lb/> way is instituted, which
                    continues for a day or more, whereby they ap-<lb/>prehend the wants of the
                    deceased are satisfied.</p>
                <p>Exclusive of these, they have frequent banquets, in which they re-<lb/>gale
                    themselves with strong liquors, and pass whole nights in singing,<lb/> dancing,
                    and music - performing every whimsical and antic manœuvre<lb/> which their wild
                    imaginations can invent, and which in some instances<lb/> baffles
                    description.</p>
                <p>Their marriages are as singularly conducted as their worship, and<lb/> funerals.
                    They generally marry young, the males frequently between<lb/> fourteen and
                    eighteen, and the females from twelve to sixteen. The<lb/> match is frequently
                    agreed upon by the parents, while the children<lb/> are quite young, in which
                    case they are betrothed without consulting<lb/> each other's choice, or
                    inclination. When they arrive at maturer age<lb/> before the choice is made, and
                    a young man has fixed on the female<lb/> he wishes to make his companion, he
                    acquaints his mother or eldest<lb/> sister, if he has either living, or
                    otherwise some female relative, of his<lb/> intentions, who imparts his desires
                    to the mother or sister, or other fe-<lb/>male relative of her with whom he is
                    enamoured, and this proposal they<lb/> communicate to the young woman.</p>
                <pb n="29" facs="SW_HJ1830_027"/>
                <p>It is also common to present her or her father with some kind of<lb/> trinkets or
                    merchandise to the value of several dollars. If his proposal<lb/> of marriage is
                    not accepted, a negative is put upon it by returning the<lb/> present, but if,
                    after some days consideration, it is satisfactory to the<lb/> young woman and
                    parties concerned, her mother or sister accompanies<lb/> her to the young man's
                    home, and presents her to him. The mother<lb/> or sister then withdraws, and she
                    stays with her proposed husband.<lb/> They appear apparently shy of each other,
                    and now perhaps their in-<lb/>timacy and knowledge of each other's
                    qualifications are only commenc-<lb/>ing. No ideas of state and grandeur - no
                    homage of wealth - no pride<lb/> of house or furniture are sought for, on these
                    occasions. The man<lb/> having signalized himself by feats of hunting, and the
                    woman by her<lb/> industry in the culture of corn and vegetables, are the
                    criteria and<lb/> summit to which their wishes aspire. As the season for
                    planting, tend-<lb/>ing, and gathering corn, procuring firewood, &amp;c. come
                    on, the female<lb/> connexions of the young woman assist her in the different
                    operations<lb/> during the first year, at the end of which, without any other
                    ceremony,<lb/> the nuptial tie is consummated and considered valid and
                    honourable.<lb/> They sometimes, however, take a shorter way for it, and too
                    commonly<lb/> part again on small disagreements. Although they appear to be
                    natu-<lb/>rally lively in their dispositions, and well calculated for social
                    inter-<lb/>course, yet the different sexes are very jealous, and apparently shy
                    of<lb/> each other, so that it is rare to see a man and woman, even of the
                    same<lb/> tribe, conversing together without witnesses. And when a woman
                    has<lb/> occasion to go from home, it is accounted honourable to take with
                    her<lb/> one or more children to testify, if needful, that she has been
                    orderly.<lb/> There are too many proofs, however, that this is only a pretended
                    shy-<lb/>ness, yet being sanctioned, and established by custom, it is
                    productive<lb/> of serious evils, by putting a negative on an open, friendly
                    acquaint-<lb/>ance of the sexes, with each other, the natural tendency whereof
                    would<lb/> be, the mutual improvement of their minds, and furnish a
                    knowledge<lb/> of each other's qualifications, which in many instances would
                    produce<lb/> undesigned and permanent attachments. Whereas they frequently<lb/>
                    marry without real affection, without a knowledge of each other's
                    dis-<lb/>positions, and before the judgment is ripe for such a choice; the
                    con-<lb/>sequence of which is that separations often take place - so that
                    there<lb/> are many instances among them, of men who have turned off
                    several<lb/> wives, and of women who have discarded as many husbands. These<lb/>
                    on both sides marry again (in a clandestine way) to others, and in some<lb/>
                    instances change back again, and thus what ought to be esteemed the<lb/> most
                    important connexion in life, is lightly formed and dissolved, and<lb/> shifted
                    about in a manner unknown among any people rightly civilized.</p>
                <p>When such separations take place, the mother generally takes the<lb/>
                    <pb n="30" facs="SW_HJ1830_028"/> children, and I believe their property
                    also descends by inheritance, in<lb/> the female line of succession.</p>
                <p>It is said that, formerly, when an Indian of distinction died, his gun,<lb/>
                    blanket, knife, and other property, not buried with him, were preserved<lb/>
                    about twelve, and sometimes eighteen months. This delay was occa-<lb/>sioned, in
                    consequence of an opinion which they entertained, that it was<lb/> not decent or
                    respectful to bring them into use sooner; they were then<lb/> sent into council,
                    and held up to public view, the Indians present being<lb/> informed that they
                    were the goods of such a deceased chief. On the<lb/> articles being thus
                    severally held up, any of the young men who inclined,<lb/> were at liberty to
                    advance and snatch them away, till the whole were<lb/> thus distributed, the
                    relatives of the deceased making no claim in con-<lb/>sequence of connexion.
                    This custom though grown out of use among<lb/> the <orgName key="seneca"
                        >Senecas</orgName>, is said still to prevail among some Indian nations, in
                    the<lb/> southern states.</p>
                <p>Although they have no regular system of laws by which they are<lb/> governed, and
                    every man is master in his own family, yet they are more<lb/> or less influenced
                    by certain principles which conduce to their general<lb/> benefit. They possess
                    their land in common, and no individual has any<lb/> further security for the
                    improvement he makes on the land, than what<lb/> custom has established. This,
                    however, is held inviolable, and no in-<lb/>stance occurred in the course of my
                    observation, of their encroaching<lb/> on each other's property, without consent
                    of parties; and if disputes<lb/> at any time happen with respect to the
                    boundaries of the land they<lb/> wish to cultivate, the interference of the
                    chiefs settles the difference.</p>
                <p>The <orgName key="seneca">Seneca nation</orgName> is composed of eight great
                    families or tribes.<lb/> These are designated by the names of Bear, Wolf, Deer,
                    Crane, Snipe,<lb/> Beaver, Turtle, and Hawk tribes. Each tribe proposes its own
                    chiefs,<lb/> and brings forward all other matters in council that particularly
                    relate<lb/> to their own people. The different tribes have each at least one
                    Chief<lb/> to represent them in council. The office of chief is not in all cases
                    in-<lb/>herited in a lineal succession, but they are promoted by the will of
                    the<lb/> people, and appointed by the united content of the chiefs in
                    council.<lb/> They have no power further than what their weight of
                    influence<lb/> gives them. Activity in hunting, wisdom in council, and exploits
                    in<lb/> war, are high traits in their character, to raise them to this
                    station;<lb/> and while they continue to hold the good opinion and respect of
                    the<lb/> nation, they are advised with, and looked up to, in all matters of
                    diffi-<lb/>culty; but when the good opinion ceases, they lose their influence
                    in<lb/> council, and are discarded from being actors in public affairs.</p>
                <p>Excepting some who have private grants and specific annuities from<lb/>
                    government, their chiefs have no pecuniary advantage above other In-<lb/>dians,
                    nor in their private capacity are they treated with any dis-<lb/>tinguished mark
                    of respect.</p>
                <pb n="31" facs="SW_HJ1830_029"/>
                <p>The genealogy of each particular tribe is traced, according to their<lb/> degrees
                    of consanguinity, by the side of the mother. They do not live<lb/> in separate
                    villages, but are settled promiscuously throughout the <orgName key="seneca"
                        >Sene-<lb/>ca nation</orgName>. There are also a number of inferior chiefs
                    appointed at<lb/> each village, who are called upon as counsellors, when
                    occasions re-<lb/>quire, and no business of importance is transacted without
                    their privity<lb/> and concurrence.</p>
                <p>These chiefs are empowered to inculcate good precepts, and encour-<lb/>age the
                    youth and warriors to sobriety and good actions. And although<lb/> their women
                    are degraded below the rank they maintain in more civil-<lb/>ized societies, yet
                    even here they possess considerable influence, in re-<lb/>gulating the conduct
                    of the men, in various respects. Some of the more<lb/> wise and knowing among
                    them are frequently admitted into their coun-<lb/>cils, and give their
                    sentiments publicly on matters of importance.</p>
                <p>They are very jealous of encroachments on what they esteem their<lb/> rights and
                    privileges; and offences of this nature have often given rise to<lb/> war
                    between nations. Such of the captives taken in war as are pre-<lb/>served alive,
                    are sometimes adopted into families, in the place of rela-<lb/>tives who have
                    been killed in the war. In such cases they are treated<lb/> kindly: and several
                    of this description remain among the <orgName key="seneca">Senecas</orgName>,
                    who<lb/> have intermarried with them, and become so habituated to their
                    man-<lb/>ners and mode of life, that they show no inclination to leave them.</p>
                <p>It is said many of the devoted number of captives were formerly<lb/> roasted and
                    eaten. There was living, since Friends settled among the<lb/>
                    <orgName key="seneca">Senecas</orgName>, one or two Indians residing on the
                        <geogName key="alleg">Alleghany river</geogName>, who had<lb/> partaken of
                    this inhuman feasting; but the custom has long since been<lb/> exploded by this
                    nation.</p>
                <p>Though honesty, in a general way, may be reckoned one of their<lb/> signal
                    virtues, yet instances of stealing sometimes occur.</p>
                <p>When any discovery is made that would lead to detection of the<lb/> person
                    committing a theft, complaint is made to the chiefs, who despatch<lb/> a
                    messenger commanding his appearance forthwith before the council;<lb/> this
                    mandate he instantly obeys; the charge is then opened to him, and<lb/> if he is
                    guilty, and confession is made, the property taken is restored,<lb/> if in
                    being. Every Chief or warrior in council is then at liberty to ex-<lb/>press
                    what they think, or wish to say, one by one, on the occasion,<lb/> which the
                    offender is obliged to hear. This is considered a severe pu-<lb/>nishment, but
                    no other is inflicted. Should the person charged deny<lb/> that he is guilty, he
                    is considered innocent - for it is remarkable that<lb/> they generally confess
                    when justly charged, and also that their eyes<lb/> and countenances immediately
                    betray them. There is no corporeal<lb/> punishment practised among them, except
                    where the crime is consider-<lb/>ed worthy of death.</p>
                <pb n="32" facs="SW_HJ1830_030"/>
                <p>The Indian names are often significant of something in nature, as<lb/>
                    <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName>'s name in the Seneca language is
                    Ky-on-twa-ky; Connu-<lb/>dia signifies a handsome lake, Ogis-quah-tah is dry
                    musk, Oenda<lb/> means the first ripe corn, Yeang-qwa-haunt, chew-tobacco,
                    &amp;c. They<lb/> are also frequently named from occurrences that happen near
                    the time<lb/> of their birth, and their names are occasionally changed in
                    consequence<lb/> of remarkable circumstances taking place, or of particular
                    employ-<lb/>ments, or acts of individuals.</p>
                <p>It is supposed that in a general way the Indians rather exceed white<lb/> people
                    in longevity, often living, as they imagine, to the age of ninety<lb/> and one
                    hundred years; but as they keep no written records of births<lb/> or other
                    occurrences, nor have any regular method of computing time,<lb/> other than by
                    moons and winters, or the remembrance of remarkable<lb/> events, very few of
                    their elderly people can give a correct account<lb/> how old they are. There is
                    now living on the <geogName key="alleg">Alleghany river</geogName> an old<lb/>
                    woman, who can call her descendants round her to the sixth generation.</p>
                <p>There was also an Indian living at <placeName key="catta1"
                        >Cattaraugus</placeName>, in the year 1800,<lb/> who said he was one hundred
                    and twenty-one years of age. He said<lb/> he had been in <placeName key="phila"
                        >Philadelphia</placeName> when it was a very small town, and gave<lb/> such
                    a circumstantial and regular account of his life, as (together with<lb/> his
                    aged brow and furrowed cheeks,) induced me to credit his relation.</p>
                <p>The Indians are frequently skilful in the application of simples, as<lb/> also in
                    the knowledge of the medicinal qualities of divers herbs and<lb/> plants.</p>
                <p>They, however, practice bleeding on trivial occasions, and when a<lb/> person has
                    been a considerable time sick, in a lingering condition, and<lb/> the foregoing
                    applications prove ineffectual to restore him to health, it<lb/> is common for
                    the friends of the diseased person to collect, and, dressing<lb/> two or more
                    men with masks and other accoutrements, as in times of<lb/> public worship, they
                    repair to the habitation of the sick, which they<lb/> go round, rattling and
                    rubbing the tortoise shell, and whooping in a<lb/> frightful manner.</p>
                <p>Although this is a known custom, and in time of health gives no<lb/> alarm, yet
                    on the debilitated Indian, whose fears are awakened by<lb/> knowing what is to
                    be endured, it has considerable effect. The men<lb/> then enter the house,
                    continuing the noise and acting every wild con-<lb/>tortion and manœuvre which
                    their imaginations devise. Sometimes<lb/> they pull the sick person (male or
                    female,) about the house, dirtying<lb/> them with their black hands, rubbing
                    their heads and bodies over with<lb/> ashes, and handling the patient in so
                    rough a manner, that a person<lb/> unacquainted with their custom, might suppose
                    they were going to kill<lb/> him. After this wild treatment, and having
                    thoroughly dirtied the<lb/> house with ashes, they withdraw, and leave the nurse
                    to clean after<lb/> them.</p>
                <pb n="33" facs="SW_HJ1830_031"/>
                <p>Absurd as this practice appears, in many cases it is said to have had<lb/> a
                    beneficial effect, by restoring perspiration, working on the imagina-<lb/>tion,
                    and rousing the indisposed person to a salutary exertion.</p>
                <p>Their idea is, that they drive away the evil spirit by this procedure.</p>
                <p>Their skill in painting and hieroglyphics is somewhat extraordinary.</p>
                <p>In their travelling excursions, they frequently describe on the bark<lb/> of
                    trees, by certain emblems or characters which they understand, the<lb/> time
                    they have been from home, the number of persons in company,<lb/> the ensign of
                    the tribe they belong to, the course they are going, and<lb/> the number of deer
                    or other animals they have killed.</p>
                <p>They are also very ingenious in their idea of the geography of the<lb/> country
                    with which they are acquainted, and readily trace on a map<lb/> the particular
                    waters they have traversed, pointing out their bearings<lb/> and courses.</p>
                <p>Their reckoning of time is by moons and winters, and the length of<lb/> their
                    journey is computed by the number of days it takes to travel it.</p>
                <p>They also divide the day into certain parts, such as morning, noon,<lb/> and
                    evening; and in speaking of the time of day, point to the sun's<lb/> place in
                    the firmament. In speaking of sun-set, they say, Onah Gagh-<lb/>qua, (the sun is
                    gone.)</p>
                <p>Their ideas are very confused with regard to astronomy, and they<lb/> have mean
                    conceptions of the rotundity of the earth.</p>
                <p>They cannot conceive that a person travelling in a direct line could<lb/> ever
                    come back to the same place again, or that men can walk on the<lb/> opposite
                    side of the globe to them. They, like some of the ancients,<lb/> rather favour
                    the idea of the earth being an extended plain, and not<lb/> understanding the
                    principles of gravitation and attraction, they believe<lb/> that if the world
                    turned round, the water would unquestionably fall<lb/> off from it.</p>
                <p>Their ancient notion respecting thunder was, and still has considera-<lb/>ble
                    place among them, that a being whom they call Eno, sent from the<lb/> Great
                    Spirit, and inhabiting the southern mountains, was in the prac-<lb/>tice of
                    discharging a short gun which he employed in that way, and<lb/> sometimes
                    striking the trees to show his great strength and power.<lb/> They supposed him
                    to live on large snakes and wild beasts, and that he<lb/> was always a friend to
                    the Indians, though he sometimes killed white<lb/> people.</p>
                <p>They believe that Eno sends down a stone bolt about one inch in<lb/> diameter,
                    and seven or eight in length, with which he splits trees, &amp;c.<lb/> and when
                    they are so fortunate as to procure this bolt, they entertain<lb/> an opinion
                    that constant success will attend all their undertakings while<lb/> they possess
                    it. They also believe that fire taken from a tree burning<lb/> by lightning and
                    kindled in their houses, is an antidote against fatal <lb/>5 <pb n="34"
                        facs="SW_HJ1830_032"/> disorders. This they keep burning for a certain
                    time, and then ex-<lb/>tinguish it, and kindle another fire in it, stead. In
                    times of drought,<lb/> they frequently go to a tree that has been lately struck
                    with lightning,<lb/> and kindle a fire at the root, in the smoke whereof
                    ascending, they of-<lb/>fer up a petition to Eno, praying him to send rain; and
                    circumstances<lb/> of this ort frequently occur a little previous to rain
                    coming, which<lb/> greatly tends to keep up this superstitious idea among them.
                    These<lb/> notions, however, are rather declining among the <orgName
                        key="seneca">Senecas</orgName>.</p>
                <p>These Indians, in general, (their young people excepted,) were un-<lb/>happily
                    the victims of great intemperance, when they could obtain<lb/> strong liquors;
                    and most of the evils that afflict them might be traced<lb/> to that source.
                    This article of strong drink was sometimes carried<lb/> among them by white
                    traders, who also furnished them with abundance<lb/> of silver trinkets, beads,
                    and the like ornaments adapted to their taste.</p>
                <p>The Indian themselves were also in the practice of trading to the<lb/> frontier
                    settlements of white people, and exchanging their skins, furs,<lb/> and other
                    merchandise, for liquor, which they often brought home to<lb/> their villages,
                    and sold out by retail. This kept many of them conti-<lb/>nually in a state of
                    intoxication, while they could obtain the liquor,<lb/> and many scenes of human
                    wretchedness were the fatal consequences<lb/> thus produced. Their aged women,
                    in particular, were conspicuous<lb/> sufferers by this evil, and were often seen
                    lying beside the paths, over-<lb/>come by it.</p>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
