<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei-print.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" hkey="global.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>Halliday Jackson's Journal, 1806: Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>Emma Remsberg</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Journal transcribed by</resp>
                    <name>Emma Remsberg</name>

                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Tri-Co Digital Humanities Initiative</sponsor>
                <funder>Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 136 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>This work is the property of the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore
                        College. It may be copied freely by individuals for personal use, research,
                        and teaching (including distribution to classes) as long as this statement
                        of availability is included in the text. It may be linked to freely in
                        Internet editions of all kinds, including for—profit works.</p>
                    <p>Publishers, libraries, and other information providers interested in
                        providing this text in a commercial or non—profit product or from an
                        information server must contact Swarthmore College for licensing and cost
                        information.</p>
                    <p> Scholars interested in changing or adding to these texts by, for example,
                        creating a new edition of the text (electronically or in print) with
                        substantive editorial changes, may do so with the permission of Swarthmore
                        College. This is the case whether the new publication will be made available
                        at a cost or free of charge.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2014">2014</date>
                <idno type="local">SW_HJ1806</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Native Americans and Quakers: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>Miscellaneous Manuscripts</collection>
                        <idno>Mss003/43</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>72 pp. (1 volume)</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The 1806 journal of Halliday Jackson is in the collections of Friends Historical
                    Library of Swarthmore College. It was transcribed and encoded as part of a
                    larger project to make available a number of Quaker journals which document
                    contact between Friends and Native Americans between 1790 and 1810.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> The transcribers and editor attempted to render the author’s orthography and
                    grammar as they appear on the page of his journal, even when the author’s own
                    spelling and usage are inconsistent. Additionally, many questions remain about
                    spelling the names of his Quaker acquaintances, individual Native Americans who
                    populate his journal, and Indian villages and towns. The transcribers and editor
                    attempted to remain faithful to the author’s Anglicized spellings in all cases. </p>
                <p>The author of the original journal does not include page numbers on his
                    manuscript; the page numbers have been interpolated by the transcribers to
                    correspond with the manuscript sheets.</p>
            </editorialDecl>

        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written in <date when="1806">1806</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Quakers--Pennsylvania</item>
                        <item>Alleghany River Valley (Pa. and N.Y.)—History</item>
                        <item>Church and state--Ohio</item>
                        <item>Cornplanter, Seneca chief, 1732?-1836</item>
                        <item>Indian reservations</item>
                        <item>Indians of North America--Missions</item>
                        <item>New York (State)--Description and travel</item>
                        <item>Pennsylvania--Description and travel</item>

                        <item>Philadelphia Yearly Meeting of the Religious Society of Friends</item>
                        <item>Quakers--Pennsylvania--Diaries</item>
                        <item>Quakers--Political activity</item>
                        <item>Seneca Indians</item>
                        <item>Society of Friends--Missions</item>
                        <item>Voyages and Travels</item>

                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>

        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>

        <body>
            <div type="narrative">
                <pb n="1" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_001"/>
                <head>Some Account of a Visit <unclear>pa<damage/></unclear><lb/> to the Friends at
                        <placeName key="tunes">Tunesassa</placeName> &amp;
                    <unclear>the</unclear><lb/> Indians liveing on <geogName key="alleg"
                        >Allegany</geogName> &amp; <geogName key="catta1"
                        ><unclear>Cata-</unclear><lb/> raugus</geogName> Rivers, agreably to an
                        <unclear>appoint-</unclear><lb/> ment of the Committee on Indian<lb/>
                    Affairs in the <date when="1806-08">8th Month 1806</date>--</head>

                <p> I left home on Seconday the <date when="1806-09-01">first of the <lb/> ninth
                        month</date>, &amp; pursuant to agreement<lb/> met with <persName
                        key="jphil1">John Philips</persName>, &amp; <persName key="ibons1">Isaac
                        Bonsal</persName><lb/> who were to be my Companions on the inten-<lb/> ded
                    embassy, &amp; <persName key="nwaln1">Nicholas Waln Jr</persName> also
                        <unclear>pro</unclear>-<lb/> pos'd accompanying us for the benefit of<lb/>
                    his health. -- On the <date when="1806-09-02">2nd</date> we set out<lb/> from
                        <persName key="ibons1">Isaac Bonsals</persName> and traveling by way of<lb/>
                    <geogName key="maide">Maidencreek</geogName>, <placeName key="catta"
                        >Catawessy</placeName>, <placeName key="muncy">Muncy</placeName>, <placeName
                        key="wport">Williams-<lb/> port</placeName>
                    <unclear>and</unclear>
                    <placeName key="tmorr1">Morris's Settlement</placeName> on <geogName key="pinec"
                        >pine Creek</geogName><lb/> we <unclear>reached</unclear>
                    <persName key="fking1">Francis Kings</persName> on the
                    <unclear>Oswega</unclear><lb/> in <unclear>the after</unclear>noon of the <date
                        when="1806-09-10">10th</date> all in good<lb/>
                    <unclear>health, having</unclear> had pleasant weather for<lb/>
                    <unclear>traveling</unclear> the night previ<unclear>ous</unclear><lb/>
                    <damage/><unclear>lay on our Blankets</unclear>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="2" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_002"/>
                    <unclear>in</unclear> the woods near one of the head springs<lb/>
                    <unclear>of the</unclear>
                    <geogName key="alleg">Alligany River</geogName> --</p>
                <p><gap/> This Morning was very Cool for the Time<lb/>
                    <unclear>of y</unclear>ear and a large white frost which nearly<lb/>
                    <unclear>de</unclear>stroy'd the Buckwheat in that settlement<lb/> and injur'd
                    the Corn very much--Agreably<lb/> to an appointment of <persName key="ibons1"
                        >Isaac Bonsals</persName>, today <lb/> at ten Oclock a Meeting was held with
                    the<lb/> few Settlers in this place. <persName key="mbell1">Mary
                    Bell</persName>, with<lb/> her Children attended and several others to<lb/> the
                    amount of near twenty in number, &amp;<lb/>
                    <persName key="ibons1">I.B.</persName> had good Counsel to communicate--</p>
                <p> After dineing with <persName key="fking1">F.K.</persName> we rode to Major<lb/>
                    Hoopes's settlement at the mouth of <unclear>Issue</unclear> on<lb/>
                    <geogName key="alleg">Allegany River</geogName>, 12 Miles. and was
                    entertain'd<lb/> in a friendly and hospitable manner--<lb/> This evening two
                    Indians with whom I<lb/> was acquainted arived here from th<unclear>ier
                        set</unclear>tle-<lb/> ment at <placeName key="tunes"
                    >Tunessassa</placeName>, on their way <unclear>to <placeName key="genes"
                            >Gen</placeName></unclear><placeName key="genes">esee</placeName><lb/>
                    They also know me, seem'd <unclear>glad to see us,</unclear><lb/> said our
                    friends at <placeName key="tunes">Tunesas</placeName><unclear><placeName
                            key="tunes">sa</placeName> were well</unclear> and <lb/> would look for
                    us in a day <damage/><lb/> This morning was <gap/>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="3" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_003"/> early and rideing down the <geogName
                        key="alleg">Allegany River</geogName><lb/> arivd at the upper Settlements of
                    Indians<lb/> near the Mouth of the Little Valley about<lb/> one Oclock. We stopt
                    at <persName key="psnyd1">Peter Sniders</persName> to<lb/> feed our horses and
                    take some refreshment<lb/> ourselves &amp; a number of Indians collected<lb/>
                    about us, most of them knew one &amp; seem'd<lb/> much pleas'd with our
                    comeing--</p>
                <p> This was about 12 Miles Above <placeName key="tunes">Tunesassa</placeName>,<lb/>
                    and as we past down the <geogName key="alleg">River</geogName> we found<lb/> a
                    good road open'd by the Indians most of the <lb/> way saw a large number of
                    Cornfields,<lb/> many new Settlements made, and several<lb/> small villages
                    built since <del><gap/></del> I left<lb/> them six years before-- Many of the
                    Indians<lb/> came to shake hands with us as we rode along<lb/> expressing their
                    Joy to see us, in their usual way<lb/> of exultation-- We ariv'd at <placeName
                        key="tunes">Tunesassa</placeName><lb/> a little before sunset, found our
                    friends <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob<lb/> Taylor</persName>, <persName
                        key="jswai1">Joel Swayne</persName>, <persName key="bcoop1">Benjamin
                        Cope</persName> his wife<lb/>
                    <persName key="rcoop1">Rachel</persName>, &amp; <persName key="hjack2">Hannah
                        Jackson</persName> all well, much<lb/> pleas'd to see us and gratifyed with
                    hearing<lb/> from their Relations and friends and receiving <lb/>
                    <pb n="4" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_004"/>
                    <gap/> a large number of acceptable letters---<lb/> according to computation I
                    made the distance<lb/> in all my Route thus far about 308 Miles -<lb/> and after
                    a long Wilderness Journey over many<lb/> rough Mountains, Bad roads, and in
                    some<lb/> places but poor accommodations, the compa-<lb/> ny of our friends this
                    evening in a comfortable<lb/> house was Mutually satisfactory ---</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1806-09-13">13th</date> - <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p> Last night a very heavy rain fell with<lb/> much lightening and heavy
                    thunder--this<lb/> enabled our friends to get a good deal of Grind-<lb/> ing
                    done, as the water had been very low for<lb/> some time past, by reason of a
                    great drouth<lb/> they have had in those parts the latter part<lb/> of Summer --
                    We spent the forenoon in<lb/> viewing the Farm, Mills and other im-<lb/>
                    provements and friends have made at this<lb/> place - It appears they have got
                    about<lb/> 54 Acres of Land Clear'd well enclos'd and in<lb/> good Order - the
                    Buildings thereon are very<lb/> good - the dwelling House 22 by 36 feet is<lb/>
                    situated on a beautiful eminence command-<lb/> ing a view of the whole farm and
                    Mills - it<lb/> is two stories high containing four rooms <lb/>
                    <pb n="5" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_005"/> on each floor besides Closets Pantry
                    &amp;c<lb/> and a good Cellar under a part of it--a little<lb/> distance from
                    this they have erected a house<lb/> 18 by 22 feet for the purpose of
                    instructing<lb/> the Indian Women in, also a convenient<lb/> Barn built this
                    Summer 29 by 50 feet --</p>
                <p> The Mills look well and are Capable<lb/> of doing considerable business -- The
                    Grist<lb/> Mill upon a full head will grind 120 bushels<lb/> of Grain pr. day
                    reckoning from daylight<lb/> till evening &amp; the sawmill will cut near<lb/>
                    two thousand feet of boards in the same time</p>
                <p> Altho the water has been low for several<lb/> weeks past they have mostly been
                    able to<lb/> grind all the Grain the Indians brought to<lb/> the mill, and for
                    the most part this is a very<lb/> forcible stream, and with a little labour<lb/>
                    may be made Navigable from the Mill<lb/> to the <geogName key="alleg"
                        >River</geogName> -- Our friends had about<lb/> 400 Dozens of winter Grain
                    the late harvest mostly<lb/> wheat, besides a quantity of Oates &amp;c.
                    Their<lb/> potatoes Turnips Garden &amp;c looks well --<lb/> They have about 8
                    Acres of Good bottom <lb/>
                    <pb n="6" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_006"/> in Grass, &amp; about 21 Acres of new
                    Ground<lb/> clear'd this Summer to put in with winter<lb/> Grain which they are
                    now preparing to sow.</p>
                <p> A White Man with a family lives in ano-<lb/> ther house on the farm, who works
                    the saw<lb/> Mill to the shares and all the logs the<lb/> Indians bring to the
                    Mill are saw'd to the<lb/> halves, and Boards are sold to such of them<lb/> as
                    want to buy at half the present Market<lb/> price -- A survey of the farm is
                    not<lb/> yet made, and must necessarily include<lb/> a part of two mountains to
                    secure the ad-<lb/> vantage of the water, but will also include<lb/> a large
                    proportion of two Valleys of<lb/> exelent land Cover'd with a great
                    quantity<lb/> of good pine timber, also some Whiteoak<lb/> hemlock, Sugar Maple
                    &amp;c. In our walks at<lb/> the foot of a Mountain 50 or 60 perches from<lb/>
                    the house we went to view a large stone<lb/> which we thought something of a
                    curiosity<lb/> it was about 24 feet in circumference<lb/> about 18 inches
                    elevated above ground, the<lb/> top of it nearly horizontal and twelve <lb/>
                    <pb n="7" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_007"/> hollows work'd out thereon about the<lb/>
                    size of a large disk, which appear'd to have<lb/> been done by the Indians in
                    antient times<lb/> and probably they have often made use<lb/> of them for eating
                    their victuals on --</p>
                <p> We also visited <persName key="halft1">Levi Halftown</persName>, who is
                    setled<lb/> adjoining our friends farm, and works at<lb/> the Smiths business -
                    He was at work in<lb/> his Smithshop makeing an Oxchain, &amp;<lb/> we
                    understand the other Smith who is setled<lb/> up the <geogName key="alleg"
                        >River</geogName>, is a very ingenius Man &amp;<lb/> industrious at his
                    trade. ----</p>
                <p> In the afternoon we all walk'd down the<lb/>
                    <geogName key="alleg">River</geogName> in company with <persName key="jtayl1"
                        >Jacob Taylor</persName> &amp;<lb/>
                    <persName key="jswai1">Joel Swayne</persName> to view the Old farm at<lb/>
                    <persName key="genes1">Genesinguhta</persName> &amp; visit the few families<lb/>
                    that remain there -- The place look'd<lb/> very natural to me &amp; the Indians
                    my<lb/> Old neighbours, much pleas'd with my<lb/> comeing again to see them --
                    The house<lb/> I had assisted in building &amp; liv'd in while<lb/> there is now
                    occupie'd by an Indian Chief<lb/> the name of <persName key="mush1"
                        >Mush</persName>, but the high fresh <lb/>
                    <pb n="8" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_008"/> in the <geogName key="alleg"
                        >River</geogName> last Spring was a year had<lb/> wash'd away a good deal of
                    the soil, &amp; injur'd the<lb/> improvements very much so that most of<lb/> the
                    Indians has mov'd and setled higher up<lb/> the <geogName key="alleg"
                        >River</geogName> -- While we were here <placeName key="connu1"
                        >Connudia</placeName><lb/> came to see us in order to agree upon a time<lb/>
                    for holding a counsel, &amp; altho we desired a little<lb/> time to go about,
                    &amp; view their improvements<lb/> previous to meeting them in Counsel, yet
                    as<lb/> we understood they were going off in a few days<lb/> to meet a General
                    Counsel of the six Nations<lb/> at <geogName key="buffc1">Buffalo
                        Creek</geogName> we thought most expedient<lb/> to fix upon Seconday next,
                    &amp; <persName key="connu1">Connudia</persName> agreed<lb/> to inform the
                    Indians accordingly ---</p>
                <p> After returning to <placeName key="tunes">Tunesassa</placeName> and haveing<lb/>
                    some conferrence with our friends we under-<lb/> stood some little uneasiness
                    had got into a<lb/> few of the Indians minds with respect to our<lb/> friends
                    not lending them tools and working<lb/> for them as much as they formerly did -
                    we<lb/> also understood that one or two of their<lb/> young Chiefs had
                    introduc'd some Liquor in<lb/> a Clandestine manner in order to sell to<lb/> the
                    white people, but that the Indians in <lb/>
                    <pb n="9" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_009"/> general was much oppos'd to such conduct
                    --<lb/> it also appear'd there was some little divisions<lb/> among the Indians
                    with respect to their<lb/> Chiefs that several young men had rose<lb/> up of
                    Considerable influence, and <persName key="cornp2">Cornplan-<lb/>
                        -ter</persName> was not esteem'd among them as a<lb/> principal Chief &amp;
                    that they had very late-<lb/> -ly been holding a general counsel among<lb/>
                    themselves about these matters -- After<lb/> deliberating on these subjects and
                    several others<lb/> that came under consideration it appear'd<lb/> necessary to
                    form an address in writeing to<lb/> lay before them at the ensuing Counsel<lb/>
                    and accordingly some essay was made for<lb/> that purpose --</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1806-09-14">14th</date>
                    <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p> This being Firstday we sat with our<lb/> friends in their oppertunity of
                    religeous<lb/> retirement - <persName key="jbell1">John Bell</persName> attended
                    &amp; two<lb/> Men our friends have employ'd in their<lb/> service - It was a
                    comfortable season &amp;<lb/> a renewed evidence felt that friends in<lb/> their
                    secluded situation was in their<lb/> proper alottment, and at times comforted <lb/>
                    <pb n="10" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_010"/> with a prospect that their Labours<lb/>
                    among this people was under the direction<lb/> of best wisdom and the concern
                    own'd by him<lb/> who hath called them to the work ----</p>
                <p> Just before dinner <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> came<lb/> to
                    see us and said he was glad to hear of<lb/> our Arival. He knew me and
                    enquir'd<lb/> after my family - I gave several friends<lb/> love to him who had
                    sent it by me, among<lb/> the rest <persName key="jparr1">John
                        Parrish</persName> who he was wellpleas'd<lb/> to hear from and enquir'd
                    particularly whe-<lb/> ther the Old Man was yet able to ride about -<lb/> he
                    din'd with us had a good deal of conversa-<lb/> tion &amp; said he would meet us
                    in counsel<lb/> tomorrow...</p>
                <p> In the afternoon most of our Company<lb/> took a walk thro' part of the
                    Adjacent<lb/> woods intended to be included in the survey<lb/> of this farm, and
                    ascended a mountain<lb/> on the South side of the Farm (call'd<lb/> the
                        <geogName key="soutm">South Mountain</geogName>) nearly to the top<lb/> with
                    considerable difficulty, climbing<lb/> over abundance of logs <del>then</del>
                    overgrown<lb/> with Briars and Bushes -- from the <lb/>
                    <pb n="11" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_011"/> north side of the Mountain we had<lb/> a
                    fair view of the farm and improvements<lb/> thereon, also an extensive view of
                    surrou-<lb/> nding hills and interveneing valleys - after<lb/> gratifying
                    ourselves with such prospects<lb/> as then open'd to our view we descended<lb/>
                    the Mountain rather more hastily than<lb/> we went up, &amp; found our Women
                    friends<lb/> had a delicious repast prepar'd for us of<lb/> Nutmeg Cantilopes,
                    and Watermellons -- </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <p>
                    <date when="1806-09-15">15th</date> About 8 Oclock we walkt up the <geogName
                        key="alleg">River</geogName><lb/> to the new Town at the <placeName
                        key="colds">Cold Spring</placeName> where<lb/> the Counsel was propos'd to
                    be held - After<lb/> sounding the Trumpet several times<lb/> the Indians
                    Collected and about twelve Oclock<lb/> we were invited into the Counsel
                    room<lb/> which is a long building prepard for that<lb/> purpose - After being
                    seated <persName key="connu1">Connudia</persName><lb/> Arose and using their
                    Usual Ceremony<lb/> said he was thankful to the Great Spirit<lb/> for our
                    preservation on our long Journey<lb/> and that we had arived safe and found<lb/>
                    the Indians all well &amp; our friends who live<lb/> among them and that they
                    had all liv'd in <lb/>
                    <pb n="12" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_012"/> in peace and friendship with them -
                    he<lb/> also said they were very Glad to see us<lb/> and was now ready to hear
                    us speak -- </p>
                <p> After returning them a little Ceremony<lb/> of the same kind the address from
                    the<lb/> Committee on Indian affairs was read<lb/> &amp; interpreted by
                        <persName key="habee1">Henry Abeal</persName> being as follows</p>
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body>
                        <opener>
                            <gap/> To the Chiefs and others of the<lb/>
                            <orgName key="seneca">Seneca Nation</orgName> setled on and near the<lb/>
                            <geogName key="alleg">Allegany River</geogName> --</opener>
                        <p> Brothers,<lb/> Your friends the Quakers continue<lb/> frequently to meet
                            in counsel to think of you.</p>
                        <p>Brothers,<lb/> Our minds have been made glad<lb/> to hear from time to
                            time of your good<lb/> resolutions to live soberly and to refrain<lb/>
                            from strong drink as likewise that you<lb/> improve in industry and in
                            the ma-<lb/> nagement of your Land - we hope the<lb/> good Spirit will
                            enable you to keep<lb/> your minds strong in these good resolutions</p>
                        <p> Brothers,<lb/> Let your ears be open and may<lb/> your hearts be
                            prepar'd to understand - <lb/>
                            <pb n="13" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_013"/> You have own'd that the Counsel
                                <del>of</del><lb/>
                            <del><gap/></del> we have for several years given you<lb/> and that the
                            assistance of our young men<lb/> in learning you how to cultivate
                            your<lb/> Land &amp; to live comfortably, has been good<lb/> for
                            yourselves, your wives, and your children.</p>
                        <p> Brothers,<lb/> We now feel desirous to say some-<lb/> thing to you on a
                            subject of great importance<lb/> which we wish you would seriously
                            attend<lb/> to and consider --</p>
                        <p> Brothers,<lb/> You know that the people<lb/> called Quakers are a
                            peaceable people<lb/> they can have no concern in wars and<lb/>
                            fightings, and the destruction of their fellow<lb/> men, they desire
                            that al men should<lb/> live in peace and feel love for each other.</p>
                        <p> Brothers,<lb/> There are two great command-<lb/> ments which all ranks
                            of Christians thro-<lb/> -out the world profess a belief in and
                            that<lb/> it is their duty to observe and obey them<lb/> They are first
                            - that we should love the<lb/> Lord our God with all our hearts and
                            with<lb/> all our souls and with all our strength --</p>

                        <pb n="14" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_014"/>

                        <p> Second, and to love our neighbours as ourselves<lb/> of these
                            commandments had these proper effect<lb/> in the hearts of men and the
                            did in sincerity<lb/> and truth love worship and adore the<lb/> Great
                            and good Spirit from whom all <gap/><lb/> blessings come it would be a
                            happy state<lb/> and preserve from war and Bloodshed --</p>
                        <p> Brothers,<lb/> We desire not to fill your ears<lb/> with words, but
                            rather to recommend<lb/> you to retire and gather your mind,<lb/> into
                            Quiet and Settlement, and thus as you<lb/> humbly wait and have prayers
                            and desires<lb/> raised in your minds to be rightly instructed<lb/> and
                            continue inwardly attendtive you will<lb/> be in the way of receiveing
                            light knowledge<lb/> and Counsel superior to any we can import,<lb/> for
                            there is a divine principal of light<lb/> and grace in every heart, by
                            it our forefa-<lb/> -thers were taught and we their descendants<lb/>
                            have been taught to love all men as<lb/> Brethren, and have been
                            restraind from<lb/> revengeing injuries or rendering evil for<lb/> evil,
                            and this has been the profession<lb/> of your friends the Quakers for
                            more<lb/> than one hundred and fifty years --</p>

                        <pb n="15" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_015"/>

                        <p> Brothers,<lb/> Influenced by desires for the wel-<lb/> fare of you our
                            Indian Brothers three<lb/> of our friends have agreed to visit you<lb/>
                            this fall - Their names are <persName key="ibons1">Isaac
                                Bonsal</persName><lb/>
                            <persName key="jphil1">John Philips</persName> &amp; <persName
                                key="hjack1">Halliday Jackson</persName> ----</p>
                        <p>Brothers,<lb/> Attend these friends are<lb/> beloved by us, and as their
                            desires for<lb/> your welfare are strong we hope you<lb/> will keep your
                            ears open to what advice<lb/> they may give you and let it sink
                            deep<lb/> in your hearts. </p>
                        <closer><dateline><placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName><date
                                    when="1806-08-12">8 Mo. 12th 1806</date></dateline>Sign'd <signed><list>
                                    <item><persName key="jparr1">John Parrish</persName></item>
                                    <item><persName key="nwaln1">Nicholas Waln</persName></item>
                                    <item><persName key="hdrin1">Henery Drinker</persName></item>
                                    <item><persName key="opaxt1">Oliver Paxson</persName></item>
                                    <item><persName key="jelli1">John Elliott</persName></item>
                                    <item><persName key="tstew1">Thomas Howardson</persName></item>
                                    <item><persName key="twist1">Thomas Wistor</persName></item>
                                </list></signed><lb/>and a number of others</closer>

                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <pb n="16" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_016"/>
                <p>After a little pause our speech which we<lb/> had committeed to writing was then
                    read &amp;<lb/> Interpreted being as follows ---</p>
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body>
                        <opener>To the Chiefs and Indians in general<lb/> residing on the <geogName
                                key="alleg">Allegany River</geogName>-- </opener>
                        <p>Brothers Attend<lb/> You have now heard<lb/> the speech your Brothers the
                            Quakers<lb/> have sent with us from <placeName key="phila"
                                >Philadelphia</placeName> and<lb/> we hope the advice they have
                            given you will<lb/> sink deep in your hears, and if any<lb/> part of it
                            does not feel easy that you will tell us Brothers,<lb/> We have come a
                            great ways to<lb/> see you and our friends who live beside<lb/> you, and
                            are thankful to the great Spirit to<lb/> find them and you well, and
                            that love<lb/> and friendship still continues between<lb/> you and them
                            -- Brothers,<lb/> We have often heard that<lb/> you were growing more
                            industrious<lb/> &amp; since comeing among you it has afforded<lb/> us
                            much satisfaction to see the improve-<lb/> ments you have made, that you
                            have<lb/> built comfortable house, fenced in many <lb/>
                            <pb n="17" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_017"/>
                            <lb/> Farms, and have such good Corn and<lb/> other things growing,
                            where the Land was<lb/> so lately cover'd with trees and Bushes.<lb/> We
                            hope you will not be discouraged at<lb/> the labour it takes to Clear
                            your land<lb/> for your land we believe is very good<lb/> and if you
                            farm it well, it will produce<lb/> a great deal of Grain and Grass,
                            which will<lb/> enable you to keep your stocks of Cattle<lb/> much
                            better than you now do, and you<lb/> will live more comfortably
                            yourselves --</p>
                        <p> Brothers<lb/> We see you have a great many<lb/> Children and we want you
                            to learn<lb/> them to work while they are young<lb/> for when Children
                            grow up in Idleness<lb/> they dont like to go to work afterwards<lb/>
                            and so get into Lazy habits --</p>
                        <p> Brothers,<lb/> As we are very desirous to<lb/> promote your welfare we
                            have some<lb/> things to propose for your consideration.<lb/> We think
                            if you would place two of<lb/> your boys under the care of our
                            friends<lb/> at <placeName key="tunes">Tunesassa</placeName> to be
                            instructed in the<lb/> farming business or learn to manage <lb/>
                            <pb n="18" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_018"/> the Mills, they might be of great
                            use<lb/> among your people - These Boys should<lb/> be of Sober conduct
                            and such as our friends<lb/> would think suitable ot take - They
                            might<lb/> stay six months or longer if necessary<lb/> and when they
                            were instructed others<lb/> might come in their places and by<lb/> this
                            means some of your Boys might be<lb/> learn'd to carry on business as
                            our friends<lb/> do.</p>
                        <p> Brothers,<lb/> Two of our Women have been<lb/> sometime at <placeName
                                key="tunes">Tunesassa</placeName> with a desire<lb/> to instruct
                            your Women in things that<lb/> will make your lives more
                            comfortable<lb/> We hope you have received some<lb/> benefit from some
                            of your women<lb/> learning how to make soap, which<lb/> enables
                                <del>you</del> them to keep your houses more<lb/> Clean -- This is
                            very good -- but we think<lb/> if some of your girls would go to
                            our<lb/> women and learn how to spin flax and<lb/> Wool it would be of
                            great advantage to<lb/> you and our friends will assist you in<lb/>
                            getting it made into Cloth -- Wool we<lb/> dont expect you can get a
                            great deal of<lb/> yet, but we saw some flax of your own<lb/> raising
                            and our friends have a little <lb/>
                            <pb n="19" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_019"/> wool and a little flax which
                            they<lb/> will be willing to give you to begin with<lb/> and next year
                            you can raise more<lb/> flax - A house is built for such of your<lb/>
                            girls to work in as incline to be instruc-<lb/> ted and some Wheels
                            provided ---</p>
                        <p> Brothers,<lb/> We are glad to observe you have<lb/> made such good roads
                            in many places<lb/> along this River - this makes it com-<lb/> frotable
                            traveling and opens a way for you<lb/> to get your Grain to the Mill --
                            We are<lb/> satisfied with the proposals our friends<lb/> have made to
                            you with respect to grind-<lb/> ing your grain and sawing your<lb/>
                            boards but we think it will be necessary<lb/> for them to take toll
                            after the time<lb/> they propos'd to you, and it would be a<lb/>
                            satisfaction both to our friends and us<lb/> if you would not bring your
                            Grain<lb/> to the Mill on the first day of the<lb/> week as your friends
                            the Quakers do not<lb/> wish to be interrupted in the time of<lb/> their
                            Meeting or work on that day</p>

                        <pb n="20" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_020"/>

                        <p>Brothers,<lb/> If you wish us to send on any<lb/> more tools for our
                            friends to sell to you<lb/> we hope you will tell us your minds as
                            you<lb/> knew we told you before we would send<lb/> on a few
                                <del>tools</del> Sythes, Sickels, Augurs and<lb/> some such tools
                            for our friends to sell to<lb/> such of you as might want to buy,<lb/>
                            but that they should leave off lending --<lb/> and we hope your
                            blacksmiths will<lb/> be industrious and make you what<lb/> tools they
                            can ---</p>
                        <p>Brothers<lb/> We have said much to you<lb/> but we wish to add a little
                            more - <lb/> Our friends in their speech have told<lb/> you their desire
                            "that all men should<lb/> live in <del>harmony and</del> peace and
                            love<lb/> one another," and we know it is pleas-<lb/> -ing to the Great
                            Spirit for mankind to<lb/> love one another and try to do good<lb/> to
                            each other -- we therefore desire<lb/> you may all live in harmony
                            and<lb/> be like the family of one man --<lb/> united together in good
                            works and <lb/>
                            <pb n="21" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_021"/> then you will be strong, then
                            when<lb/> one of you fall another will help<lb/> him up, and the Great
                            Spirit will<lb/> prosper you, and bless the work of your<lb/> hands -
                            Your Chiefs will then unite<lb/> together in leading you on to do
                            right.</p>
                        <p> Brothers, we have often heard of your<lb/> good resolutions against
                            drinking whisky<lb/> and other strong drink, and it has<lb/> made our
                            hearts glad to find you have<lb/> kept these good resolutions, for you
                            as<lb/> well as us, are very sensible that long<lb/> ago it was your
                            greatest enemy, and<lb/> that your quiting the use of it, has been<lb/>
                            a great blessing to you -- We wish you<lb/> to keep your eyes open, and
                            your<lb/> minds strong, that you may not let<lb/> this enemy rise again
                            - and we desire<lb/> that you will not buy or sell it any<lb/> more for
                            fear of offending the Great Spirit.</p>
                        <p>Brothers<lb/> There are other things which <lb/>
                            <pb n="22" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_022"/> does much harm, such as playing
                            Cards<lb/> Gameing and other idle practices - We<lb/> hope you will keep
                            out of these things<lb/> as the hinder the good work we desire<lb/> to
                            promote among you ---</p>
                        <p> Brothers Attend,<lb/> You must not think<lb/> our friends who live at
                                <placeName key="tunes">Tunesassa</placeName> have come<lb/> there
                            for the sake of pay to spend so much<lb/> time among you, but felt their
                            hearts<lb/> so warmd with love to our Indian Bro-<lb/> thers that they
                            were made willing to<lb/> leave their comfortable dwellings<lb/> and
                            near and dear friends in order to<lb/> promote your welfare, and we
                            believe<lb/> their endeavours to do you good has<lb/> been pleasing to
                            the great Spirit which<lb/> has made their minds easy in staying<lb/> so
                            long from their relations and friend<lb/> we hope you will attend to the
                            good<lb/> advice they may give you, and as you<lb/> continue to
                            persevere in industry<lb/> and sobriety, your friends will still<lb/> be
                            happy to see your improvement, <lb/>
                            <pb n="23" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_023"/> but if at any time you fall
                            into<lb/> your former habits of drinking, and<lb/> other bad practices,
                            it will discourage<lb/> your friends the Quakers from assisting<lb/> you </p>
                        <p> Brothers<lb/> As our friends at <placeName key="tunes"
                                >Tunesassa</placeName><lb/> have the Mills and farm to attend
                            to<lb/> themselves you cannot expect them<lb/> to do a great deal of
                            work for you<lb/> but if at any time you want instruction<lb/> about
                            fenceing, you farms, building <lb/> your houses, Laying out roads
                            &amp;c<lb/> apply to them and they will be al-<lb/> ways willing to give
                            you such coun-<lb/> -sel as they may think best ---</p>
                        <p> Brothers<lb/> We have now spoken our minds<lb/> plainly and we wish you
                            to speak plainly<lb/> to us, that if there is any thing that<lb/> is not
                            understood between us, or between<lb/> our friends and you, we may have
                            the difficul-<lb/> ty remov'd out of the way -- We intend<lb/> to spend
                            a few days more among<lb/> you and go and view some more of your<lb/>
                            improvements that we may be enabled <lb/>
                            <pb n="24" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_024"/> to carry back a true account to
                            our<lb/> friends in their counsel at <placeName key="phila"
                                >Philadelphia</placeName> --<lb/>
                        </p>
                        <closer><dateline><date when="1806-09-15">9 Mo. 15th 1806</date></dateline><signed><list>
                                    <item><persName key="ibons1">Isaac Bonsal</persName></item>
                                    <item><persName key="jphil1">John Philips</persName></item>
                                    <item><persName key="hjack1">Halliday Jackson</persName></item>
                                </list></signed></closer>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>


                <p> After the foregoing was read and ex-<lb/> -plain'd to them some verbal
                    observations<lb/> were made encourageing them to live in<lb/> peace and harmony
                    with their wives &amp;<lb/> not to let trifling matters part them<lb/> but
                    consider them companions for life<lb/> for it was pleasing to the Great Spirit
                    for<lb/> man and Woman to live together in har-<lb/> mony - also some remarks
                    directing<lb/> them to the inward principal of Light<lb/> in the heart, which
                    would make their<lb/> minds uneasy when they did wrong, and<lb/> afford them
                    peace and tranquility when<lb/> they did, that which was pleasing to the<lb/>
                    great Spirit -- They were also encoura-<lb/> ged to live in harmony and
                    friendship<lb/> among themselves, that this would<lb/> enable them to make a
                    progress in the<lb/> good work we were endeavouring to pro-<lb/> mote among
                    them, but if they split <lb/>
                    <pb n="25" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_025"/> and divided it would weaken them,<lb/>
                    and either part would be easy broken<lb/> like a stick split into many pieces -- </p>
                <p> After being inform'd <del><gap/></del> we had<lb/> done speaking, they confer'd
                    a while<lb/> together and one of the Chiefs inform'd<lb/> us it would take some
                    time to consider<lb/> of a reply, and that they would meet<lb/> us in counsel
                    tomorrow about noon &amp;<lb/> answer our Speeches --</p>
                <p>
                    <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> (tho' not esteemd as a<lb/> chief
                    at this time) made a short speech<lb/> to the Indians directing their
                    attention<lb/> to what we had said to them and told<lb/> them it was all right
                    and true - he<lb/> being then on his way to <placeName key="buffa"
                        >Buffalo</placeName> took<lb/> leave of us for the present -- We sent
                    infor-<lb/> -mation by him to the Chiefs of <placeName key="catta1"
                        >Catarau-<lb/> gus village</placeName> that we expected to be there<lb/> in
                    a few days and would wish to<lb/> see them --</p>
                <p> This was the largest Counsel I had<lb/> ever been at among them, A number<lb/>
                    of their principal Women attended<lb/> and the Indians in general appear'd <lb/>
                    <pb n="26" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_026"/> more steady in their Conduct &amp;
                    more<lb/> Clean and decent in their dress than I<lb/> had ever saw them before
                    -- their<lb/> houses are also kept much cleaner<lb/> than formerly, and one
                    thing I several<lb/> times observ'd which I thought something<lb/> of a novelty
                    among Indians &amp; a ple[as]in[g]<lb/> indication that they were beginning to
                    be<lb/> asham'd of their dirty way of liveing<lb/> that when the women saw us
                    aproa-<lb/> -ching their Doors they immediately<lb/> began to sweep their houses
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1806-09-16">16th</date>
                    <placeName key="colds"/></dateline>
                <p> This Morning about nine Oclock we<lb/> rode up the <geogName key="alleg"
                        >River</geogName> to <placeName key="genes2">Genesinguhta
                    flats</placeName><lb/> above the <placeName key="colds">Cold Spring</placeName>
                    to view what<lb/> improvements the Indians had made<lb/> there -- we found a
                    considerable num-<lb/> -ber of Cornfields extended along the Creek<lb/> between
                    two and three miles from the<lb/>
                    <geogName key="alleg">River</geogName>, enclos'd under good fence, and<lb/> the
                    Corn look'd well in the General<lb/> being on land of a superior quality -</p>
                <p> We sat a while in <persName key="bluee1">Blue Eyes</persName> house<lb/> eat
                    some Indian Squashes, and on our<lb/> way back, stopt to view <persName
                        key="habee1">Henery Abeals</persName>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="27" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_027"/> farm -- He is setled some distance
                    from<lb/> the <geogName key="alleg">River</geogName> in the woods by himself
                    --<lb/> and hath a neat little house built<lb/> with a Pannel Door and Jack
                    windows<lb/> on a stately eminence at the head of<lb/> a rich flat, and hath
                    made a beginning<lb/> to Clear land -- We return'd to the<lb/>
                    <placeName key="colds">cold Spring</placeName> about twelve Oclock and<lb/>
                    found the Indians in Counsel --In about<lb/> an hour after they called us into
                    the<lb/> Counsel room, and after being seated<lb/> one of the Chiefs call'd
                        <persName key="mush1">Mush</persName> stood<lb/> up and spoke to us nearly
                    as follows,</p>
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body>
                        <dateline><date when="1806-09-16"/><placeName key="colds"/></dateline>
                        <p> Brothers<lb/> When your young men came<lb/> first to live amongst us
                            they saw we<lb/> were poor, they took pity upon us,<lb/> and they told
                            us they came to assist<lb/> us -- At first we did not fully under-<lb/>
                            -stand what your intentions were, but<lb/> after consulting among
                            ourselves we<lb/> thought it was, a great thing that you<lb/> should
                            come to live amongst us, to<lb/> instruct us, being more than white<lb/>
                            people had ever done before. and we<lb/> concluded to try you one, or
                            five years <lb/>
                            <pb n="28" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_028"/> we said nothing more about it for
                            three<lb/> years, to see whether you were our friends<lb/> or not -- You
                            also brought tools on<lb/> for us to work with in which we found<lb/> a
                            great advantage -- we then began to<lb/> improve and do much better than
                            before.<lb/> You then wish'd to instruct our chil-<lb/> dren to read and
                            write - this we could<lb/> not agree too because our people were<lb/>
                            then so fond of hunting &amp; they would<lb/> take their wives &amp;
                            children into the<lb/> woods with them you must not think<lb/> hard of
                            this -- In our counsels with<lb/> you at that time <persName
                                key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> answer'd<lb/> your speeches
                            without consulting us,<lb/> but it is not so now, we are all<lb/> agreed
                            to what we say ---</p>

                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>
                    <persName key="tekia1">Te,ki,an,da</persName>, generally called
                        <emph rend="underline">Blacksnake</emph><lb/> then arose and made reply to
                    the address<lb/> the Committee had sent with us,<lb/> nearly as follows --</p>
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body>
                        <dateline><date when="1806-09-16"/><placeName key="colds"/></dateline>
                        <p> Brothers the Quakers,<lb/> We expect it is the<lb/> mind of the Great
                            Spirit that we have<lb/> met together in Counsel to day, and <lb/>
                            <pb n="29" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_029"/> we thank the Great Spirit that
                            we<lb/> are all well, and that he has given us<lb/> a fine clear day to
                            meet together --</p>
                        <p> Brothers,<lb/> Yesterday you told us all<lb/> the Speech you brought
                            from the<lb/> counsel at <placeName key="phila"
                            >Philadelphia</placeName>, and we thank<lb/> our friends for it,
                            especially our Old<lb/> friend <persName key="jparr1">John
                                Parrish</persName>, as it was like<del>ing</del><lb/> shakeing hands
                            together with both<lb/> men and Women -- You told us<lb/> to Open our
                            ears and listen to all you<lb/> say -- now we hope you will make<lb/>
                            your minds easy, as we have but a few<lb/> words to say -- You say you
                            have<lb/> often heard how we on <geogName key="alleg"
                                >Alligany</geogName><lb/> are increasing in industry, and<lb/> that
                            you also heard our continued<lb/> resolutions against the use of
                            spirit<lb/> -ous Liquors, and you hope we would<lb/> not let it rise
                            again, you wish your<lb/> words might sink deep in our hearts.</p>
                        <p> Brothers<lb/> We are now all together <lb/>
                            <pb n="30" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_030"/> we suppose you feel
                            yourselves<lb/> happy and we also feel ourselves happy<lb/> All the
                            Indians and the white People know<lb/> that the Great Spirit talks with
                            our<lb/> Prophet, it is now seven years since he<lb/> first began to
                            talk with him - &amp; he told<lb/> the Indians they must leave of
                            drink-<lb/> ing Whisky, and they have declin'd<lb/> the use of it --</p>
                        <p> Brothers - <lb/> you must tell your friends<lb/> when you go home to
                            make their<lb/> minds quite easy, for we are determined<lb/> never to
                            let the whisky rise again, and<lb/> also to pursue habits of industry,
                            and never<lb/> them -- Your young men and us are<lb/> like one - when we
                            want any thing<lb/> done we consult them and they assist<lb/> us, and
                            our Prophet tells us what to<lb/> do and so we get instruction from
                            both.</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p><persName key="jsilv1">Johnson Silverheels</persName> (a young Chief -<lb/>
                    rather disaffected) then made a speech<lb/>
                    <emph rend="underline">to us</emph> nearly as follows ---</p>
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body>
                        <dateline><date when="1806-09-16"/><placeName key="colds"/></dateline>
                        <p>Brothers<lb/> You have told us you wished<lb/> two of our Boys to go and
                            live with<lb/> your friends at <placeName key="tunes"
                                >Tunesassa</placeName> to learn their Business and you <lb/><pb
                                n="31" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_031"/> to have the care of them
                            yourselves,<lb/> &amp; we have concluded to comply with<lb/> your
                            wishes, &amp; let you have the choice of<lb/> two, but we want you to
                            tell us how<lb/> they are going to live there, and<lb/> what they are
                            going to get by staying</p>
                        <p>You also think best for some of our<lb/> Girls to go to your women and
                            learn<lb/> how to work, but we want to know<lb/> what them girls are
                            going to get by<lb/> working there -- You also wished<lb/> to know if we
                            wanted any more<lb/> tools brought on to sell <del>to sell</del> to
                            us,<lb/> and we have agreed that if you can<lb/> send on tools to sell
                            cheaper than those<lb/> you sent before, you may send them<lb/> but if
                            you cannot sell them cheaper<lb/> we dont wish you to bring any as<lb/>
                            we can buy them cheaper elswhere</p>
                        <p>Brothers you told us to speak our<lb/> minds plainly and if there was
                            any<lb/> thing we did not like to let it be known<lb/> We will now tell
                            you of some things that<lb/> is not quite agreable to us -- We all know<lb/>
                            <pb n="32" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_032"/> there is but one God, who made us
                            all<lb/> and directs us all to do alike -- but we cannot<lb/> all agree
                            as there is so many Sinners,<lb/> the reason is because we dont do as
                            well<lb/><lb/> as we know how -- The Great Spirit orders<lb/> us all to
                            do right ---</p>
                        <p>We suppose you thought when you came<lb/> to live among the Indians, the
                            Great Spirit<lb/> would be pleased with you -- The Great<lb/> Spirit was
                            not blind but could see every<lb/> thing, and was pleasd with your
                            liveing<lb/> amongst us - as you have had no sickness<lb/> among you
                            since you first came --</p>
                        <p>It was but a short time you assisted<lb/> us - for three years past you
                            have<lb/> not lent us any tools, and when you<lb/> quit lending us tools
                            we were like a<lb/> man <del>sleep</del> just wakeing out of a
                            sleep<lb/> reach out his hands for help and you<lb/> withdrew the
                            necessary assistance --<lb/> we still expected to get tools to Borrow
                            after<lb/> you brought tools to sell to us - and<lb/> since we have
                            found out the mind<lb/> of the Great Spirit, we think he is best<lb/>
                            pleas'd when People use one another well, <lb/>
                            <pb n="33" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_033"/> and he is pleas'd when people
                            give<lb/> one another victuals when they go to their<lb/> houses whether
                            they are hungry or not<lb/> we think when our people go to the
                            Mill,<lb/> and get hungry, your friends ought to<lb/> feed them, or when
                            Indians come from<lb/> other Towns they ought also to feed them<lb/>
                            this would be pleasing to us, as this is<lb/> the custom among ourselves
                            --</p>
                        <p>We have now told you our minds<lb/> plainly because you told us so
                            many<lb/> good things since you came to see us --</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>
                    <persName key="jpier1">John Pierce</persName> then arose and made<lb/> the
                    following speech</p>
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body>
                        <dateline><date when="1806-09-16"/><placeName key="colds"/></dateline>
                        <p> Brothers<lb/>
                            <gap/><gap/><gap/><gap/> I have a few words to say --<lb/> what I am
                            going to say is about the<lb/> great Spirit, as you told us a great<lb/>
                            deal about it yesterday, and it has sunk<lb/> deep in my mind -- We are
                            poor<lb/> and ought to be pitied - I us'd to have ma-<lb/> ny bad tricks
                            but have concluded to quit<lb/> them and try to instruct others -- I
                            know<lb/> what Ideas the Quakers have, they are always <lb/>
                            <pb n="34" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_034"/> always thinking abou the Great
                            spirit<lb/> and the have no crook in their mind, nor<lb/> dont follow
                            bad ways -- One thing you told<lb/> us struck me very deep -- You said
                            if we<lb/> done well here and pleas'd the Good Spirit<lb/> we should
                            meet again in a better world --<lb/> I want you, when you go home, to tell<lb/>
                            <persName key="jthom2">Jonathan Thomas</persName> of the resolution I
                            have<lb/> taken to do well, because he often told me<lb/> about these
                            things, &amp; advis'd me to do better --<lb/> Two of us have now agree'd
                            to assist the<lb/> Chiefs and instruct the other Indians<lb/> &amp; I
                            hope we will try more and more to do<lb/> better for we know we dont all
                            do right<lb/> about our Wives but we mean to try to do<lb/> better, and
                            if the Chiefs dont do right we<lb/> will try to help them, &amp; if one
                            falls another<lb/> will help him up ----</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>
                    <persName key="connu1">Con,nu,di,a</persName> (their Prophet so
                    call'd)<lb/> then arose and spoke to the following<lb/> effect --</p>
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body>
                        <dateline><date when="1806-09-16"/><placeName key="colds"/></dateline>
                        <p> Brothers,<lb/> We have now told you all we<lb/> agreed to say, except a
                            few words I will<lb/> ad - I thank our friends in <placeName key="phila"
                                >Philadelphia</placeName><lb/> &amp; I have it on my mind to do as
                            you <lb/>
                            <pb n="35" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_035"/> told us not to let those bad
                            things<lb/> rise again -- It is me that talks about<lb/> what the Great
                            Spirit wishes us to do, &amp;<lb/> I always try to instruct the Chiefs
                            and<lb/> others to do right &amp; to be of one mind as<lb/> it is the
                            will of the Great Spirit that all<lb/> people should be of one mind, but
                            some of them<lb/> will not listen to what I say -- In six days<lb/> I
                            expect to go to <geogName key="buffc1">buffalo Creek</geogName>, and six
                            men<lb/> with me <del>and</del> there I expect to meet a<lb/> great many
                            Indians from <placeName key="oneid">Onieda</placeName> and<lb/> other
                            places &amp; there I will speake these<lb/> things you have told us to
                            them, as if I was<lb/> at home --</p>
                        <p> Brothers, the Great Spirit hears all<lb/> we now say, and is glad to see
                            us all well<lb/> together -- I hope he will preserve you<lb/> safe home
                            &amp; that you may find your fami-<lb/> lys all well and this is the
                            wish of all the<lb/> Indians ---</p>
                        <p> Brothers this is <emph rend="underline">all we got to say --</emph></p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p> After a little conferrence among ourselves<lb/> we replied to them nearly
                    as<lb/> follows ---</p>
                <pb n="36" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_036"/>
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body>
                        <dateline><date when="1806-09-16"/><placeName key="colds"/></dateline>
                        <p> Brothers<lb/> We are glad to meet you again<lb/> in counsel &amp; to
                            find that you and us<lb/> are so much of one mind, about most<lb/> of
                            the things we have been speaking to<lb/> you about. But we think there
                            are<lb/> a few things which you have not quite<lb/> understood, &amp; we
                            will now explain to<lb/> you -- You mention that you wish to<lb/> know
                            what we will give those Boys we<lb/> propose takeing to instruct -- You
                            may<lb/> understand that our friends will find<lb/> them in victuals
                            which with the instruc<lb/> -tion they give them we think will be<lb/> a
                            sufficient compensation for all the<lb/> benefit they will receive from
                            them -</p>
                        <p> You also enquire what we will<lb/> give those Girls that go to our
                            Women<lb/> to learn to work -- These Girls are to<lb/> find their own
                            provisions, &amp; our friends<lb/> will find them some wool and
                            some<lb/> flax &amp; instruct them how to spin<lb/> it, &amp; assist
                            them getting it made into<lb/> cloth, &amp; that Cloth will be yours -- <lb/>
                            <pb n="37" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_037"/> And as you think you can buy<lb/>
                            tools Cheaper than our friends sell to<lb/> you -- we think it will be
                            best not to<lb/> send on any more tools, The tools that<lb/> was sent,
                            has been sold to you at the<lb/> same price the cost us, and we can
                            not<lb/> afford them at a lower Price -</p>
                        <p> You may remember that the first par-<lb/> cel of tools we brought among
                            you, was<lb/> all given up three years ago, and you<lb/> were desir'd to
                            chose some of your Chiefs<lb/> to take care of them -- You were
                            then<lb/> told our young men, must quit lend-<lb/> ing you tools &amp;
                            this account was car-<lb/> ried back to the Counsel at <placeName
                                key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName><lb/> and our friends was
                            satisfied with it.<lb/> But you now complain that we assisted<lb/> you
                            but a short time - that for three<lb/> years past you could get no
                            tools<lb/> to Borrow, and say when we quit lending<lb/> you tools, you
                            were just like a man -<lb/> wakeing out of a sleep, reaching out his
                            <lb/> hands for help and the necessary assistence was <lb/>
                            <pb n="38" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_038"/> withdrawn from him -- We
                            answer<lb/> that when we first came among the Indians,<lb/> we
                            considered them as Children begining<lb/> to learn to walk, and then we
                            thought<lb/> necessary to assist them, but after they<lb/> had made some
                            progress, and learn'd to<lb/> do many things: it was not so necessary
                            --<lb/> that now we did not expect to work much<lb/> for the Indians,
                            but to teach them to work for<lb/> themselves - And that Children when
                            they<lb/> were learning to walk must be taken by the<lb/> hand and helpt
                            along, but when they got<lb/> able to go alone, they learn'd the
                            faster<lb/> by that assistance being withdrawn from<lb/> them --</p>
                        <p> You also complain that our friends<lb/> at <placeName key="tunes"
                                >Tunesassa</placeName> will not give you victuals<lb/> when you go
                            to the mill or when you are <lb/> there about your own business -- We
                            now want<lb/> you to understand plainly, that our<lb/> friends at
                                <placeName key="tunes">Tunesassa</placeName> are not come there<lb/>
                            to feed you -- there is a great many of<lb/> you, and but one family of
                            them and<lb/> if they always entertained you, when you<lb/> went to the
                            Mill, or when you were <lb/>
                            <pb n="39" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_039"/> there upon other occasions,
                            and<lb/> wanted victuals, it would take our women<lb/> most of their
                            time, that they would<lb/> have no time to instruct the Indians<lb/> in
                            useful things -- You also know there<lb/> are some of your people, does
                            not like<lb/> work very well - these might go &amp; stay<lb/> several
                            days liveing on our friends, &amp;<lb/> and this would be unreasonable
                            --</p>
                        <p> You say it is a common thing for you<lb/> to entertain one another -
                            this is very<lb/> good - you may also understand it is a<lb/> common
                            thing among your friends<lb/> the Quakers to entertain one another<lb/>
                            when ever the go to see each other, and<lb/> stand in need of victuals,
                            and if any<lb/> of you will visit us in our settlements<lb/> we will
                            entertain you freely - but we<lb/> dont wish you to give our friends at<lb/>
                            <placeName key="tunes">Tunesassa</placeName> any trouble about giveing
                            you<lb/> victuals - for if the fed all the Indians that<lb/> wanted
                            victuals from them they would<lb/> not be able to raise a supply, and by
                            that<lb/> means might be forc'd to break up the settlement</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <pb n="40" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_040"/>


                <p> Some reply was also given to the speech<lb/>
                    <persName key="jpier1">John Pierce</persName> made importing that we hope'd<lb/>
                    he would keep strong in these good resolutions<lb/> &amp; that the Chiefs would
                    unite together in<lb/> trying to do good, for they might be asured<lb/> that
                    when they were endeavouring to pro-<lb/> -mote one anothers good they were doing
                    right<lb/> &amp; this conduct would be pleasing to the Great<lb/> Spirit - but
                    when they try'd to hurt one another<lb/> they offended the Great Spirit -- that
                    while<lb/> they were united together in good works<lb/> they were like a cord
                    made of many strings<lb/> not easily broken - but when they differ'd<lb/> and
                    disagreed among themselves they were<lb/> like the strings which composed that
                    cord<lb/> being seperated from each other might<lb/> by this means be the more
                    easily Broken.<lb/> and we were also glad they intended to<lb/> do better with
                    respect to their wives, and<lb/> hoped they would remain in this mind as<lb/>
                    the Great Spirit would be better pleasd with<lb/> them if they did so --</p>
                <p>
                    <persName key="habee1">Henery Abeal</persName> then made a speech<lb/> to us,
                    which was interpreted by <persName key="psnyd1">Peter Snider</persName><lb/>
                    from which the following is an extract --</p>
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body>
                        <dateline><date when="1806-09-16"/><placeName key="colds"/></dateline>
                        <p> Brothers the Quakers<lb/> I have often acted<lb/> as interpreter between
                            you and the Indi-<lb/> ans, and some times when you are gone <lb/>
                            <pb n="41" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_041"/> they complain and say I did not
                            tell<lb/> them the truth, and perhaps now after<lb/> you go away they
                            will tell me and <persName key="psnyd1">Peter<lb/> Snider</persName> we
                            are both Liars, &amp; therefore I am<lb/> determined to speak right out
                            plainly --</p>
                        <p> Brothers,<lb/> The Indians have understood<lb/> there was a large sum of
                            Money raisd by<lb/> the Quakers to assist them, &amp; they want to<lb/>
                            know how this money was laid out, and<lb/> whether these Mills was paid
                            for out of that<lb/> Money, for you have built them Mills &amp;<lb/> the
                            Indians buy Boards from you, and<lb/> sometimes they can't tell whether
                            you<lb/> are helping them, or they helping you."</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p> He also made some observations on their<lb/> improvement since we first came
                    amongst<lb/> them, contrasting their present situation<lb/> with what it then
                    was, &amp; acknowledged<lb/> their present conditition was much better<lb/> and
                    refer'd to me, to witness the same --</p>
                <p>This was replie'd to nearly as follows: <lb/> that when we first <del>came</del>
                    undertook to<lb/> assist the Indians a large sum of Money<lb/> was rais'd, &amp;
                    the first settlement was made<lb/> among their Brethren the <orgName
                        key="oneida">Onieda Indians</orgName><lb/> which continued near four years
                    and<lb/> a great deal of money was spent there -- <lb/>
                    <pb n="42" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_042"/>
                    <lb/> that we had made several presents to some<lb/> of the Indians of different
                    Nations to the<lb/> westward - that we had furnished the <placeName key="catta1"
                        >Catarau-<lb/> gus</placeName>
                    <placeName key="buffa">Buffalo</placeName> and <placeName key="tonne"
                        >Tonewanta</placeName> Indians with<lb/> divers articles - and when the
                    Settlement<lb/> was first made at <placeName key="alleg1">Allegany</placeName>
                    it was a great<lb/> expense, &amp; buying this land and building<lb/> these
                    Mills cost a great deal of Money,<lb/> but that if ever they should be sold
                    to<lb/> other People, the money would be apli'd<lb/> to the use of the Indians
                    some where<lb/> in some way or other -- that now they<lb/> might plainly see how
                    a great deal<lb/> of money had been expended, &amp; we still<lb/> wish'd to keep
                    a little in Bank to assist<lb/> them more, but that none of the<lb/> maoney
                    rais'd for the benefit of the<lb/> Indians would ever be appli'd to any<lb/>
                    other purpose ----</p>
                <p> Some further remarks were made on<lb/> both sides - &amp; the Indians inform'd
                    us they<lb/> were satisfied about the Boys and Girls<lb/> we propos'd takeing to
                    instruct &amp; left<lb/> it to their friends at <placeName key="tunes"
                        >Tunesassa</placeName> to make<lb/> the Choice --</p>

                <pb n="43" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_043"/>

                <p> We told them we had done speaking and<lb/> hop'd we fully understood each other,
                    that<lb/> all things were now strait and smoother<lb/> and would bid them
                    farewell in love<lb/> and friendship -- which we did most of the<lb/> Indians
                    shakeing hands with us in a friend-<lb/> -ly Manner --</p>
                <p> The Counsel lasted about four hours --<lb/> Several of their principal Women
                    being<lb/> present - &amp; notwithstanding some little<lb/> matters occur'd
                    rather unusual,and<lb/> a little disagreable (but we believd occa-<lb/> sioned
                    by one or two of their young assume<lb/> ing Chiefs without due considerations,
                    who<lb/> are more dispos'd to find fault from a<lb/> disposition of Covetousness
                    than to return<lb/> gratitude for the many benefits they<lb/> have receiv'd from
                    the kindness our friends<lb/> have shown them) yet we left them pretty<lb/> much
                    to our satisfaction, &amp; our friends<lb/> at <placeName key="tunes"
                        >Tunesassa</placeName> were of the opinion our<lb/> Communications to the
                    Indians would<lb/> have a good effect at the present time --</p>
                <p> Their speeches to us were all interpreted<lb/> by <persName key="psnyd1">Peter
                        Snider</persName> and not being well qualifi- ed <lb/>
                    <pb n="44" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_044"/> for the service a considerable loss was
                    sus-<lb/> taind -- and a very evident loss among the<lb/> Indians for want of a
                    Chief qualified to<lb/> deliver their Speeches with ease and cor-<lb/> rectness,
                    notwithstanding they had previ-<lb/> ously agreed upon the subjects of their
                    com<lb/> munications --</p>
            </div>



            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1806-09-17">17th</date>
                    <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p> The most of this day employ'd in write-<lb/> ing &amp;c. In the afternoon
                        <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanters</persName><lb/> Sister (who is a
                    principal woman and was pre-<lb/> -sent at the Counsel) came to see us and<lb/>
                    told us she did not feel satisfied with<lb/> the Speech <persName key="jsilv1"
                        >Silverheels</persName> made to us yeas-<lb/> terday - that it was a very
                    bad speech,<lb/> &amp; she hoped we would not make our<lb/> minds uneasy about
                    it. She said she<lb/> was glad to see us &amp; the Indians were<lb/> generally
                    satisfied with us - and she<lb/> hoped we would be encouraged, for she<lb/> knew
                    the Women wished the Girls to learn<lb/> &amp; many of the Girls also wish'd to
                    be in-<lb/> structed, &amp; said our Women were fully<lb/> capable of
                    instructing them -- Several<lb/> Girls came in the afternon and spun<lb/> and
                    knit a little ---- </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="45" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_045"/>
                <dateline><date when="1806-09-18">18th</date><placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p>Some preparations makeing towards<lb/> leaveing our friends tomorrow --</p>
                <p> With respect to the Indians improve<lb/> ment in the general, it appears
                    from<lb/> our obsevation and the account of our<lb/> friends here that they
                    continue to perseve-re<lb/> in habits of industry - near 100 new<lb/> houses
                    have been built since the commit-<lb/> -tee visited them three years ago most
                    of<lb/> them well put up with hewn Logs -<lb/> very neatly notcht in at the
                    Corners --<lb/> many of them cover'd with shingles<lb/> &amp; have pannel Doors
                    and Glass Windows<lb/> and the houses kept much cleaner than<lb/> formerly so
                    that an evident Change in<lb/> this respect has taken place since our<lb/> women
                    came among them --</p>
                <p> Their farms are enclos'd under good<lb/> fence from 8 to 10 rails high, and
                    more<lb/> detatch'd from each other than formerly --<lb/> a much greater
                    proportion of Corn plan-<lb/> ted this season then has been known<lb/> before
                    which generally looks well --</p>
                <p> Many of them have rais'd Wheat &amp; Oats --<lb/> Several have raisd flax and we
                    saw some<lb/> buckwheat growing, besides Potatoes, Turnips <lb/>0<pb n="46"
                        facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_046"/> &amp;c in abundance -- We also saw some<lb/>
                    lots sow'd with Timothy -- They appear'd to<lb/> be clearing more land in many
                    places some of<lb/> which is intended to be put in, with Wheat<lb/> this fall --
                    They have a good stock of Cattle<lb/> and abundance of Swine -- They have
                    several<lb/> horses among them, but the greater part<lb/> of their farming
                        <del>is done</del> Drawing Logs<lb/> &amp;c is done with Oxen -- Their
                    improve-<lb/> ment in divers respects since I left them, has<lb/> rather
                    exceeded my expectation &amp; quite<lb/> equal to any improvement I have
                    observ'd<lb/> in any of the new settlements made by<lb/> Whites in the same
                    length oftime, &amp; their<lb/> houses better put up, &amp; fences in a general
                    way<lb/> far superior to those made by White set-<lb/> lers in the Back parts of
                        <placeName key="penns">Pensylvania</placeName> &amp;<lb/>
                    <placeName key="newyo">York</placeName> States. Their continued resolutions<lb/>
                    against the use of Spiritous Liquors af-<lb/> -fords an encourageing prospect,
                    that friends<lb/> Labour among them has been peculiarly blest.<lb/> Several Old
                    Men whom I well knew had former<lb/> been very much addicted to drinking
                    and<lb/> generally intoxicated when they could<lb/> obtain Liquor, is now become
                    sober &amp;<lb/> industrious, &amp; very few Instances of intoxication - <lb/>
                    <pb n="47" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_047"/> have occur'd among the
                    <orgName key="allegany">Allegany<lb/> Indians</orgName> for two or three years past -
                    towards<lb/> the Close of our last interview I observ'd<lb/> to them "the
                    satisfaction I felt in seeing<lb/> the happy change had taken place among<lb/>
                    them in this respect, that when I and<lb/> my companions first came among
                    them<lb/> &amp; setled at <placeName key="genes1">Genesinguhta</placeName> it
                    was disagre<lb/> able being <del><gap/></del> in their Towns<lb/> on account of
                    the Liquor -- that now I<lb/> could see them at work on their farms,<lb/>
                    Building houses, &amp; clearing Land but then it<lb/> was common to see them in
                    their Towns<lb/> several of their old people in a huddle<lb/> together, trying
                    to prop one another from<lb/> falling" -- One of the Old Women<lb/> who was
                    present - cry'd out in the Coun-<lb/> sel &amp; said "<emph rend="underline"
                        >that was the truth</emph>" ---</p>
                <p> In the Course of this day an Indian chief call'd<lb/>
                    <persName key="jsnow1">Jacob Snow</persName> (with <persName key="cbone1"
                        >Captain Bone</persName> &amp; several<lb/> others) came to see us &amp;
                    said he was not satis<lb/> fied with the Speech <persName key="jsilv1"
                        >Silverheels</persName> made to<lb/> us at the Counsel, &amp; that the
                    Indians in<lb/> general was much displeas'd with it<lb/> that most of them was
                    well satisfied with <lb/>
                    <pb n="48" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_048"/> Our proceedings &amp; hope'd we
                    would<lb/> not think of leaveing them to themselves<lb/> for that would make his
                    mind very uneasy<lb/> &amp; he hop'd we would not tell the speech of that<lb/>
                    young Chief to the Counsel at <placeName key="phila"
                    >Philadelphia</placeName><lb/> for altho. he had got liberty from the Other<lb/>
                    Chiefs to make such a speech, it was by<lb/> importunity, and was very
                    contrary<lb/> to their wishes -- but if we did speak of<lb/> it to our friends
                    at <placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName> we must<lb/> also tell them
                    what <emph rend="underline">he</emph> had now told us -</p>
                <p> He also told us he was very desirous to<lb/> have one of his children educated
                    with<lb/> our friends, and taught the same<lb/> ways and some thoughts of the
                    Quakers --<lb/> &amp; wish'd us to give him a grant that it<lb/> should be so
                    educated when it was old<lb/> enough it being now but two years<lb/> old -- This
                    request we could not com<lb/> ply with, as we told him it was uncer-tain<lb/>
                    whether any friends would remain at<lb/>
                    <placeName key="tunes">Tunesassa</placeName> so long a time --- He appeard<lb/>
                    to be a sober sensible Man, said he<lb/> was very desirous to become a good<lb/>
                    farmer, we understand has a good deal<lb/> of money, and shew'd us several
                    deeds,<lb/> he had forlots of Ground he had purcha-<lb/> sed from the White
                    people in some <lb/>
                    <pb n="49" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_049"/> of the villages down the <geogName
                        key="alleg">River</geogName> ---</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1806-09-19">19th</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p> The Morning fair about seven Oclock we<lb/> took leave of our friends at
                        <placeName key="tunes">Tunesassa</placeName> and set<lb/> out for <placeName
                        key="catta1">Cataraugus</placeName>
                    <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName> accompanying<lb/> us -- We rode
                    up the river to <unclear>Tusquirewuhty</unclear><lb/> valley near to the upper
                    settlement of Indians<lb/> &amp; as we past along a number of them came<lb/> out
                    to bid us farewell - &amp; many of them<lb/> were at work in the woods mauling
                    rails<lb/> Clearing Land &amp;c -- We also saw a number<lb/> of large Cornfields
                    we had not observ'd on<lb/> our way down the <geogName key="alleg"
                        >River</geogName> -- &amp; several houses<lb/> Building -- <persName
                        key="jpier2">John Peirce</persName> (whose Indian<lb/> name is Tus,sky) is
                    building a house<lb/> at the <placeName key="colds">Cold Spring</placeName> of
                    an elegant construction<lb/> being two stories high - weather boarded on<lb/>
                    the outside &amp; intended to be seald within --<lb/>
                    <persName key="jbell1">John Bell</persName> is employ'd in doing the
                    Carpen-<lb/> ter work for him &amp; in his speech to us at the<lb/> Counsel the
                    16th instant he told us "that he<lb/> had a job of work in hands now with
                    which<lb/> he thought the great Spirit would be<lb/> well pleas'd" -- Leaveing
                    the <geogName key="alleg">Allegany<lb/> River</geogName> we rode up this valley
                    on a new<lb/> road cut by the <orgName>holland Company</orgName>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="50" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_050"/> leading from the west Branch of<lb/>
                    <geogName key="susqu">Susquehannah</geogName> to <geogName key="lakee">Lake
                        Erie</geogName> a little<lb/> south of the Mouth of <geogName key="catri"
                        >Cateraugus River</geogName> -<lb/> pasing by the navigable waters of the<lb/>
                    <geogName key="concr">Conewango</geogName> north of <geogName key="chaut"
                        >Chatoughqua Lake</geogName> --</p>
                <p> This road was possible for horses &amp; not<lb/> much more can be said in its
                    favour altho<lb/> the ground will admit of a Good road being<lb/> made -- We
                    traveld on it about 14 Miles<lb/> takeing a circuitous route to escape a<lb/>
                    very bad piece of road in the Old Indian <del><gap/></del><lb/> path -- On our
                    way traveling an Indian<lb/> path this afternoon, I discover'd a log I lay<lb/>
                    under one night, without fire &amp; snow<lb/> on the Ground, when traveling the
                    same<lb/> path alone near eight years before --</p>
                <p> This evening we enampt on a branch of the<lb/>
                    <geogName key="catri">Cataraugus River</geogName> at the foot of the broad<lb/>
                    Mountain, haveing roade about 35 Miles Mostly<lb/> thro <del>fertile</del> land
                    of a good quality -- Supt on<lb/> Chocolate &amp; the weather being
                    pleasant<lb/> had Comfortable lodgeing beside the fire on<lb/> our
                    Blankets--</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">

                <pb n="51" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_051"/>
                <dateline><date when="1806-09-20">20th</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p> Breakfasted at our Lodgeing (which<lb/> we nam'd Bonsals Camp) and cross'd the<lb/>
                    <geogName key="broam">broad Mountain</geogName> about 12 miles over to<lb/>
                    <geogName key="catri">Catauraugus River</geogName> -- on our way crossing<lb/>
                    this mountain we overtook a company<lb/> of <orgName key="munseeind">Munsy
                        Indians</orgName> who had been out hunting<lb/> they left the road to let us
                    past but kept very<lb/> close to our heels - one Woman was in their<lb/> company
                    mounted on horseback carrying<lb/> several great packs of Skins and a young<lb/>
                    Child in her arms. In descending this<lb/> mountain we had a remarkable
                    steep<lb/> narrow ridge to go down for several hundred<lb/> feet and only just
                    wide enough for one horse to<lb/> travel on, with any degree of safety, and
                    we<lb/> thought dangerous to sit on horseback, but<lb/> the Indian Woman rode
                    down with as much<lb/> ease &amp; unconcernedness as one of our Women<lb/> would
                    ride a Square in <placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName> --</p>
                <p> After Crossing the <geogName key="catri">River</geogName> we stop &amp; fed
                    our<lb/> horses eat some ourselves and spent a little time<lb/> in viewing a
                    very rich flat at the head<lb/> of the Indians reservasion being land of<lb/>
                    the first quality cover'd in many places <lb/>
                    <pb n="52" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_052"/>
                    <del>cover'd</del> with Large black Walnut &amp; on<lb/> the South side of the
                        <geogName key="catri">River</geogName>
                    <del>a</del> fine Stream<lb/> of Water flowing thro' it forming a good<lb/>
                    Millseat -- Rode down the <geogName key="catri">River</geogName> about<lb/> 12
                    miles further to the <orgName key="seneca">Seneca</orgName> village, pasing<lb/>
                    thro. the Village of <orgName key="munseeind">Muncy</orgName> or <orgName
                        key="delaware">Deleware<lb/> Indians</orgName> who live near them -- We
                    arivd<lb/> about three Oclock found the Indians<lb/> Generally at home and glad
                    to see us --<lb/> Took our quarters at <persName key="waund1"
                        >Waundeguhtas</persName><lb/> the Chief Warriors house made ourselves<lb/>
                    some chocolate and his wife was very kind<lb/> in helping us to such provisions
                    as they had --<lb/> This evening we proposed to the Chief<lb/> Warrior meeting
                    them in Counsel to mor-<lb/> row, to which he readily assented &amp; ten<lb/>
                    Oclock was the hour appointed for that<lb/> purpose ---</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1806-09-21">21st</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p> Last Night a little rain fell<lb/> with a good deal of thunder and
                    Lightening<lb/> The Indians told us there had been no rain<lb/> there before for
                    near 20 days -- We lodg'd<lb/> in a new house the Chief warrior had<lb/> built -
                    the lower story of which was oc-<lb/> cupied as a Barn, haveing some Wheat <lb/>
                    <pb n="53" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_053"/> and Corn laying in it &amp; altho we<lb/>
                    were in the Second Story some of <lb/> our company complain'd hard of of
                    disagre-<lb/> -able bedfellows and about midnight<lb/> were somewhat alarm'd by
                    the Yeling of<lb/> the Indians one of our company enquire<lb/> ing whether it
                    was wolves -- We understood<lb/> they were performing some kind of Ceremony<lb/>
                    round a sick Child ----</p>
                <p> This morning we committed a<lb/> sort speech to writeing which we thought<lb/>
                    necessary to communicate to them at the<lb/> Counsel &amp; a little after 10 O
                    clock about<lb/> 19 of their Chiefs &amp; principle men<lb/> assembled in the
                    Camber we lodg'd in,<lb/> &amp; the Chief Warriors Wife with them --</p>
                <p> Soon after being sealed the Chief<lb/> Warior Arose, and said "that four
                    days<lb/> ago he had a message by <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName>
                    that<lb/> some of the Quakers was comeing to see them<lb/> We suppose (said he)
                    you are the people<lb/> we heard of, and are glad and thankful <lb/>
                    <pb n="54" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_054"/> to the Great Spirit for preserveing<lb/>
                    you on your Long Journey, so that you<lb/> have arived here in safety and no
                    accident<lb/> has befallen you on the way" -- and after<lb/> some further
                    remarks relative to our<lb/> Comeing said they were now ready<lb/> to hear us
                    speak --</p>


                <p> Our Speech was then read, and<lb/> Interpreted by <persName key="hyork1">Henry
                        York</persName> being as<lb/> follows ---</p>
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body>
                        <opener><salute>To the Chiefs and others of the<lb/>
                                <orgName key="seneca">Seneca Nation</orgName> of Indians at
                                    <placeName key="catta1">Catarau-<lb/> gus</placeName>
                                ----</salute></opener>

                        <p> Brothers<lb/> As We have been seeing<lb/> your Brethren at <orgName key="allegany">Allegany</orgName> we felt<lb/> such strong desires for
                            your welfare as<lb/> to induce us to come this way and take<lb/> you by
                            the hand, that we might talk<lb/> with you, and know what progress<lb/>
                            you are makeing in farming and<lb/> other good works ----</p>
                        <p> Brothers<lb/> We feel happy in once more <lb/>
                            <pb n="55" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_055"/> being among you, and believe
                            you<lb/> have made some advancement since our<lb/> friends visited you
                            three years ago - We now<lb/> want to encourage you to industry in
                            the<lb/> Cultivation of your Land, for your Land we<lb/> see is very
                            good and easy Clear'd, and will<lb/> produce a great deal of wheat as
                            well as Corn<lb/> if you are industrious and farm it well ---</p>
                        <p> Brothers<lb/> We wish you to learn your Boys to<lb/> work while they are
                            young and by this<lb/> means they will get to love work and be<lb/> able
                            to assist you when they grow older --<lb/> and as you become industrious
                            and raise<lb/> plenty of grain it will afford you a<lb/> much better
                            Liveing &amp; more certain than<lb/> depending on huntery ----</p>
                        <p> Brothers<lb/> We see you have a good stock<lb/> of Cattle &amp; we hope
                            you are careful to<lb/> provide plenty of fodder for them in the<lb/>
                            winter -- We think if you would sow some<lb/> of your rich Bottoms on
                            the <geogName key="catri">River</geogName> with<lb/> Timothy it would
                            afford you a great deal <lb/>
                            <pb n="56" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_056"/> of hay and be an easy way of
                            keeping<lb/> your Cattle --</p>
                        <p> Brothers<lb/> As we have furnish'd you with<lb/> a set of smith tools,
                            we hope your young<lb/> men will be industrious in trying to<lb/> learn
                            that business, that they may be<lb/> able to make and mend your tools
                            --</p>
                        <p> Brothers<lb/> We understand that many of<lb/> your people have left of
                            drinking Whisky<lb/> and we want to encourage you all<lb/> to quit this
                            practice, and to keep your<lb/> minds strong against it, for we
                            know<lb/> it has been the ruin of a great many<lb/> White people, &amp;
                            you know it has been<lb/> a great hurt to the Indians and helpt<lb/> to
                            keep them poor -- but we hope many<lb/> of you have got your eyes open
                            to see that<lb/> Whisky and other strong drinks has been<lb/> your great
                            enemy, and we now want<lb/> you to unite together in keeping this<lb/>
                            enemy from riseing up again, and<lb/> this we believe will be pleasing
                            to the Great Spirit.</p>

                        <pb n="57" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_057"/>

                        <p> Brothers,<lb/> we dont wish to say a great deal<lb/> to you at this
                            time, but rather to encourage<lb/> you to listen to the voice of the
                            good Spirit<lb/> in your own hearts which will teach you<lb/> what is
                            right, and as you obey its dictates<lb/> will make you feel happy in
                            your selves<lb/> and live in love and friendship with one<lb/> another,
                            and with Mankind generally.</p>
                        <p> Brothers if you do what the good<lb/> Spirit tells you is right it will
                            strength<lb/> -en your desires to do good &amp; will make<lb/> you
                            strong in all your good resolutions<lb/> will bless you in this world
                            and make<lb/> you happy when you die ---</p>
                        <closer><dateline><placeName key="catta1">Cataraugus</placeName>
                                <date when="1806-09-21">9 Mo 21st 1806</date></dateline><signed><list>
                                    <item><persName key="ibons1">Isaac Bonsal</persName></item>
                                    <item><persName key="jphil1">John Philips</persName></item>
                                    <item><persName key="hjack1">Halliday Jackson</persName></item>
                                </list></signed></closer>

                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p> The Indians confer'd a few minutes<lb/> together, &amp; the Chief Warrior
                    presently<lb/> stood up and made reply to each particular<lb/> part of our
                    Speech in substence nearly<lb/> as follows --- </p>

                <pb n="58" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_058"/>

                <p> That they were very glad to hear our<lb/> Speech and thankful to the Great
                    Spirit<lb/> for the advice we had given them - that our<lb/> advice heretofore
                    had been very useful and<lb/> encourageing to them to pursue industrious<lb/>
                    habits and they had already got their<lb/> eyes open and were determined to go
                    on<lb/> in the Cultivation of their Land, for they<lb/> knew their Land was very
                    good and they<lb/> suppos'd it was the mind of the Great<lb/> Spirit that they
                    were setled here in this<lb/> good Land -- that they were determined<lb/> to
                    take our advice in learning their<lb/> Children to work while they were
                    young<lb/> &amp; they had for several years past been<lb/> in the practice of
                    learning them -- that<lb/> ten years ago they had little or no cattle<lb/> or
                    stock of any kind, but now they<lb/> were geting plenty and our advice was<lb/>
                    very good respecting their provideing<lb/> fodder, &amp; that some of them had
                    already<lb/> made a beginning to sow Timothy seed-<lb/> for they had sometimes
                    found it diffi-cult <lb/>
                    <pb n="59" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_059"/> to bring their cattle thro' the Winter
                    --</p>
                <p> He also said they were very thankful<lb/> for the Smiths Tools we had sent
                    them<lb/> and that two of their young men was<lb/> active at the smiths business
                    - that some<lb/> years ago if they broke a hoe or an ax they<lb/> must go thirty
                    miles to get it mended --<lb/> which took a great deal of time besides<lb/>
                    paying for it, but now their smiths<lb/> were capable of doing such things for
                    them<lb/> and they only last an hour or two ----</p>
                <p> He further said, we might rely upon<lb/> it they had taken up strong resolutions
                    against<lb/> the use of Whisky and other strong drink --<lb/> and that all that
                    was then present were Chiefs<lb/> and each of them kept a daily watch over<lb/>
                    the rest of the Indians to caution them<lb/> against drinking Whisky playing
                    Ba<gap/><lb/> and other bad practices which they believ'd<lb/> was not
                    pleasing to the Great Spirit --<lb/> but were of the mind the Great Spirit<lb/>
                    was better pleased with them when they<lb/> took hold of the hoe and the Ax and
                    went<lb/> to work -- that since they had got <lb/>
                    <pb n="60" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_060"/> their Eyes open to see, they were<lb/>
                    sensible that strong drink had done them<lb/> a great deal of mischief and kept
                    them<lb/> poor, but now they had got master of it<lb/> &amp; was determined
                    never to let it rise again<lb/> &amp; were in hopes all the Indians of the
                    six<lb/> nations would in time become master of it.</p>
                <p> He also said they were very thankful<lb/> we had given them our speech upon<lb/>
                    paper &amp; deliver'd it to them &amp; said they<lb/> would not only advise
                    their young peo-<lb/> ple themselves but would have our speech<lb/> to apply to
                        <del><gap/></del> strengthen their minds -<lb/> &amp; since they had taken
                    up these good<lb/> resolutions they had daily conferrences<lb/> on these
                    Subjects &amp; were continually<lb/> trying to encourage one another in<lb/>
                    good works --</p>
                <p> He then made some remarks<lb/> about their saw Mill which he said<lb/> they were
                    very anxious to have repair'd<lb/> this fall, &amp; <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob
                        Taylor</persName> inform'd them<lb/> he was then on his way to <placeName
                        key="buffa">Buffalo</placeName><lb/> to procure a Millright to do it
                    for<lb/> them -- for which they returnd many thanks</p>

                <pb n="61" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_061"/>

                <p> After he had done speaking each<lb/> of our company had some further<lb/>
                    remarks to make tending to strengthen<lb/> them in their Good resolutions,
                    and<lb/> encourage them to persevere in habits<lb/> of industry and Sobriety, to
                    all which<lb/> the Chiefs Warrier particularly replied --<lb/> addressing each
                    of us,&amp; first rehearsing what<lb/> we had said nearly verbatim,
                        <del>&amp;</del> concluded<lb/> with saying, "he hop'd the Great Spirit<lb/>
                    would preserve us in as good health as<lb/> we now were, till we got home to
                    our<lb/> wives &amp; Children, &amp; that on our arival<lb/> we might find them
                    all well and all<lb/> the Great men at our Counsel in <placeName key="phila"
                        >Phila</placeName>.</p>
                <p> We then shook hands with them &amp;<lb/> ended the Counsel which was the<lb/>
                    most satisfactory one we have had<lb/> among the Indians, the most of them<lb/>
                    being sober solid looking Men, and<lb/> the Chief Warrior a man of grave<lb/>
                    deportment retentive memory &amp;<lb/> sound Judgement fully capable of<lb/>
                    retaining every thing we had communicated</p>

                <pb n="62" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_062"/>

                <p> Presently after the Counsel, the chiefs<lb/> wife brought us up some dinner of
                    her<lb/> own prepareing, of which some of us eat<lb/> hearty, but some others
                    partook but<lb/> spareingly of her bounty ---</p>
                <p> The Indians of this Village, have<lb/> a large extent of ground under good<lb/>
                    fence in one enclosure stretching<lb/> along the <geogName key="catri"
                        >River</geogName> for near three miles<lb/> on a very rich bottom -- a great
                    deal<lb/> of which is planted with Corn and looks<lb/> well some of it they are
                    now pulling<lb/> nearly all these improvements<lb/> have been made within three
                    years.<lb/> They have a pretty large stock of Cattle<lb/> and Swine &amp; the
                    extensive natural<lb/> Meadows that lay contiguous to them<lb/> affords them a
                    great outlet to feed in<lb/> &amp; the most elegible place for raising
                    Cattle<lb/> of any I have ever seen on Indians Grounds.<lb/> But altho their
                    situation is so very<lb/> favourable for Agriculture they have<lb/> by no means
                    made such a progress<lb/> therein as the <orgName key="allegany">Allegany</orgName> Indians, <lb/>
                    <pb n="63" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_063"/> neither are their houses &amp;
                    Clothes<lb/> kept so clean and neat which is a strong<lb/> evidence that friends
                    Labour and exam-<lb/> ple at <orgName key="allegany">Allegany</orgName> has
                    had a powerful<lb/> effect in these respects ----</p>
                <p> Being now near the extent of our<lb/> Journey - <persName key="jphil1">John
                        Philips</persName> &amp; myself propos'd<lb/> takeing our route homewards by
                    way of<lb/>
                    <placeName key="buffa">Buffalo</placeName> &amp; <placeName key="genes"
                        >Genesee</placeName> - <persName key="ibons1">Isaac Bonsal</persName> &amp;
                        <persName key="nwaln1">Nicho-<lb/> -las Waln</persName> being bound for the
                    state of<lb/> Ohio by way of <placeName key="presq">Pressqu Isle</placeName> --
                    we concluded<lb/> to go down to the <geogName key="lakee">Lake</geogName> near
                    the Mouth<lb/> of <geogName key="catri">Cataraugus River</geogName> and Lodge
                    this night<lb/> together -- Accordingly between four and<lb/> five oclock we set
                    off (most of the Indians<lb/> in the village comeing to to bid us fare-<lb/>
                    well) and rode down the <geogName key="catri">River</geogName> through<lb/> some
                    fine natural meadows coverd<lb/> with much Grass and herbage &amp; rich
                    wal-<lb/> nut flats five Miles to Captain Sidness<lb/><lb/> Tavern - and we
                    ferry'd over the River<lb/> near the <geogName key="lakee">Lake</geogName> in a
                    flat -- We also saw<lb/> a number haystacks on the way which<lb/> was cut and
                    put up by the Indians --</p>

                <pb n="64" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_064"/>

                <p> As we apprehended some advantage<lb/> might arise from takeing some notice<lb/>
                    of the <orgName key="munseeind">Muncy Indians</orgName> who live near<lb/> the
                        <orgName key="seneca">Senecas</orgName> &amp; no oppertunity likely to<lb/>
                    offer to meet them in Counsel we conclu-<lb/> ded to write a short address and
                    leave<lb/> with <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName> to read and
                    explain to<lb/> them on his return, accordingly this<lb/> evening the following
                    was agreed upon<lb/> for that purpose ----</p>
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body>
                        <opener>To the Chiefs and others of the Mun-<lb/> cy Village of <orgName
                                key="munseeind">Indians</orgName> setled near the <geogName
                                key="catri">Catarau<lb/> -gus River</geogName><lb/><salute>Friends
                                and Brothers</salute></opener>
                        <p> </p>

                        <p> As we have<lb/> been on a visit to the Indians at <geogName key="alleg"
                                >Alegany</geogName><lb/> and also to see your near neighbours the<lb/>
                            <orgName key="seneca">Senecas</orgName> at <placeName key="catta1"
                                >Cataraugus</placeName>, we feel such strong<lb/> desires for your
                            welfare that we want<lb/> to say a few words to you tho we cannot<lb/>
                            at this time meet you in Counsel --</p>
                        <p> Brothers<lb/> It is now several years since<lb/> we first began to
                            encourage the <orgName key="seneca">Seneca</orgName><lb/> Nation of
                            Indians to Cultivate their<lb/> land - and some of them have
                            hearken<lb/> ed to our advice, and tell us they are <lb/>
                            <pb n="65" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_065"/> in a much better condition
                            than<lb/> they were before they began to be so<lb/> Industrious --</p>
                        <p> Brothers<lb/> As we passed along thro' your<lb/> Town we were very
                            thoughtful about<lb/> you, and we want you should open your<lb/> ears
                            and listen to our talk --</p>
                        <p> We don't want any thing from you, but we<lb/> wish to encourage you to
                            take up work, &amp;<lb/> to pursue those good ways we will point<lb/>
                            out to you which will make your lives<lb/> more comfortable ---</p>
                        <p> Brothers<lb/> You know that Game is Getting<lb/> scarce and sometimes in
                            the year you<lb/> have no certainty of procureing a liveing<lb/> by
                            hunting - how necessary then is it<lb/> for you to learn to work and
                            raise plenty<lb/> of Corn and other good things that will<lb/> grow out
                            of the Ground -- you may<lb/> also raise plenty of Cattle &amp;
                            Swine<lb/> which will be much more certain than<lb/> the Deer and the
                            Bear ---</p>

                        <pb n="66" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_066"/>

                        <p> Brothers<lb/> As our desires for the wel-<lb/> fare of all our Indian
                            Brothers are<lb/> Strong, we want to speak a few words<lb/> more in your
                            Ears -- We have seen<lb/> that many of the Indian Tribes have<lb/> been
                            much hurt by the use of Whisky<lb/> and Other Strong drink, &amp; we
                            wish<lb/> to encourage you to take up strong<lb/> resolutions to quit
                            the practice of<lb/> drinking it as some of your brethren<lb/> the
                                <orgName key="seneca">Senecas</orgName> have done - By drinking<lb/>
                            much Whisky you spend your Money<lb/> your Skins and many other
                            things<lb/> which you might buy tools to go to<lb/> farming with &amp;
                            also supply yourselves<lb/> with Cattle and Other useful Animals -</p>
                        <p> Brothers<lb/> While you continue to drink<lb/> Whisky &amp; other strong
                            drink, you can not<lb/> expect to improve your land, or to live<lb/>
                            comfortable but if you leave of this<lb/> practice, you will then be
                            able to pro-<lb/> vide yourselves a more comfortable<lb/> Liveing &amp;
                            being Sober &amp; industrious<lb/> The Great Spirit will be pleased
                            with<lb/> you &amp; do you good ---</p>

                        <pb n="67" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_067"/>

                        <p> You know that by drinking <gap/><lb/> Whisky you distress your own
                                m<unclear>ind</unclear><lb/> &amp; bring trouble on your selves
                            &amp; th<unclear>is</unclear><lb/> is displeasing to the Great Spirit
                            --</p>
                        <p> Brothers<lb/> We send this by our friend<lb/>
                            <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName>, who is also a friend
                            to<lb/> the Indians, &amp; who will have this speech<lb/> read &amp;
                            explaind to you ---</p>

                        <closer><salute>We are your friends and
                                    Brothers</salute><lb/><dateline><placeName key="catta1"
                                    >Cataraugus</placeName>
                                <date when="1806-09-21">9 Mo 21st</date></dateline><signed><list>
                                    <item><persName key="jphil1">John Philips</persName></item>
                                    <item><persName key="ibons1">Isaac Bonsal</persName></item>
                                    <item><persName key="hjack1">Halliday Jackson</persName></item>
                                </list></signed></closer>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1806-09-22">22nd</date>
                    <placeName key="catta1"/></dateline>
                <p> Breakfasted at our Lodgeing and about<lb/> 8 Oclock took leave of our Companions
                        <persName key="ibons1">I.B.</persName> &amp;<lb/>
                    <persName key="nwaln1">N. Waln Jr.</persName> &amp; <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob
                        Taylor</persName> accompanying<lb/> us - we had a pleasant Journey along
                    the<lb/> beautiful Margin of <geogName key="lakee">Lake Erie</geogName> 36 Miles to<lb/>
                    <placeName key="buffa">New Amsterdam</placeName> at <geogName key="buffc1"
                        >Buffalo Creek</geogName> -- several<lb/> new Settlements were forming
                    along<lb/> the side of the <geogName key="lakee">Lake</geogName> in this days
                    Journey<lb/> on Land of an exelent Quatity</p>
                <p> We arivd about 5 Oclock and took Quarters<lb/> at <persName key="jcrow1">J
                        Crows</persName> Tavern where <persName key="egran1">Erastus
                        Granger</persName>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="68" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_068"/>
                    <gap/> tendant of Indian Affairs<lb/>
                    <gap/> his home, Who appears to be a<lb/>
                    <gap/> ty Man &amp; much disposd to promote<lb/> the Indians welfare - He
                    invited us<lb/> into his room, to spend the evening &amp;<lb/> entertaind us
                    Cheerfully converseing<lb/> about Indian affairs, tho in a very<lb/> weak state
                    of health --</p>
                <p> He gave us a satisfactory account of the<lb/> Tonewanta Indians, that they were
                    progress-<lb/> ing in Agriculture, and last season most<lb/> of them had rais'd
                    wheat; also said the<lb/> Indians at <placeName key="buffc">Buffalo
                        Creek</placeName> were becoming<lb/> more Sober and some of them more<lb/>
                    Industrious -- He also spoke of the satis-<lb/> faction he had in visiting the
                    Indians<lb/> at <orgName key="allegany">Allegany</orgName> in the Course of
                    the last<lb/> Summer &amp; seeing the improvements<lb/> they had made; &amp;
                    said he thought it<lb/> had a stimulating influence on the <orgName key="seneca"
                        >Seneca<lb/> Nation</orgName> generally to become more acquain-<lb/> ted
                    with Agriculture -- that he had<lb/> endeavoured to animate the Indians<lb/> at
                        <placeName key="buffa">Buffalo</placeName> by telling them their Brothers <lb/>
                    <pb n="69" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_069"/>
                    <gap/> was taking the <gap/><lb/> a <gap/> as as tho' his views were <gap/><lb/>
                    coincident with <del>with</del> the prospects of our<lb/> society in promoteing
                    the welfare of the<lb/> Indians -- In a counsel he had with the Indians<lb/> at
                    <orgName key="allegany">Allegany</orgName> (we understand by our friends
                    that<lb/> were present) he applauded them much <lb/> for their attention to
                    farming and raising<lb/> cattle &amp; recommended them in future to build<lb/>
                    their houses and lay out their farms more<lb/> detatch'd from each other which
                    would afford<lb/> them a better oppertunity of pursuing the<lb/> desirable
                    object of farming and raising<lb/> cattle -- "If you pass thro' the Country
                    among<lb/> the White people (<emph rend="underline">said he</emph>) you will
                    find each<lb/> man on his farm attending to his grain Cattle<lb/> hogs &amp;c
                    but if you go into their Towns there<lb/> you will find the Doctors, the
                    Lawyers, Mini-<lb/> -sters &amp; Merchants, which is a class of people<lb/> I
                    wish may never come among you</p>
                <p> He further Observ'd that he had been infor-<lb/> -m'd of a man who intended to
                    come and reside<lb/> among them in order to make bobs &amp; Brotches<lb/> &amp;
                    such like useless ornaments. "now (said h<unclear>e)</unclear><lb/> I would
                    advise you not to suffer this <gap/>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="70" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_070"/>
                    <gap/>te on your Land by <gap/><lb/>
                    <gap/> you do he will pick up a gre<gap/><lb/>
                    <gap/>nay, and you will be none the <gap/><lb/> If you keep your money you can
                    buy Oxen<lb/> or other useful property from the White<lb/> People but if you
                    carry a white man a<lb/> Basket full of those Bobs and brotches he will<lb/> not
                    Look at them -- Towards the close of<lb/> his speech he said he had not visited
                    them<lb/> as often as he intended, but if they stood in<lb/> need of any advice
                    they had friends who were<lb/> always dispos'd to assist them "for the
                    Quakers<lb/> (said he) have done more for the Indians,<lb/> than any other
                    society of people in the<lb/> world --</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1806-09-23">23rd</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p> Breakfasted at our Lodgeing &amp; got good<lb/> entertainment, tho' at a high
                    rate, especially<lb/> for our horses, pay 4 <unclear>s</unclear> pr night each
                    york Mon-<lb/> =ney - &amp; wheat <unclear>9</unclear>d pr quart haveing no
                    other<lb/> grain for horses, by reason of a great drouth<lb/> they have had in
                    these parts this Summer.<lb/> &amp; the frost the <date when="1806-09-11"
                        >11th</date> instant has injured<lb/> the corn in many places here a
                    way.</p>
                <p> This Morning the <persName key="egran1">Superintendant</persName> took<lb/> us
                    to see a stone of perhaps 100 weight which<lb/> was full of small pores a little
                    similar to<lb/> honey Comb &amp; strongly impregnated<lb/> with Seneca Oil which
                    was easily <lb/>
                    <pb n="71" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_071"/>
                    <gap/> ed by the warmth of the <gap/><lb/>
                    <gap/>nter of these stones have been fo<gap/><lb/>
                    <gap/>ut <geogName key="buffc1">Buffalo Creek</geogName>, &amp; probably in some
                    <gap/><lb/> the bowels of the Earth contains a mass of<lb/> Rocks of the same
                    medical qualitys from which the<lb/> Seneca Oil Issues ----</p>
                <p> We left <placeName key="buffa">Amsterdam</placeName> about eight Oclock and<lb/>
                    rode to <placeName key="batav">Batavia</placeName> 40 Miles - Some part of
                    the<lb/> way thro' Open plains of limestone land<lb/> &amp; a great scarcity of
                    Water and other parts<lb/> cover'd with heavy timber of several kinds<lb/> such
                    as Bass Beech, Sugar Maple, hemloc &amp; <gap/><lb/> pine, the land of an
                    exelent quality &amp; <gap/><lb/> fort -- <placeName key="batav"
                        >Batavia</placeName> is situated at the Great P<gap/><lb/> of the Tonewanta
                    - a very fine Mill, Court<gap/><lb/> two Taverns - &amp; several good dweling
                    p<gap/><lb/> compose the Village which with s<gap/><lb/> improv'd farms
                    adjoining, have <gap/><lb/> built &amp; Made within five years <gap/><lb/>
                    evening a number of Indians fro<gap/><lb/> ariv'd here on their way to the
                    Grea<gap/><lb/> at <placeName key="buffc">Buffalo Creek</placeName> -- they had
                    one <gap/><lb/> with them dress'd neatly in an engl<gap/><lb/> for which we gave
                    her some credit -- <gap/><lb/> all behav'd sober &amp; civilly without
                    <gap/><lb/> a drop of Liquor to our knowledge, <gap/><lb/> be noted with
                    satisfaction that i<gap/>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="72" facs="SW_HJ1806_Page_072"/>
                    <gap/> our journey many al<gap/><lb/>
                    <gap/> settlements we have passed thr<gap/><lb/>
                    <gap/> have not saw one Indian the Last<lb/>
                    <gap/> intoxicated with Liquor --</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1806-09-24">24th</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p> Breakfasted by invitation with <persName key="jelic1"
                        >Jos<unclear>eph</unclear><lb/> Ellicott</persName> who promis'd to send on
                    a Surveyor<lb/> in a few days to run of the Farm at <placeName key="tunes"
                        >Tunesassa</placeName>.</p>
                <p> He took us up stairs to see a curious Clock<lb/> of his Fathers invention -
                    which stood in the<lb/> Center of a room - had 4 faces made several<lb/> kinds
                    of Music &amp; represented the Sun, Moon,<lb/>
                    <gap/> Earth with several Planets performing<lb/> their Annual &amp; Diannal
                    revolutions at<lb/>
                    <gap/> act periods as the move in the heavens -<lb/>
                    <gap/>bout 8 Oclock we left <placeName key="batav">Batavia</placeName> takeing<lb/>
                    <gap/>
                    <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName> who had accompanied us<lb/>
                    <gap/> traveling by way of <placeName key="genes">Genesee</placeName>
                    <placeName key="cones">Conesteo</placeName><lb/>
                    <gap/> house, <placeName key="newbe">Newberry</placeName> - <placeName
                        key="muncy">Muncy</placeName><lb/>
                    <gap/>
                    <placeName key="harri">Harrisburgh</placeName> &amp; <placeName key="lanca"
                        >Lancaster</placeName> 2<lb/>
                    <gap/>ne on the fourth of the 10th<lb/>
                    <gap/> about <gap/> noon haveing<lb/>
                    <gap/>way 34 days and traveld<lb/>
                    <gap/> putation about <emph rend="underline">820 Miles</emph></p>
            </div>
        </body>

    </text>
</TEI>
