<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei-print.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" hkey="global.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>Halliday Jackson 1800 Journal (continued): Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>Emma Remsberg</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Journal transcribed by</resp>
                    <name>Emma Remsberg</name>

                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Tri-Co Digital Humanities Initiative</sponsor>
                <funder>Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 92 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>This work is the property of the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore
                        College. It may be copied freely by individuals for personal use, research,
                        and teaching (including distribution to classes) as long as this statement
                        of availability is included in the text. It may be linked to freely in
                        Internet editions of all kinds, including for—profit works.</p>
                    <p>Publishers, libraries, and other information providers interested in
                        providing this text in a commercial or non—profit product or from an
                        information server must contact Swarthmore College for licensing and cost
                        information.</p>
                    <p> Scholars interested in changing or adding to these texts by, for example,
                        creating a new edition of the text (electronically or in print) with
                        substantive editorial changes, may do so with the permission of Swarthmore
                        College. This is the case whether the new publication will be made available
                        at a cost or free of charge.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2014">2014</date>
                <idno type="local">SW_HJ1800</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Native Americans and Quakers: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>Miscellaneous Manuscripts</collection>
                        <idno>Mss003/43</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>43 pp. (1 volume)</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This 1800 journal of Halliday Jackson is in the collections of Friends Historical
                    Library of Swarthmore College. It was transcribed and encoded as part of a
                    larger project to make available a number of Quaker journals which document
                    contact between Friends and Native Americans between 1790 and 1810.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> The transcribers and editor attempted to render the author’s orthography and
                    grammar as they appear on the page of his journal, even when the author’s own
                    spelling and usage are inconsistent. Additionally, many questions remain about
                    spelling the names of his Quaker acquaintances, individual Native Americans who
                    populate his journal, and Indian villages and towns. The transcribers and editor
                    attempted to remain faithful to the author’s Anglicized spellings in all cases. </p>
                <p>The author of the original journal does not include page numbers on his
                    manuscript; the page numbers have been interpolated by the transcribers to
                    correspond with the manuscript sheets.</p>
            </editorialDecl>

        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written in <date when="1800">1800</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Society of Friends</item>

                        <item>Alleghany River Valley (Pa. and N.Y.)—History</item>
                        <item>Church and state--Ohio</item>
                        <item>Cornplanter, Seneca chief, 1732?-1836</item>
                        <item>Indian reservations</item>
                        <item>Indians of North America--Missions</item>
                        <item>New York (State)--Description and travel</item>
                        <item>Pennsylvania--Description and travel</item>

                        <item>Philadelphia Yearly Meeting of the Religious Society of Friends</item>
                        <item>Quakers--Pennsylvania--Diaries</item>
                        <item>Quakers--Political activity</item>
                        <item>Seneca Indians</item>
                        <item>Society of Friends--Missions</item>
                        <item>Voyages and Travels</item>


                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>

        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change><date/></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>

        <body>
            
            <div type="undetermined">
                <pb n="1" facs="SW_HJ1800_001"/>
            </div>
            
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="2" facs="SW_HJ1800_002"/>
                <head>Some account of my residence among<lb/> the Indians Continued --</head>


                <dateline><date when="1800-03-01">3rd Mo the 1st</date><placeName key="genes1"/></dateline>
                <p>The weather very<lb/> Cold and Snow near three feet deep<lb/> In the last month
                    the Indians generally<lb/> collected to <placeName key="cornp">Cornplanters
                        Town</placeName> to perform<lb/> their Yearly sacrifice where the
                    continued<lb/> near twenty days with their usual parade<lb/> of dancing musick
                    and feasting, and such was<lb/> their zeal to have their people generally<lb/>
                    collected that a certain lame man whom<lb/> we had instructing in school
                    learning<lb/> the drag'd on Deer skins to the Lower village<lb/> and an old lame
                    man unable to travel the<lb/> drew 13 or 14 miles in the same manner --</p>
                <p> At this time they had much counseling<lb/> about appointing some young
                    Chiefs<lb/> but could not agree generally in their<lb/> Choice --</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1800-03-02"/><placeName key="cornp"/></dateline>
                <p> At the Indians request the 2nd of this<lb/> month I went to <placeName
                        key="cornp">Cornplanters village</placeName><lb/> in order to write
                    something which they<lb/> wish'd to keep in remembrance and on<lb/> my arival
                    they people were generally <lb/>
                    <pb n="3" facs="SW_HJ1800_003"/> collectd together when I found the
                    writeing<lb/> they wanted done was a speech which <persName
                        key="cornp2">Corn-plan<lb/> ters</persName> <persName key="conud1">Brother</persName> was going to make
                    respecting what<lb/> (he saith) he had seen in a trance some time<lb/> before,
                    which I would willingly have evaded write<lb/> ing but could not without giveing
                    offence to the<lb/> Indians which I though best to avoid at that time.</p>
                <p> The old man related several strange things<lb/> which he said was shown unto
                    him, all which<lb/> I wrote but shall avoid inserting here - and after<lb/> the
                    whole was related they desired me to tell them<lb/> my opinion of it and whether
                    I thought<lb/> it was true -- But I told them I had, had but<lb/> little time to
                    think about it and could not<lb/> tell, and therefore
                    avoided giveing them an<lb/> answer at that time -- Then the Council<lb/> ended
                    and next day I return'd home --</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1800-03-29">29th of the month</date><placeName key="genes1"/></dateline>
                <p> By a certain <persName key="fking1">Francis<lb/> King</persName> who was setled
                    on the waters of<lb/> this <geogName key="alleg">River</geogName> about 60 miles
                    above us we received<lb/> a number of Letters from <placeName key="phila"
                        >Philadelphia</placeName><lb/> and also from our relations in the<lb/>
                    adjacent parts which after a long winter<lb/> in which we had receivd but little
                    informa<lb/> tion from them was truly satisfactory</p>
                <p> We also got intelligence from the committee <lb/>
                    <pb n="4" facs="SW_HJ1800_004"/> on Indian affairs which informd us that
                    the<lb/> two Young Men - (<persName key="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName> and
                        <persName key="jthom2">Jonathan Thomas</persName>)<lb/> who had been
                    residenters at the <placeName key="oneid">Onieda settlement</placeName><lb/> did
                    not appear releast from further service among<lb/> the Indians and that there
                    was some expec-<lb/> tation of them comeing to spend some time at<lb/> our
                    settlement which was encourageing and<lb/> comfortable intelligence to me as I
                    had for<lb/> several months past had a prospect of being<lb/> releast from the
                    present engagement the<lb/> ensuing summer, haveing inform'd the<lb/> Committee
                    on Indian affairs thereof<lb/> accordingly --</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1800-05-04">5th month the 4th</date><placeName key="genes1"/></dateline>
                <p> Receivd a letter from<lb/>
                    <persName key="ijack1">my Father</persName> in which he express much<lb/> desire
                    for my return before the ensuing<lb/> Harvest if the way should open for it,
                    men<lb/> tioning his bodily infirmities were much<lb/> encreased so as to render
                    him incapable<lb/> of takeing the necessary care of his concerns<lb/> which
                    created a little anxiety in my mind<lb/> on his account as the prospect of my
                    get-<lb/> ting away that soon was somewhat uncertain<lb/> no certain accounts
                    haveing yet arived of<lb/> others comeing forward to keep up the<lb/> settlement
                    at this place --</p>


                <pb n="5" facs="SW_HJ1800_005"/>

                <p> About this time <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> and a member<lb/>
                    of his people went to <placeName key="buffc">Buffalo Creek</placeName> to
                    receive their<lb/> yearly annuity from Goverment at which<lb/> place a general
                    Council of the <orgName key="seneca">Seneca
                        Nation</orgName> was<lb/> held where the Superintendant of Indian
                    affairs<lb/> Attended -- On their return <persName key="cornp2"
                        >Corn-planter</persName><lb/> requested us to attend at their <placeName
                        key="cornp">Village</placeName> when<lb/> the collected to divide their
                    money which we<lb/> did accordingly the <date when="1800-05-08">8th of this
                        month</date>, <persName key="cornp2">Corn-<lb/> planter</persName> then
                    informd us of their proceeding<lb/> at the Late Counsel at <placeName
                        key="buffc">Buffalo Creek</placeName> and of<lb/> the disunity that was like
                    to take place<lb/> among the different tribes -- also gave us a<lb/> sorrowful
                    account of a Murder that was com-<lb/> mitted at that
                    place during his stay there,<lb/> by an Indian who lived in the Genesee<lb/>
                    Countrey. -- In the house of <persName key="wjohn1">Wm. Johnson</persName><lb/>
                    a Negro Man was playing with a Child<lb/> that was runing about the Floor - The
                    Indian<lb/> comeing in said to him <said who="undetermined">You are a Negro,
                        you<lb/> have no business here, do you go away</said> -- but<lb/> the poor
                    Black man little thinking his<lb/> doom was so near paid little attention to
                    him<lb/> but being told the Indian had a knife in<lb/> his hand he flew back to
                    the wall, &amp;<lb/> the Indian without any further provocation <lb/>
                    <pb n="6" facs="SW_HJ1800_006"/> immediately pursued him and stab'd him<lb/>
                    throw the heart so that he expird in a few minutes<lb/> The murderer stay'd
                    about and saw him expire<lb/> without any appearance of conviction or
                    dismay<lb/> and was not apprehended at that time tho<lb/> numbers of White
                    people were present --</p>
                <p> While we were speaking with <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName><lb/> a
                    member came in to tell him of another murder<lb/> that was committed a few days
                    before among<lb/> his own people -- Two Indians that were brothers<lb/> being
                    down the River about <geogName key="stump">Stump Creek</geogName> a hunt-<lb/>
                    ing differed between themselves and the oldest kill'd<lb/> the younger -- This
                    latter appear'd to be the dread<lb/> ful efforts of strong drink that great
                    engine of<lb/> Human wretchedness which too many alas that<lb/> are called
                    Christians are earnestly contending for<lb/> the use of notwithstanding the
                    dismal effects it<lb/> produces in almost every quarter of the land and<lb/>
                    more particularly among these poor Ignorant<lb/> inhabitants of the wilderness
                    -- These affecting<lb/> Circumstances and many others produced by<lb/> the use
                    of Spiritous Liquors together with some<lb/> occurrences that took place during
                    the late<lb/> Council at <placeName key="buffc">Buffalo Creek</placeName> caused
                        <persName key="cornp2">Corn-plan<lb/> ter</persName> to write to Congress on
                    the Occasion --</p>
                <p> After the Indians had divided their money <lb/>
                    <pb n="7" facs="SW_HJ1800_007"/> which amounted to three dollars a Soul they
                    call'd<lb/> us into the house and inform'd us that the had<lb/> reserv'd a
                    little for us -- Observeing that we had<lb/> now been a great while among them
                    trying to do<lb/> them good and had given them a great deal, &amp;<lb/> said
                    they knew we were not in the way of hunt-<lb/> ing to get meat as they did, that
                    we had to buy<lb/> Skins to make ourselves Mokinsons, and that<lb/> it was very
                    hard if they should never give us<lb/> any thing to help us to get our liveing
                    --</p>
                <p> We replied the offer was very kind of<lb/> them but that we did not stand in
                    need<lb/> of any assistance - that we came among them<lb/> to do them good and
                    try to learn them the<lb/> good ways of the White people, and that we<lb/> often
                    had told them we wanted nothing<lb/> from them for all our trouble, but
                    when<lb/> we stood in need of any money to buy provisions<lb/> our friends gave
                    it to us, that we did not<lb/> depend on the forrests for meat but killd<lb/>
                    the Pig and the Cow, and that many of<lb/> the Indians was very kind to us
                    when<lb/> they killd plenty of meat they often gave<lb/>
                    us share --</p>
                <p>
                    <persName key="cornp2">Corn-planter</persName> then observ'd we had but <lb/>
                    <pb n="8" facs="SW_HJ1800_008"/> one Cow to give us milk, and that it was
                    hard<lb/> we had not plenty of Milk that we might<lb/> go and buy ourselves
                    another good Cow, and insisted<lb/> upon us takeing the money, which as it
                    was<lb/> given as a present from the Indians we accepted<lb/> though with much
                    reluctance, but concluded to give<lb/> them the value of it in something else
                    that would<lb/> be of as much use to them --</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>The <date when="1800-05-25">25th of this month</date><placeName key="genes1"/></dateline>
                <p>in the morning arived<lb/> our friends <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob
                        Taylor</persName> and <persName key="jthom2">Jonathan Thomas</persName><lb/>
                    whom we had some expectation of for several<lb/> weeks past -- Their arival to
                    me was glad<lb/> tideings of much Joy, as I had since receiving<lb/> the last
                    letter from <persName key="ijack1">my father</persName> some
                    <del>expect</del><lb/> Anxiety to hear of some comeing forward to<lb/> unite in
                    endeavouring to promote the welfare<lb/> of the Natives in this Quarter - but
                    now the<lb/> Addition of two valuable experienced friends<lb/> caused those
                    anxieties to subside and the way<lb/> appeard to open with considerable
                    Clearness<lb/> for me to look towards my native land<lb/> with gladening
                    Sensations which appear'd to<lb/> mingle with the expectations and desires
                    of<lb/> some of my relations and concern'd friend who<lb/> visited me with
                    several acceptable letters by<lb/> the late oppertunity --</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">

                <pb n="9" facs="SW_HJ1800_009"/>


                <dateline><date when="1800-06-02">6 mo the 2nd</date><placeName key="cornp"/></dateline>
                <p>Went down to the <placeName key="cornp">lower Village</placeName><lb/> with
                        <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName> and <persName key="jthom2"
                        >Jonathan Thomas</persName>, <persName key="cornp2">Corn<lb/>
                        planter</persName> and a number of his people being gone to<lb/>
                    <placeName key="pitts">Pittsburgh</placeName> prevented us from haveing an
                    interview<lb/> with the Indians to inform them generally of<lb/> the intentions
                    of our newly come friends but<lb/> the few that were at home appeard
                    respectful<lb/> and glad to see them --</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1800-06-08">8th of the month</date><placeName key="genes1"/></dateline>
                <p> An express came from<lb/> the Cataraugus Indians that the Millwrights<lb/> were
                    ariv'd at <placeName key="buffc">Buffalo Creek</placeName> who had
                    undertaken<lb/> to build their Saw Mill and was therefore desirous<lb/> that
                    some of us might go over and give them<lb/> a little assistance in planing the
                    business, as<lb/> they had such a Grant from <persName key="jtayl1"
                        >Jacob Taylor</persName> and<lb/>
                    <persName key="jthom2">Jonathan Thomas</persName> if call'd upon -- Altho, I
                    was<lb/> only waiting for the Indians return from <placeName key="pitts"
                        >Pitts<lb/> burgh</placeName> to take leave of this place and return to<lb/>
                    my native land, this intelligence from <placeName key="catta1"
                        >Cataraugus</placeName><lb/> reviv'd some desires <del>to</del> Which
                    <gap/> before had<lb/> to <del>town</del>
                    see that place, again before I left the Countrey
                    &amp;<lb/> therefore <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName> and myself
                    concluded<lb/> to set forward next morning on the Journey.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1800-06-09">9th</date><placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p> Accordingly set out about 8 Oclock and<lb/> rode thro' the woods till
                    near sundown, came<lb/> to the <orgName key="delaware"
                        >Delaware Indians</orgName> hunting Camp found <lb/>
                    <pb n="10" facs="SW_HJ1800_010"/> a fire ready kindled and rested
                    comfortably<lb/> beside it till morning --</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1800-06-11">9st</date><placeName key="catta1"/></dateline>
                <p> Set forward on our way and reach'd the<lb/> Neighbourhood of <placeName
                        key="catta1">Cataraugus</placeName> about noon, and<lb/> spent sometime in
                    exploreing a Stream of<lb/> water a little east of the Delaware vilage on
                    which<lb/> we thought a favourable situation might be had<lb/> for a sawmill,
                    and where was some open plains<lb/> I had not before seen the most delightful
                    for cul-<lb/> -tivation of any I had ever seen being extensive<lb/> fertile
                    flats surrounded with beautiful groves<lb/> of White Oak White Pine &amp; sugar
                    Maple -- And<lb/> a pretty stream flowing thro' the Midst thereof<lb/>
                    furnishing abundant oppertunities for settlements<lb/> on either side -- We then
                    rode down to the <orgName key="seneca"
                    >Seneca</orgName><lb/> village and went to the Chief Warriors house who was<lb/>
                    not at home but his wife treated us with much<lb/> hospitallity and manifested
                    her hearty good <del>will</del><lb/> will towards us by furnishing us with the
                    best<lb/> accommodations she could afford -- The Mill<lb/> wrights we understood
                    was ariv'd and gone to the<lb/> propos'd place for building the sawmill which
                    was<lb/> on the south side of the <geogName key="catri">River</geogName> near a
                    mile above<lb/> the Village -- After
                    refreshing ourselves the<lb/> Chiefs wife and several others accompanied us<lb/>
                    to the place whe the Millwrights had begun to work
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="11" facs="SW_HJ1800_011"/> The situation was very beautifull for the
                    purpose<lb/> but the stream we thought was rather smal &amp;<lb/> several of the
                    Indians express'd their fears about it.<lb/> And seem'd desirours we should take
                    a review of<lb/> the other Stream which we attended to the next<lb/> day in
                    company with the Millwrights and were<lb/> still of the mind a good mill seat
                    might be had<lb/> at that place but the Mill wrights seem'd to throw<lb/>
                    several Obstacles in the way, and persisted in going on<lb/> with the work where
                    the had begun and the Indians<lb/> conclueding the
                    other stream might answer their pur-<lb/> pose tho' it would not saw all the
                    year, we found<lb/> best to <del><gap/></del> leave the Matter pretty much
                    to them<lb/> selves, yet the return'd us many thanks for our<lb/> care in
                    comeing to advise them --</p>
                <p> This evening we mentioned to some of their Chiefs<lb/> that we propos'd going
                    home to morrow &amp; should<lb/> like to see a few of them collected together
                    next<lb/> morning to take leave of them before we departed.<lb/> They replied
                    they had thought of the same<lb/> thing and would be happy to speak a few
                    words<lb/> with <del>them</del> us before we went away --</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1800-06-12">12th of the month</date><placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p> Accordingly this forenoon<lb/> the chiefs and others collected and call'd us
                    into<lb/> the Counsel room where we had some further<lb/> conversation about the
                    sawmill with which the <lb/>
                    <pb n="12" facs="SW_HJ1800_012"/> appear'd satisfied -- I also thought
                    proper to inform<lb/> them that I was now about to leave the Indian<lb/> Country
                    and go home to any friends, that I had been<lb/> very happy in liveing this thwo
                    years among their<lb/> Brethren on the <geogName key="alleg">Allegany
                        River</geogName> endeavouring to be<lb/> useful to them, and that I felt so
                    much regard for them<lb/> as to come and see them before I left their
                    Countrey<lb/> that I was well pleas'd in viewing their Land and<lb/> glad the
                    had reserv'd such a fine piece of Land to<lb/> live upon, and was desirous they
                    might use all<lb/> endeavours to cultivate this Land that they might<lb/> came
                    to enjoy plenty to live upon -- also that I<lb/> heard of their resolutions to
                    quit the use of Strong<lb/> drink, and hoped they might be strong in them<lb/>
                    so as to gain a victory -- After some further re-<lb/> marks the Young war Chief
                    (who appears to be<lb/> a man of an active understanding) made a reply<lb/> that
                    he was thankful the Great Spirit above<lb/> had preseved such a fine day for us
                    to meet together<lb/> and that we appear'd to be of one mind -- And<lb/> then
                    repeated a Speech nearly in substance<lb/> to what he had delivered to <persName
                        key="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName> &amp;<lb/>
                    <persName key="jthom2">Jonathan Thomas</persName> about two weeks before, which<lb/>
                    <del>which</del> was as follows "We feel happy to see you<lb/> arive at our Town
                    &amp; thank the great Spirit<lb/> for preserveing you safe on the Journey as if <lb/>
                    <pb n="13" facs="SW_HJ1800_013"/> he had appointed this day for us to meet
                    together -<lb/> We call you Brothers because you are willing to instruct<lb/> us
                    and we thank you for takeing the pains<lb/> to call to see us - we now want to
                    enquire of<lb/> you concerning a speech we sent down to <placeName key="phila"
                        >Philadel-<lb/> phia</placeName> last winter to our friends - Quakers -
                    we<lb/> have had a great deal of difficulty about the sale<lb/> of our lands,
                    and much counseling together have<lb/> got this piece reserved for ourselves to
                    live upon -<lb/> we have looked round on every side to see if<lb/> there was any
                    people that regarded the good<lb/> Spirit so much as to deal Justly and
                    honestly<lb/> with us - we heard of the Quakers that they<lb/> were honest and
                    might be depended on, &amp; we<lb/> unanimously agreed in counsel to apply
                    to<lb/> them for assistance and instruction, and in<lb/> the first place
                    requested them to furnish us with<lb/> a set of Sawmill Irons which they have
                    kindly<lb/> granted and sent forward -- we often consider<lb/> our wild
                    situation and sometimes think we<lb/> are too wild to become a civilized people,
                    but<lb/> we have come to a resolution to try all we<lb/> can, and now their is
                    not any body can<lb/> charge the people of this Town with doing any<lb/> damage
                    or Mischief neither has there been <lb/>
                    <pb n="14" facs="SW_HJ1800_014"/> one shilling of our annuity kept back on
                    account<lb/> of the misconduct of our warriors -- we are deter-<lb/> mined to
                    persevere in the resolutions we have formed<lb/> and altho' we may not yet make
                    much progress in<lb/> this way yet we look forward to our Children and
                    think<lb/> the instruction of our friends Quakers will have a<lb/> lasting good
                    effect on them -- we therefore think<lb/> our friends may afford us assistance
                    as the see<lb/> encouragement and according as our conduct deserves."</p>
                <p> This was in substance repeated to us at this<lb/> time and the Young Chief also
                    made some<lb/> further observations desireing that I might tell<lb/> their Old
                    friends the Quakers when I went home<lb/> that they were exceedinly thankful for
                    the<lb/> kindnesses shewn them and the assistance we<lb/> had already given them
                    that they were now<lb/> determined to follow our advice as far as
                        they were<lb/> Able, and to spill all the Whisky that
                    traders<lb/> should bring among them for sale -- &amp; that we<lb/> must not
                    think they were offended at us try<lb/> ing to make them sensible of
                    their weaknesses<lb/> for even their young men &amp; young women<lb/> rejoiced
                    to hear it and were in hopes their<lb/> hands would grow stronger that they
                    might<lb/> be enabled to gain the victory -- <lb/>
                    <pb n="15" facs="SW_HJ1800_015"/> Also that they were determined to try to
                    help<lb/> themselves and lay up money to purchase<lb/> useful articles to go to
                    farming with for the pitied<lb/> their poor women and saw it was too hard for
                    them<lb/> to do all their Labour and work out in the hot sun.<lb/> and altho the
                    could not ask any more favours<lb/> of us - they were desirous we should
                    remember<lb/> them, and as we saw on knew their poor situation<lb/> they would
                    leave it to ourselves to do whatsoever<lb/> we thought best for them, but one
                    thing in<lb/> particular (they said) we desire you to remem-<lb/> ber that we
                    are a poor Ignorant people and for<lb/> want of Learning, in the course of our
                    dealings<lb/> with the white people have been greatly
                    wronged<lb/> and Lost much of our property -- we want some<lb/> of our Children
                    instructed that they may<lb/> have their eyes open'd and be able to do the<lb/>
                    business of our nation, and if any of your<lb/> society will come and live
                    amongst us and<lb/> instruct our Children that rich flat which<lb/> we were
                    viewing yeasterday we have set apart<lb/> for them to live upon and it shall be
                    for them<lb/> as long as the choose to stay on it" --</p>
                <p> We told them we were glad to hear the resolu<lb/> tions they had formed and
                    desired they<lb/> might be strong and keep to them, and that <lb/>
                    <pb n="16" facs="SW_HJ1800_016"/> I would inform their Old friends in
                        <placeName key="phila">Philadel<lb/> phia</placeName> of their talk, but we
                    could not tell whether<lb/> any of our society would come to live among
                    them<lb/> or not, yet we would still remember them &amp;<lb/> be their friends,
                    and when the got their saw<lb/> mill built if the wanted any assistance
                    about<lb/> it or instruction to work with it some of our<lb/> company from the
                        <placeName key="alleg1">Allegany</placeName> would be willing<lb/> to come
                    and spend some time with them &amp;<lb/> that in addition to some hoes and Axes
                    that<lb/> were comeing forward for their use we would<lb/> add a set of plow
                    Irons, for all which they<lb/> returnd many thanks and thus our inter-<lb/> view
                    ended to good satisfaction, a favourable<lb/> openness we thought appearing
                    Among the<lb/> Indians at that place for further endeavours<lb/> being used to
                    promote the work of Civilization.<lb/> About noon we set off homewards, call'd
                    by<lb/> the way to see the <orgName key="delaware"
                        >Delaware Indians</orgName>, lodg'd<lb/> again under an Indians camp and reach'd<lb/>
                    <placeName key="alleg1">Allegany</placeName> next day about two Oclock --</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1800-06-14">14th</date><placeName key="cornp"/></dateline>
                <p> The Indians being return'd from<lb/>
                    <placeName key="pitts">Pittsburgh</placeName> we all went down in a Cannoe<lb/>
                    to <del><gap/></del>
                    <placeName key="conis">Conishadaga</placeName> to Meet them in counsel<lb/>
                    haveing sent them word the evening before --<lb/> Shortly after we ariv'd a
                    Number of the <lb/>
                    <pb n="17" facs="SW_HJ1800_017"/> Indians collected when four new come
                    friends certi<lb/> ficate from the Committee on Indian affairs was<lb/> read and
                    explaind to them with which they<lb/> appeard well satisfied and said
                    it was true what<lb/> our friends had told them last fall that if any<lb/> other
                    young men should incline to come and live among<lb/> the Indians they
                    would be encouraged to come for-<lb/> ward <del><gap/> good <gap/> by
                        civilization</del> and they were<lb/> well pleas'd with the
                    Quakers being among them for<lb/> they thought it was so ordered by the Great
                    Spirit--</p>
                <p> I then told them I was about to take up my<lb/> pack and go to my own Countrey
                    -- that I had<lb/> lived very happy this two years among them<lb/> endeavouring
                    to be useful to them and was<lb/> thankful to the Great Spirit that all
                    that<lb/> time we had lived together like Brothers and in good<lb/> friendship,
                    &amp; they must not think hard of<lb/> my leaveing them
                    for I still desired their prosperrity<lb/> and welfare and hoped the would
                    gradually<lb/> come forward in the good work of civilization<lb/> and be strong
                    in their resolutions to overcome<lb/> that great evil strong drink --
                    Several<lb/> further remarks were made to them but for<lb/> want of an
                    interpreter well qualified for the<lb/> business we could not explain matters so
                    fully<lb/> as was desirable -- <lb/>
                    <pb n="18" facs="SW_HJ1800_018"/> We told them that some time ago they
                    had<lb/> made us a small present of some money which<lb/> we were not willing to
                    keep and had therefore<lb/> concluded to add as much to it of our money<lb/> as
                    would purchase them a Yoke of Oxen for<lb/> the use of that Town -- Several
                    matters were<lb/> spoken too by our company for their encourage<lb/> ment in a
                    sober industrious life, and <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName><lb/>
                    enquireing which way I intended to go home I told<lb/> him up the waters of this
                        <geogName key="alleg">River</geogName> and from thence<lb/> across to the
                        <geogName key="susqu">susquehannah</geogName> - he then concluded<lb/>
                    sending some of his people with me a part of the<lb/>
                    way and said he would come and see me set out on the<lb/> Journey --
                    Our interview lasted two or three hours<lb/> and ended to good satisfaction an
                    openness still<lb/> appearing among the Indians towards us as at<lb/> the
                    begining, and the way appear'd clearly open<lb/> in my View, to leave them,
                    feeling nothing but<lb/> love towards them as at the begining, and the<lb/>
                    reward of peace for my feeble endeavours to render<lb/> their lifes more
                    comfortable and happy --</p>
                <p> And notwithstanding their advancement in<lb/> the work of civilization was but
                    slow and no<lb/> very great progress as yet observable
                    there is sufficient<lb/> cause to hope the work is gradually advan-<lb/> cing,
                    that the Labour bestowd upon that <lb/>
                    <pb n="19" facs="SW_HJ1800_019"/> poor distressed people will not be lost but thro'<lb/> faithfulness in those called
                    thereunto be in<lb/> due time crown'd with a degree of the desired<lb/> success
                    at least so far as to leave them with-<lb/> out excuse, and perhaps be like
                    bread cast<lb/> upon the waters which may be gathered<lb/> after many days
                    --</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1800-06-17">17th</date><placeName key="genes1"/></dateline>
                <p> Being the day appointed for my leaveing<lb/> the Indian Countrey <persName
                        key="cornp2">Corn-planter</persName> came early in<lb/> the morning to take
                    leave of me and return'd<lb/> many thanks for my services amongst<lb/> them,
                    also desired me to remember him to<lb/> my people, and wish'd I might get
                    home<lb/> safe and find my people all well, and in<lb/>
                        particular<unclear>ly</unclear> desired me to tell the Chiefs of<lb/> the
                    Quakers that he was very thankful<lb/> for their kind endeavours to
                    instruct<lb/> them in a life of civilization and believ'd<lb/> the Great Spirit
                    above was well pleas-<lb/> ed with <del>them</del> it -- My intended route<lb/>
                    being up the <geogName key="alleg">Allegany River</geogName> and across<lb/> to
                    the waters of the <geogName key="susqu">Susquehannah</geogName>
                    <persName key="cornp2">Corn-<lb/> planter</persName> thought proper that
                    three<lb/> Indians should accompany a part of the<lb/> way One to take my
                    Creature by land<lb/> and two to take me in a Cannoe by water <lb/>
                    <pb n="20" facs="SW_HJ1800_020"/> about 60 miles up this <geogName
                        key="alleg">River</geogName> -- Most of<lb/> the men women and Children in our<lb/>
                    <placeName key="genes1">Village</placeName> came to see me set off and divers
                    of<lb/> them appeard very sorry saying it was hard<lb/> they should never see me
                    again -- All thing<unclear>s</unclear><lb/> being ready and my companion
                        <persName key="jswai1">Joel</persName> in-<lb/> tending to accompany me a
                    part of the<lb/> way about 8 Oclock We embark'd and<lb/> bid adieu to <placeName
                        key="genes1">Genesinguhta</placeName> where I had<lb/> spent two years &amp;
                    upwards very conten<lb/> ted and happy --</p>
                <p> As we past up the <geogName key="alleg">river</geogName> I call'd to bid<lb/>
                    the Indians of the upper Settlement<lb/> farewell who appear'd very friendly
                    and<lb/> some of them manifested their hearty<lb/> good will by furnishing us
                    with the<lb/> best provisions they could afford --<lb/> This day went up the
                        <geogName key="alleg">river</geogName> about 30 miles<lb/> encampt near the
                    mouth of a Creek<lb/> comeing in on the South side of the<lb/> River call'd
                        <geogName key="tunun">Teunewanguant</geogName> which<lb/> Cannoes can pass
                    up several miles<lb/> the evening being wet erected a bark<lb/> shed under which
                    we Lodg'd comfort<lb/> ably, &amp; the Indians haveing kill'd a<lb/> Deer in the
                        <geogName key="alleg">River</geogName> it afforded us plenty <lb/>
                    <pb n="21" facs="SW_HJ1800_021"/> of fresh venison which we
                    roasted at<lb/> the fire --</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1800-06-18">18th</date><placeName key="checkPlace"/>
                </dateline>
                <p> Set forward early, pass'd by some<lb/> fertile flats on the north side of the
                        <geogName key="alleg">River</geogName><lb/> on one of which is a large plumb
                    Orchard<lb/> near the head of the Indians reservation,<lb/> past the mouth of
                        <geogName key="chica">Chicaswanue</geogName>, &amp; <geogName key="ischu"
                            >Issue</geogName><lb/> about noon, the latter
                    of which is a boatable<lb/> stream for near forty miles and interlocks<lb/> with
                    the waters of the <geogName key="genes2">Genesee River</geogName> - at the<lb/>
                    mouth of this stream the Indians former<lb/> -ly lived -- Eight miles above
                        <geogName key="ischu">Issue</geogName> the <lb/>
                    <geogName key="osweg">Oswega</geogName> unites with the <geogName key="alleg"
                        >Allegany</geogName> comeing<lb/> in on the North Side which we passt
                    up<lb/> to <persName key="fking1">Francis Kings</persName> Settlement 6 miles
                    from<lb/> its mouth and 60 miles from <placeName key="genes1">Genesinguh<lb/>
                        ta</placeName> -- At this place a Town is laid out calld<lb/>
                    <placeName key="ceres">Ceres</placeName> and near it a place calld <placeName
                        key="leban">Lebanon</placeName>.<lb/> Several houses built, a sawmill
                    erected and<lb/> proposals made for building a Grist mill<lb/> this Summer --
                    The Land appears to be fertile<lb/> and (except some flats along the river
                    which<lb/> abound with White walnut Hickory &amp; Sugar<lb/> Maple) Generally
                    heavy timbered and hard<lb/> to Clear being Coverd with Hemlock white<lb/> pine,
                    Beech, &amp;c. At this place we Lodg'd <lb/>
                    <pb n="22" facs="SW_HJ1800_022"/> and a path being markt thro' the
                    wilderness<lb/> to <geogName key="pinec">pine creek</geogName> which emties into
                    the west Branch<lb/> of <geogName key="susqu">Susquehannah</geogName>
                    <persName key="fking1">Francis King</persName> propos'd send<lb/> ing a pilot
                    with me <del>thro the</del> as far as the<lb/> first settlement on <geogName
                        key="pinec">Pine Creek</geogName> --</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1800-06-19">19th</date><placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p> About eight Oclock tok Leave of my<lb/> companion <persName key="jswai1"
                        >Joel</persName> &amp; the Indians that were with<lb/> me, and proceeded on
                    thro' the wilderness nearly<lb/> an east and sometimes southeast
                    direction--<lb/> past up the waters of the <geogName key="osweg">Oswego
                        Creek</geogName> about<lb/> 15 miles, thence over two or three mountains<lb/> and encampt on one of the head waters of the<lb/>
                    <geogName key="alleg">Allegany River</geogName> where it was about large
                        enough<lb/> to turn a mill haveing come I supose
                    twenty<lb/> five miles the path generally pretty good, the Land<lb/> Clear of
                    Stone and of an exelent Quality abound<lb/> ing with Hemlock white paine Beech,
                    and<lb/> in some places wild Cherry and Sugar Maple.<lb/> The night being Clear
                    Lodg'd very comfort-<lb/> ably beside our fire with out any Covering --</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1800-06-20">20th</date><placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p> Set forward early and pass'd up a remark<lb/> able hollow or narrow vale for
                    about three<lb/> miles which appeard to be about 40 Rod wide<lb/> at the
                    entrance and terminated at a point<lb/> In very high Land running nearly
                    eastward<lb/> thence over the high ridge to the head <lb/>
                    <pb n="23" facs="SW_HJ1800_023"/> waters of <geogName key="pinec">pine
                        Creek</geogName> about 20 miles from our<lb/> lodgeing -- This ridge is
                    supposed to be the<lb/> highest Land in the state of Pensylvania, as<lb/> it divides the head waters of the
                        <geogName key="alleg">Allegany</geogName><lb/> which runs to the westward
                    from the head<lb/> waters of the <geogName key="tioga">Tioga</geogName> and
                    other waters of the<lb/>
                    <geogName key="susqu">Susquehannah</geogName> running eastward, and<lb/> the
                    head waters of the <geogName key="genes2">Genesee River</geogName> which<lb/>
                    runs north, from other waters of the<lb/>
                    <geogName key="susqu">Susquehannah</geogName> running Southward --<lb/> all
                    these streams haveing their sources<lb/> within a few miles of each other
                    --</p>
                <p> The land on this Ridge is of a superior<lb/> quality Clear of Stone and
                    favourable<lb/> for Cultivation abounding with much<lb/> Sugar Maple and wild
                    Cherry --</p>
                <p> On the East side is the head waters<lb/> of <geogName key="pinec">pine
                        Creek</geogName> which runs very swiftly<lb/> the Land Stony and path very
                    diffi<lb/> cult getting along in places, after going<lb/> down it about 3 miles
                    met with seve<lb/> ral hands cutting a road thro' the<lb/> woods towards the
                        <geogName key="alleg">Allegany River</geogName><lb/> who were moveing out
                    with their<lb/> Families to settle on the western<lb/> waters -- in a few miles
                    further we <lb/>
                    <pb n="24" facs="SW_HJ1800_024"/> come to their encampments where their<lb/>
                    wives were sitting with a number of<lb/> small children beside them, haveing
                    been<lb/> about a month on their Journey thus far<lb/> and I suppos'd it would
                    take them near<lb/> another month to get thro' to the Boat<lb/> able waters of
                    the <geogName key="alleg">Allegany</geogName> -- The men<lb/> cut the road: open
                    about 2 miles pr.<lb/> day, and every few days mov'd their encamp-<lb/> ments
                    their property being drawn on<lb/> sleds by Oxen -- The women were com<lb/>
                    plaining their provisions were nearly<lb/> exhausted &amp; I thought indeed they
                    had a<lb/> dull prospect before them, going into a<lb/> new Countrey where
                    little could be had<lb/> but what they could obtain by hunting.</p>
                <p> After traveling down this Rapid stream<lb/> 12 or 14 miles, some part of the
                    way<lb/> good Land and several smaller streams<lb/> emtying in furnishing
                    abundand opper<lb/> tunity for water works we came to the<lb/> Great <geogName
                        key="elkli">Elk lick</geogName> at which place I was<lb/> inform'd a white
                    man had killed &amp;<lb/> salted up 14 Barrels of Elk meat last<lb/> Fall -- It
                    appeard to be a small pond<lb/> about fifty or sixty yards in circumferance <lb/>
                    <pb n="25" facs="SW_HJ1800_025"/> and roads beat in every direction
                    from<lb/> it by the numurous herds of Elk and<lb/> deer that resort thither to
                    water - it is<lb/> said near thirty Elk have been seen<lb/> about it in one
                    drove, &amp; evident marks<lb/> appear that the Indians have formerly<lb/> made
                    it a memorable place -- To this<lb/> place Canoes can come up this stream<lb/>
                    being near 70 miles from where it<lb/> unites with the <geogName key="susqu"
                        >Susquehannah</geogName> --<lb/> past on about six miles further and<lb/>
                    met with a small cabbin, (one of the<lb/> before mentioned peoples
                    encampments)<lb/> where we lodg'd comfortably on our blankets<lb/> an exelent
                    flat being near afforded pasture<lb/> for our horses haveing traveled about 30
                    miles --</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1800-06-21">21st</date><placeName key="checkPlace"/>
                </dateline>
                <p> Set out early and rode down the <geogName key="pinec">Creek</geogName><lb/> 6
                    miles to the third fork Where stands the<lb/> first house being 60 miles from
                        <persName key="fking1">kings</persName> Settle<lb/> ment -- this was
                    formerly a noted place<lb/> by the Indians, calld the big Meadows -<lb/> some
                    exelent flats here abounding with<lb/> Hickory &amp; White Walnut --</p>
                <p> At this place lived one <persName key="jmill1">James Mills</persName>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="26" facs="SW_HJ1800_026"/> who had a large family, and one
                    Daughter<lb/> whose activity in hunting was nearly<lb/> equal to that of an
                    Indian, killing Elk<lb/> Deer, and Bears in great numbers --<lb/> Breakfasted
                    here and rode down the<lb/>
                    <geogName key="pinec">Creek</geogName> about 18 miles to the next<lb/>
                    Settlement - the way very difficult to get<lb/> along in many places - the
                        <geogName key="pinec">creek</geogName> on all<lb/> sides Bounded by high
                    towering mountains whose<lb/> craggy lofty tops
                    surpasseth all description -<lb/> In some places I suppos'd them to be 500
                    feet<lb/> high, cover'd with such stupendous piles<lb/> of Rocks as renderd all
                    approach inac-<lb/> cessible, and some of the tops projected over<lb/> so much
                    that the sun shineing in<lb/> the Front in the afternoon of the day<lb/> made a
                    shadow a considerable ways down<lb/> the Side -- On the summit of one of
                    these<lb/> Rocks I saw a large white animal sitting<lb/> which appeard to be of
                    the fowl kind --<lb/> what it was I could not tell, but the<lb/> wild romantic
                    prospect of the place<lb/> exceeded any thing of the kind I had ever<lb/> ever
                    before seen, and probably had never been<lb/> trodden by the foot of man --</p>

                <pb n="27" facs="SW_HJ1800_027"/>

                <p> This afternoon I saw two Elk Does in the<lb/>
                    <geogName key="pinec">Creek</geogName> with their young ones by their sides<lb/>
                    about Large as young Calves -- <del>Lodg</del><lb/> travel'd about 24 miles to
                    day, much of<lb/> the way in the water and over stone &amp;<lb/> Rocks without
                    number and Lodg'd in<lb/> a Whitemans Cabbin where the people were<lb/> very
                    kind, but the knots or small flies so<lb/> very numerous as to render it
                    impossible<lb/> resting comfortably. --</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1800-06-22">22nd</date><placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p> This day parted with my pilot and pro<lb/> ceeded on down the <geogName
                        key="pinec">Creek</geogName> to the mouth about<lb/> 38 miles -- The
                    mountains still continue<lb/> to bound the <geogName key="pinec"
                        >Creek</geogName> on each side but the<lb/> valleys more extensive than in
                    yesterdays<lb/> Journey, and Settlements made every few<lb/> miles, several
                    sawmills are also erected<lb/> where timber is saw'd and rafted down<lb/> the
                        <geogName key="susqu">Susquehannah</geogName> -- The inhabitants<lb/> appear
                    kind and glad to see travelers<lb/> chiefly depending on hunting for meat<lb/>
                    and many of them were about move<lb/> ing over to the <geogName key="alleg"
                        >Allegany</geogName> waters, saying <lb/>
                    <pb n="28" facs="SW_HJ1800_028"/> they were tir'd of this place and
                    determi<lb/> ned to move further back in the woods--<lb/> I concluded they were
                    as far back in the wood<lb/> already as I should like to settle, but there<lb/>
                    appears to be a Class of people advanc'd in<lb/> civilization but one degree
                    about Indians<lb/> that cannot live contented when the inha-<lb/> bitants crowds
                    in upon them -- the like<lb/> to be on the frontiers of the Countrey<lb/> their
                    children are brought up without<lb/> education &amp; indulg'd in the habits
                    of<lb/> Savage life, whereby their morals are<lb/> greatly corrupted, and often
                    prove pernitious<lb/> examples to the poor aborigines of the<lb/> Land -- Near
                    the mouth of <geogName key="pinec">pine Creek</geogName><lb/> in a body of
                    exelent Land some well cultiva<lb/> ted farms and Large fields of good Grain --<lb/>
                    <del>At</del> Lodg'd at Morrisons Tavern where I got<lb/> good entertainment
                    --</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1800-06-23">23rd</date><placeName key="muncy"/>
                </dateline>
                <p> In the morning cross'd the <geogName key="pinec">Creek</geogName> again<lb/>
                    where it was about 100 yards wide (after have<lb/> ing cross'd it I suppose more
                    than 50 times in<lb/> that many miles distance) and rode down<lb/> the west
                    Branch of the <geogName key="susqu">Susquehannah</geogName>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="29" facs="SW_HJ1800_029"/> to <placeName key="wport"
                        >Williamsport</placeName> where I din'd -- fine cultiva<lb/> ted farms along
                    the <geogName key="susqu">River</geogName> this stage and great<lb/> Crops of
                    Grain -- also a little village call'd<lb/>
                    <placeName key="newbe">Newberry</placeName> near <geogName key="lycom">Licoming
                        Creek</geogName> -- At <placeName key="wport">Williams<lb/> port</placeName>
                    the County Courts are held for <placeName key="lycco">Lycoming<lb/>
                        County</placeName> a prosperous little village in which<lb/> is five taverns
                    &amp; situate in a fertile Countrey.</p>
                <p> In the afternoon met with 15 Waggons Loaded<lb/> with families moveing from
                        <placeName key="bucks">Bucks county</placeName><lb/> out to <placeName
                        key="genes">Genesee</placeName> and <placeName key="niaga"
                        >Niagara</placeName> -- A number<lb/> of Women and Children were on foot
                    drive<lb/> ing herds of Cattle before them--</p>
                <p> About dark ariv'd at <placeName key="muncy">Muncy</placeName> and<lb/> Lodg'd at
                    our friend <persName key="welli1">Wm. Ellises</persName> a man<lb/> of Great
                    possessions and wonderful building<lb/> on his farm -- 30 miles to day
                    --</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1800-06-24">24th</date><placeName key="catta"/></dateline>
                <p> Set out about 10 Oclock and rode to<lb/>
                    <placeName key="catta">Catawessy</placeName> about 30 miles -- the most<lb/> of
                    the way a hilly Barren Countrey<lb/> coverd with pitch pine, yet the soil<lb/>
                    in places natural for Grain &amp; Grass<lb/> where settlements are made
                    --<lb/> about 10 miles from <placeName key="catta">Catawessy</placeName> I saw <lb/>
                    <pb n="30" facs="SW_HJ1800_030"/> the first Locusts which were there in
                    great<lb/> numbers -- Cross'd the ferry near the<lb/> mouth of <geogName
                        key="fishi">fishing Creek</geogName>, and rode into <placeName key="catta"
                        >Catawessy</placeName><lb/> about sunset a pleasant little village<lb/>
                    containing about 80 houses, &amp; lodg'd at<lb/>
                    <persName key="iwill1">Isaiah Willits</persName> Tavern --</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1800-06-25">25th</date><placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p> Set forward early and rode this<lb/> day about 40 miles to <persName
                        key="pensi1">Pensingers</persName> tavern -<lb/> The most of the way a
                    barren mountain<lb/> ous Countrey a few valleys excepted about<lb/> the head
                    waters of <geogName key="schri">Schuylkill River</geogName> -- plenty<lb/>
                    of Taverns on the Road to accommodate Travelers.<lb/> Lodgd at
                        <persName key="pensi1">Pensingers</persName> - the evening very wet --</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1800-06-26">26th</date><placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p> Rode 9 miles to <placeName key="carte">Carterstown</placeName> before
                    Break-<lb/> fast - a pleasant little village containing<lb/> 60 or 70 houses
                    mostly Dutch people - situ-<lb/> ated on the fertile Banks of the <geogName
                        key="schri">Schuylkill<lb/> River</geogName> - <gap/> in thence thro'
                        <placeName key="readi">Reading</placeName> and on<lb/> to <placeName
                        key="potts">Pottsgrove</placeName> in the evening where I had<lb/> the
                    consolation to meet with my beloved<lb/> Kinsman <persName key="jlind1">Jacob
                        Lindley</persName> and his wedding<lb/> Guests haveing that day taken to
                    wife<lb/> the worthy <persName key="rruth1">Ruth Anna Ruther</persName> a<lb/>
                    Citizen of that place -- on reflecting <lb/>
                    <pb n="31" facs="SW_HJ1800_031"/> on the great change that had taken
                    place<lb/> since my parting with him I was some<lb/> what affected, but meeting
                    with a number<lb/> of my friends and relations at this place<lb/> It was a feast
                    of no little satisfaction --<lb/> In two days more reached home being<lb/> the
                        <date when="1800-06-28">28th of the month</date>, after haveing been<lb/>
                    away two years and two months -- and<lb/> in my route home traveled about
                    390<lb/> miles --</p>
            </div></body>
        <back>
            <div type="narrative">
                <dateline>In the Summer of <date when="1805">1805</date></dateline>

                <pb n="32" facs="SW_HJ1800_032"/>

                <p> a number<lb/> of the principal Chiefs and warriers of the Six<lb/> Nations of
                    Indians principally <orgName key="seneca"
                        >Senecas</orgName> assem<lb/> bled at <placeName key="buffc">Buffalo
                        Creek</placeName> in the State of <placeName key="newyo">New
                        York</placeName><lb/> at the particular request of a Missionary from<lb/>
                    the State of <placeName key="massa">Massachusets</placeName> --</p>
                <p> The Missionary being furnished with an<lb/> Interpreter and accompanied by the
                    agent of<lb/> the United States for Indian affairs met the<lb/> Indians in
                    council when the following talk took<lb/> place, first by the Agent</p>
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body>
                        <p> Brothers of the Six Nations<lb/> I rejoice to meet you at this time and
                            thank<lb/> the Great Spirit that he hath preserved you<lb/> in health
                            and given me another oppertunity<lb/> of takeing you by the hand - -
                            -</p>
                        <p> Brothers the person who now sits by me<lb/> is a freind who has come a
                            great distance to hold<lb/> a talk with you, he will inform you what
                            his<lb/> Business is and it is my request that you should<lb/> listen
                            with attention to his words.</p>
                        <p> Missionary. . .<lb/> My friends I am thankful for the<lb/> oppertunity
                            afforded us in meeting together<lb/> at this time. I had a great desire
                            to see you<lb/> and enquire into your state and welfare <lb/>
                            <pb n="33" facs="SW_HJ1800_033"/> for this purpose I have
                            traveled a great distance<lb/> being sent by your old friends the
                                <orgName key="bosmiss">boston Missionary<lb/> Society</orgName>. You will
                            recollect they formerly sent<lb/> missionaries among you to instruct you
                            in<lb/> religeon and labour for your good. Although<lb/> they have not
                            heard from you for a long time<lb/> yet they have not forgoten their
                            brothers of<lb/> the Six Nations and are still anxious to do you<lb/>
                            good.</p>
                        <p> Brothers,<lb/> I have not come to get your<lb/> lands or your money but
                            to enlighten your<lb/> minds, and to instruct how to worship the<lb/>
                            Great Spirit agreably to his mind and will<lb/> and to preach to you the
                            Gospel of his son<lb/> Jesus Christ. There is but one religeon and<lb/>
                            one way to serve God and if you do not em<lb/> -brace the right way you
                            cannot be happy<lb/> hereafter, you have never worshiped the<lb/> Great
                            Spirit in a manner acceptable to<lb/> him, but have all your lives been
                            in Great<lb/> errors and darkness. To endeavour to remove<lb/> these
                            errors and open your eyes so that you<lb/> may see clearly is my
                            business among you.</p>
                        <p> Brothers<lb/> I wish to talk with you as one<lb/> friend talks with
                            another. and if you have<lb/> any objections to receive the religeon
                            which I<lb/> preach I wish you to state them and I will <lb/>
                            <pb n="34" facs="SW_HJ1800_034"/> endeavour to satisfy your minds
                            and<lb/> remove the objections.</p>
                        <p> Brothers<lb/> I want you to speak your
                            minds<lb/> freely for I wish to reason with you on the<lb/> subject and
                            if possible to remove all doubts<lb/> if there be any on your minds. The
                            subject<lb/> is an important one and it is of consequence<lb/> that you
                            give it an early attention while the<lb/> offer is made you. Your
                            friends the <orgName>Boston<lb/> Missionary Society</orgName> will
                            continue to send you<lb/> good and faithful ministers to instruct
                            and<lb/> strengthen you in religeon if on your part<lb/> you are willing
                            to receive them. --</p>
                        <p> Brothers<lb/> Since I have been in this part<lb/> of the Countrey I have
                            visited some of your<lb/> small Villages and talked with your
                            people,<lb/> they appear willing to receive instruction --<lb/> but as
                            the look up to you as their older brothers<lb/> in Council they want
                            first to know your opinion<lb/> on the subject. You have now heard what
                            I have<lb/> to propose at present I hope you will take<lb/> it into
                            consideration and give me an answer<lb/> before we part. --</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>

                <p> After about two hours consultation<lb/> among themselves the Chief commonly
                    cal-<lb/> led by the white people *<persName key="redja1">Red Jacket</persName>
                    arose &amp;<lb/> spoke as follows -- </p>
                <note resp="author" rend="asterix"> * His Indian name is <foreign xml:lang="iro"><persName key="redja1"
                        >Se,go,he,wautah</persName></foreign>, which <lb/> signifies keeper Arise. - -
                    -</note>



                <pb n="35" facs="SW_HJ1800_035"/>

                <floatingText type="speech" xml:id="redja1">
                    <body>
                        <p>
                            <del>Brother you say you want an<lb/> answer to your talk before you
                                leave this place<lb/> - it is wright you should have one as you
                                are<lb/> a great distance from home and we dont wish<lb/> to detain
                                you, but we will first look back a<lb/> little and tell you what our
                                Fathers have told<lb/> us and what we have heard from the white<lb/>
                                people --</del></p>
                        <p> Friend &amp; Brother<lb/> It was the will of the<lb/> Great Spirit that
                            we should meet together<lb/> this day - he orders all things and has
                            given us<lb/> a fine day for our council - He has taken<lb/> his Garment
                            from before the Sun and caused<lb/> it to shine <del>in</del>
                            with brightness upon us - Our eyes<lb/> are
                            open that we see clearly, our ears are<lb/> unstoped that we have been
                            able to hear<lb/> distinctly the words you have spoken, for<lb/> all
                            these favours we tahank the Great Spirit<lb/> and him only --</p>
                        <p> Brother<lb/> This Council fire was kindled<lb/> by you it was at your
                            request that we<lb/> came together at this time - we have listen'd<lb/>
                            with attention to what you have said - you<lb/> requested us to speak
                            our minds freely - This<lb/> gives us great joy for we now consider <lb/>
                            <pb n="36" facs="SW_HJ1800_036"/> that we stand upright before you
                            and<lb/> can speak what we think -- all have heard your<lb/> voice and
                            all speak to you now as one man, our<lb/> minds are agreed --</p>
                        <p> Brother<lb/> You say you wanted an answer<lb/> to your talk before you
                            leave this place - it is<lb/> right you should have one as you are
                            a<lb/> great distance from home and we dont<lb/> wish to detain you --
                            but we will first look<lb/> back a little and tell you what our
                            fathers<lb/> have told us, and what we have heard from<lb/> the white
                            people --</p>
                        <p> Brother listen to what we say,<lb/> There was<lb/> a time when our fore
                            fathers owned this Great<lb/> Island -- There seats extended from the
                            riseing to<lb/> the Setting sun - The Great Spirit had made<lb/> it for
                            the use of Indians - he had created the <lb/> Buffalo the Deer and other
                            Animals for food<lb/> he made the Bear and the Beaver, their skins<lb/>
                            served us for clotheing - he had scattered them<lb/> over the Countrey
                            and taught us how to take<lb/> them -- he had caused the earth to
                            produce<lb/> corn for bread. All this he had done for his<lb/> Red
                            children because he loved them - If we<lb/> had some disputes about
                            hunting ground<lb/> they were generally setled without the sheding<lb/>
                            of much blood - But an evil day came up
                            <lb/>
                            <pb n="37" facs="SW_HJ1800_037"/> upon us. Your forefathers crossed
                            the great<lb/> waters and landed on this Island -- Their num<lb/> bers
                            were small, they found friends and not<lb/> enemies -- They told us they
                            had fled from<lb/> their own Countrey for fear of wicked men<lb/> and
                            had come here to enjoy their religeon --</p>
                        <p> They asked for a small seat -- we took pity<lb/> on them granted their
                            request and they<lb/> sat down <del>beside</del>
                            amongst -- we gave them corn and<lb/> meat they
                            gave us pison (alludeing it is<lb/> suppered to ardent spirits) in
                            return.</p>
                        <p> The White people had now found our Countrey<lb/> Tideings were carried
                            Back and more came<lb/> amongst us, yet we did not fear them, we<lb/>
                            took them to be friends they called us Bro-<lb/> thers, we believed them
                            and gave them a<lb/> larger seat -- at length their numbers had<lb/>
                            greatly encreased - they wanted more land<lb/> they wanted our Countrey
                            - our eyes were<lb/> open'd and our minds <del>were</del>
                            became uneasy - Wars<lb/> took place - Indians
                            were hired to fight against<lb/> Indians -- and
                            many of our people were<lb/> destroy'd -- They also brought strong
                            liquors<lb/> amongst us -- it was strong and powerful<lb/> and has slain
                            thousands --</p>
                        <p> Brother<lb/> Our seats were once large and<lb/> yours were small - you
                            have now become<lb/> a great people - and we have scarcely a <lb/>
                            <pb n="38" facs="SW_HJ1800_038"/> place left to spread our blankets
                            - you<lb/> have got our countrey but are not satisfied<lb/> you want to
                            force your religeon upon us.</p>
                        <p> Brother Continue to listen<lb/> You say you are<lb/> sent to instruct us
                            how to worship the<lb/> great Spirit agreably to his mind, and if<lb/>
                            we dont take hold of the religeon which you<lb/> teach we shall be
                            unhappy hereafter -- You<lb/> say that you are right and we are lost --
                            how<lb/> do you know this to be true? - we understand<lb/> that your
                            religeon is written in a book. if<lb/> it was intended for us as well as
                            you -- why<lb/> has not the Great Spirit given to us, and<lb/>
                            not only to us -- but why did he not give to
                            our<lb/> forefathers the knowledge of that book with<lb/> the means of
                            understanding it rightly?<lb/> We only know what you tell us about
                            it.<lb/> How shall we know what to believe being<lb/> so often deceivd
                            by the white people --</p>
                        <p> Brother<lb/> You say there is but one way<lb/> to worship &amp; serve the Great Spirit -- if there<lb/> is
                            but one religeon why do you white<lb/> people differ so much about it?
                            Why not<lb/> all agree as you can all read the book. --</p>
                        <p> Brother<lb/> We do not understand these things <lb/>
                            <pb n="39" facs="SW_HJ1800_039"/> We are told that your religeon was
                            given<lb/> to your forefathers and has been handed<lb/> down from father
                            to son - we also have a<lb/> religeon which was given to our
                            forefathers<lb/> and has been handed down to us their children<lb/> we
                            worship in that way, it teaches us to<lb/> be thankful for all the
                            favours we receive<lb/> to love each other and to be unite, we
                            never<lb/> quarrel about religeon....</p>
                        <p> Brothers,<lb/> The Great Spirit has made us<lb/> all but he has made a
                            great difference --<lb/> between his white &amp; red children. He
                            has<lb/> given us different complexions and differ<lb/> -ent customes.
                            To you he has given the <lb/> ark, to these he has not open'd our
                            eyes<lb/> we know these things to be true. Since he<lb/> has made so
                            great a difference between<lb/> us in other things - why may we not
                            con<lb/> clude that he has given us a different<lb/> religeon --
                            according to our understand-<lb/> -ings. the great Spirit does right. He
                            knows<lb/> what is best for his children - we are satisfied.</p>
                        <p> Brother<lb/> we do not want to destroy you<lb/> religeon or to take it
                            from you we only <lb/>
                            <pb n="40" facs="SW_HJ1800_040"/> want to enjoy our own.</p>
                        <p> Brother we are told that you have<lb/> been preaching to the white
                            people in<lb/> this place - These people are our neighbours<lb/> we are
                            acquainted with them. we will wait<lb/> a little while and see what
                            effect your prea-<lb/> -ching has upon them - If we find it does
                            them<lb/> good - makes them honest and less dispos'd to<lb/> cheat
                            Indians we will then consider again<lb/> what you have said. --</p>
                        <p> Brother<lb/> You have now heard our answer<lb/> to your talk, and this
                            is all we have to<lb/> say at present as we are going to part<lb/> we
                            will come and take you by the hand<lb/> and hope the Great Spirit will
                            protect<lb/> you on your Journey and return you<lb/> safe to your
                            friends --</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
           
                <p> As the Indians began to approach the<lb/> missionary he arose hastily from his
                    seat<lb/> and replied that he would not take them<lb/> by the hand - that there
                    was no fellowship<lb/> between the religeon of God and the works<lb/> of the
                    Devil. This being interpreted to the<lb/> Indians they smild and retir'd in a
                    peac-<lb/> able manner --</p>

                <pb n="41" facs="SW_HJ1800_041"/>

            </div>
            <div type="speech"><dateline><date when="1811-05"/><placeName key="buffc"/></dateline>
                <p> The Speech of <persName key="redja1">Red Jacket</persName> a chief<lb/> of the
                        <orgName key="seneca">Seneca Nation</orgName> in
                    answer to a <lb/> Speech of one <persName key="richa2">Richardson</persName> who applied<lb/> to <del>the</del>
                    buy the Indians right to the reser-<lb/> -vations lying in the territory
                    commonly<lb/> called the Holland purchase delivered (at<lb/> a Council held at
                       Buffalo Creek in may<lb/> 1811 --</p>
                <p> Brother we opened our ears to the talk<lb/> you lately delivered to us at our
                    council<lb/> fire. In doing important business it is<lb/> Best not to tell long
                    stories but to come<lb/> to it in a few words. we therefore shall not<lb/>
                    repeat your talk which is fresh in <del>y</del>our minds<lb/> we have well
                    considered it, and the advantages<lb/> and disadvantages of your offers. we
                    request<lb/> your attention to our <del>offers</del> answer which is<lb/> not
                    from the speaker alone but from<lb/> all the Sachems and chiefs now round
                    our<lb/> Council fire --</p>
                <p> Brother We know that great men as well<lb/> as great Nations haveing different
                    interrest<lb/> have different minds, and do not see the same<lb/> subject in the
                    same light, but we hope our<lb/> answer will be agreable to you and your<lb/>
                    employers --</p>
                <p> Brother your application for the purchase<lb/> of our lands is to our minds very
                    extra-<lb/> -ordinary. It has been made in a crooked <lb/>
                    <pb n="42" facs="SW_HJ1800_042"/> manner -- You have not walked in the<lb/>
                    strait path pointed out by the great coun-<lb/> -cil of your nation -- you have
                    no writeing<lb/> from our Great father the President. In make-<lb/> -ing up our
                    minds we have looked back and re-<lb/> membered how the Yorkers purchased and
                    lands<lb/> in former times. They bought them piece after<lb/> piece for a little
                    money paid to a few men<lb/> in our nation and not to all our Brethren<lb/>
                    untill our planting &amp; hunting grounds have become
                    very<lb/> small - &amp; if we sell these we know not where to<lb/> spread our
                    blankets --</p>
                <p> Brother you tell us your employers have purchased<lb/> of the Council of Yorkers
                    a right to buy our lands<lb/> we do not understand how this can be the<lb/>
                    lands do not belong to the Yorkers they are<lb/> ours and were given to us by
                    the Great Spirit</p>
                <p> Brother, we think it strange that you should<lb/>
                    <unclear>Jump</unclear> over the lands of our brethren in the<lb/> east and came
                    to our council fire so far off<lb/> to get our lands. When we sold our lands
                    in<lb/> the East to the white people, we determined<lb/> never to sell those we
                    kept which are as small<lb/> as we can live comfortably on --</p>
                <p> Brother you want us to travel with you<lb/> and look for other lands. If we
                    should sell our<lb/> lands and move off into a distant countrey<lb/> towards the
                    Setting Sun, we should be look'd <lb/>
                    <pb n="43" facs="SW_HJ1800_043"/> upon in the Countrey to which we go
                    as<lb/> forreigners &amp; strangers and be despised by the<lb/> red as well as
                    the white <del>people</del> men and we<lb/> should soon be surrounded by the
                    white<lb/> people who will there also kill our game<lb/> come upon our lands and
                    try to get them<lb/> from us --</p>
                <p> Brother - We are determined not to sell our<lb/> lands but to continue on them.
                    They are<lb/> fruitfull and produce us corn in abundance<lb/> for the support of
                    our women and chil-<lb/> dren and grass and herbs for our Cattle --</p>
                <p> Brother At the Treaties held for the purchase of<lb/> our lands the white men
                    with sweet voices<lb/> and smileing <del>countenances</del> faces told us<lb/>
                    they loved us &amp; that they would not cheat<lb/> us -- but that the kings
                    children on the other<lb/> side of the Lake would cheat us. When we go on<lb/>
                    the other side of the Lake the kings children tell<lb/> us <del>they</del> your
                    people will cheat us best with<lb/> sweet voices and smileing faces assure us of
                    their<lb/> love; and that they will not cheat us. These<lb/> things puzzle our
                    heads and we believe that<lb/> they Indians must take care of themselves<lb/>
                    and trust either in your people or in the<lb/> Kings children --</p>
                <p> Brother At a late Council we requested<lb/> our Agents to tell you that we would
                    not sell<lb/> our lands and we think you have not spoken <lb/>
                    <pb n="44" facs="SW_HJ1800_044"/> to our Agents since <gap/> they would
                    have told<lb/> you so, and we should not have met you at our<lb/> Council fire
                    at this time.</p>
                <p> Brother they white people buy and sell false<lb/> rights to our Lands and your
                    employers you say<lb/> have paid a great price for their right - They must<lb/>
                    have plenty of money to spend it in buying and<lb/> selling false wrights to
                    lands belonging to Indians<lb/> They loss of it will not hurt them but our<lb/>
                    lands are of great value to us and we wish<lb/> you to go back to your employers
                    and to tell them<lb/> and the Yorkers that they have no right to<lb/> buy and
                    sell false wrights to our lands <del>belonging to</del><lb/>
                    <del>Indians --</del></p>
                <p> Brother this is all we got to say.</p>


            </div>
            </back>


    </text>
</TEI>
