<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei-print.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" hkey="global.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>Halliday Jackson's Book [of Corrrespondence], Genesinguhta, 1798-1800:
                    Electronic Version</title>
                <author>Halliday Jackson</author>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by </resp>
                    <name>Cara Ehlenfeldt</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcribed by </resp>
                    <name>Keat Murray</name>
                    <name>Tiffany Lee</name>
                    <name>Youda Cao</name>
                    <name>Brent Stanfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 102 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>This work is the property of the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore
                        College. It may be copied freely by individuals for personal use, research,
                        and teaching (including distribution to classes) as long as this statement
                        of availability is included in the text. It may be linked to freely in
                        Internet editions of all kinds, including for—profit works.</p>
                    <p>Publishers, libraries, and other information providers interested in
                        providing this text in a commercial or non—profit product or from an
                        information server must contact Swarthmore College for licensing and cost
                        information.</p>
                    <p> Scholars interested in changing or adding to these texts by, for example,
                        creating a new edition of the text (electronically or in print) with
                        substantive editorial changes, may do so with the permission of Swarthmore
                        College. This is the case whether the new publication will be made available
                        at a cost or free of charge.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2014">2014</date>
                <idno type="local">SW_HJ1798</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Native Americans and Quakers: Electronic
                    Collection</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>Jackson Family Papers</collection>
                        <idno>RG5/182</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>1 volume</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>


        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The manuscript of Halliday Jackson’s <emph>Genesinguhta</emph> is housed at
                    Friends Historical Library, on the campus of Swarthmore College. In the fall
                    semester of 2010, Swarthmore students enrolled in English 50A (“Reading Red,
                    White, and In-Between in Early American Literature”) transcribed Jackson’s
                    manuscript as part of a larger project to make the library’s rich store of
                    Quaker Indian mission writings more accessible to researchers. The project was
                    designed by Christopher Densmore, curator of Friends Historical Library, and
                    Keat Murray, Visiting Assistant Professor of English. Transcribers included:
                    Professor Murray (Title -3), Tiffany Lee (4-26), Youda Cao (27-55), and Brent
                    Stanfield (56-61). Students’ transcriptions were compiled and edited in the
                    present form by Professor Murray. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> Jackson does not include page numbers on his manuscript; the page numbers have
                    been interpolated by the transcribers to correspond with the manuscript sheets.
                    In this case, the title page is counted as the first page.</p>

                <p> The transcribers and editor attempted to render Halliday Jackson’s orthography
                    and grammar as they appear on the page of his journal, even when Jackson’s own
                    spelling and usage are inconsistent. Additionally, some questions remain about
                    spelling the names of Jackson’s Quaker acquaintances, individual Native
                    Americans who populate his journal, and Indian villages and towns. The
                    transcribers and editor attempted to remain faithful to Jackson’s Anglicized
                    spellings in all cases. </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written in <date when="1824">1824</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Alleghany River Valley (Pa. and N.Y.)—History</item>
                        <item>Church and state--Ohio</item>
                        <item>Cornplanter, Seneca chief, 1732?-1836</item>
                        <item>Indian reservations</item>
                        <item>Indians of North America--Missions</item>
                        <item>New York (State)--Description and travel</item>
                        <item>Pennsylvania--Description and travel</item>

                        <item>Philadelphia Yearly Meeting of the Religious Society of Friends</item>

                        <item>Quakers--Political activity</item>
                        <item>Seneca Indians</item>
                        <item>Society of Friends--Missions</item>
                        <item>Voyages and Travels</item>


                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change><date/></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
        <pb n="1" facs="SW_HJ1798_001"/>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle>
                    <pb n="2" facs="SW_HJ1798_002"/>
                    <titlePart>Halliday Jackson’s<lb/>Book 1799<lb/>
                        <lb/>Genesinguhta</titlePart>
                    <pb n="3" facs="SW_HJ1798_003"/>
                    <titlePart>Correspondence<lb/>Between the Committee<lb/> on Indian affairs
                        at<lb/>Philadelphia and<lb/>the Friends residing amongst<lb/>the Seneca
                        Nation of Indians<lb/>settled on the Allegheny <lb/> River</titlePart>
                </docTitle>

            </titlePage>


        </front>

        <body>

            <div type="letter">
                <pb n="4" facs="SW_HJ1798_004"/>
                <opener><title>First Letter to the Committee<lb/> on Indian affairs--</title>
                    <salute>Dear Friends</salute></opener>
                <p> Under the protection of<lb/> a Merciful Creator we are favored to enjoy<lb/> a
                    good state of health, and we do know that<lb/> many of you have sympathizing
                    Hearts<lb/> with us, and very tender feelings for the good<lb/> of those People
                    we are placed amongst; there<lb/>fore we feel duty bound to write to you at<lb/>
                    every convenient opportunity, letting you<lb/> know how the business we are
                    entrusted with is<lb/> going on amongst us. </p>
                <p> The Indians continue to treat us with<lb/> great civility and respect, and we
                    believe there<lb/> is no cause of discouragement in the present<lb/> undertaking
                    amongst them; though we cannot<lb/> expect a great deal done by them at
                    Farming<lb/> until they are better supplied with<lb/> working Creatures— <lb/>
                    <pb n="5" facs="SW_HJ1798_005"/> We have assisted them in building several
                    houses and<lb/> have made a considerable progress in Farming on our<lb/> own Lot
                    for what time we have been on it; our<lb/> Corn, Potatoes Garden etc. affords a
                    beautiful<lb/> aspect, and we intend to sow some Wheat and Rye<lb/> this Fall if
                    we can procure Seed, which can-<lb/>not be obtained nearer than <placeName
                        key="frank">Franklin</placeName> and <placeName key="pitts"
                        >Pitts-<lb/>burgh</placeName> that we know of— We are also<lb/> about
                    preparing to build ourselves a com-<lb/>fortable house before Winter sets in</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute> We are your affectionate Friends</salute>
                    <dateline><placeName key="genes1">Genesinguhta</placeName><lb/>
                        <date when="1798-07-29">7th mo 29th 1798</date></dateline>
                    <signed><list>
                            <item><persName key="hsimm1">Henry Simmons</persName></item>
                            <item><persName key="jswai1">Joel Swayne</persName></item>
                            
                            <item>&amp; <persName key="hjack1">Halliday Jackson</persName></item>
                        </list></signed></closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>NB We have received no accounts from Philadel-<lb/>phia or parts Adjacent
                        since we left them</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>


            <div type="letter">
                <pb n="6" facs="SW_HJ1798_006"/>
                <note resp="author"><date when="1799-10-24">24 of 10th mo.</date> We received the
                    following of<lb/>
                    <persName key="twist1">Thomas Wistar</persName> who was appointed to answer
                    our<lb/> Letters on behalf of the Committee when nothing<lb/> of importance
                    required their Uniting therein--</note>
                <opener>
                    <salute>Dear Friends,</salute></opener>
                <p> At a meeting of the Indian<lb/> Committee held last month, your joint
                    Letter<lb/> was read the contents whereof was very satisfactory<lb/> to such of
                    the Members as were present, who<lb/> were few in number owing to a renewed
                    dispensation of sickness<lb/> and Mortality which has been permitted<lb/> again
                    to visit poor <placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName>, and which<lb/>
                    though most prevalent in the Northern &amp;<lb/> Southern extremities of the
                    City has spread<lb/> pretty generally thro' it, and driven the<lb/> Greater part
                    of the inhabitants from their<lb/> Homes; and by the latest accounts I have<lb/>
                    received of those that remain, from fifty<lb/> to sixty are daily removed from
                    this muta<lb/>ble state—</p>
                <p> I (with my family) have been removed <lb/>
                    <pb n="7" facs="SW_HJ1798_007"/> to this place about two weeks during which
                    time<lb/> I have not had an opportunity of receiving any<lb/> letters that may
                    have been directed to me at<lb/>
                    <placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName>, and from not having my
                    papers<lb/> with me have it not in my power to refer to<lb/> the dates of your
                    Letters, but if my recollection<lb/> is correct have received but one from you
                    Joint<lb/>-ly, and one from <persName key="hjack1">H. Jackson</persName> (the
                    latter of which<lb/> it is my wish to answer shortly)—</p>
                <p> Dear friends, in the exiled, humiliated Situation<lb/> in which I at present am,
                    do not feel myself<lb/> capable of saying much more to you, than<lb/> that I
                    continue to hope the dedication you<lb/> have manifested in the cause of
                    humanity<lb/> and good will to man, may, as you continue<lb/> properly under the
                    exercise, yield you the unde-<lb/>scribable reward of peace in your own
                    bosoms<lb/> &amp; that during the trying seperation you<lb/> experience from the
                    Bosom of Society, you may<lb/> be favored to feel the support of the
                    everlasting<lb/> arms-- </p>
                <closer><salute>I am affect<supplied>ionately</supplied> Your fr</salute>
                    <signed><persName key="twist1">Thomas Wistar</persName></signed>
                    <dateline><placeName key="monmo">Monmouth </placeName> New Jersey <lb/><date
                            when="1799-09-08">9 mo 8 1799</date></dateline><lb/>
                    <salute>To <persName key="hjack1">H.J.</persName>
                        <persName key="jswai1">J.S.</persName>
                        <persName key="hsimm1">H Simmons</persName></salute>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <pb n="8" facs="SW_HJ1798_008"/>
                <opener>
                    <title>2nd Letter to the Committee</title>
                    <dateline><date when="1798-11-16">11th mo. 16th
                        1798</date></dateline><title><lb/> Wrote by my companions when I was on a
                        Journey.</title>
                    <salute><lb/> Dear Friends</salute>
                </opener>

                <p>Since we wrote to you we received<lb/> a letter from <persName key="twist1"
                        >Thomas Wistar</persName> which gave us an<lb/> account that the Yellow
                    Fever had again been<lb/> permitted to visit the City of <placeName key="phila"
                        >Philadelphia</placeName>,<lb/> no doubt but it has been a very distressing
                    time<lb/> to many--We have been employed the<lb/> latter part of this Season in
                    building a comfortable two<lb/> story log house 18 by 22 feet, covered with<lb/>
                    Pine Shingles, Sellar’d underneath, and the<lb/> Chimney composed of Stone and
                    Clay--<lb/>We have erected a good stable large enough<lb/> to accommodate our
                    Horses and a Cow, also<lb/> assisted several of the Indians in building<lb/>
                    etc. We have lately bought a dry Cow of one<lb/> of the Indians who was desirous
                    of parting<lb/> with her, in hopes that she will supply us<lb/> with Milk next
                    Summer--</p>
                <p> We expect shortly to commence a School <lb/>
                    <pb n="9" facs="SW_HJ1798_009"/> at <placeName key="cones"
                        >Conescotago</placeName> as the children are generally at that<lb/>
                    place--</p>
                <closer><salute>We are at present in a reasonable state of<lb/> health and remain
                        your loving Friends</salute>
                    <signed><persName key="hsimm1">Henry Simmons</persName> &amp; <persName
                            key="jswai1">Joel Swayne</persName>
                        <lb/>&amp;</signed></closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p><persName key="hjack1">Halliday Jackson</persName> being Absent on a
                        Journey<lb/> to <placeName key="catta1">Cattaraugus </placeName> with a
                        young man who met<lb/> with an accident which disabled him from<lb/> Walking
                        and not returning so soon as we<lb/> expected, and an Indian now waiting to
                        take<lb/> the letter to <placeName key="ffran">fort franklin </placeName> we
                        think it<lb/> expedient to send it without his Name </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>

            <div type="letter">

                <opener>
                    <title>3rd Letter to the Committee</title>
                    <dateline><date when="1799-01-23">1st mo. 23rd 1799</date></dateline><lb/>
                    <salute> Dear Friends,</salute>
                </opener>

                <p> We have written two letters to you<lb/> since our settling here the last of
                    which was dated<lb/>
                    <date when="1798-11-16">16 of 11 mo 98</date>, and altho’ we have received
                    no<lb/> answer from you in a Collective capacity we<lb/> doubt not but many of
                    you sympathize with<lb/> us, and we are often mercifully favored to feel
                    the<lb/> help of your Spirits cooperating and strength- <lb/>
                    <pb n="10" facs="SW_HJ1798_010"/> -ening us in our present engagement—<lb/>We
                    expect there are letters from you delayed at<lb/>
                    <placeName key="pitts">Pittsburgh </placeName> or <placeName key="frank"
                        >Franklin</placeName> for want of opportunities<lb/> of forwarding them to
                    us, which is very rare<lb/> at this Season of the Year otherwise we would
                    write<lb/> oftener to you than we do </p>
                <p> We received a plentiful increase of the most<lb/> of our Summer produce, and
                    also prepared ground<lb/> to sow several bushels of Winter Grain, but the<lb/>
                    River being so low we got disappointed in getting<lb/> Seed, altho’ we wrote to
                        <placeName key="pitts">Pittsburgh</placeName> for it soon<lb/> after Harvest
                    and our Agents there forwarded<lb/> it to <placeName key="frank"
                        >Franklin</placeName> for us—We expect it to<lb/> come forward in the Spring
                    and do to sow<lb/> another year—Several of the Young Indians<lb/> manifest some
                    inclination to take up work, and<lb/> last fall we had one employ'd a while at
                    our<lb/> business—We have kept up a School at<lb/>
                    <placeName key="conis">Conishadaga</placeName> this Winter in one of the
                    Indians<lb/> Houses where from 12 to 25 Children have attended<lb/> who appear
                    to make as much progress in learn-<lb/>ing-<lb/>
                    <pb n="11" facs="SW_HJ1798_011"/> as can reasonably be expected: and we have
                    had<lb/> in contemplation the propriety of erecting a<lb/> School house at that
                    place the ensuing Summer<lb/> as the Children are principally there, we
                    think<lb/> it will be of the most general utility, which<lb/> we submit to
                    You—The most of the<lb/> Cloth, Linen, etc. which You sent with us, we<lb/> have
                    exchang'd for Meat, Boards, and other<lb/> Necessaries we stood in need of, and
                    a little of<lb/> it we sold for money to accommodate they<lb/> Indians at a
                    price to reimburse the accruing expen<lb/>ses of bringing it here— </p>
                <p> We think it will be necessary for us to be furnish'd<lb/> with a Yoke of Oxen to
                    go on with Farming the<lb/> ensuing Summer, as one of our horses is a<lb/>
                    little lame and the ground very hard to break<lb/> up and we wish to be able to
                    assist they Indians<lb/> a little at Farming—We sent you word in<lb/> our last
                    letter that we had purchased a dry Cow<lb/> which we since find is not likely to
                    supply us with<lb/> Milk, and if a Yoke of Oxen is sent it would be<lb/>
                    <pb n="12" facs="SW_HJ1798_012"/> a great accommodation to us if a good
                    Milk<lb/> Cow was sent with them, and the one we have at<lb/> present will do
                    for Beef next Fall</p>
                <p> We also think it may tend to the promotion<lb/> of the work and believe it
                    expedient to Submit<lb/> to you the consideration of sending us the<lb/>
                    following articles as early as practicable next<lb/> Spring to Wit </p>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item> A Set of Smith Tools</item>
                        <item>1 Bar of Iron 1 do steel</item>
                        <item>1 faggot of Nail rods</item>
                        <item> 1 pair of Cart Wheels</item>
                        <item>1 Doz. Sythes made Short &amp; Strong</item>
                        <item>3 or 4 Sickels</item>
                        <item>6 Sets of Sythe Hangings</item>
                        <item>6 long Drawing knives</item>
                        <item>2 Broad Axes</item>
                        <item>2 Firmer Gouges [illegible abbreviations]</item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item>2 Mill Picks to make Grindstone</item>
                        <item>1 piece of Strong Cloth</item>
                        <item>1 do of Ticklenburgh <gap/> or strong linen</item>
                        <item>1 do of Blanketing</item>

                        <item>a few dozens of pocketknives</item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item>a few do of coarse and fine Combs</item>
                        <item>Some coarse Needles &amp; thread</item>
                        <item>1 Peck of Flax seed</item>
                        <item>1 do of Timothy seed</item>
                        <item> ½ do Clover Seed</item>
                        <item>2 Doz. Spelling Books</item>
                        <item>3 or 4 do. Trimmers</item>
                        <item>6 Testaments 6 Slates &amp; Pencils</item>
                        <item>1 or 2 School Masters assistants</item>
                        <item> Some writing papers &amp; Quills</item>
                        <item>2 Bushels of Salt</item>
                        <item>3 Barrels of Flower</item>
                        <item>Some Chocolate</item>


                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb n="13" facs="SW_HJ1798_013"/>
                <p>We may also inform you we are hard set<lb/> to keep enough of the falling axes at
                    home for<lb/> our own use if a few more was sent the would<lb/> be acceptable
                    The Cattle and some of these<lb/> articles we expect by your order may be
                    procured<lb/> at <placeName key="pitts">Pittsburgh</placeName> and altho’ some
                    of them may not<lb/> be immediately wanted here we think it will<lb/> be the
                    best economy to send them altogether<lb/> as it is difficult and expensive
                    getting things<lb/> conveyed to us—The Sythes that were sent last<lb/> Spring
                    were not suitable for the purpose, and<lb/> the drawing knives were too short
                    and Slim </p>
                <p> If a Smith or other well qualified Person<lb/> should offer we hope He will be
                    encourage<lb/>ed to come forward, as there is a probability<lb/> of one of us
                    being profitably stationed at<lb/> the lower Village, to superintend the
                    School<lb/> and other wise endeavor to promote the<lb/> desirable work of
                    Civilization—and <persName key="hsimm1">Henry<lb/> Simmons</persName> now
                    expressing a prospect of being<lb/> releas'd from this place the latter end of
                    next <lb/>
                    <pb n="14" facs="SW_HJ1798_014"/> Summer we hope this Subject will be
                    weightily<lb/> impressed on your minds, all which we Submit<lb/> to your Solid
                    deliberation—</p>
                <closer> We are well and are your affectionate<lb/> Friends—Signed &amp;c. </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <note>2nd from <persName key="twist1">Thomas Wistar</persName> received the <date
                        when="1799-02-01">1st of 2nd mo 99</date></note>
                <opener>
                    <dateline><placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName>
                        <date when="1798-11-19">11th mo 19-98</date></dateline>
                    <salute> Dear Friends </salute></opener>

                <p> I wrote to you (I think) some<lb/> time in the last month from
                        <placeName>Monmouth<lb/> County, New Jersey</placeName> to which place I had
                    remo-<lb/>ved with my Family on account of the aw<lb/>ful visitation of Sickness
                    under which many<lb/> of the inhabitants of this City were then labor<lb/>ing,
                    and which continued until about the<lb/> 5th of this month when it pleased
                    the<lb/> great disposer of events to cause a dispensation<lb/> of more general
                    health—In the course of<lb/> about three months, near three thousand<lb/> five
                    hundred of my fellow Citizens have been<lb/>
                    <pb n="15" facs="SW_HJ1798_015"/> removed from this Earthly Scene in the
                    City—<lb/>and many have ended their lives in the neigh-<lb/>boring country: But
                    it is not <placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName><lb/> alone that has to
                    mourn her slain, several parts<lb/> of the country adjacent lossed some of
                    their<lb/> most valuable Members—About thirteen<lb/> of the friends who came to
                    the City at the<lb/> usual time of holding the Yearly Meeting were<lb/> by this
                    Disease removed (amongst whom<lb/> were <persName key="wmiff1">Warner
                        Mifflin</persName> &amp; <persName key="jemle1">James Emlen</persName> two
                    mem<lb/>bers of our Committee, <persName key="jsloa1">Joseph Slone</persName>
                    another<lb/> member died some time before whether of<lb/> the prevailing disease
                    I know not) </p>
                <p> The neighboring Villages particularly those<lb/> on the <geogName key="delaw"
                        >Delaware</geogName> were Deep snares in this great<lb/> affliction, of
                    these perhaps <placeName key="chest1">Chester</placeName> and <placeName
                        key="wilmi">Wilming<lb/>ton</placeName> were most Conspicuous, as in the
                    first<lb/> thirty-seven Persons are said to have died, and<lb/> of the remainder
                    of the inhabitants it is<lb/> also said but five families staid in their
                    Ha-<lb/>bitations, the others seeking safety in flight<lb/> which also was
                    generally the case in <placeName key="wilmi">Wilmington</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="16" facs="SW_HJ1798_016"/> where the mortality was such that three
                    Sisters<lb/> were seen carried at one time in one Cart to their<lb/> Graves—The
                        <placeName key="nycit">City of New York</placeName> was visited at<lb/> the
                    same time in a similar manner tho’ not<lb/> I believe to so great a degree </p>
                <p> Things being thus afflictingly circumstances<lb/> amongst us, there was no
                    meeting of the <orgName key="pymind">Committee<lb/> on Indian Affairs</orgName>
                    from the <date when="1798-08-18">18th of the 8th mo</date><lb/> untill the 17th
                    of this, when a number of us<lb/> being in unmerritted mercy favourd with
                    ability<lb/> to attend at the usual time &amp; Place, a meeting<lb/> was held,
                    and we should have been pleased<lb/> to have heard from you which has been the
                    case<lb/> but once in an official way since <persName key="jshar1">Joshua
                        Sharples</persName><lb/> &amp; <persName key="jpier1">John Pierce</persName>
                    left You; for notwithstanding<lb/> our minds have been exercised with the
                    awful<lb/> Scenes about us, yet I believe you have often<lb/> been brought into
                    remembrance, &amp; to have<lb/> have heard at the last meeting of your
                    welfare<lb/> etc. would have afforded satisfaction to all then<lb/> present-</p>
                <p> The desire I feel that you should from time to time <lb/>
                    <pb n="17" facs="SW_HJ1798_017"/> be informed that you live in the
                    remembrance<lb/> of your friends here, more than any qualificati-<lb/>on at
                    present experienced for writing, is the<lb/> cause of my addressing you at this
                    time—for tho’ it<lb/> might be possible for my head to dictate &amp; my<lb/>
                    hand to write something that should sound<lb/> agreeable, yet without a
                    correspondent feeling<lb/> of the heart, it would be alas! but as sounding<lb/>
                    Brass— </p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>In sincere love in which I<lb/> am joined by my wife I am
                        affectionatly<lb/> your friend,</salute>
                    <signed><persName key="twist1">Thomas Wistar</persName></signed> -- To <persName
                        key="jswai1">Joel Swayne</persName>
                    <persName key="hjack1">Halliday Jackson</persName> &amp; <persName key="hsimm1"
                        >Henry Simmons</persName>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">

                <opener><title> Fourth Letter to the Committee </title>
                    <dateline><placeName key="genes1">Genesinguhta</placeName><date
                            when="1799-03-24">3rd mo. 24th 1799</date></dateline><lb/>
                    <salute>Dear Friends,</salute></opener>
                <p>Our last letter to you was dated<lb/> the <date when="1799-03-02">23rd of the 3rd
                        month</date> last but was delay'd here<lb/> some time before we could get it
                    forwarded to<lb/>
                    <placeName key="frank">Franklin</placeName>, since which we received a letter from<lb/>
                    <persName key="twist1">Thomas Wistar</persName> dated the <date
                        when="1798-11-19">19th of 11th mo. 98</date><lb/> and were thankful to find
                    that the late <lb/>
                    <pb n="18" facs="SW_HJ1798_018"/> afflicting dispensation of sickness in
                    your parts<lb/> was in a great measure abated and that you<lb/> were again
                    permitted to meet in your usual<lb/> manner, and altho’ it affected us much
                    that<lb/> so many of our worthy Friends laid down<lb/> their lives in the
                    calamaty, it affords us<lb/> consolation to find that we still live in the
                    rem-<lb/>embrance of some of the survivors, altho’ the<lb/> intercourse between
                    you and us is not so fre-<lb/>quent as we could desire</p>
                <p> Our School at <placeName key="conis">Conishadaga</placeName> grows larger<lb/>
                    and the progress in the Children’s Learning<lb/> affords an encouraging
                    prospect—several<lb/> Grown persons have also evinced some incli<lb/>nation to
                    be instructed, and paid some attention<lb/> thereto—The Indians have made
                    proposals<lb/> of assisting us in building a schoolhouse at<lb/> that place, and
                    as our present accommo<lb/>dations there are but indifferent we think<lb/> it
                    necessary to carry the work into effect<lb/> pretty early this Spring—Numbers
                    of<lb/> them propose building more comfortable<lb/>
                    <pb n="19" facs="SW_HJ1798_019"/> Dwellings for themselves the ensuing
                    Summer<lb/> &amp; request our assistance and instruction therein,<lb/> and we
                    are not without a hope that some of them<lb/> will take up farming also, altho’
                    the want of Do-<lb/>mestic animals is a great impediment in<lb/> their way—</p>
                <p> Five of us have been mostly employ'd in<lb/> Mechanical Business at our
                    Settlement the<lb/> late Winter have prepared Plows and other<lb/> necessary
                    implements of Husbandry, and also<lb/> made a good deal of Cooper ware and
                    other<lb/> Articles which we exchange with they Indians<lb/> for Sugar and other
                    house necessaries—</p>
                <p> We have lately had some serious considera<lb/>tions about taking an Indian Lad
                    as we<lb/> think it may tend to the promotion of<lb/> the work &amp; that he may
                    be useful to us, but<lb/> are willing to submit the matter to you—</p>
                <p> We are also united in Judgement, that<lb/> if a well-qualified family should
                    offer they<lb/> may be encouraged to come forward this <lb/>
                    <pb n="20" facs="SW_HJ1798_020"/> Spring in order to make a more
                    permanent<lb/> settlement at this place, as there is a probabili<lb/>ty of our
                    business being a good deal scattered,<lb/> and suitable accommodations will be
                    pro<lb/>vided for this reception—</p>
                <p> Having lately wrote pretty largely to<lb/> you we have little to "alleghany"
                    only that we<lb/> continue to enjoy our health, and that<lb/> you are often
                    feelingly brought into our<lb/> remembrance—</p>
                <closer> We remain your affectionate Friends <signed><list>
                            <item><persName key="hsimm1">H.S.</persName></item>
                            <item><persName key="jswai1">J.S.</persName></item>
                            <item>&amp; <persName key="hjack1">H.J</persName></item>
                        </list></signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <note resp="author">The following Letter we received from the<lb/>
                    <orgName key="seneca">Indians</orgName> of <placeName key="catta1">Cataraugus
                        Village</placeName></note>
                <opener>
                    <dateline><placeName key="catta1"> Cataraugus</placeName>
                        <date when="1799-04-11">April the 11th</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>To the Allegeny Quakers -- </salute></opener>
                <p>This day we have met with our<lb/> Brothers as opportunity to write a few
                    lines,<lb/> we return thanks to our Maker for our op-<lb/>portunity to proceed,
                    our business is to <lb/>
                    <pb n="21" facs="SW_HJ1798_021"/> desire our Friends to take it in
                    consideration, we<lb/> desire to get the knowledge of Farming from our<lb/>
                    Friends, as one god made us both, we have advanced<lb/> ourselves but still
                    think fit to embrace opportu<lb/>-nity offer'd us by our Friends if we have
                    any<lb/> Gift, that we may have our eyes opened—<lb/>We first lay our matter
                    before you our friends<lb/> as you have come forward and offer'd to assist<lb/>
                    in our undertakings, as their is 381 Souls<lb/> in this Village that have agreed
                    to receive<lb/> instructions from you, in all the various<lb/> Branches of
                    learning, letters, pen and till-<lb/>ing the Field, as we have seen Great
                    bene<lb/>fit by <persName key="cornp2">Captain Obeals</persName> learning, we
                    desire<lb/> to be instructed in the same Rules—</p>
                <p> Brothers if you will take into consideration<lb/> to Favor us according to our
                    desire, and<lb/> send such men as you think fit to instruct<lb/> us, they shall
                    have houses and Lands<lb/> to make themselves comfortable and shall<lb/> not be
                    molested by friend, nor foe—but<lb/> be protected according to the best of our
                    abilities. </p>
                <pb n="22" facs="SW_HJ1798_022"/>
                <p> And Brothers, if you conclude to assist us<lb/> in this time of need and
                    necessity we<lb/> desire you would help us to a set of saw<lb/> mill Irons—</p>
                <closer><salute>An we are your friends,</salute><signed>
                        <list>
                            <item><foreign xml:lang="iro"><persName key="saosn1">Sa os non
                                        da</persName></foreign></item>

                            <item><foreign xml:lang="iro"><persName key="wontw1"
                                        >Won,two,guh,ta</persName></foreign></item>
                            <item><foreign xml:lang="iro"><persName key="tiann"
                                    >Ti,an,na</persName></foreign></item>
                            <item><foreign xml:lang="iro"><persName key="senah1">Se nahc to
                                        gura</persName></foreign></item>

                            <item><foreign xml:lang="iro"><persName key="gooty"
                                        >Goo,ty,gont</persName></foreign></item>
                        </list>
                    </signed>In this year of our Lord 1799</closer>

            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <opener><title>Fifth letter to the Committee</title>
                    <dateline><date when="1799-04-21">4th mo. 21st 99</date></dateline>
                    <salute> Dear Friends,</salute></opener>
                <p>The occasion of our writing<lb/> to you at this time is on account of the
                    en-<lb/>clos'd Letter which we received from the <orgName key="seneca"
                        >Ca-<lb/>ttaraugus Indians</orgName> a few days ago, and after<lb/> due
                    deliberation on the subject, we forward<lb/> it to your consideration, believing
                    there<lb/> is a favorable opening for help profit<lb/>ably to be administered to
                    the Indians of that Village, and<lb/> as they are a part of the Seneca Nation to <lb/>
                    <pb n="23" facs="SW_HJ1798_023"/> whome our Certificate was addressed;
                    they<lb/> have an Idea that they ought to be partakers<lb/> of the instruction
                    and assistance our society<lb/> have propos'd affording that People— </p>
                <p> Their present situation is favourable for the<lb/> promotion of civilization
                    amongst them,<lb/> having a reservation of 42 Square Miles situate on<lb/>
                    <geogName key="catar">Cataraugus River</geogName> adjoining <geogName
                        key="lakee">Lake Erie</geogName><lb/> and land of a superior quality several
                    hundred<lb/> Acres of which is already clear'd of the tim-<lb/>ber—They have
                    several head of horse<lb/> Creatures and a good many Cattle, but<lb/> are very
                    desirous of haveing somebody among<lb/> them to instruct their children,
                    learn<lb/> them the art of Farming and also sup-<lb/>ply them with some
                    necessary implements<lb/> to carry on that business which they are<lb/> not able
                    to purchase themselves as we were<lb/> lately informed by one of their
                    chiefs.<lb/> We understand there are several good<lb/> Millseats on their Land:
                    and altho we con-<lb/>sider the smallness of our Funds established for <lb/>
                    <pb n="24" facs="SW_HJ1798_024"/> the benefit of the Indians we are of
                    the<lb/> Judgment it would be proper to give them<lb/> a little assistance as
                    soon as practicable, all<lb/> which we submit to you—If Friends<lb/> conclude to
                    send them any assistance we<lb/> have thought whether or no such articles
                    as<lb/> they request could not be procur'd in <lb/>
                    <placeName key="canad">upper Canada</placeName> at a much cheaper rate than<lb/>
                    taken from <placeName key="penns">Pennsylvania</placeName>—<lb/><persName
                        key="cornp2">Corn Planter</persName> and a number of his<lb/> People are
                    lately gone to Pittsburgh<lb/> by whom we wrote to you, and en-<lb/>joying usual
                    health have nothing to<lb/> add but </p>
                <closer>remain your affectionate<lb/> Friends — <signed><list>
                            <item><persName key="hsimm1">H.S.</persName></item>
                            <item><persName key="jswai1">J.S.</persName></item>
                            <item>&amp; <persName key="hjack1">H.J.</persName> — </item>
                        </list></signed></closer>

            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <pb n="25" facs="SW_HJ1798_025"/>
                <note resp="author"><date when="1799-04-28">Fourth month 28th</date> receiv'd the
                    First letter from<lb/> the Committee Being as follows — </note>

                <opener><dateline><placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName>
                        <date when="1799-02-19">2nd mo. 19th 1799</date></dateline><salute>Dear
                        Friends,</salute></opener>


                <p> Feeling our minds solici-<lb/>tous on your accounts, which solicitude<lb/> our
                    Ignorance of your situation has<lb/> considerably augmented, not haveing<lb/>
                    received any information from you since your<lb/> letter of the <date
                        when="1798-11-19">11th mo. 19th last</date>, which is the second<lb/> we
                    receiv'd since <persName key="jshar1">Joshua Sharpless</persName> and <persName
                        key="jpier1">John<lb/> Pierce</persName> left you </p>
                <p> We are desirous you may be supported<lb/> under any discouragements may
                    present<lb/> owing to the interruption that we appre<lb/>hend has happened to
                    our<lb/> correspondence, and that you may be ena-<lb/>bled to persevere in the
                    cause we are mutu-<lb/>ally engaged in, of which so arduous a task<lb/> has
                    fallen to your lot; a cause which the<lb/> more we are engaged in, and
                    contemplate on <lb/>
                    <pb n="26" facs="SW_HJ1798_026"/> the more we are confirm'd in a belief that
                    it<lb/> had its Origin in benevolence and Good will<lb/> to man: and altho’
                    prosecuted with much dif-<lb/>ficulty, labor, and expence, and the
                    advantages<lb/> resulting therefrom as yet observable but few;<lb/> yet we trust
                    as all engaged there in help<lb/> steadily, &amp; patiently to the Single
                    Object,<lb/> we shall in due time experienced it own'd<lb/> and blest with by
                    the Author of all good;<lb/> who we are taught to believe will not suffer<lb/>
                    the Smallest Labor of love to go unrewarded. </p>
                <p> By information receiv'd from the settlement<lb/> at <placeName key="oneid"
                        >Oneida</placeName> we are encouraged to hope considera-<lb/>ble progress is
                    makeing there </p>
                <p>Feeling and sympathizing with you<lb/> as we do, raises in us desires of hearing
                    from<lb/> you as often as opportunity will admit</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>We are affectionately your Friends</salute><lb/> Signed on behalf of the
                    Committee<lb/> By<lb/>
                    <signed><persName key="twist1">Thomas Wistar</persName> Clerk</signed><lb/> To
                        <persName key="jswai1">Joel Swayne</persName><lb/>
                    <persName key="hjack1">Halliday Jackson</persName><lb/> &amp; <persName
                        key="hsimm1">Henry Simmons</persName>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <pb n="27" facs="SW_HJ1798_027"/>
                <opener><title>6th Letter to the Committee</title>
                    <dateline><date when="1799-06-16">6th mo. 16st 1799</date></dateline>
                    <salute>Dear Friends,</salute></opener>
                <p>Since we wrote to you last<lb/> we received your very acceptable letter of the<lb/>
                    <date when="1799-02-19">2nd mo. 19th last</date>, which is the first we
                    have<lb/> receiv'd from you jointly since our settling here<lb/> – Some weeks
                    since we received a few<lb/> lines from <persName key="twist1">Thomas
                        Wistar</persName>&amp; <persName key="tstew1">Thomas -<lb/>
                        Howardson</persName>, desiring one of us to go to the<lb/> kozy Town for a
                    Yoke of Oxen, which accord-<lb/>ingly was done, and explor'd the
                    settlements<lb/> as far as <placeName key="ffran">Fort Franklin</placeName> in
                    quest of a Cow<lb/> but could find none for Sale. The price<lb/>
                    <persName key="gwilk1">General Wilkins</persName> had fix'd on the Oxen was<lb/>
                    one hundred Dollars, but we are now of the<lb/> Judgment 80 Dollars is their
                    full value.<lb/> They are nearly Old enough to turn off</p>
                <p> We know of no opportunity at present<lb/> of getting a Cow but we hope to avail
                    our<lb/>selves of one by some means in the<lb/> course of this Summer – We think<lb/>
                    <pb n="28" facs="SW_HJ1798_028"/> we have 8 or 9 Acres of our Wilderness
                    bottom<lb/> Clear'd, have got 4 Acres of Corn in the<lb/> Ground, 5 Bushels of
                    Oates sow'd, and 8<lb/> Bushels of Potatoes Planted this Spring<lb/> have also
                    plow'd several small lots<lb/> for the Indians near us and divers of the<lb/>
                    men have assisted in the Labor of the Field.<lb/> One has fenc'd in a farm near
                    us and more<lb/> are about doing it – We have erected a<lb/> commodious
                    Schoolhouse at <placeName key="conis">Conishadago</placeName><lb/> which the
                    Indians assisted us in doing,<lb/> and also found materials for it </p>
                <p> Altho’ we find sufficient encouragement<lb/> to persevere in the work, we cannot
                    but<lb/> lament the evil effects produced by an<lb/> intemperate use of
                    Spirituous Liquors<lb/> amongst those poor people – The procured<lb/> much of it
                    this Spring when out in the<lb/> Frontier Settlements disposing of their<lb/>
                    Skins, Furrs, &amp;c., which has caused us<lb/> some renewed engagement of mind
                    to bear a Testimo<lb/>ny <lb/>
                    <pb n="29" facs="SW_HJ1798_029"/> against it, and qualification was
                        <del>measurably</del><lb/> measurably experimented to point out the<lb/>
                    miseries to which they were subjected by it,<lb/> And we are not without a hope
                    that things<lb/> are bettering in that respect</p>
                <p> We receiv'd intelligence from our Agents<lb/> at <placeName key="pitts"
                        >Pittsburgh,</placeName> that the articles you ordered<lb/> would be
                    forwarded to <placeName key="ffran">Fort Franklin</placeName> for us<lb/> one of
                    us therefore propose, starting tomorrow<lb/> with several Canoes and a company
                    of<lb/> Indians in order to transport them<lb/> to our place – We hope the
                    considerati<lb/>-on of an addition to our number will<lb/> seriously engage your
                    attention, as another<lb/> of us have a distant prospect of being<lb/> releas'd
                    from this place – </p>
                <p> We have not the accounts in readiness<lb/> to forward at this time, and think
                    nothing<lb/> will suffer by delaying them untill we<lb/> receive the other
                    Articles – </p>
                <closer><salute>Enjoying our<lb/> health as usual we remain your affectat<lb/>
                        Friends</salute>
                    <signed><list>
                            <item><persName key="hsimm1">H.S</persName></item>
                            <item><persName key="jswai1">J.S.</persName></item>
                            <item>&amp; <persName key="hjack1">H.J</persName></item>
                        </list></signed></closer>

                <pb n="30" facs="SW_HJ1798_030"/>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <opener><title>2nd Letter from the Committee received <date when="1799-06-24">6 mo.
                            24th </date></title>
                    <dateline><placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName>
                        <date when="1799-04-20">4th mo. 20th 1799</date></dateline><lb/>
                    <salute>Dear Friends,</salute></opener>
                <p> Your letter of 1st mo. 23rd<lb/> was received and read in the Committee for
                    Indian<lb/> affairs at their meeting Last month, its General<lb/> contents
                    affording satisfaction a renewal of that<lb/> general sympathy was felt which
                    frequently<lb/> accompanies our minds on your behalf,<lb/> secluded as you are
                    from the Society you<lb/> have been accustomed to: yet where an evidence<lb/>
                    attends the mind that we are in our proper<lb/> allotments in obedience to him
                    who has a right<lb/> to our Services in such situations and exercises<lb/> of
                    duty as He is pleased to manifest, those<lb/> things which would otherwise be
                    very trying<lb/> and Irksome are made easy –</p>
                <p> your intimation of a prospect that one of<lb/> you might during the winter
                    season profit<lb/>ably reside at the Lower Village to instruct<lb/> the Children
                    in School Learning has<lb/> claimed our serious deliberation, and we <lb/>
                    <pb n="31" facs="SW_HJ1798_031"/> are free to suggest that you rather
                    encourage<lb/> some of the Indians to second a few of their Chil-<lb/>dren to
                    reside near you in winter – perhaps<lb/> by so doing the school will be smaller,
                    but<lb/> we hope quite as useful to such as do attend<lb/> and afford you more
                    comfort and satisfaction,<lb/> believeing you will strengthen and encourage<lb/>
                    one another and be less exposed by resideing<lb/> as much together as may be –
                    we would<lb/> not wish to be understood as disapproveing<lb/> of the trial
                    already made but feel a solici-<lb/>tude for your preservation under the
                    safe<lb/> direction of pure unerring wisdom</p>
                <p> Enclosed is Invoice of such of the Articles<lb/> you wrote for, as was by the
                    Committee<lb/> concluded to forward – except the three<lb/> Barrels of Flower,
                    and Flax seed, which it<lb/> is expected <persName key="abark1">Abner</persName>
                    &amp; <persName key="jbark1">Jesse Barker</persName> will<lb/> forward with the
                    other articles from<lb/>
                    <placeName key="pitts">Pittsburgh</placeName> – </p>
                <closer><salute>We remain your affection<lb/>ate friends</salute> – Signd on behalf
                    of the committee<lb/> To <persName key="hjack1">H.J.</persName>
                    <persName key="jswai1">J.s.</persName>
                    <persName key="hsimm1">H Simmons</persName>
                    <signed><persName key="twist1">Tho. Wistar</persName> Clerk </signed></closer>
                <pb n="32" facs="SW_HJ1798_032"/>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <opener><title>Seventh Letter to the Committee</title>
                    <dateline><date when="1799-08-22">8th mo. 22 - 99</date></dateline><lb/>
                    <salute>Dear friends</salute></opener>
                <p>We have had no accounts from<lb/> you since your letter of the 4th mo. 13th
                    which<lb/> accompanied the Articles you sent us, all of<lb/> which we received
                    agreeably to the Invoice en<lb/>closed. We feel solicitous in the
                    prosecution<lb/> of our present engagement to be preserved under<lb/> the
                    direction of best wisdom, and also to act agree<lb/>ably to your council; yet
                    upon serious delibera<lb/>tion on the Subject you propos'd of the Indians<lb/>
                    sending their Children to our village to be<lb/> instructed in School Learning
                    we are again<lb/> free to suggest to you that we believe it will<lb/> afford the
                    most general satisfaction, &amp; be most<lb/> advantageous to the Indians for
                    the School<lb/> to be kept at the lower village, while three suita<lb/>ble
                    persons are stationed in this quarter, as<lb/> the Children are mostly there and
                    but little<lb/> hopes of them comeing nearer to us – But<lb/> the prospect of
                    one of us returning this Fall will<lb/> probably prevent the School being kept at<lb/>
                    <pb n="33" facs="SW_HJ1798_033"/> that place the ensuing winter unless
                    their<lb/> is an addition to our member</p>
                <p> We have lately purchased a Cow which sup-<lb/>plies us with <del>plenty of</del>
                    Milk-</p>
                <p> Our Corn, Potatoes, etc. Looks well, and we<lb/> are preparing Ground to sow
                    several Bushels<lb/> of Winter Grain-</p>
                <p> Being well in health we have nothing to<lb/> "alleghany" more than we desire to
                    hear from you<lb/> as often as opportunity serves-</p>

                <closer><salute>We remain your affectionate Friends</salute>
                    <signed>
                        <list>
                            <item><persName key="hsimm1">H.S.</persName></item>
                            <item>
                                <persName key="jswai1">J.S.</persName></item>
                            <item>&amp; <persName key="hjack1">H. Jackson</persName></item>
                        </list></signed></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <opener><title>Third letter from the Committee Received <date when="1799-09-12">9th
                            mo. 12th 99</date></title>
                    <dateline><placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName>
                        <date when="1799-06-22">6 mo. 22nd 1799</date></dateline>
                    <salute>Dear Friends,</salute></opener>
                <p> Your several Letters of 3 mo. 21 &amp; 4 mo.<lb/> 21st haveing been duly
                    received were read in a mee<lb/>ting of the Committee and the 18 Ultimate,
                    their<lb/> general contents being acceptable and satisfactory</p>
                <p> Your prospect of an increasing desire of improvement </p>
                <pb n="34" facs="SW_HJ1798_034"/>
                <p>among the natives, affords encouragement to<lb/> preserve in the task allotted
                    us, though’ in its nature<lb/> arduous, and not unattended with
                    difficulties<lb/> which it is however hoped may prove temporary<lb/> and
                    surmountable Your apparent lively dedication<lb/> to the service before you,
                    mingles a pleasing<lb/> sensation with our sympathy and solicitude for<lb/> you
                    in your remote and exposed situation, accompa<lb/>nied with a desire that best
                    support may be your<lb/> experience – Your views extendable to additional<lb/>
                    Bodies of Indians are liberal, &amp; becoming the<lb/> cause we are engaged to
                    promote; --how far we<lb/> can unite therein depends on a due consideration<lb/>
                    of the limited Sphere we act in which respect<lb/> to the amount of Funds to be
                    relied on; - Divine<lb/> approbation if obtained, is no doubt an ample<lb/>
                    ground of dependence; this assurance requires that<lb/> we move under the
                    direction of divine wisdom –<lb/> waiting with patient circumspection for
                    Clear<lb/> openings for the advancement of the work – </p>
                <p> Experience in Indian <del>affairs</del> concerns evinces</p>
                <pb n="35" facs="SW_HJ1798_035"/>
                <p>what must probably have occurred to your obser-<lb/>vation as well as ours, that
                    Indians build large ex-<lb/>pectation on very slight grounds; caution is
                    therefore<lb/> requisite, that we may rather exceed than fall short<lb/> of what
                    they may be led to look for at our homes. </p>
                <p> The school instruction of the Indian youth is<lb/> a desirable object, for which
                    were it convenient,<lb/> their coming to you would seem more satisfactory<lb/>
                    than you dividing to go a distance to them<lb/> for as council and strength
                    appertain to union;<lb/> we wish you as inseparable as the nature of<lb/> the
                    concern will admit Your reasons for<lb/> desiring a discreet Family may be
                    encoura<lb/>ged to come and reside at your settlement we<lb/> doubt not are
                    weighty, and the subject is serious<lb/> by before us, tho’ doubts have been
                    suggested,<lb/> whether it may yet be reasonable to invite<lb/> females to so
                    material a change of life at a distance<lb/> so great, till the manners and
                    Customs of the<lb/> Natives become more assimilated to the modes<lb/> and
                    principals of civilized life; while the con-<lb/>sideration of this matter is
                    under deliberation <lb/>
                    <pb n="36" facs="SW_HJ1798_036"/> with us, would it be amiss for you to
                    look<lb/> round you for some thoughtful well-dispos'd<lb/> elderly Female
                    Native, who may be tractable, &amp;<lb/> willing to be instructed in domestic
                    economy<lb/> the needful affairs of a kitchen etc. </p>
                <p> Your takeing an Indian Lad to instruct in<lb/> Farming and such other business
                    as he may<lb/> be capable of needs our approbation </p>
                <p> The Friends who were at <placeName key="oneid">Oneida</placeName> and those<lb/>
                    who went about the same time you left us all<lb/> remain there, and have been
                    favour'd to enjoy<lb/> a good state of health – We have receiv'd
                    sa-<lb/>tisfactory accounts from them respecting<lb/> the improvement of some of
                    they Indians, &amp;<lb/> several Lads have undertaken to learn the<lb/> Smiths
                    business </p>
                <p> In respect to the application of the<lb/>
                    <orgName key="seneca">Cataraugus Indians</orgName>, we may inform you<lb/> the
                    same has received our serious attention<lb/> and deliberation which is intended
                    to be<lb/> Confirmed and the result communicated<lb/> to you – in meantime (as
                    we are desirous<lb/>
                    <pb n="37" facs="SW_HJ1798_037"/> to supply them with a set of mill
                    Irons)<lb/> enquiry is intended to be made how, and where<lb/> they can be
                    procur'd the most advantageous<lb/> for them, and at the least expense to us</p>
                <p> But it is of the highest importance to<lb/> the Success of what this people
                    appear to have<lb/> in prospect, that they be constantly and<lb/> closely
                    excited to a sober and diligent<lb/> attention to frugality &amp; economy in
                    hus-<lb/>banding the pecuniary means afforded them<lb/> for improvement </p>
                <closer><salute> Signed on behalf of the Committee To <persName key="hjack1">H.
                            Jackson.</persName>
                        <persName key="jswai1">J. Swayne</persName> | <persName key="twist1">Thomas
                            Wistar</persName> Cl:<lb/> &amp; <persName key="hsimm1">H.
                            Simmons</persName></salute>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <opener><title>Eighth Letter to the Committee</title>
                    <dateline><date when="1799-11-10">da. 11 mo. 10 1799</date></dateline><lb/>
                    <salute>Dear Friends,</salute></opener>
                <p> The latest written intelligence<lb/> we received from you was your letter of the<lb/>
                    <date when="1799-06-22">6 month 22nd</date> which came to hand about<lb/> the
                    time and mutually beloved Friends visited <lb/>
                    <pb n="38" facs="SW_HJ1798_038"/> us in the 9 mo. last – its general
                    con-<lb/>tents being salutary, &amp; encouraging to fur-<lb/>ther degrees of
                    dedication in the arduous<lb/> task which now seems to be devolv'd on a<lb/>
                    very small number of us in this quarter: yet<lb/> as we are at home favourd with
                    a renewed<lb/> evidence that the work is sanctioned by<lb/> divine approbation,
                    and that we as instru-<lb/>ments engaged therein, <gap/> and in our proper<lb/>
                    allotments, it has a tendency to sweeten the<lb/> bitter cups, and make hard
                    things easy,<lb/> and withal to hope we shall experience<lb/> strength
                    sufficient unto the Burden of the<lb/> day, and that our labour will not be in
                    vain<lb/> notwithstanding the discouragements that<lb/> at times arise, and the
                    slowness of they<lb/> Indians improvements </p>
                <p> Several Indians have manifested a disposition<lb/> to work at our business this
                    Fall, which we em-<lb/>ploy'd to assist in gathering our Corn &amp;
                    Potatoes<lb/> – of the former we had in all about 200 bushels<lb/>
                    <pb n="39" facs="SW_HJ1798_039"/> and of the latter about 90, also about 9
                    bushels<lb/> of buckwheat, but had a difficult time in<lb/> collecting them by
                    reason of much wet<lb/> weather in last month. – </p>
                <p> We have near four Acres of Wheat &amp; rye<lb/> sow'd which looks well present – </p>
                <p> We have got a good Smith Shop erected<lb/> and are now about building a Barn
                    which<lb/> we expect to Finish in a few days </p>
                <p> We have some prospect of teaching several<lb/> small Indians who reside near us,
                    at our<lb/> house the ensuing Winter, and now have<lb/> a more Adult person
                    living with us<lb/> to be instructed in School Learning,<lb/> whose debilitated
                    situation of Body renders<lb/> him incapable of procuring livelihood<lb/> in the
                    common way </p>
                <p> Haveing some intelligence of the Yellow [fever]<lb/> being again prevalent in
                        <placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName><lb/> raises in us desires of
                    hearing from you<lb/> often, either in a collective or individual<lb/> capacity </p>
                <p><persName key="cornp2">Corn planter</persName>: and several of his people
                    proposes going to <placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName> in the early
                    part of this winter</p>

                <closer><salute>We are well and remain your affectionate<lb/> Friends.</salute><signed><list>
                            <item><persName key="jswai1">J. S</persName></item>
                            <item><persName key="hjack1">H. J</persName></item>
                        </list></signed></closer>

                <pb n="40" facs="SW_HJ1798_040"/>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <opener><dateline><date when="1799-12-28">12th month 28th</date></dateline><note
                        resp="author">We received the following Letter<lb/> from the <orgName
                            key="seneca">Indians of Cataraugus
                        Village</orgName></note><salute>Brothers Friends Quakers at the <geogName
                            key="alleg">Allegany</geogName></salute></opener>

                <p> We have received your letter that you wrote and<lb/> left with <persName
                        key="wjohn1">Wm. Johnson</persName> at <placeName key="buffc1">Buffalo creek
                    </placeName> – we have<lb/> Got a full understanding of what you wrote in
                    your<lb/> Letter – The instructions you gave pleases us very<lb/> much in
                    general – you may rely upon it that we<lb/> are going to follow your directions,
                    for we have swallow<lb/> it in our breast and heart – </p>
                <p> Now Brothers we must inform you that we are<lb/> a going to lay up money to buy
                    Cattle and other<lb/> useful articles <unclear>250</unclear> Dollars, and for
                    the following<lb/> year we mean to lay up as much more – </p>
                <p> The mill is a going on all agree when we are ready<lb/> we will call on our
                    friends the Quakers, we<lb/> wish you to give us all assistance you can
                    when<lb/> we come to build, so that we don’t give too much<lb/> for our works,
                    our minds are determined to have<lb/> our Brothers, Friends Quakers to oversee – </p>
                <p> We have fully determined to throw up drink-<lb/>ing Whisky – and if there comes
                    Traders on we<lb/> have determined to order them off the Ground </p>
                <p> Brothers, </p>
                <p> We hope you will keep your mind strong<lb/>
                    <pb n="41" facs="SW_HJ1798_041"/> as you was at first, and we return you
                    great<lb/> thanks for the kindness you have done already.</p>
                <p> Our principal women return you their hearty<lb/> thanks, they understand that
                    their friends<lb/> Quakers is going to give them assistance-</p>
                <closer><signed><list>
                            <item><foreign><persName>Tak con non dee</persName></foreign></item>
                            <item><foreign><persName>Won two guh tah</persName></foreign></item>
                            <item><foreign><persName>se noch quo gau</persName></foreign></item>
                            <item><foreign><persName>Te ni an nee</persName></foreign></item>
                        </list></signed></closer>

            </div>

            <div type="letter">
                <note resp="author"> The following we wrote to them in answer --</note>
                <opener>To the Chiefs and others of <placeName key="catta1">Cataraugus
                        Village</placeName> – <salute> Friends and Brothers</salute></opener>
                <p> We received your letter in<lb/> Company with the one you wrote to <persName
                        key="cornp2">Captain<lb/> Obeal</persName>, and are glad to find you got a
                    full<lb/> understanding of what our friends wrote to<lb/> you at <geogName
                        key="buffc1">Buffalo Creek</geogName> and that the instructions<lb/> they
                    gave you pleases you generally –</p>
                <p> Now Brothers we did not see that speech<lb/> which our friend left at <geogName
                        key="buffc1">Buffalo Creek</geogName> for you<lb/> but as you say you are
                    determined to take their<lb/> advice and have already swallow’d it down in<lb/>
                    your breast, we hope you will often remember <lb/>
                    <pb n="42" facs="SW_HJ1798_042"/> and consider it –</p>
                <p>Brothers,</p>
                <p>We are glad to hear that you have come<lb/> to a resolution to lay up so much of
                    your money<lb/> in order to buy Cattle and other useful articles<lb/> and that
                    you are determined to quit drinking<lb/> Whisky and not to allow any traders to
                    sell it<lb/> on your Ground –</p>
                <p> Now Brothers this is a very Wise resolution<lb/> in you, and we hope you will be
                    sincere and<lb/> keep to it – We heartily wish all the Indian Tribes<lb/> would
                    join you in driveing Whisky and Rum out<lb/> of the Land – We hope some of you
                    have got<lb/> your eyes opened to see that Whisky and Strong<lb/> drink has been
                    the Cause of much Evil and wicked-<lb/>ness among you, and that it has taken
                    away much<lb/> of your money, your skins, &amp; your furrs, which<lb/> the great
                    Spirit has given you to buy Blankets<lb/> and Clotheing, &amp; oxen, axes and
                    hoes, and other<lb/> useful articles to assist you in tilling the field –<lb/>
                    and we fear in time past it has taken away some<lb/> of the Corn your poor Women
                    have work'd hard<lb/> at raising with their Hoes –</p>
                <p> Brothers, </p>

                <p> You must know there are many White <lb/>
                    <pb n="43" facs="SW_HJ1798_043"/> People that love money, and they know that
                    you<lb/> love Whisky, and this is the way they take to<lb/> get your money and
                    Property from you, but<lb/> if you keep to your resolution not to drink it<lb/>
                    then there will be no danger, you will then<lb/> have money to buy Oxen and
                    Plows to plow<lb/> your Ground and raise a great deal of Corn, and<lb/> to buy
                    axes and Hoes and other useful Articles to<lb/> go to Farming with, and then
                    when your Brothers<lb/> the Quakers see that you are trying to do good for<lb/>
                    your selves, and makeing good use of your money<lb/> it will encourage them to
                    help you more –</p>
                <p> Brothers,</p>
                <p> We desire you often to think upon the<lb/> Great Spirrit, and pray to him in
                    your hearts,<lb/> and then he will shew you what is good, and what<lb/> is evil;
                    and we want you to take up work like<lb/> the White people, for your land we
                        <del>think</del> believe is<lb/> very good and will produce a great deal of
                    Grain if<lb/> you are industrious, and when you get plenty of<lb/> Cattle, and
                    Sheep, and Swine, they will afford you<lb/> plenty of meat, and be much easier
                    taken than<lb/> the Elk, the Deer, &amp; the Bear – Then will your<lb/> Old men,
                    your Wives and your Children be<lb/> happy and enjoy the Comforts of Life, and <lb/>
                    <pb n="44" facs="SW_HJ1798_044"/> you can look on your Flocks, your Fields
                    and your<lb/> Fruit Trees, with contentment and Pleasure </p>
                <p> Brothers and Sisters, </p>
                <p> We are young men and cannot<lb/> say a great deal to you but we intend to send
                    an account<lb/> how you are comeing on to our Older Brethren in<lb/>
                    <placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName> and we can assure you they will
                    be<lb/> your Friends and will counsel you wisely in every<lb/> thing for your
                    good, and we hope your ears will always<lb/> be open to Listen to their Talk
                    –</p>
                <p> We commend you to the Care of the Great Spirit<lb/> and are your Friends and
                    Brothers</p>
                <closer><signed><persName key="jswai1">Joel Swayne</persName><lb/></signed><dateline>
                        <placeName key="alleg1">Allegany</placeName> – <date when="1799-12-29">12
                            mo. 29 1799</date></dateline><lb/><persName key="hjack1">Halliday
                        Jackson</persName></closer>

            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <opener>
                    <title>Ninth Letter to the Committee </title><dateline><date when="1800-01-16"
                            >1st mo. 16th 1800</date></dateline>
                    <salute> Dear Friends,</salute></opener>
                <p> Our last was dated <date when="1799-11-10">11 mo. 10th</date> since<lb/> which
                    we have received no intelligence from you<lb/> either collectively or
                    individually – </p>
                <p> Our Living here the present Winter is in a good<lb/> degree comfortable and we
                    are encouraged to hope<lb/> we shall experience an addition to our number
                    the<lb/> ensuing Summer whereby one of us may be<lb/> released from the present
                    engagement <lb/>
                    <pb n="45" facs="SW_HJ1798_045"/> A Smith would be very desirable and we
                    think ex-<lb/>tensively useful at this place – </p>
                <p> We have kept up a school at our house the present<lb/> Winter where several
                    small children have attended<lb/> and make some progress in learning – and
                    an<lb/> Indian Lad about 13 years of age is now resideing<lb/> with us, whom we
                    have a prospect of keeping to<lb/> instruct in our business – </p>
                <p> We have lately received a letter from the Indians<lb/> of <placeName
                        key="catta1">Cattaraugus Village</placeName>, who appear to continue<lb/>
                    their prospect of looking toward us for assistance<lb/> and instruction –on
                    serious deliberation on<lb/> the subject we felt easy to write them an
                    answer<lb/> in order to strengthen and encourage them in<lb/> the resolutions
                    the appear to have adopted, a<lb/> copy of which with the letter the sent us is
                    here<lb/> enclosed for your perusal – What ever result<lb/> may take place in
                    the Committee respecting those<lb/> Indians, we are free to suggest, if nothing
                    further<lb/> is attempted for their advancement in civilization,<lb/> whether or
                    no a few Axes &amp; Hoes or such like use-<lb/>ful articles; would not be
                    expedient to send among<lb/> them in order to support that Friendship and<lb/>
                    Confidence they appear to have in our Society –<lb/>And if the Committee should
                    see cause to afford<lb/>
                    <pb n="46" facs="SW_HJ1798_046"/> them a few of those useful articles we
                    think if they<lb/> were deposited in our care the Indians would not think<lb/>
                    hard of coming to us for them – In the mean time<lb/> if we should have further
                    intercourse with that people<lb/> we mean to extend our inquiries into their
                    conduct<lb/> and situation, and transmit our knowledge thereof<lb/> to you –</p>
                <p> A few articles may be necessary to send forward in the<lb/> Spring for our
                    accommodations here, of such as we<lb/> recollect at present is – Chocolate Tea,
                    2 Bushels<lb/> of fine Salt – a short piece of Strong Cloth – 1 do of
                    strong<lb/> shirten linen, some Candle wick – 1 doz nail Gimblet<lb/> 100 Sprigs
                    – 6 plain bits &amp; an Almanack –</p>
                <p> The Cloth and linen is intended for the accommoda<lb/>tion of the Family here –
                    we don’t desire any more<lb/> to traffic with the Indians, and if a Smith
                    should<lb/> come forward some more Tools, Iron &amp; Steele per-<lb/>haps will
                    be necessary All which we submit to<lb/> you, and being well in health remain
                    your</p>
                <closer><salute>Affectionate Friends – </salute>
                    <signed><list>
                            <item><persName key="jswai1">Joel Swayne</persName></item>
                            <lb/>
                            <item><persName key="hjack1">Halliday Jackson</persName></item>
                        </list></signed></closer>




            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <pb n="47" facs="SW_HJ1798_047"/>
                <opener><note resp="author">Received <date when="1800-03-29">3 mo. 29
                        1800</date></note>
                    <dateline><placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName>
                        <date when="1800-02-22">2 mo. 22 1800</date></dateline><lb/>
                    <salute>Dear Friends,</salute></opener>
                <p> Your Letter to the Committee<lb/> on Indian affairs dated 16 Ultimate was<lb/>
                    duly received and afforded much satisfaction<lb/> to find you were preserved in
                    health, and<lb/> that your situation was rendered comfortable<lb/> during the
                    inclemency of the present Season. </p>
                <p> Various consideration have induced the<lb/> Committee to believe it right to
                    withdraw our<lb/> friends from the <orgName key="oneida">Oneida Nation</orgName>
                    – Several<lb/> of the Indians have been instructed in the<lb/> best mode of
                    tilling their land and two<lb/> or three young men have acquired so much<lb/>
                    knowledge in the Smiths business as to be able<lb/> to do what may be wanted in
                    that line for<lb/> the use of the Nation so that by proper ap-<lb/>plication on
                    their part they will be essen-<lb/>tially benefitted by the labor bestow'd
                    upon<lb/> them – <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName> &amp; <persName
                        key="jthom2">Jonathon Thomas</persName><lb/> attended the meeting of the
                    Committee this<lb/> day; neither of them appear to be fully<lb/> releas'd from a
                    prospect of further service<lb/> among the Indians, We are therefore not
                    with<lb/>out a hope of the subject being so matured in their <lb/>
                    <pb n="48" facs="SW_HJ1798_048"/> minds by the next meeting of the committee
                    as to pro-<lb/>duce a willingness to spend some time in your settlement.</p>
                <p> Your answer to the letter of the <orgName key="seneca">Cataraugus</orgName>
                    Chiefs<lb/> is such a proof of your Guarded care and anxious<lb/> concern for
                    their Good as it could not fail of being<lb/> very satisfactory to the Committee
                    who have<lb/> agreed to forward for their use some hoes and<lb/> Axes together
                    with the Articles for your accom-<lb/>modation when convenient opportunity
                    occurs, and<lb/> for your information we enclose a Copy of a<lb/> letter
                    addressed to that tribe by our friends who were<lb/> at your country last Fall
                    –</p>
                <p> Under a full persuasion that every act of obedience<lb/> is not only noticed but
                    in the lords time<lb/> fully rewarded, we doubt not but your dedicati<lb/>on to
                    the very trying duty allotted you will<lb/> (as patience is abode in) be
                    abundantly recom-<lb/>pensed, with that peace which surpasseth<lb/> every
                    Temporal acquisition – </p>
                <p> With desires that you may be favoured with<lb/> the continuance of that divine
                    support<lb/> which hath hitherto been graciously afforded for<lb/> your strength
                    and encouragement we remain<lb/> your affectionate friends</p>
                <closer>
                    <lb/>
                    <signed><list>
                            <item><persName key="jswai1">Joel Swayne</persName></item>
                            <item>&amp; <persName key="hjack1">H Jackson</persName></item>

                            <item><persName key="jelli1">John Elliott</persName></item>

                            <item><persName key="eyarn1">Ellis Yarnall</persName></item>
                        </list></signed>
                    <lb/> on behalf of the committee </closer>
                <pb n="49" facs="SW_HJ1798_049"/>
            </div>
            <div type="speech">
                <opener><title>Copy of an address to the Indians of <placeName key="catta1"
                            >Cataraugus Village</placeName> --</title>
                    <lb/><salute>Brothers,</salute></opener>
                <p>Your Friends the Quakers in <placeName key="phila">Phila-<lb/>delphia</placeName>
                    received a letter which you sent to our<lb/> young men Who live at <placeName
                        key="genes1">Genesinguhta</placeName> on the<lb/>
                    <geogName key="alleg">Allegany River</geogName> in which letter you say you<lb/>
                    want to build a saw Mill and request them<lb/> to help you to get the Irons, and
                    also desire<lb/> some instruction to put you in a better way<lb/> of farming – </p>
                <p> Brothers we write to you on behalf of<lb/> your friends the Quakers in
                        <placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName>.<lb/> We have lately been to
                    see our young Men<lb/> at <placeName key="genes1">Genesinguhta</placeName> and
                    our brothers the Indi-<lb/>ans whom they are endeavouring to instruct<lb/> in
                    farming, and we were pleased to find that<lb/> some of the Indian men are
                    beginning to help<lb/> their Women to work and raise Corn and make<lb/> fence
                    –We were also at <placeName key="catta1">Cataraugus</placeName> and would<lb/>
                    have been Glad to have seen you, and taken<lb/> you by the hand, but understood
                    you chiefs<lb/> were not at home – We now inform you<lb/> the saw mill Irons are
                    made and on the<lb/> way comeing to be placed under the care of <lb/>
                    <pb n="50" facs="SW_HJ1798_050"/>
                    <persName key="wjohn1">Wm Johnson</persName> at <placeName key="buffa"
                        >Buffalo</placeName> who will deliver them<lb/> to You when you are ready to
                    build a saw mill<lb/> first informing <persName key="hjack1">Halliday
                        Jackson</persName> and <persName key="jswai1">Joel Swayne</persName><lb/>
                    our two young men who live at <placeName key="genes1"
                    >Genesinguhta</placeName><lb/> and getting their Order for delivering them to
                    you.<lb/> Brothers we cannot at this time give you any assis-<lb/>tance about
                    Farming, but if the men will begin<lb/> to be industrious ( we see your land is
                    very good)<lb/> you may soon raise abundance of Grain and if<lb/> you take our
                    advice in that and leave off drink<lb/>ing Whisky, we shall be encouraged to
                    try, to<lb/> instruct you further in farming and work-<lb/>ing your land, but if
                    you will spend your<lb/> money that you should buy Cattle and other<lb/> useful
                    things with, for Whisky, we shall be<lb/> discouraged from trying to get our
                    young men<lb/> to come and live with you, and instruct you, for<lb/> we see that
                    bad white men who get drunk do<lb/> very little good for themselves or anybody
                    else. </p>
                <closer><dateline><placeName key="buffa">Buffalo</placeName>
                        <date when="1799-10-09">10 mo. 9 – 1799</date></dateline><lb/>Signd by <signed><list>
                            <item><persName key="jshar1">Joshua Sharpless</persName></item>
                            <item><persName key="icoat1">Isaac Coates</persName></item>
                            <item><persName key="jcoop1">James Cooper</persName></item>
                            <item><persName key="tstew1">Thomas Howardson</persName></item>
                        </list></signed></closer>


            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <pb n="51" facs="SW_HJ1798_051"/>
                <note resp="author">The following is copied from a Newspaper<lb/> 1 mo. 1811</note>
                <opener>To the Legislature of Virginia</opener>
                <p>The Memorial and Petition of the<lb/> religious society of friends commonly
                    called Quakers<lb/> Respectfully showeth:<lb/> That your Memo-<lb/>rialists
                    expanding the high regard with which<lb/> the Legislature will be disposed to
                    consider every<lb/> Subject <del>with which the Legislature will be
                        dis-<lb/>posed to consider ever ry</del> affecting the great<lb/> principals
                    of civil and religious liberty beg leave<lb/> to solicit your attention to the
                    militia laws of<lb/> this Commonwealth and to the incompatibility<lb/> which
                    sometimes results between the requisition of<lb/> Law and the obligations of
                    religious duty.</p>
                <p> For this enlightened age and country and before this<lb/> Legislature your
                    memorialists conceive it unnecessary<lb/> to urge the unalienable rights of
                    conscience as to<lb/> adduce any arguments to show that the relations<lb/>
                    between man and his <del>maker</del> Creator neither can<lb/> nor ought to be
                    prescribed by any human authority.<lb/> It is unnecessary because the
                    preposition <gap/> is self<lb/> evident and especially because it is one of the
                    fun-<lb/>damental principals when which the civil and<lb/> political
                    institutions of this country are<lb/> established. </p>

                <pb n="52" facs="SW_HJ1798_052"/>
                <p>This principal is recognized in the bill of rights<lb/> it is confirmed by the
                    law of 1785 passed in the<lb/> enlightened and liberal spirit of that
                    instrument<lb/> and the state itself by its convention which rati<lb/>-fied the
                    federal constitution explicitly declared that “the<lb/> liberty of conscience
                    cannot be canceled or abridged<lb/> restrained or modified by any authority of
                    the U. St.</p>
                <p> The free exercise of religion therefore is not mere-<lb/>-ly tolerated, it is
                    declared in the most solemn<lb/> form; it is confirmed in the most explicit
                    manner.</p>
                <p> But the liberty of conscience your memorialists<lb/> conceive cannot be
                    restricted to the mere liberty<lb/> of thinking or to the violent and unseen
                    modification<lb/> of religious opinion – Religion has duties to be
                    performed<lb/> and it points out offences to be avoided; its free exercise
                    must<lb/> therefore consist in an active compliance with its<lb/> dictates
                    enforced by no legal compulsion restrained by<lb/> no legal impediment.</p>
                <p> Your memorialists in common with every virtuous<lb/> citizen would disdain any
                    execution under the colour<lb/> of religious liberty from the universal
                    obligations of<lb/> moral duty but the law of 1789 in making – <lb/>“overt acts”
                    of an injurious nature the limit of the<lb/> privilege and the criterion of its
                    abuse removes all<lb/> danger to the community. An encroachment<lb/> on the
                    rights of other as evolution of the moral<lb/> law under pretence of liberty of
                    conscience would<lb/> immediately betray its own guilt and hypocrisy<lb/> and
                    afford a legitimate cause for the interposition<lb/> of the civil authority.</p>
                <p> More considerations are suggested as applicable<lb/> to the cause which is now
                    submitted to the wis<lb/>-dom and justice of the Legislature. </p>

                <pb n="53" facs="SW_HJ1798_053"/>
                <p> Your memorialists are christians and im-<lb/>-pressed with a firm conviction
                    that war<lb/> is forbidden under the Gosple – they cannot<lb/> bear Arms – to
                    require it under legal penalties<lb/> is to reduce them to the alternative of
                    refuseing<lb/> a compliance with the laws of their country<lb/> as of violating
                    what they most solemnly believe<lb/> is to them a law of God, clothed with the
                    most<lb/> awful sanctions </p>
                <p> Your memorialist plead for no new doctrine<lb/> the set up no novel pretentions.
                    The ask permissi-<lb/>-on only to practice the precepts of Jesus Christ.<lb/> To
                    adhere to a principal which prevailed through<lb/> the first centuries of the
                    Christian dispensation<lb/> which pious men through every subsequent age
                    have<lb/> maintained, and which their predecessors from the<lb/> time they have
                    been known as a religious society<lb/> under various forms of Government and
                    through<lb/> suffering imposed by rigorous and persecuting<lb/> laws, have
                    uniformly supported.</p>
                <p> It is true that in the laps of time the Spirit of<lb/> time - the Spirit of
                    persecution has faded before the<lb/> light of truth. Our own Country as
                    already<lb/> stated has been particularly distinguished for<lb/> maintaining the
                    principals of civility and reli-<lb/>-gious liberty and for rejecting those of
                    coercive law<lb/> and religious intolerance. The very grievance<lb/> to which we
                    now solicit your attention has been<lb/> acknowledged and redefined. A
                    Legislature composed<lb/> of <lb/>
                    <pb n="54" facs="SW_HJ1798_054"/> enlightened statesmen and sages who had
                    assisted<lb/> in establishing the chartered rights of America<lb/> who had seen
                    the principals which your memorial-<lb/>-ists maintain tested through the
                    revolutionary<lb/> war convinced it is believed of their sincerity<lb/> and of
                    the Justice of their claims, exempted the<lb/>m from the obligation to bear arms
                    and from<lb/> certain fines and penalties which had been impo-<lb/>-sed on their
                    non-compliance with military<lb/> requisitions. But the laws are changed.
                    They<lb/> now require that your memorialists, notwith<lb/>-standing
                        the<del>ir</del>
                    <gap/> objections of their<lb/> religious scruples should be trained to arms.
                    Their<lb/> refusal subjects them to fines which within certain<lb/> limitations
                        <del>subjects them</del> are fixed at the discretion<lb/> of the Court
                    Martial and become in numerous<lb/> instances extremely oppressive. Nor is this
                    all your<lb/> memorialists conceive that the voluntary payment<lb/> of a fine
                    imposed, for adherence to religious duty or<lb/> the receiving of surplus money
                    arising from the<lb/> sale of their property seized for the satisfying of
                    these<lb/> demands, <del>but</del> would be to acknowledge a delinquen<lb/>-cy
                    which they cannot admit and to become parties<lb/> in a traffic or commutation
                    of their principals.<lb/> Hence also considerable loss is sustained. And<lb/>
                    notwithstanding your memorialists may<lb/> acknowledge that many officers in the
                    government<lb/> in these cases manifest great reluctance, and<lb/> execute their
                    trust with a scrupulous regard to<lb/>
                    <pb n="55" facs="SW_HJ1798_055"/> the interest of the sufferers: yet there
                    are<lb/> others in which wanton depredations are made<lb/> on the property of
                    individuals </p>
                <p> Your memorialists are aware that it may be said<lb/> that the law does not
                    discriminate between them &amp;<lb/> others and that they ought equally to
                    support the<lb/> public burthens, and yield their services to the
                    exigen-<lb/>ces of the state. This objection supposes that a general<lb/> law
                    cannot have a partial or unequal operation.<lb/> It supposes that what may be
                    deemed a nati-<lb/>onal concern may supersede the chartered rights &amp;<lb/>
                    and privileges of the people. But your memorialists<lb/> cannot suppose that
                    these principals which indeed<lb/> are no other than the maxims of tyrant will
                    ever<lb/> be deliberately adopted and acted upon by this<lb/> legislature. If
                    one member of the community<lb/> believe that it is duty to fight and to slay
                    the<lb/> enemies of his country, and if another believe<lb/> that he is
                    prohibited by divine command from<lb/> planning the destruction of shedding the
                    blood of<lb/> his fellow creatures, the question as it relates to the<lb/>
                    present subject is not which or whether either is wrong<lb/> but whether a law
                    commanding both to take up<lb/> arms would not operate unequally and
                    violate<lb/> the rites of conscience? It would operate unequal<lb/>-ly because
                    it does not discriminate because to<lb/> the conscience of the one it does not
                    enjoin the<lb/> performance of a duty, to that of the other the<lb/> commission
                    of a crime. It would violate the<lb/> liberty of conscience because it would compel<lb/>
                    <pb n="56" facs="SW_HJ1798_056"/> under pains and penalties the performance
                    of<lb/> an act which is believed offensive to the divine being.</p>
                <p> Human authority cannot like the Great<lb/> searcher of hearts try the Spirits of
                    men respecting<lb/> truth and error, it cannot remit the penalties<lb/> of sin
                    or controll the convictions of the heart and<lb/> therefore in this country at
                    least the liberty of<lb/> conscience is wisely plac'd beyond the Sphere of<lb/>
                    legislation, and protected from the encroachments<lb/> of any power in the
                    government.</p>
                <p> It may be recollected too that in every nation<lb/> of the civilized world,
                    where this society is found they<lb/> profess and maintain the same principals,
                    that no<lb/> hope of reward no dread of punishment, not confis-<lb/>cations
                    imprisonment or death, would induce them to<lb/> bear arms against this Country,
                    as in any other<lb/> cause whatever and that every attempt to coerce<lb/> them
                    would result on the one side in the Triumph<lb/> of principal however severely
                    tested, and with un-<lb/>availing persecution on the other. While it is
                    there<lb/>fore evident that the ostensible object of the Law<lb/> or training
                    them to arms - cannot be effective<lb/> and it is presumed from the general
                    notori\e/ty of their<lb/> principals that it is not even expected to be
                    attain<lb/>-ed- while your memoriallists believe that the<lb/> principals they
                    hold can in no sence prove<lb/> injurious to the community, and are
                    persua<lb/>-ded that this Legislature would disclaim the<lb/> Idea of raising
                    revenue by laws inflicting fines<lb/> on the free exercise of conscience they
                    trust that<lb/> a privilege conferred by the Supreme being and <lb/>
                    <pb n="57" facs="SW_HJ1798_057"/> by the highest authority in this Country
                    decla-<lb/>red to be sacred and inviolable may be safe-<lb/>ly expected from its
                    justice and liberality.<lb/> They therefore respectfully petition that the<lb/>
                    Laws imposing military requisitions and<lb/> penalties for non-compliance may be
                    consi-<lb/>-dered as they respect your petitioners and such<lb/> relief afforded
                    as wisdom of the Legislature<lb/> shall deem just and necessary.</p>
                <closer>Signed by order and on behalf of a meeting<lb/> of the representatives of
                    the aforesaid society held<lb/> in <dateline><placeName key="dinwi">Dinwiddie
                            County</placeName> the <date when="1810-11-17">17 of 11 mo
                        1810</date></dateline><lb/><signed>By <persName key="bbate1">Benjamin
                            Bates</persName> Clerk at this time</signed></closer>


            </div>

        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <pb n="58" facs="SW_HJ1798_058"/>
                <p> Cattalogue of Books belonging to <persName key="hjack1">H.J.</persName>
                    <date when="1824-02-15">2 mo. 15 1824</date></p>
                <p><list>
                        <item>The Holy Bible</item>

                        <item>Crudens Concordance</item>

                        <item>Journal of George Fox</item>
                        <item>William Penns Select Works</item>
                        <item>Goughss History - 4. Vol.</item>
                        <item>Barclays Apology</item>
                        <item>Penns No Cross no Crown</item>
                        <item>John Wolman’s Journal</item>
                        <item>John Griffiths Journal</item>
                        <item>Original of present State of Man</item>
                        <item>Collections of memorials- 1787</item>
                        <item>Chalkleys Works</item>
                        <item>John Richardsons Journal</item>
                        <item>Primitive Christianity reviv'd</item>
                        <item>John Churchmans Journal</item>
                        <item>William Edmonsons Journal</item>
                        <item>Daniel Slantons Journal</item>
                        <item>Sarah Grubbs Journal</item>
                        <item>George Whiteheads Light of life of Christ within</item>
                        <item>Life of Mary Alexander &amp; memorials N.Y. printed</item>
                        <item>Kerseys Treatise on Church government</item>
                        <item>Job Scotts Journal</item>
                        <item>Samuel Fishers works</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb n="59" facs="SW_HJ1798_059"/>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item>Sarah Stephensons Journal</item>
                        <item>Treatise on Church Government by Robert Barclay</item>
                        <item>John Fothergills Journal</item>
                        <item>Barclays Cattchism</item>
                        <item>Piety promoted</item>
                        <item>Nailers Works</item>
                        <item>Newcombs Harmony of the Evangelists</item>
                        <item>Book of Martyrs</item>
                        <item>The Devout Christians Companion</item>
                        <item>Memorials printed 1821.</item>
                        <item>Dillwyns Reflections</item>
                        <item>Haylands Epitome- 2 Vol.</item>
                        <item>Life of Penn by Clarkson 2 Vol.</item>
                        <item>Clarkson’s Portraiture of Quakerrism 3 Vol.</item>
                        <item>Hervey’s meditations</item>
                        <item>Complaint of Peace by Erasmus</item>
                        <item>Life of Christ</item>
                        <item>Jerusalem Destroy'd</item>
                        <item>Life of Barclay</item>
                        <item>Zimmerman on Solitude</item>
                        <item>Advices of the Yearly Meeting</item>
                        <item>Blairs Philosophy</item>
                        <item> Cowpers Lark</item>
                        <item>Paradise Lost</item>
                    </list></p>

                <pb n="60" facs="SW_HJ1798_060"/>
                <p><list>
                        <item>Beauties of the poets</item>
                        <item>Christian Researches in Asia-</item>
                        <item>Refind Weeks’s Poems</item>
                        <item>Sutcliffts Travels in N. America</item>
                        <item>Scripture Lessons</item>
                        <item>Woodards Warnings</item>
                        <item>Youngs Night Thoughts</item>
                        <item>Rileys &amp; Paddocks Narrative of<lb/> their Sufferings in
                            Africa-</item>
                        <item>Paul &amp; Amicus-</item>
                        <item>Vindex<lb/> Philanthropist - 2. Vol.</item>
                        <item>The Reformer. 3 Vol. in pamphlets-</item>
                        <item>Avenia - a poem</item>
                        <item>American Monitor</item>
                        <item>Pennsylvania Farmer</item>
                        <item>Clerks Magazine</item>
                        <item>Navigator of Ohio River</item>
                        <item>American Miscellany</item>
                        <item> Lancaster school</item>
                        <item>Western Gazetteer</item>
                        <item>English Reader</item>
                        <item>Scotts Gazetteer</item>
                        <item>Captivity of John R. Jewitt</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb n="61" facs="SW_HJ1798_061"/>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item>Observations on the Indians etc</item>
                        <item>Haytian Papers by Prince Sanders</item>
                        <item>Indian Wars.- -</item>
                        <item>Lorenzo Dows Journal</item>
                        <item>The Journeyings of the Children of Israel &amp; some<lb/>
                            extraordinary dispensation</item>
                        <item>Purdons Digest of the Laws of Pennsylvania</item>
                        <item> Blackstone’s Commentaries</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
