<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei-print.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei.css"?> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="global.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>Joseph Moore's Journal: Electronic Version</title>

                <editor>Friends Historical Library</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by</resp>
                    <name>Rebecca H. Astatke</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>Friends Historical Library, Swarthmore College</distributor>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>This work is the property of the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore
                        College. It may be copied freely by individuals for personal use, research,
                        and teaching (including distribution to classes) as long as this statement
                        of availability is included in the text. It may be linked to freely in
                        Internet editions of all kinds, including for—profit works.</p>
                    <p>Publishers, libraries, and other information providers interested in
                        providing this text in a commercial or non—profit product or from an
                        information server must contact Swarthmore College for licensing and cost
                        information.</p>
                    <p> Scholars interested in changing or adding to these texts by, for example,
                        creating a new edition of the text (electronically or in print) with
                        substantive editorial changes, may do so with the permission of Swarthmore
                        College. This is the case whether the new publication will be made available
                        at a cost or free of charge.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2014">2014</date>
                <idno type="local">SW_JM1793</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Native Americans and Quakers: An Electronic
                    Collection </title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>

                        <title>Joseph Moore's Journal</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Friends Miscellany</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                            <biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
                            <date when="1835">1835:</date>
                            <biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="343"/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>

        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>In the fall semester of 2010, Swarthmore students enrolled in English 50A
                    (“Reading Red, White, and In-Between in Early American Literature”) transcribed
                    a number of journals, both published and in manuscript form, which document the
                    interaction of Quakers and Native Americans. In 2014 a decision was made to
                    encode these and other journals as part of a larger project to make the
                    library’s rich store of Quaker Indian mission writings more accessible. The
                    project was designed by Christopher Densmore, Curator of Friends Historical
                    Library.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written in <date when="1793">1793</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="English">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                        <item>Quakers - Ohio</item>
                        <item>Wyandot Indians</item>


                        <item>Indian reservations</item>
                        <item>Indians of North America--Missions</item>

                        <item>Ohio--Description and travel</item>

                        <item>Philadelphia Yearly Meeting of the Religious Society of Friends</item>
                        <item>Quakers--Pennsylvania--Diaries</item>
                        <item>Quakers--Political activity</item>

                        <item>Society of Friends--Missions</item>
                        <item>Voyages and Travels</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <titlePart><title type="main">JOSEPH MOORE'S JOURNAL</title>
                <title type="sub"><emph rend="italics">Of a tour to Detroit, in order to attend a
                        Treaty, proposed to be held with the Indians at
                San-dusky</emph></title></titlePart>
            <div type="preface">
                <p> In the second volume of Friends' Miscellany, was published, <persName
                        key="jlind1">Jacob<lb/> Lindley</persName>'s Account of a Journey to attend
                    this Treaty, with preli<lb/>minary remarks and a brief history of the
                    circumstances which led to<lb/> this measure. The following Journal, while it
                    corroborates <persName key="jlindl">Jacob<lb/> Lindley</persName>'s account,
                    presents a view of divers interesting incidents<lb/> and occurrences, not noted
                    in that narrative. <persName key="jmooor3">Joseph Moore</persName> was a<lb/>
                    valuable friend and minister belonging to Kingwood monthly meet-<lb/>ing, New
                    Jersey. The place of his residence was near <placeName key="flemi">
                        Flemington</placeName>. </p>
            </div>
        </front>

        <body>

            <div type="entry">


                <dateline>On the <date when="1793-04-01">17th of 4th mo. 1793</date>, <placeName
                        key="phila"/></dateline>
                <p>I set out for Philadel-<lb/>phia, and attended the <orgName key="pymsufferings"
                        >meeting for sufferings</orgName>, where<lb/> were divers Friends who had
                    given up to attend the<lb/> Indian treaty proposed to be held at <placeName
                        key="sandu">Sandusky</placeName>, on<lb/> the waters of <geogName
                        key="lakee">Lake Erie</geogName> — having previously obtained
                    <lb/>certificates from our several monthly meetings for<lb/> that purpose. The
                    commissioners appointed by go-<lb/>vernment are,<persName key="genlinc">general
                        Lincoln</persName>, <persName key="cpic">colonel Pickering</persName>,<lb/>
                    and <persName key="grand1">Beverly Randolph</persName>. <persName key="genlinc"
                        >Lincoln</persName> goes by water to <lb/><placeName key="alban"
                        >Albany</placeName>, &amp;c. ; <persName key="wsave1">William
                        Savery</persName>, <persName key="jlind1">Jacob Lindley</persName>, and<lb/>
                    <persName key="whart">William Hartshorne</persName>, go with him: and <persName
                        key="jparr1">John Par-<lb/>rish</persName>, <persName key="jelli1">John
                        Elliott</persName>, and myself, with <persName key="cpic">Timothy
                        Pick-<lb/>ering</persName> and <persName key="grand1">Beverly
                        Randolph</persName>, go through the coun-<lb/>try by land. I have some days
                    past, been very poor-<lb/>ly with the ague; but am now bravely. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">

                <dateline><date when="1793-04-30">30th.</date><placeName key="muncy"/></dateline>
                <p>In the afternoon set out in company with <pb n="290"/>
                    <lb/>
                    <persName key="grand1">Beverly Randolph</persName>,<persName key="jparr1">John
                        Parrish</persName>, <persName key="jelli1">John Elliott</persName>, and<lb/>
                    <persName key="habee1">Henry Cornplanter</persName>, or Obeal — got that evening to<lb/>
                    <placeName key="norrist">Norristown </placeName>, where <persName key="cpic"
                        >colonel Pickering</persName> met us. Next<lb/> day we proceeded to
                        <placeName key="readi">Reading</placeName> — thence to <placeName
                        key="harrisb">Harris-<lb/>burgh</placeName> and over the <geogName
                        key="broadm">Broad Mountain</geogName>, <placeName key="mackin"
                        >Mackinoy</placeName>, and<lb/>
                    <placeName key="tuscar">Tuscarora</placeName>, to <placeName key="sunb"
                        >Sunbury</placeName> — thence crossed the <geogName key="susqueh"
                        >Susque-<lb/>hanna</geogName> at <placeName key="northu"
                        >Northumberland</placeName>, a town standing in the<lb/> point where the
                    east and west branches come toge-<lb/>ther. Here, leaving the commissioners
                    behind, we,<lb/> in company with <persName key="jhain2">Josiah
                    Haines</persName>, proceeded to <persName key="welli1">Wil-<lb/>liam
                        Ellis</persName>'s, and attended <orgName key="muncym">Muncy</orgName>
                    meeting of Friends.<lb/> After which, went to <persName key="swall1">Samuel
                        Wallace</persName>'s, where we<lb/> met the commissioners, and were
                    liberally and friend-<lb/>ly entertained. </p>

            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1793-05-06">5th mo. 6th.</date>
                    <placeName key="ppost"/></dateline>
                <p> The forepart of this day, we passed<lb/> a rapid stream, called the <geogName
                        key="loyalso">Loyalsock</geogName> — and in the af-<lb/>ternoon we crossed
                    another large stream, called <geogName key="lyc">Ly-<lb/>coming</geogName>,
                    seven times — lodged at <persName key="jkyle1">James Kyle</persName>'s.
                    Next<lb/> day rode forty-three miles without any entertain-<lb/>ment on the way,
                    except what we had with us. —<lb/> Where we put up, there was no hay to be had
                    for<lb/> our horses, so we fed them with oats, and tied them<lb/> up for the
                    night— went to bed, or rather lay on the<lb/> floor with our own blankets, in a
                    very small house;<lb/> but rested well. In the morning, the weather was<lb/>
                    fine and pleasant — rode to major <persName key="slind">Samuel
                        Lindley</persName>'s,<lb/> crossed the <geogName key="tioga"
                        >Tioga</geogName> twice, and the <geogName key="cowni">Cownisky</geogName>;
                    then to<lb/> the <placeName key="ppost">Painted Post</placeName>, crossing the
                        <geogName key="cohoc">Cohocton</geogName> at <persName key="dfull"
                        >David<lb/> Fuller</persName>'s. On our way here, we swam our horses<lb/>
                    over the <geogName key="tioga">Tioga</geogName>, and went ourselves in a canoe.
                    The<lb/> country from <placeName key="northu">Northumberland</placeName>to this
                    place, abounds<lb/> with large streams of water, and abundance of flat<lb/> land
                    on their banks, exceedingly rich. We observed<lb/> in many places, old Indian
                    fields, with signs of the <lb/>
                    <pb n="291"/> old corn hills. On each side of these creeks and flats,<lb/> are
                    ridges of mountains. We have now travelled ac-<lb/>cording to the several
                    distances from place to place,<lb/> two hundred, and forty-seven miles. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-09">9th.</date><placeName key="willi"/></dateline>
                <p> Rode about thirty miles, and a little be-<lb/>fore night, got to an old Indian
                    cabin, with fire in<lb/>the middle, where we lodged. We let our horses<lb/>
                    browse awhile in the woods, then fed them with oats<lb/> we had with us, and
                    tied them up for the night. —<lb/> This cabin stands on the bank of the
                        <geogName key="cohoc">Cohocton</geogName> . The<lb/> roads here are new, and
                    of course rough, which is<lb/> trying to the poor horses that are rid hard all
                    day,<lb/> and at night tied to a tree. Next day, rode thirty-<lb/> six miles to
                        <placeName key="willi">Williamsburgh</placeName>. Some parts of the
                    road<lb/> very rough. We passed over some of the steepest<lb/> hills I ever saw
                    travelled. But the country is new<lb/> — and I have no doubt in a few years, the
                    roads will<lb/> be much improved, as there is abundance of excel-<lb/>lent land
                    that is settling fast in some places. Stayed<lb/> this night at captain
                        <persName key="cwilm">Charles Williamson</persName>'s, where we<lb/> were
                    kindly entertained. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-11">11th.</date><placeName key="willi"/></dateline>
                <p> This morning the commissioners despatch-<lb/>ed a messenger to <placeName
                        key="canan">Canandaigua</placeName> for an interpreter;<lb/> so we rested
                    here and were finely refreshed. Set<lb/> out again next day, and rode to
                        <persName key="gberr">Gilbert Berry</persName>'s, on<lb/> the bank of the
                        <geogName key="genes2">Genesee river</geogName>. Here we found<lb/> about
                    fifty Indians collected, amongst whom were<lb/> some of their chiefs; <persName
                        key="farme1">Farmer's Brother</persName>, <persName key="redja1">Red
                        Jacket</persName>,<lb/>
                    <persName key="litbi1">Little Billy</persName>, and others, to all of whom a
                    dinner<lb/> was given by the commissioners. They expressed<lb/> their gladness
                    in seeing us, and we also in seeing<lb/> them. In the evening we had some
                    weighty con-<lb/>versation together, wherein the commissioners im-<lb/>parted a
                    little of their business concerning the treaty; <lb/>
                    <pb n="292"/> which appeared to give general satisfaction. After<lb/> which, the
                    Indians gave our friend <persName key="jparr1">John Parrish</persName> a<lb/>
                    new name, which they in their language call <foreign xml:lang="iro"
                        >Sutte-<lb/>kutte</foreign>, and signifies plain or level. This name
                    was<lb/> given by <persName key="farme1">Farmer's Brother</persName>, at which
                    there was a<lb/> small shout, in their way, and they would have given<lb/> us a
                    song on the occasion; but understanding we were<lb/> a plain people, not
                    accustomed to singing, it was<lb/> omitted, and nothing further followed than a
                    little<lb/> pleasantry. Near ten o'clock we all retired and <lb/> rested
                    bravely. </p>

                <p> In the morning the Indians showed no inclination<lb/> to depart while the
                    commissioners were here.<persName key="redja1">Red<lb/> Jacket</persName> , at
                    the close of one of his speeches last even-<lb/>ing, signified, that when he was
                    in Philadelphia, the<lb/> white people had proposed a method for them to<lb/>
                    turn buffaloes into cows, deer into sheep, and bears<lb/> into hogs; he thought
                    it now a fit time for the com-<lb/>missioners to show them a piece of their
                    skill; as<lb/> they were now on their way to <placeName key="canan"
                        >Canandaigua</placeName> for<lb/> some clothing, &amp;c, and that a good
                    buffalo would be<lb/> very agreeable for provision on the way. The
                    com-<lb/>missioners used some endeavours to obtain a fat cow;<lb/> but as there
                    was none to be had here, they gave them<lb/> a quantity of salt beef, pork, and
                    corn, at which they<lb/> appeared satisfied. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-14">14th</date>.<placeName key="buffc1"/></dateline>
                <p> We prepared to move forward; divers other<lb/> people fell in company with us
                    from <placeName key="schen">Schenectady</placeName>
                    <lb/>and other places, who were going into <placeName key="canad">Upper
                        Cana-<lb/>da</placeName>. We swam our horses over the <geogName key="genes2"
                        >Genesee river</geogName><lb/> with some difficulty, and we, with our
                    baggage,<lb/> crossed in a canoe. In the evening we put up in the<lb/> woods by
                    the side of <geogName key="tonnec">Tonnewanta creek</geogName>, where we<lb/>
                    sheltered for the night with a good fire, and tied up <lb/>
                    <pb n="293"/> our horses as before. The following day we travel-<lb/>led hard,
                    being very desirous to reach some house<lb/> to lodge in. According to the
                    account given us, we<lb/> rode about fifty miles, and truly we thought them<lb/>
                    long enough. Arrived at <geogName key="buffc1">Buffalo Creek</geogName> about
                    sun<lb/> set, and put up at <persName key="winney">landlord Winney</persName>'s;
                    most of us<lb/> lodged on the floor and slept well; also, had plenty<lb/> of
                    grass for the horses. The country we have pass-<lb/>ed through the last two
                    days, is Indian lands, and<lb/> one continued wilderness. Much of the land
                    ap-<lb/>pears very good, with a variety of timber, such as<lb/> oak, hickory,
                    sugar maple, elm, ash, beech, linn,<lb/> pine, cherry, butternut, &amp;c. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-16">16th</date>. <placeName key="nav"/></dateline>
                <p> Rode about three miles to the ferry, nearly<lb/> opposite <placeName key="ferie"
                        >Fort Erie</placeName>, most of the way along the beach<lb/> of <geogName
                        key="lakee">Lake Erie</geogName>. Here we crossed over the outlet of<lb/>
                    the lake, a large and strong current, landed in the<lb/>
                    <placeName key="brit">British dominions</placeName>, and rode down the banks of
                    the<lb/> river to <persName key="cwils">Charles Willson</persName>'s near the
                        <geogName key="niagf">great falls</geogName>. The<lb/> whole distance to
                    this place is four hundred and<lb/> twenty-seven miles. In the evening, walked
                    to<lb/> the brow of the bank to view the mighty cataract.<lb/> Next morning went
                    again, descended a very steep<lb/> hill and walked to the rock over which the
                    water<lb/>falls, which appears tremendous indeed. There are<lb/> rapids above
                    the cataract that fall, it is said, fifty feet<lb/> (and it looks likely to be
                    so) within the distance of<lb/> little more than half a mile. After satisfying
                    our<lb/> curiosity here, the commissioners went on to <persName key="gsim"
                        >gover-<lb/>nor Simcoe</persName>'s, at <placeName key="nav">Navy
                        Hall</placeName>, sixteen miles. This is<lb/> nearly opposite the <placeName
                        key="niafo">garrison</placeName>, which stands on a point<lb/> of land in
                    the United States. <persName key="jparr1">John Parrish</persName>,<persName
                        key="jelli1"> John<lb/> Elliott</persName>, and myself, went about two miles
                    to our <lb/>
                    <pb n="294"/> friend <persName key="wlund1">William Lundy's</persName>, where we
                    were kindly en-<lb/>tertained, and spent most of the next day. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-19">19th</date>. <placeName key="nav"
                        type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> Being first of the week, and having appoint-<lb/>ed a meeting to be held here at
                    the eleventh hour;<lb/> about the time there attended a pretty large
                    collection<lb/> of people, more than the house could contain. We<lb/> thought it
                    a favoured opportunity. After dinner we<lb/> had a solid opportunity with the
                    family and divers<lb/> friends who had stayed with us. Then went about six<lb/>
                    miles to our friend <persName key="jhill1">John Hill's</persName>, who, with his
                    wife,<lb/> had been at the meeting. Here we were kindly en-<lb/>tertained and
                    lodged. In the morning, had a solid<lb/> opportunity with the family, and set
                    out for <placeName key="nav">Navy<lb/> Hall</placeName>, a messenger having been
                    sent to invite us to<lb/> dine with the governor. He appears to be a plain<lb/>
                    man, and remarkably easy of access. At table we<lb/> had the company of the
                    commissioners, <persName key="cbutl1">colonel But-<lb/>ler</persName>, <persName
                        key="mlit">majors Little</persName>, <persName key="hal">Hales</persName>,
                    &amp;c. The governor, when<lb/> we were walking in his garden, said our coming
                    for-<lb/>ward at this time, did our society great honour. To-<lb/>ward evening
                    we rode up the lake about two miles<lb/> to <persName key="peacock">landlord
                        Peacock</persName>'s, and lodged. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-21">21st</date>. <placeName key="nav"
                        type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> We went up the lake twelve miles to <persName key="bpaul">Ben-<lb/>jamin
                        Paulin</persName>'s and his brother <persName key="jpaul">Jesse</persName>'s
                    — our friend,<lb/>
                    <persName key="jparr1">John Parrish</persName>, having a letter from their
                    connexions in<lb/> Philadelphia. Here we were kindly entertained. In<lb/> the
                    woods we came through, we observed the great-<lb/>est quantity of pigeons, I
                    think I ever saw; they<lb/> were flying up the lake, being chiefly young
                    ones,<lb/> and very fat. The people take abundance of them<lb/> with clubs,
                    poles, &amp;c. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-22">22d</date>. <placeName key="nav" type="unattested"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> The weather has been warm and dry since<lb/> the time of our arrival in this
                    country. I continue<lb/> very poorly, but went three miles to our friend
                        <persName key="jtayl2">John <lb/>
                        <pb n="295"/> Taylor's,</persName> though hardly able to travel. Here
                    we<lb/> were kindly treated and lodged. I believe many<lb/> were made glad in
                    seeing their friends come amongst<lb/> them, for whom in their wilderness
                    situation, we<lb/> often felt near sympathy. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-23">23d</date>. <placeName key="short"/></dateline>
                <p> I felt much better in health, and understand-<lb/>ing divers Friends live at a
                    place called the <geogName key="short">Short<lb/> Hills</geogName>, about twelve
                    miles off, we concluded to go<lb/> there. On the way we dined at <persName
                        key="trice1">Thomas Rice</persName>'s, and<lb/> thence proceeded to
                        <persName key="jgilh1">Joshua Gillam</persName>'s. We passed<lb/> through
                    some land where we saw the effects of a<lb/> hurricane that was on the 1st of
                    the 7th month last,<lb/> and truly I may say, I never saw so great
                    destruc-<lb/>tion of timber. For about two miles in width, and<lb/> said to be
                    many miles in length, there was scarce a<lb/> single tree left that was not torn
                    up by the roots, or<lb/> broken off. This tract, as far as we have passed
                    over,<lb/> appears excellent land, with a variety of good tim-<lb/>ber — white
                    and black oak, hickory, chestnut, poplar,<lb/> white pine, walnut, cherry,
                    &amp;c. We, finding a few<lb/> Friends settled in this neighborhood, concluded
                    to<lb/> stay amongst them over first-day, and have a meet-<lb/>ing with them. In
                    the interval, we visited at <persName key="jcraw1">James<lb/>
                        Crawford</persName>'s, <persName key="esnig1">Enoch Scrigley</persName>'s,
                    and <persName key="jdarl1">John Dorlin</persName>g's,<lb/> where the meeting is
                    proposed to be held. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-26">26th</date>. <placeName key="nav"/></dateline>
                <p> We had a considerable gathering of people<lb/> that behaved orderly, among whom
                    we had a satis-<lb/>factory opportunity. In the afternoon, set out on<lb/> our
                    way to <placeName key="nav">Navy Hall</placeName> , and lodged at <persName
                        key="jmoor2">Jeremiah<lb/> Moore</persName>'s. Having heard of the arrival
                    of the other<lb/> Friends that came by the way of <placeName key="alban'"
                        >Albany</placeName>, we rose<lb/> early next morning, and went to our friend
                        <persName key="bhill1">Benja-<lb/>min Hill</persName>'s, where we took
                    breakfast — then rode to<lb/> the landing, and thence to <placeName key="nav">
                        Navy Hall</placeName>. Spent a little <lb/><pb n="296"/> time at the
                    governor's, and went back to the landing,<lb/> where we met with <persName
                        key="jlind1">Jacob Lindley</persName>, <persName key="wsave1">William
                        Savery</persName>,<lb/> and <persName key="whart">William
                        Hartshorne</persName>, who had come on by wa-<lb/>ter. Our stores were
                    landed here, and we all dined<lb/> at <persName key="csmith">captain
                        Smith</persName>'s, at the mess house. In the after-<lb/>noon we set up our
                    tents on the hill, and lodged all<lb/> together. This seemed very pleasant,
                    being all in<lb/> health, and they having had a favourable passage from<lb/> New
                    York to this place, and very agreeable compa-<lb/>ny with <persName
                        key="genlinc">general Lincoln</persName>, in their covered <term>batteaux
                    </term>,<lb/> two of which they propose taking up to <geogName key="lakee">Lake
                        Erie</geogName>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-28">28th</date>. <placeName key="nav"/></dateline>
                <p> Having had a good night's rest in our tents,<lb/> were in the morning all
                    bravely. When we shall<lb/> move forward from this place appears at present
                    un-<lb/>certain, as the commissioners sent off an express yes-<lb/>terday to
                        <placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName> on some important
                    occasion,<lb/> and expect to wait his return. Young <persName key="habee1"
                        >Cornplanter</persName><lb/> went some days ago to his father's, about one
                    hun-<lb/>dred and fifty miles from this place. The Indians,<lb/> we understand,
                    are gathering from many parts to the<lb/> place appointed. Some of the <orgName
                        key="Mohawk">Mohawks</orgName> are now<lb/> here. We shortly expect a number
                    of the <orgName key="sxntns">Five Na-<lb/>tions</orgName>. <persName
                        key="jlind1">Jacob Lindley</persName> being desirous to see <persName
                        key="jmoor2">Jeremiah<lb/> Moore</persName>, we two rode there, spent the
                    afternoon, and<lb/> lodged. The weather cool and cloudy, with east-<lb/>erly
                    winds. The next day was rainy. We are now<lb/> within about three miles of the
                    great cataract — the<lb/> noise of which is much like the roaring of the sea
                    in<lb/> time of storm. The people gave us a particular ac-<lb/>count of their
                    distressed situation, about four years<lb/> ago, for want of bread, and their
                    loss of cattle and<lb/> horses; which was truly alarming ; but through the<lb/>
                    goodness of kind Providence, they have now plenty <lb/><pb n="297"/> of bread
                    and other necessaries; and plenty of good<lb/> sugar which they make from the
                    maple tree. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-30">30th</date>. <placeName key="nav"
                        type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p>
                    <persName key="jelli1">John Elliott</persName> came up from our camp at the<lb/>
                    landing, and we, with <persName key="jmoor2">Jeremiah Moore</persName> and
                        <persName key="bhill1">Benjamin<lb/> Hill</persName>, went to the <geogName
                        key="niagf">Falls,</geogName> where <persName key="jlind1">Jacob</persName>
                    had not been,<lb/> and viewed them in a different direction from what<lb/> we
                    had done before. In this as well as many other<lb/> things, the mighty works of
                    Providence are emi-<lb/>nently displayed, being far beyond the power of
                    hu-<lb/>man art to form. Some of our company descended<lb/> the mighty hill, by
                    the clefts of rocks and the help<lb/> of Indian ladders, to the water below,
                    supposed one<lb/> hundred and ten feet. Here they saw divers curi-<lb/>osities,
                    and brought up some memorials of stone,<lb/> bones, &amp;c. We then returned to
                    our camp, and I<lb/> lodged at <persName key="bcanb1">Benjamin
                    Canby</persName>'s. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-31">31st</date>. <placeName key="nav"
                        type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> We had at our little camp, the company of<lb/>
                    <persName key="haupa1">captain Hendricks</persName> and several other Indians,
                    that fed<lb/> on our provisions — and a white man, lately from<lb/>
                    <placeName key="pitts">Pittsburg</placeName>, informed that the Indians from the
                    south-<lb/>ward were coming on. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-01">6th. mo. 1st.</date>
                    <placeName key="nav"/></dateline>
                <p> The weather wet and little business<lb/> to be done — though the article
                    provision meets with<lb/> a large consumption — we being all in pretty good<lb/>
                    health, and for the most part a number of Indians and<lb/> others at our camp.
                    The commissioners are most of<lb/> the time at <placeName key="nav">Navy
                        Hall</placeName> with <persName key="gsim">governor Simcoe.</persName>
                    We<lb/> expect to move forward in a day or two, towards<lb/>
                    <placeName key="ferie"> Fort Erie</placeName>, to take passage in a vessel for
                        <placeName key="detro">Detriot</placeName> —<lb/> the commissioners not
                    likely to go from this under<lb/> a week or ten days. We endeavour to fill up
                    our<lb/> time in seeing our friends. This afternoon <persName key="jparr1">John
                        Par-<lb/>rish</persName> and <persName key="jelli1">John Elliott</persName>,
                    crossed the river and went to <lb/><pb n="298"/> an Indian settlement of about
                    eighty families, who<lb/> received them kindly. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-02">2d</date>, <placeName key="nav"/></dateline>
                <p> and first of the week, we held a meeting about <lb/>four miles from the landing,
                    in a large barn, of which<lb/> previous notice had been given. The collection
                    was<lb/> large, and proved a solid opportunity. I hope it<lb/> tended to the
                    advancement of our religious testimo-<lb/>ny. Divers Friends came many miles to
                    attend it.<lb/> After which, <persName key="wsave1">William Savery
                    </persName>and <persName key="whart"> William Harts-<lb/>horne</persName>
                    returned to our camp, in order to send for-<lb/>ward our baggage to-morrow to
                    the upper landing<lb/> above the Falls. <persName key="jparr1">John
                        Parrish</persName>, <persName key="jlind1">Jacob
                        Lindley</persName>,<persName key="jelli1">John<lb/> Elliott</persName> , and
                    myself, went to <persName key="jmoor2">Jeremiah Moore</persName>'s and<lb/>
                    dined — thence to <persName key="wlund1">William Lundy</persName>'s and lodged.
                        <persName key="eburc1">Es-<lb/>quire Burch</persName> was at meeting, and
                    kept company with<lb/> us thus far. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-03">3d</date>.<placeName key="ferie" type="unattested"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> Went on to <persName key="eburc1"> esquire Burch </persName>'s, where we
                    dined.<lb/> Bought three barrels of flour and sent forward to<lb/>
                    <orgName key="chip">Chipaway</orgName>, to be carried on with the rest of
                    our<lb/> baggage, to <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>.<persName
                        key="jparr1"> John Parrish</persName>, <persName key="jelli1">John
                        Elliott</persName><lb/>, and myself, rode up the river about seven miles
                    and<lb/> lodged at our friend <persName key="richa">Richardsun's</persName>.
                    Next morning<lb/> went to <persName key="bwill1">Benjamin Willson</persName>'s,
                    whose wife is a near<lb/> relation of mine. <persName key="bwill1"
                        >Benjamin</persName> went with us six miles<lb/> to the Fort. Here are the
                    king's stores, and a har-<lb/>bour for shipping — several topsail vessels were
                    then<lb/> lying here. We went on board the Dunmore, <persName key="cford1"
                        >cap-<lb/>tain Ford</persName>, bound to <placeName key="detro"
                        >Detroit</placeName>. The cabin passengers<lb/> besides ourselves were
                        <persName key="rinn1"> Robert Inne</persName>, <persName key="Newm"
                        >Newman</persName><lb/> and servant,<persName key="rhill1"> Richard Hillery
                        </persName> and servant,<persName key="wmcco1"> Dr. Wil-<lb/>liam
                        M'Casky</persName>, <persName key="jheck1">John Heckevvelder</persName> and
                        <persName key="wwils1">William<lb/> Willson</persName>. These, with the
                    sailors and marines(be<lb/>ing a king's ship) and about sixty Indians of
                    four<lb/> different tribes bound to the treaty, made our whole<lb/>
                    <pb n="299"/> crew about ninety. We left our horses in the care<lb/> of
                        <persName key="bwill1">Benjamin Willson</persName> — next day set sail and
                    steered<lb/> up the lake. We had fine pleasant weather until the<lb/> 8th, when
                    being near the islands towards the head <lb/>of the lake, and dark night coming
                    on us, we stood<lb/> off and on till morning — had several squalls of rain,<lb/>
                    and short blasts of high wind, with thunder and<lb/> lightning — which was
                    somewhat alarming, as our<lb/> ship had on board a large quantity of powder.
                    But<lb/> through the goodness of kind Providence we were<lb/> preserved from
                    damage. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-09">9th</date>, <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> and first of the week; — fine pleasant morning<lb/> with light airs of wind. The
                    islands now appeared<lb/> in sight. This day we had a small meeting in the<lb/>
                    cabin with our fellow passengers and two Indian<lb/> chiefs. In the evening
                    entered the mouth of <geogName key="detro"> Detriot<lb/> river</geogName>, and
                    anchored till morning; when we ran up<lb/> the beautiful river a northerly
                    course, with a fair<lb/> wind to <placeName key="detro">Detroit</placeName>.
                    This is a small garrison town, with<lb/> a variety of inhabitants. Here is much
                    of the sound<lb/> of drums and trumpets, but not much religion. The<lb/> people
                    here, as well as those on board our ship, were<lb/> very respectful to us — and
                    there was great harmony<lb/> amongst ourselves. Thanks be to kind
                    Providence<lb/> for all his unmerited favours. Here we landed our<lb/> small
                    baggage, and took lodgings at <persName key="mdols">Matthew
                        Dol-<lb/>son's</persName> for the present. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-11">11th.</date>
                    <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> Found our accommodations comfortable and<lb/> easy. We visited the
                        commandant,<persName key="cengl1">colonel Eng-<lb/>land</persName>, and
                    showed him our passport from <persName key="gsim">governor <lb/>
                        Simcoe</persName>, at <placeName key="niaga">Niagara</placeName>, and are
                    now waiting the com-<lb/>missioners coming forward, which we hope may be<lb/>
                    soon. From the present complexion of things, it<lb/> looks likely to be some
                    time before the treaty com-<lb/>
                    <pb n="300"/>mences; so that we find patience very necessary to<lb/> be
                    exercised. We hear many sentiments expressed,<lb/> some favourable and some
                    otherwise. Hope our<lb/> minds may not be diverted by either from that
                    hum-<lb/>ble dependence on the omnipotent Arm of power,<lb/> under whose banner,
                    I trust, we have enlisted in the<lb/> righteous cause of peace-makers. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-12">12th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> Took a walk down the bank of the river,<lb/> about three miles to a fine spring,
                    of which there<lb/> are few hereabouts. The inhabitants mostly use the<lb/>
                    river water, which is said to be very wholesome.<lb/> The banks of this river
                    for many miles above and<lb/> below the town, are very thickly settled,
                    mostly<lb/> with French, who have fine orchards and meadows,<lb/> and good wheat
                    growing. Their grain is mostly<lb/> manufactured by wind-mills, of which there
                    are<lb/> many in sight. The inhabitants of the town are as<lb/> great a mixture,
                    I think, as I ever knew in any one<lb/> place. English, Scotch, Irish, Dutch,
                    French, Ame-<lb/>ricans from different states, with black and yellow,<lb/> and
                    seldom clear of Indians of different tribes in the<lb/> day time. These are all
                    turned out by nine o'clock<lb/> at night, and the gates are shut — sentries are
                    placed<lb/> constantly in various parts round tire town, which is <lb/>enclosed
                    with high pickets. There is no place of wor-<lb/>ship except one <orgName
                        key="catholic">Roman Catholic</orgName> chapel. There are<lb/> large ships
                    employed on these waters, some of which<lb/> are from one hundred to one hundred
                    and fifty tons<lb/> burden; they sail up to <placeName key="michi"
                        >Michillimackinac</placeName>, several<lb/> hundred miles from this place,
                    and return with<lb/> abundance of peltry — the staple commodity of this<lb/>
                    country. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-13">13th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p>
                    <persName key="jparr1">John Parrish</persName>, <persName key="jelli1">John
                        Elliott</persName>, and myself,<lb/> dined with the commandant, <persName
                        key="cengl1">colonel Richard Eng-<lb/>land</persName>, <pb n="301"/> and a
                    number of other officers, and were friend-<lb/>ly and liberally entertained.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-14">14th</date>. <geogName key="thame" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> Took passage in a small boat, bound up the<lb/> river <geogName key="latr"
                        >Latrench</geogName>, on the east side of <geogName key="lstc">Lake St.
                        Clair,</geogName>
                    <lb/> with a fair wind — passed through the lake, more than<lb/> twenty miles
                    over, and went up the river about fif-<lb/>teen miles, to <persName key="idols"
                        >Isaac Dolson</persName>'s, where we lodged. —<lb/> Next day, with some
                    Indians in a canoe, proceed-<lb/>ed up the river about twenty miles, to
                        <persName key="edwa1">Edward<lb/> Watson</persName>'s, son of <persName
                        key="twat1">Thomas</persName>, of New York<lb/>, an intimate<lb/>
                    acquaintance. The respect I felt for him and his<lb/> connections induced me to
                    take this tour to see him,<lb/> and know how he fared here. He and his wife
                    re-<lb/>ceived me kindly. They are connected with the<lb/>
                    <orgName key="moravian">Moravian brethren</orgName>, and were very civil to me.
                        <persName key="jheck1">John <lb/>Heckewelder</persName>, Indian interpreter
                    and Moravian <lb/>minister, was passenger with me as far as <persName
                        key="jdols1">Dolson</persName>'s,<lb/> where he took horse and went up the
                    river to visit<lb/> his brethren at a settlement of that people. This<lb/>
                    appears to be a beautiful new country, just settling;<lb/> fine wheat, corn,
                    peas, &amp;c. now growing, and grass<lb/> in abundance; — the timber, white and
                    black oak,<lb/> cherry, hickory, black and white walnut, ash, linn,<lb/> poplar,
                    &amp;c. I am informed it continues in that way<lb/> for one hundred and fifty
                    miles up this river — the<lb/> the general course of which runs about east from
                    its<lb/> mouth, and the farther up, it is said, the better the<lb/> land. The
                    inhabitants here appear to want as much<lb/> cultivation as the lands they live
                    on. May the Lord's<lb/> power so reach their hearts, as to bring them into<lb/>
                    subjection to his Divine will. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-16">16th</date>, <placeName key="thame" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> and first of the week, after breakfast took<lb/> leave of this family in a solid
                    manner, and returned<lb/> to <persName key="jdols1">Dolson</persName>'s: on the
                    way, called at several houses <lb/><pb n="302"/> where divers were collected,
                    being much accustom-<lb/>ed to visit each other on first-days, — among whom<lb/>
                    I had several opportunities for religious conversa-<lb/>tion, and informing them
                    of our principles. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-17">17th</date>.<placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> The boat being ready for sailing, having on<lb/> board about twenty-five bushels
                    of wheat, we got<lb/> under way, and had a pleasant passage to the town,<lb/>
                    where we arrived about ten o'clock in the evening.<lb/> The gates being shut, we
                    were obliged to lodge with-<lb/>out the pickets. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-18">18th</date>.<placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> Went early into the town — found all my<lb/> dear friends well; they gave me an
                    account of two<lb/> public meetings held by them; one with the inhabi-<lb/>tants
                    of the town and soldiers, and a number of the<lb/> officers, in the forenoon;
                    and another in the country<lb/> in the afternoon, both to pretty good satisfaction.<lb/>
                    <persName key="jlind1">Jacob Lindley</persName>, <persName key="wsave1">William
                        Savery</persName>, and <persName key="whart">William
                        Harts-<lb/>horne</persName>, dined with the commandant yesterday.With<lb/>
                    respect to Indian affairs, things look dull and gloomy<lb/> — the commissioners
                    not yet come forward; so that<lb/> we are here in suspense with respect to the
                    time of <lb/> the opening of the treaty, and hear many frightful <lb/> stories
                    about the conduct of the Indians; but we en-<lb/>deavour to keep our minds
                    quiet, trusting in the<lb/> arm of divine power for preservation, and
                    believing<lb/> we are engaged in the righteous cause of promoting<lb/> peace on
                    earth and good will to men. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-19">19th</date>. <geogName key="detror" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p>
                    <persName key="wsave1">William Savery </persName>not very well — the rest<lb/>
                    of our company, to wit, Friends, went down the<lb/> river in a small boat, about
                    four miles, to <persName key="farno1">Frederick<lb/> Arnold</persName>'s, where
                    we dined — then went on foot about<lb/> two miles to <persName key="jmess1">John
                        Messemer</persName>'s, who is of the reli-<lb/>gious society called <orgName
                        key="dunkers">Dunker's</orgName>, — with whom and<lb/>divers of his friends
                    and neighbours we held a <lb/><pb n="303"/> meeting, which was a solid,
                    satisfactory opportuni-<lb/>ty, I believe, to them and us. Here we lodged. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-20">20th</date>. <geogName key="detror" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> After a solid opportunity with the family,<lb/> we went on towards our boat —
                    dined at <persName key="fcorn1">Francis<lb/> Cornwell</persName>’s; the weather
                    being wet and the wind<lb/> ahead, <persName key="whart">William
                        Hartshorne</persName> and I lodged here — the<lb/> rest of our company went
                    to <persName key="farno1">Frederick Arnold</persName>'s. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-21">21st</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> In the afternoon, <persName key="jelli1">John Elliott</persName> and <persName
                        key="jlind1">Jacob<lb/> Lindley</persName> went on foot up the river and
                    crossed over<lb/> to the town. The others lodged here — being very<lb/> kindly
                    entertained. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-22">22d</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> Set out and rowed up to the town — found<lb/>
                    <persName key="wsave1">William Savery</persName> and the rest of our company
                    all<lb/> well. We have frequently been visited by num-<lb/>bers of the Indian
                    chiefs that were on their way to<lb/>
                    <placeName key="sandu">Sandusky</placeName>, who mostly called us <foreign
                        xml:id="undetermined">Shemucteman</foreign>, or<lb/> long knives, the term
                    they use to describe the Ame-<lb/>ricans of the United States; but when informed
                    what<lb/> we were, they signified they had heard of our being<lb/> come, and
                    were glad. This day, we were visited<lb/> by several that had just come to town.
                    We observ-<lb/>ed the generality of all the tribes had a remarkable<lb/> thirst
                    for rum; and when intoxicated, were very<lb/> troublesome. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-23">23d</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> First of the week, we held a meeting in a<lb/> large sail loft in the shipyard;
                    had a considerable<lb/> gathering of the town's people, and a few soldiers,<lb/>
                    who behaved quietly. The meeting held about two<lb/> hours and a half, and I
                    believe, ended well. In the<lb/> afternoon had some more Indians to visit us, of the<lb/>
                    <orgName key="ojibwe"> Chipaway nation</orgName>; one of whom, called a chief,
                    was<lb/> pretty clean dressed, which is not general among<lb/> that nation. </p>
                <pb n="304"/>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1793-06-24">24th</date>. <geogName key="rushr" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> Our landlord's boat set out for the <geogName key="rushr">river<lb/>
                        Rushe</geogName>, with grain, to the mill. I took passage<lb/> therein with
                        <persName key="wsave1">William Savery</persName>. <persName key="mdols"
                        >Matthew Dolson</persName><lb/> met us at the mill, and <persName
                        key="wsave1">William</persName>returned with him<lb/> in the evening; I
                    stayed all night at <persName key="jtrox">Jacob Troxler</persName>'s,<lb/> a
                    Dutchman, who served his time in Jersey. The<lb/> people were as kind as it was
                    in their power. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-25">25th</date>.<placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> The boat with the cargo being ready, we<lb/> rowed most of the way home, being
                    about ten<lb/> miles. This river is called <geogName key="rushr"
                        >Rushe</geogName>, which signifies<lb/> red, and the water appears stained
                    with something<lb/> which causes it to appear with remarkable red-<lb/>ness.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-26">26th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p>
                    <persName key="jheck1">John Heckewelder</persName> returned from <geogName
                        key="latr">Latrench <lb/> river</geogName>; with him came a number of the
                        <orgName key="moraind">Moravian<lb/> Indians</orgName>, who adhere to the
                    religion of that family<lb/> of the brethren. We understand they suffered<lb/>
                    much in the time of the late war, and since, — hav-<lb/>ing had a number of
                    their friends killed by the<lb/> white people, with the loss of most of their
                    sub-<lb/>stance, of which they had plenty while in their<lb/> peaceable
                    habitations at <placeName key="musk">Muskingum</placeName>. They were<lb/> now
                    in the sixth place of their retreat, in the <orgName key="brit">Bri-<lb/>tish
                        government</orgName>, and on good land. Our commis-<lb/>eration was excited
                    by the above account, and we<lb/> granted some relief to the amount of one
                    hundred<lb/> dollars, which they received thankfully. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-27">27th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> The Indians are every day here, on their<lb/> way to the treaty. Twenty-eight
                    are just arrived<lb/> from <placeName key="michi">Michillimackinac</placeName>,
                    some of whom I saw this<lb/> morning; they were well dressed, curiously
                    painted,<lb/> and decorated with wampum, and ear and nose bobs;<lb/> all young,
                    and the handsomest I think I have as<lb/> yet seen. They appeared good humoured
                    and plea-<lb/>sant, <lb/>
                    <pb n="305"/> having, as I was informed, brought no arms or<lb/> warlike
                    instruments with them, except their bows<lb/> and arrows, with flutes for music,
                    of their own<lb/> making, which appeared simple, but pleasing to<lb/>
                    themselves. Some of the British officers asked<lb/> them to play, which they
                    readily did, by putting<lb/> the instrument to the mouth, and sometimes to
                    the<lb/> nose; as handily to the one as the other.</p>

                <p> This evening had the company of <persName key="cdrak1">capt. John
                        Drake</persName>,<lb/> a coaster between this and <placeName key="macki"
                        >Mackinaw</placeName>, distant one<lb/> hundred and thirty leagues — sails
                    in a sloop of se-<lb/>venty or eighty tons burthen. He gave us some<lb/> account
                    of the north-west fur trade, and the man-<lb/>ner of its being carried on by the
                    companies con-<lb/>cerned, who employ many hundred men, that stay<lb/> many
                    years in the country, travelling and trading<lb/> with the northern Indians for
                    peltry; an abundance<lb/> of which, of the richest kind, is brought from
                    the<lb/> high northern latitudes, which nets the companies<lb/> very large
                    profit. But among what people, or in<lb/> what part of the world, except the
                        <orgName key="lowcan">Canadian French</orgName>,<lb/> could persons be found
                    for their purpose, I know<lb/> not. They are allowed a very small portion
                    of<lb/> provisions from this to the <placeName key="grandp">Grand
                        Portage</placeName>, at the<lb/> head of <geogName key="lakes">Lake
                        Superior</geogName>, which is about eight hun-<lb/>dred miles; there they
                    are allowed about one bushel<lb/> (forty-two quarts French measure) of Indian
                    corn<lb/> per man, for a year, and a little fat, which they<lb/> may use at
                    their own discretion. The corn is pre-<lb/>pared in a curious manner at
                        <placeName key="detro"> Detroit</placeName>, being first<lb/> boiled in
                    strong lye, which takes off the outside<lb/> hull; afterwards it is spread out
                    and dried, then<lb/> packed up for use. With this they set out, and re-<lb/>
                    turn not until the end of the year, when a fresh <lb/>
                    <pb n="306"/> supply of goods is taken up with canoes, &amp;c. by<lb/> many
                    hundred men to the <placeName key="grandp">Portage</placeName>, where they
                    ex-<lb/>change commodities to a very great amount. Thus<lb/> goes on the trade
                    from year to year. The men in<lb/> the north live principally on fish, and the
                    flesh of<lb/> beasts of divers kinds, without bread or salt, and<lb/> when they
                    return appear as robust and healthy, and<lb/> even more so than those who live
                    on the greatest<lb/> delicacies. The principal fish in <geogName key="lakes"
                        >Lake Superior</geogName> are<lb/> the white fish and salmon trout, which
                    are fine<lb/> and delicate: we have eat of them, brought fresh from<lb/> the
                    lake to this place in six days. </p>
                <p> We understand one <persName key="mkenz1">M'Kenzie</persName> is now out
                    with<lb/> ten men, exploring the <placeName key="northw"> North-west
                        Territory</placeName> : he<lb/> once attempted it before; was out more than
                    a year,<lb/> and discovered large frozen waters in the north, but,<lb/> whether
                    lakes or ocean, he knew not — supposed the<lb/> latter, the water being salt. </p>

                <p>
                    <persName key="cdrak1">Captain Drake</persName>, by his own account, had been
                    se-<lb/>veral voyages to <placeName key="afri">Africa</placeName>, in the horrid
                    business of <lb/>fetching slaves, which he now very much condemns.<lb/> He told
                    us many curious tales; — and is certainly<lb/> a very temperate man with respect
                    to drink, taking<lb/> nothing but water — a rare instance in a seafaring<lb/>
                    man. Happy would it be for many thousands in<lb/> the world, were his example
                    followed in that re-<lb/>spect; families would be preserved from ruin and<lb/>
                    distress, morality increase, the poor Indians be<lb/> saved from many acts of
                    violence, and the end of<lb/> our creation be more fully answered by
                    honouring<lb/> God, our Creator. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-28">28th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> We are frequently visited by the officers of<lb/> this place, both civil and
                    military, who appear<lb/> friendly, and treat us with much respect, often <lb/>
                    <pb n="307"/> wishing us success in our laudable undertaking; as-<lb/>suring us,
                    that nothing should be wanting that lay<lb/> in their power, to render us happy
                    and comfortable.<lb/> The commandant said, that if he apprehended dan-<lb/>ger
                    at any time, he should lay his commands on us<lb/> not to depart the place. But,
                    although we sought<lb/> not the protection of military power, we were not<lb/>
                    insensible of his great good will towards us, which<lb/> we were not wanting to
                    acknowledge. </p>

                <p> Visits from the Indians are almost every day re-<lb/>peated, by different tribes
                    constantly coming in,<lb/>, this being the thoroughfare for all the northern
                    In-<lb/>dians. It would be difficult to describe the various<lb/> appearances
                    they make, and languages they speak.<lb/> It is wonderful to find the vast
                    expense the <orgName key="brit">British<lb/> government</orgName> is at with
                    this people. <persName key="gsim1">Governor Sim-<lb/>coe</persName> said it cost
                    them thirty thousand pounds per an-<lb/>num. Here are agents appointed, that are
                    daily<lb/> giving out large quantities of provision, &amp;c. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-29">29th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> This day had a visit from a <orgName key="wyandot">Wyandot</orgName> chief,<lb/>
                    who appeared to have much concern respecting the<lb/> approaching treaty, and
                    mentioned the remem-<lb/>brance of some long and broad belts that were
                    given<lb/> out in former treaties, intended to bind us by the<lb/> hands and
                    arms, so that no small accident in future<lb/> should be able to make a
                    separation; and, notwith-<lb/>standing all that had happened, they (<orgName
                        key="wyandot">the Wyan-<lb/>dots</orgName>) felt some of the old affection
                    to remain, and he<lb/> hoped we would find it so at the general council;<lb/>
                    but could speak for none but themselves. We as-<lb/>sured him we had the same
                    love and friendship for<lb/> them and all others, as our forefathers had, and
                    that<lb/> our principles had always restrained us from war;<lb/> and when we
                    believed the government was disposed <lb/>
                    <pb n="308"/> to make peace with them on principles of justice,<lb/> we were
                    made willing to leave our homes and take<lb/> this long journey to endeavour to
                    promote it, and<lb/> to be present at the concluding of so good a work.<lb/> He
                    said, he knew long ago, we did not fight, but<lb/> were for peace, and that, as
                    we had come a long<lb/> journey, preserved in health, it was evident the<lb/>
                    Great Spirit was pleased with our coming, and he<lb/> hoped some good would be
                    done, and that the<lb/> Great Spirit would bring us home in health and<lb/>
                    safety. </p>

                <p> We had a visit also this morning from <persName key="Ab">Abram</persName>,
                    an<lb/> Indian chief, <persName key="katha">Katharine</persName> his wife, and
                    their daugh-<lb/>ters, richly clad, with plates of silver, &amp;c. </p>

                <p> The introduction of distilled spirits among the<lb/> people appears to have been
                    their ruin. The frauds,<lb/> in consequence of it, imposed upon them, taking
                    in<lb/> the ravages and depredations of war made amongst<lb/> themselves, with
                    multiplied murders and thefts,<lb/> seems to have prevented their being a
                    wealthy peo-<lb/>ple. The contrary with many is sorrowfully their <lb/>
                    situation, I fear to our condemnation; yet the his-<lb/>tory of Indian
                    barbarity, and breach of faith to<lb/> white people, and to one another, which
                    we have<lb/> heard related since we came here, would be shock-<lb/>ing to
                    recite, and is almost at times ready to stagger<lb/> the faith of their best
                    friends. One of the <orgName key="moravian">Moravian<lb/> missionaries</orgName>
                    signified his sense, that if peace should<lb/> be concluded, it would not last
                    long, until they were<lb/> further chastised. <persName key="jparr1">John
                        Parrish</persName> asked, by what<lb/> means? Did he mean the sword? He was
                    answered,<lb/> yes. This sentiment, from one of those who make<lb/> profession
                    of the peaceable principles of the gospel,<lb/> was really discouraging. </p>


                <pb n="309"/>
                <p> We often hear many frightful things suggested; as,<lb/> that we shall be either
                    killed, or kept as hostages at<lb/> the ensuing council. This, with the accounts
                    of the<lb/> Indian warriors in time past, frequently passing with<lb/> numbers
                    of scalps and their disconsolate prisoners,<lb/> seemed dreadful; yet we are not
                    discouraged from<lb/> pursuing our first prospect; believing he that put us<lb/>
                    forth, will go before us, if we are not wanting on our<lb/> part. </p>

                <p> It must be said to the honour of British humani-<lb/>ty, and in commendation of
                    this government of Up-<lb/>per <placeName key="canad">Canada</placeName>, and
                    its truly respectable and generous<lb/> officers, that they have interfered to
                    the relief of<lb/> great numbers of persons, and obtained their redemp-<lb/>tion
                    at a great price; divers of whom that we met<lb/> with appeared as the outcasts
                    of <placeName key="euro">Europe</placeName> ; some of<lb/> them, as <persName
                        key="cengl1">colonel England"</persName> and other officers told us,<lb/>
                    hardly had manners or gratitude to acknowledge<lb/> the kindness, though in some
                    instances it cost one<lb/> hundred pounds. But in the case of a real
                    Ameri-<lb/>can, they never grudged it. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-30">30th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> First of the week. This morning we were<lb/> visited by a principal man of the
                        <orgName key="wyandot">Wyandots</orgName>, called<lb/> the <persName
                        key="bchie1">Blind Chief</persName>, with his nephew, grand, and great<lb/>
                    grandson; with whom we had some friendly con-<lb/>versation. He told us eight of
                    their principal men<lb/> were gone on to the council. We held meetings<lb/> fore
                    and afternoon in the king's sail loft, to a good<lb/> degree of satisfaction;
                    being largely attended by the<lb/> citizens, officers, and soldiers, who behaved
                    quietly. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-01">7th mo. 1st</date>. </dateline>
                <p> Took breakfast with <persName key="celli1"> captain Elliot</persName>,<lb/>
                    Indian commissioner. After which, went to the bu-<lb/>rial of <persName
                        key="ishon">Isidore Shone</persName> at the Roman chapel. He was<lb/> an old
                    Indian interpreter, supposed to have shorten-</p>

                <p>
                    <pb n="310"/> ed his days by the immoderate use of strong drink.<lb/> On this
                    occasion there was a good deal of form and<lb/> ceremony, in their way. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-02">2d</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> Yesterday arrived the ship Ottoway,<persName key="ccow"> captain<lb/>
                        Cowan</persName> , from <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>. He
                    brought about eighty<lb/> Indians — more than sixty were landed at <geogName
                        key="miamr1">Mia-<lb/>mi rapids</geogName>, with <persName key="cbutl1"
                        >colonel Butler</persName>; eighteen of the <orgName key="oneida"
                        >Onei-<lb/>das</orgName> were on board here. It was said <persName
                        key="cbutl1">Butler</persName> was<lb/> fearful they might be hurt by some
                    other Indians<lb/> that were there, on account of some dislike they had<lb/> to
                    one of their chiefs, who had given his interest in<lb/> favour of the Americans,
                    in such a manner as to cre-<lb/>ate jealousies amongst them. They,
                    notwithstand-<lb/>ing apprehend themselves quite safe in the British<lb/> lines,
                    where the tribes of all the nations from east,<lb/> west, north, and south, are
                    daily supplied with pro-<lb/>visions, &amp;c. And we hear nothing but wishes for
                    <lb/> peace among the people every where.</p>

                <p> This day we crossed the river in our landlord's<lb/> boat, with himself, wife,
                    &amp;c. to his farm, where we<lb/> regaled ourselves with fine ripe cherries,
                    and to-<lb/>wards evening returned. The weather very warm,<lb/> and for many
                    days past it has been very wet — but<lb/> through divine favour we are all
                    preserved in good<lb/> health. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-03">3d</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> We had a visit from <persName key="cengl1">colonel England</persName>, who
                    is<lb/> constantly manifesting his regard in a very respect-<lb/>ful manner. He
                    invited us to walk with him to his<lb/> garden, and some of our company went. We
                    had<lb/> also the company, at our lodgings, of a young <orgName key="shawnee"
                        >Shaw-<lb/>neese</orgName> chief, neatly and richly dressed in Indian<lb/>
                    style; he stayed and dined with us, behaving with<lb/> decency at table. But we
                    sometimes find great dif-<lb/>ficulty in conversing with the Indians, in such
                    man-<lb/>
                    <pb n="311"/> tier as we wish, on account of our interpreter's sen-<lb/>timents
                    and prospects differing in some respects so<lb/> widely from ours. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-04">4th.</date>
                    <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> I was this day very poorly with a fever.—<lb/> We were visited by fourteen of
                    the Indians that<lb/> came in the Ottoway, with one Shawnee, who find-<lb/>ing
                    our <persName key="wmcco1">doctor M'Caskey</persName> had been with <persName
                        key="gstcl1">St. Clair's<lb/> army </persName>at the time of the defeat,
                    told him, <said who="undetermined">you're<lb/> my friend, though you ran away
                        from me once.</said>
                </p>

                <p> The commissioners are not yet arrived — we are<lb/> still in suspense, and weary
                    of our long detention<lb/> here — though we are well supplied with
                    provisions,<lb/> &amp;c, and decently treated by our respectable land-<lb/>lord
                    and landlady, as well as by the inhabitants in<lb/> general, being often invited
                    to dine, &amp;c. In the even-<lb/>ing I felt better and slept pretty well. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-05">5th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> We are much confined within the narrow<lb/> limits of this small garrisoned
                    town, where, the<lb/> streets being narrow, there is a want of air. A
                    fa-<lb/>vourable opportunity presenting for a small tour on<lb/> the water, we,
                    except <persName key="wsave1">William Savery</persName> and <persName
                        key="whart">William<lb/> Hartshorne</persName>, went in a boat, provided by
                    our friend<lb/>
                    <persName key="wbak1">William Baker</persName>, up the river about nine miles, to<lb/>
                    <persName key="nwill1">Nathan Williams</persName>'s, where we were kindly
                    received,<lb/> and dined. His place is situate at the entrance of<lb/><geogName
                        key="lakst"> Lake St. Clair</geogName>. While here, Nathan gave us an
                    ac-<lb/>count, that in digging a cave for a root house, they<lb/> found, about
                    six feet below the surface of the<lb/> ground, large quantities of human bones,
                    that must<lb/> have been for a long time there: and at another<lb/> place on the
                    bank of the lake, it being washed away<lb/> when the lake was high, there were
                    seen great<lb/> numbers of the same kind, which they gathered up<lb/> and
                    buried. The Indians said they must have been <lb/>
                    <pb n="312"/> from people a great while ago that they knew no-<lb/>thing of.
                    There is also near this lake, as we are in-<lb/>formed, the appearance of old
                    forts, curiously made<lb/> in ancient time, where pieces of earthenware are<lb/>
                    often found, though large trees are now standing in<lb/> the entrenchments, of
                    which the present Indians<lb/> can give no account. We seem pretty generally
                    led<lb/> to believe, from various circumstances, that the na-<lb/>tives of this
                    land must be the descendants of old<lb/> Jacob, and are of the scattered tribes,
                    who probably<lb/> found their way here through <placeName key="rus"
                        >Russia</placeName>, and crossed<lb/> over the narrow strait from <placeName
                        key="kams">Kamschatka</placeName> to the west<lb/> side of America. Be all
                    this as it may, we find them<lb/> here in great numbers, at present a savage,
                    barbarous<lb/> people when at war, and more particularly when in-<lb/>toxicated
                    with strong drink, which has been intro-<lb/>duced by the white people that
                    suppose themselves<lb/> by far their superiors in religious and natural
                    under-<lb/>standing. Happy would it have been for them and<lb/> us, had we used
                    those superior talents, in mercy<lb/> conferred upon us, more to the honour of
                    God, by<lb/> following the example of our holy leader, Christ<lb/> Jesus, who
                    said he <quote type="biblical">came not to destroy men's lives,<lb/> but to save
                        them.</quote> May all Christendom more and<lb/> more labour to experience a
                    renovation of heart and<lb/> mind, submitting and conforming to the will of
                    hea-<lb/>ven in all our conduct, consistent with the design of<lb/> our
                    creation. Then might we have reason to hope<lb/> for a blessing on our labours,
                    tending to stop the<lb/> effusion of human blood, and the establishment of<lb/>
                    Christ's kingdom on the mountain of love and holi-<lb/>ness, where the lion and
                    the lamb might lie down<lb/> together, there being nothing to make us
                    afraid.<lb/> In the afternoon we re-embarked and returned to <lb/>
                    <pb n="313"/> town. <persName key="wsave1">Wm. Savery</persName> and <persName
                        key="whart">Wm. Hartshorne</persName> in our<lb/> absence, were visited by a
                        <orgName key="shawnee">Shawnese</orgName> warrior, who<lb/> announced to
                    them what had frequently been sug-<lb/>gested to us before, by divers persons,
                    that if the<lb/> commissioners did not immediately agree that all<lb/> the land
                    west of the <geogName key="ohior">Ohio</geogName> should be given up by the<lb/>
                    <placeName key="usa">United States</placeName>, or even hinted any thing to the
                    con-<lb/>trary, by offering gifts or money as purchase, that<lb/> not one of
                    them or their company would go off the<lb/> ground alive; for their fathers, who
                    were all gone,<lb/> had sold lands for knives, rum, &amp;c. till they were<lb/>
                    now driven almost to the sun setting, where they<lb/> were determined to make a
                    stand. He also pointed<lb/> out very sensibly, the sad effects strong drink
                    had<lb/> on their fathers in general. He then appeared per-<lb/>fectly sober —
                    informing that four days before he left<lb/> the <geogName key="miamr1">Miami
                        Rapids</geogName>, a deputation of two chiefs from<lb/> a tribe, embarked
                    for <placeName key="niagf">Niagara</placeName> to meet the commis-<lb/>sioners,
                    and let them know the outlines of their con-<lb/>clusions; and that if the white
                    people would settle<lb/> to the banks of the <geogName key="ohior"
                        >Ohio</geogName> on the east side, and agree<lb/> that the river should be
                    the line, they would be glad,<lb/> and take them by the hand and call them
                    brothers.<lb/> But we apprehended no such power lay with the<lb/> commissioners,
                    nor of its being the design of govern-<lb/>ment, — the cloud looked dark and
                    heavy, and por-<lb/>tended some dreadful scenes of desolation, except<lb/> the
                    Lord should be pleased, in his abundant mercy,<lb/> to interpose and spare this
                    wicked generation. </p>

                <p> The aforesaid Indian, notwithstanding his sensi-<lb/>bility and calmness, about
                    two hours after, returned<lb/> much intoxicated with rum — behaved very
                    rudely,<lb/> and drew a stroke with his tomahawk at one <persName key="sash1"
                        >Sylves-<lb/>ter Ash</persName>, an interpreter, who had long resided with <lb/>
                    <pb n="314"/> the <orgName key="shawnee">Shawnese</orgName>, and now lives at
                        <placeName key="fpitt1">Fort Pitt</placeName>. We sup-<lb/>posed he had a
                    grudge against him for leaving them;<lb/> but <persName key="sash1"
                        >Ash</persName> prevented his doing him mischief. This,<lb/> with other
                    insolent behavior to our landlord, caused<lb/>
                    <persName key="cmuns1">captain Munsey</persName>, who was there, to send for
                    some<lb/> soldiers to turn him out of the garrison. These<lb/> things look
                    gloomy, and tend to confirm us that no-<lb/>thing short of wisdom from above
                    will do for us to<lb/> lean to. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-06">6th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> The weather is now dry and warm — the<lb/> wheat it fast ripening, of which
                    there is an appear-<lb/>ance of very fine crops. Vegetables are plenty,<lb/>
                    such as new potatoes, peas, beans, &amp;c. The sloop<lb/> Felicity just arrived
                    from the <orgName key="miami">Miamies</orgName>, confirms<lb/> the account of
                    the Indian deputation being gone to<lb/> meet the commissioners at <placeName
                        key="niafo">Niagara</placeName>, accompanied by<lb/>
                    <persName key="cbutl1">colonel Butler</persName> and <persName key="sgirt1"
                        >Simon Girty</persName>. The schooner<lb/> Nancy also just arrived from
                        <placeName key="michi">Michillimackinac</placeName>, with<lb/> peltry — made
                    her passage to this place in seventeen<lb/> days — distance three hundred and
                    ninety miles. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-06">7th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> First of the week. We held a meeting in<lb/> the forenoon in the old sail loft:
                    it was to good satis-<lb/>faction, being large and solid. In the afternoon
                    we<lb/> went about five miles to the <geogName key="rushr">river
                        Rushe</geogName> — held a<lb/> meeting with the inhabitants there and
                    several who<lb/> went with us from the town. This also we thought<lb/> was
                    comfortable and edifying. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-08">8th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> The weather hot and sultry — a heavy thun-<lb/>der shower. We have no account
                    from the commis-<lb/>sioners — hope they may come on with the Indian<lb/>
                    deputies, if any thing is likely to be done. This is<lb/> truly a trying scene
                    to us, to be kept in this expen-<lb/>sive place so long in suspense; yet hope it
                    may not<lb/> be altogether in vain. We think we have done the <lb/>
                    <pb n="315"/> best we could in our present circumstances. Various<lb/> reports
                    are daily coming in, with respect to the In-<lb/>dians' disposition. We much
                    desire an opportunity<lb/> with them in council, if it could be come at
                    proper-<lb/>ly, whether the commissioners come or not. The<lb/> opinion of many
                    is, there will be no general treaty.<lb/> We received a letter from <persName
                        key="amcke1">colonel M'Kee</persName> in answer<lb/> to one written him some
                    time ago; — says he will at-<lb/>tend to our request, and give us every
                    intelligence<lb/> he apprehends necessary; — and yesterday, one from<lb/>
                    <persName key="haupa1">captain Hendricks</persName>, at the <geogName
                        key="miamr1">rapids of Miami</geogName>, request-<lb/>ing some favours from
                    us, — which were granted.<lb/> And truly we have many requests, that in our
                    pre-<lb/>sent circumstances we are not able to comply with<lb/> to the full.
                        <persName key="haupa1">Hendrick</persName>s' account is more favourable<lb/>
                    than some others we have had. He expresses a<lb/> hope there will be a peace.
                    The general cry among<lb/> the gentlemen and more knowing inhabitants of
                    this<lb/> place is, <said who="undetermined">for God's sake, gentlemen, don't
                        venture<lb/> yourselves to <placeName key="sandu"
                        >Sandusky</placeName>.</said> This we believe is from<lb/> motives of entire
                    friendship and good will to us,<lb/> and makes it at times very trying. And
                    though we<lb/> have not felt any slavish fears — yet hope to move<lb/>
                    cautiously, as wisdom, which is profitable to direct,<lb/> may point out the
                    way. One of the Indians, a <orgName key="delaware">De-<lb/>laware</orgName>,
                    that brought <persName key="haupa1">captain Hendricks'</persName> letter,
                    says<lb/> the western Indians keep their runners constantly<lb/> out to watch
                    the motion of <persName key="gwayn1">general Wayne's</persName> army,<lb/> from
                    whom they have some fearful apprehensions;<lb/> which we hope are
                    groundless.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-09">9th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> We had a visit from <persName key="bljac1">captain Blue Jacket</persName>,
                    a<lb/> principal warrior among the <orgName key="shawnee">Shawnese</orgName>. He
                    was in<lb/> command at the defeat of St. Clair's army. He was<lb/> richly
                    dressed. His appearance is lofty and mascu-<lb/>
                    <pb n="316"/> line.He said he had heard of the Quakers — that<lb/> they were a
                    harmless people that did not fight; and<lb/> was glad now to see us. We had also
                    a visit from<lb/> several others of the same tribe. One of a solid<lb/>
                    countenance said, he heartily desired we might<lb/> succeed in the great work of
                    peace; and appeared<lb/> much pleased to see us. We have several capable<lb/>
                    interpreters with us; but our sentiments being peace-<lb/>ful, serious and
                    religious, are so opposite to theirs,<lb/> that when they do interpret, it is
                    with such reluc-<lb/>tance as puts it out of our power to relieve our<lb/> minds
                    so fully as we could wish. This day received<lb/> a letter from the <orgName
                        key="moraind">Moravian Indians</orgName> and their minis-<lb/>ter,
                    expressing their grateful sense of Friends' kind-<lb/>ness to them. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-10">10th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> The sloop Detroit, bound to <placeName key="macki">Mackinaw</placeName>,
                    ar-<lb/>rived from <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName> in eight days.
                    We were in<lb/> hopes of letters, but were disappointed. However<lb/> we
                    understand the commissioners, with a number of<lb/> Indians, are coming in the
                    Dunmore which was<lb/> nearly ready to sail, and may be soon expected, if<lb/>
                    not met with by the <orgName key="ojibwe">Chipaway</orgName>, and detained by
                    the<lb/> chiefs who were to have a conference with them<lb/> previous to their
                    coming forward to the treaty. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-11">11th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> Had the company of several Indians — one<lb/> of whom, <persName key="dcan"
                        >David Canada</persName>, speaks good English, and<lb/> interprets well. His
                    father was a white man. He<lb/> has been in Europe — appears friendly to the
                    Ame-<lb/>rican interest, and says he will go with us to the<lb/> treaty. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-12">12th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> We all went over the river to our land-<lb/>lord's farm, where we dined on
                    provision we took<lb/> with us. Spent most of the day there and in
                    visit-<lb/>ing some neighbours. Returned in the evening. </p>
                <pb n="317"/>
                <p> The sloop Sagonay is just arrived from <placeName key="ferie">Fort
                        Erie</placeName>.<lb/> The Dunmore was waiting for a wind, when the<lb/>
                    deputation of Indians arrived — and the commission-<lb/>ers returned to
                        <placeName key="nav">Navy Hall</placeName> to have a conference.<lb/> This
                    is an additional disappointment, and further<lb/> trial of our faith and
                    patience. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-13">13th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> The weather fair and pleasant — the people<lb/> very busy in hay-making, and
                    some beginning their<lb/> wheat harvest. In the afternoon the sloop
                    Speed-<lb/>well arrived from <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>, by
                    which we had letters<lb/> from our friends at home, and one from the
                    commis-<lb/>sioners, informing of their return to <placeName key="nav"> Navy
                        Hall</placeName>; but<lb/> that they expect to come forward in a few days.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-14">14th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> First of the week. For some days I have<lb/> felt rather dull and heavy — my
                    spirits low. I feel<lb/> the importance of our embassy with much weight. —<lb/>
                    The dark conversation frequently heard respecting<lb/> war, is truly distressing
                    and discouraging. I am <lb/>frequently led to recur back to the first
                    principles<lb/> from whence the concern took its rise; and have, as<lb/> yet, no
                    cause to doubt of its propriety, although<lb/> many discouraging prospects are
                    frequently thrown<lb/> in our way. We are comfortably preserved in unity<lb/>
                    one with another in the main cause we are engaged<lb/> in, hoping we shall not
                    be shaken from the right<lb/> ground by the enemies of peace, — of which
                    there<lb/> are many. </p>

                <p> This day we had another meeting in the usual<lb/> place, which was large and
                    solid. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-15">15th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> Had an interview with <persName key="celli1">captain Elliot</persName>, who<lb/>
                    had just returned from the <geogName key="miamr1">Rapids</geogName>, where the
                    Indians<lb/> are collected; but nothing further has transpired.<lb/> He appears
                    somewhat reserved; and our anxious<lb/> state of suspense still continues. We
                    are apprehen-<lb/>
                    <pb n="318"/> sive the Indian embassy to the commissioners may<lb/> prevent the
                    proposed treaty. We wrote a letter to <lb/><persName key="amcke1">colonel
                        McKee</persName>, and an epistle to the Indians, to be<lb/> forwarded the
                    first opportunity. </p>

                <p> Here we observe a species of Indian slaves called<lb/>
                    <orgName key="pawnee">Pawnees</orgName>, or Punins, — who are captives taken
                    by<lb/> the <orgName key="chippewa">Chipaways</orgName> from the <orgName
                        key="sioux">Suse</orgName>, or <orgName key="pawnee">Pawnee</orgName>
                    nations.<lb/> It is sorrowful to think that a nation so famed for<lb/> liberty,
                    should hold them, and a number of the Afri-<lb/>can race, in a state of bondage
                    during life. The go-<lb/>vernment here, we understand, has made some essay<lb/>
                    towards their enlargement, which, it is hoped, will,<lb/> in time, amount to a
                    total abolition. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-16">16th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> Had a solid opportunity with <persName key="celli1">captain
                        El-<lb/>liot</persName>, deputy agent for Indian affairs, and again
                    ex-<lb/>pressed our anxious desires to him, that a solid peace<lb/> might take
                    place; we also queried if it would be<lb/> proper for us, or any of our company,
                    to visit the In-<lb/>dians in their present council at the <geogName
                        key="miamr1">Rapids</geogName>, where<lb/> he was now about to return. He
                    told us, he thought<lb/> in the present state of things, it would not be
                    eligi-<lb/>ble to move that way. He gave us to understand,<lb/> that the Indians
                    were generally acquainted with our<lb/> being here, and our views towards them;
                    and hoped<lb/> on the return of the Indian embassy, some way would<lb/> open for
                    our relief. For the present, we concluded<lb/> to forward the letters to and the
                    <persName key="amcke1">M'Kee</persName> Indians, by<lb/>
                    <persName key="celli1">Elliot</persName>, and as our having a personal interview
                    with<lb/> the Indians appeared doubtful, we forwarded Friends'<lb/> Address to
                    them, to be read by <persName key="amcke1">M'Kee</persName> in case we<lb/>
                    should fail of an opportunity ourselves. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-17">17th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> The people are very busy in their harvest,<lb/> having good crops: but in some
                    places the grain is <lb/>
                    <pb n="319"/> injured by a kind of smut, supposed to be occasion-<lb/>ed by much
                    wet and rapid growth. </p>

                <p> We have lately heard of the arrival of a number<lb/> of <orgName key="creek"
                        >Creeks</orgName> and <orgName key="cherokee">Cherokee</orgName> Indians, in
                    the neighbour<lb/>hood of the Indian council — we fear, with views not<lb/>
                    friendly to a peaceable accommodation of matters<lb/> with the Western Indians —
                    as we hear hostilities<lb/> between them and the whites have been renewed
                    to<lb/> the southward. These accounts are alarming and<lb/> discouraging. The
                    commissioners are not yet come.<lb/> We wait as patiently as we can, until we
                    hear fur-<lb/>ther from them. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-18">18th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> This morning had an interview with <persName key="cwell2">cap-<lb/>tain
                        Wellbank</persName>, who came with the detachment of<lb/>
                    <orgName key="cherokee">Cherokee</orgName> and <orgName key="creek"
                        >Creek</orgName> Indians from the southern ter-<lb/>ritory, he says, more
                    than a thousand miles, and<lb/> that they were ninety days on their journey.
                    His<lb/> principal business seemed to be with <persName key="cengl1">colonel
                        Eng-<lb/>land</persName> , who gave immediate orders for the sloop
                    Feli-<lb/>city to sail with him on board, to <placeName key="ferie"> Fort
                        Erie</placeName>, on his<lb/> way to <persName key="gsim">governor
                        Simcoe</persName>. We suppose they have<lb/> some matters of importance, as
                    colonel England<lb/> a few days ago assured us the Felicity was detained<lb/> on
                    purpose to take us to <placeName key="sandu">Sandusky</placeName>, or <placeName
                        key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>,<lb/> as was most eligible, on the
                    shortest notice, which<lb/>looked kind and friendly to our purpose. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-19">19th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> The weather fair and pleasant, and through<lb/> Divine favour, we are all in
                    health ; but are still in<lb/> great suspense, with respect to the event of this
                    in-<lb/>tended treaty, which every day looks more and<lb/> more discouraging.
                    Yet we think we have been in<lb/> the line of our duty in coming forward and
                    labour-<lb/>ing thus far; and hope our being here may be of<lb/> some use on
                    divers accounts. Some of our compa-<lb/>
                    <pb n="320"/> ny walked yesterday to the spring about three miles<lb/> below the
                    town, where they had a satisfactory op-<lb/>portunity with some <orgName
                        key="oneida">Oneida Indians</orgName> that were en-<lb/>camped there. They
                    seem jointly concerned with<lb/> us for the accomplishment of peace. This day
                    we<lb/> were all together in the arbour in the colonel's gar-<lb/>den, looking
                    over some writings on Indian affairs.<lb/> To this place we frequently resort,
                    as it is retired<lb/> and pleasant — being indulged with this privilege by<lb/>
                    invitation from the colonel soon after our arrival<lb/> here. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-20">20th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> The harbour is now clear of shipping. —<lb/> We are anxiously waiting the
                    arrival of the Dun-<lb/>more, by which we expect the commissioners, or to<lb/>
                    hear from them, hoping our detention here will be<lb/> shortly closed by our
                    going on to <placeName key="sandu">Sandusky</placeName>, or re-<lb/>turning to
                        <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName> on our way home: till
                    which<lb/> we desire humbly to submit to the wise Disposer of<lb/> events. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-21">21st</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> First of the week. We held a meeting in<lb/> the sail loft at the tenth hour,
                    which was a favour-<lb/>ed time, it being large and solid. Soon after our
                    re-<lb/>turn, we heard of the arrival of the Dunmore at the<lb/> mouth of the
                    river, by a passenger who came in her,<lb/> and that the commissioners are on
                    board, expecting<lb/> to go forward soon to <placeName key="sandu"
                        >Sandusky</placeName>. In the afternoon<lb/> we had another comfortable
                    meeting, crowned as<lb/> we thought, with the Master's good presence. And<lb/>
                    now it looks likely to be a parting one, — the peo-<lb/>ple behaved with
                    remarkable quietness — manifest-<lb/>ing much respect to us. I believe there are
                    a few<lb/> tender-hearted ones in this place that will remember<lb/> us, and I
                    hope we shall not forget them; — though it<lb/> is sorrowful to behold the power
                    and influence that <lb/>
                    <pb n="321"/> satan has too generally amongst the inhabitants of<lb/> these
                    parts. <persName key="cgibs">Captain Gibbons</persName>, who came passenger<lb/>
                    in the Dunmore, gave us the above intelligence re-<lb/>specting the
                    commissioners, and further says, the<lb/> Indian deputies and they held a very
                    friendly con-<lb/>ference together at <placeName key="nav">Navy
                    Hall</placeName>, and things appeared<lb/> in a favourable way respecting the
                    treaty. This ac-<lb/>count is more pleasant than any we have had for<lb/> many
                    days past. In this fluctuating state of things<lb/> we find great need to keep
                    on the right bottom, so<lb/> that we may not be shaken from that
                    foundation,<lb/> and a humble confidence in the Divine power, which<lb/>I trust
                    we felt in our embarkation. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-22">22d</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p>
                    <persName key="jparr1">John Parrish</persName>, <persName key="jelli1">John
                        Elliott</persName>, and myself, paid<lb/> a visit to the <orgName
                        key="catholic">Roman Catholic</orgName> priest, who appeared<lb/> to take it
                    kind. We also had a short interview with<lb/> the commandant, who has manifested
                    much respect<lb/> to us during our long stay here, and now told us,<lb/> that
                    nothing should be wanting that lay in his power<lb/> to make our way easy. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-23">23d</date> and <date when="1793-07-24"
                    >24th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> We now began to prepare for leav-<lb/>ing <placeName key="detro"
                        >Detroit</placeName>. The commandant visited us at our quar-<lb/>ters, and
                    informed us he proposed going with us in<lb/> the Dunmore to see the
                    commissioners. It seemed<lb/> very pleasant to find that respect which it is
                    hoped<lb/> may tend to strengthen the unity between them. —<lb/> We should have
                    been glad to see the commissioners<lb/> here, but understanding neither they nor
                    any others<lb/> from a foreign state under military characters, are<lb/>
                    admitted within the limits of this garrison, which<lb/> includes the town that
                    consists of about one hun-<lb/>dred houses; under which consideration we think
                    it<lb/> cause of thankfulness for the indulgence, remarkable<lb/> attention, and
                    kind treatment we have met with <lb/>
                    <pb n="322"/> during our six weeks stay in this place. This even-<lb/>ing, paid
                    a short visit at <persName key="crin1">commissary Rinold</persName>'s, who,<lb/>
                    with his wife and sensible daughter, appear to have<lb/> as much solidity,
                    uprightness, and vital religion, as<lb/> any in the place. There are a few
                    others we highly<lb/> esteem, and towards whom we now feel a near
                    affec-<lb/>tion on taking our solemn farewell. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-25">25th</date>. </dateline>
                <p> Took leave of most of our acquaintances in<lb/> town and went on board the
                    Dunmore, in which<lb/> were <persName key="cengl1">colonel England</persName>
                    and several other officers; fell<lb/> down to the mouth of the river, about
                    eighteen<lb/> miles, and landed at <persName key="celli1">captain
                        Elliot</persName>'s, whose house<lb/> the commissioners had taken, being
                    large and con-<lb/>venient for their purpose. We were truly glad to<lb/> see
                    them, and they us. Here the vessel is ordered<lb/> to lay until we are ready to
                    go forward to <placeName key="sandu">Sandus-<lb/>ky</placeName>, which depends
                    on the time the Indians say they<lb/> are ready. It was pleasant to behold the
                    friend-<lb/>ship apparent between the <persName key="cengl1">colonel</persName>
                    with the other<lb/> British officers, and our commissioners. This place<lb/> is
                    very agreeable; there being a large farm, with<lb/> fields well stored with
                    grain, standing in shock —<lb/>supposed to be about one thousand bushels; a
                    large<lb/> new barn eighty feet long and about thirty-six<lb/>wide; round the
                    house a beautiful green, on which<lb/> we encamped with fourteen tents, large
                    and small,<lb/> containing our little company and the commission-<lb/>ers'
                    train, with some British officers who designed<lb/> to go with us to the grand
                    treaty. The commis-<lb/>sioners gave us the substance of what passed
                    be-<lb/>tween them and the Indian deputies at <placeName key="niaga"
                        >Niagara</placeName>: all<lb/> which appeared encouraging, and favourable
                    towards<lb/> an accommodation. We dined and supped all toge-<lb/>ther, and slept
                    quiet and well in our tents. </p>
                <pb n="323"/>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-26">26th</date>. </dateline>
                <p> Spent the day very agreeably together,<lb/> having one general table. At night
                    we had a great<lb/> rain and heavy thunder; our tents not as well
                    forti-<lb/>fied as might have been. Towards day some of us<lb/> got very wet by
                    the water coming in; but through<lb/> Divine favour we were preserved. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-27">27th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> A fine morning. Having an opportunity to<lb/> go to Detroit in a small boat with
                        <persName key="gsensi">Gotlieb Sensiman</persName>,<lb/> a <orgName
                        key="moravian">Moravian</orgName> minister from <geogName key="thame"
                        >Latrench river</geogName>, and three<lb/> Indians of their family, we
                    embraced it. <persName key="wsave1">William<lb/> Savery</persName> and myself
                    took our passage in order to do<lb/> some business for the commissioners, and a
                    little for<lb/> ourselves. The wind was ahead and we had to row<lb/> all the
                    way, Went to our old quarters. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-28">28th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> First of the week. I felt weary with yester-<lb/>day's hard rowing, and almost
                    ready to give out the<lb/> prospect of a meeting. But towards evening, at<lb/>
                    about an hour's notice, we met at the old sail loft<lb/> with many of the
                    inhabitants, who appeared glad of<lb/> the opportunity, and it was satisfactory
                    to ourselves. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-29">29th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> The colonel's boat going down the river to<lb/> our camp, with <persName
                        key="cfree1">captains Freeman</persName> and <persName key="jbroa1"
                        >Broadhead</persName>,<lb/> we were invited to return with them; but our
                    busi-<lb/>ness not being completed, I concluded to stay, and<lb/> take my
                    passage in the schooner Nancy, bound to<lb/>
                    <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>, and <persName key="wsave1">William
                        Savery</persName> went with the offi-<lb/>cers. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-30">30th</date>. <geogName key="detror" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> I went on board the schooner, and near<lb/> night landed at our camp, where I
                    was informed a<lb/> deputation of Indians from the <geogName key="miamr1"
                        >Rapids</geogName> had been here,<lb/> and held a conference with the
                    commissioners. They<lb/> appeared uneasy with what had passed at <placeName
                        key="niaga">Niagara</placeName>,<lb/> asserting that nothing short of
                        <geogName key="ohior">Ohio river</geogName> being the<lb/> line, would
                    satisfy them; they requested the com-<lb/>missioners’ <pb n="324"/> answer
                    to-morrow, on that head, and re-<lb/>tired over the river. This unexpected
                    change look-<lb/>ed again discouraging; believing our worthy com-<lb/>missioners
                    had nothing but upright views in their<lb/> proceedings, consistent with the
                    trust reposed in them<lb/> by the government of the United States. Though<lb/>
                    what their views are, is yet unknown to us; but we<lb/> hope, and expect, they
                    will be generous and liberal,<lb/> evincing to the world that the present
                    proceedings<lb/> and designs of the <orgName key="usag">United States</orgName>
                    are founded on<lb/> reason, equity, and justice. And so far as this may<lb/> be
                    the case, we hope the Lord may be on our side,<lb/> in this our trying
                    situation. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-31">31st</date>. <geogName key="detror" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> In the afternoon the Indians came over, and<lb/> being seated on the beautiful
                    green in the shade of<lb/> some trees, the commissioners came forth with
                    their<lb/> speech in writing, which was interpreted by <persName key="tjones"
                        >Tho-<lb/>mas Jones</persName>, from the <placeName key="genec"
                        >Genesee</placeName>, in the Seneca lan-<lb/>guage. In it was contained many
                    candid and gen-<lb/>erous proposals; but not coming up so fully to their<lb/>
                    demands as they seemed to wish, they declined to<lb/> make any reply at present.
                    But having the paper<lb/> given to them, said they would consider it
                    mature-<lb/>ly, and return an answer tomorrow. On which the<lb/> council broke
                    up, and the Indians returned again to<lb/>
                    <geogName key="whiti">Whitewood Island</geogName>, opposite to our camp.
                    Among<lb/> these were the chiefs often different nations, who ap-<lb/>peared in
                    council solid and sober. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-01">8th mo. 1st</date>. <geogName key="detror" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> The Indian deputies returned in the<lb/> morning early, and being seated, the
                        <orgName key="wyandot">Wyandot</orgName> chief<lb/> called <persName
                        key="carry1">Carry-all-about</persName>, whose name signifies King of<lb/>
                    all the western nations up the Lakes, — made a short<lb/> speech, importing,
                        <said who="carry1">That many treaties had been<lb/> held at different places
                        from time to time, wherein <lb/>
                        <pb n="325"/> you say lands have been purchased; but would ac-<lb/>knowledge
                        no legal and permanent conveyance<lb/> since the treaty at <placeName
                            key="fstan">Fort Stanwix</placeName>, twenty-five years<lb/> ago. So
                        that the lands on this side the <geogName key="ohior"> Ohio</geogName>
                        are<lb/> ours, and the lands on the other side are yours. — <lb/> And you
                        may go home and tell <persName key="gwash1">Washington</persName> what<lb/>
                        we say. We understand all you said to us very<lb/> well, and we expect you
                        understand us.</said>
                    <persName key="sgirt1">Simon<lb/> Girty</persName> was their interpreter. After
                    rising up and<lb/> stepping off a few yards, they found a mistake in<lb/>
                    expression, and recalled their words, desiring the<lb/> commissioners would stay
                    where they are, till they<lb/> could go to the council and return with an
                    answer,<lb/> which, if favoured with wind and weather, may be<lb/> accomplished
                    in about five days. We had some de-<lb/>sire to go with them to the <placeName
                        key="miamr1">Rapids</placeName>, as <persName key="celli1">captain
                            El-<lb/>liot</persName>, <persName key="tmcke1">captain Thomas
                        M’Kee</persName>, and others were go-<lb/>ing to the council. But this was
                    not approbated;<lb/> and as our letters sent by <persName key="celli1">captain
                        Elliot</persName> had not<lb/> been forwarded by him on account of his
                    meeting<lb/> the commissioners here, who thought proper to de-<lb/>tain them,
                    concluding we should have an opportu-<lb/>nity shortly to see them ourselves, —
                    after opening<lb/> and reading them, and adding a short postscript, we<lb/> were
                    encouraged to send them forward, though at a<lb/> late stage.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-02">2d</date>. <geogName key="detror" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> Towards evening, several of us in company<lb/> with our good old general, took a
                    walk up the river<lb/> about a mile, and drank tea at <persName key="jcol">James
                        Colwell</persName>’s. The<lb/> result of this great business is cause of
                    much close<lb/> exercise at times — our minds being made sensible<lb/> that
                    nothing but supernatural wisdom will do for us<lb/> to lean to. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-03">3d</date>. <geogName key="detror" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> The sloop Detroit came to, here, on her way <lb/>
                    <pb n="326"/> to <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>, from <placeName
                        key="michi"> Michillimackinac</placeName>, loaded with<lb/> peltry, having
                    on board three hundred and thirty-<lb/> three packs, the greatest part supposed
                    to be worth<lb/> twenty guineas each. So great is the fur trade in<lb/> this
                    country, that it is almost beyond description.<lb/> In the afternoon, <persName
                        key="jelli1">John Elliott</persName> and myself took a<lb/> walk to
                        <persName key="sgirt1">Simon Girty</persName>'s, and from thence about
                    half<lb/> a mile further down the lake, where we saw some<lb/> plain traces of
                    one of the very old forts, among the<lb/> many that are in divers parts of this
                    country, of<lb/> which the present Indians can give no account from<lb/>
                    tradition or otherwise. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-04">4th</date>. <geogName key="detror" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> First of the week. We held a small meet-<lb/>ing at <persName key="sgirt1">Simon
                        Girty</persName>'s, we hope to profit: — himself<lb/> gone to the Indian
                    council with the deputies that<lb/> were here from the Rapids.<persName
                        key="wsave1"> William Savery</persName> and<lb/> myself being comrades in a
                    small tent, our bedding<lb/> got a good deal wet with the great rain that fell
                    to-<lb/>day, and having no opportunity for drying, we slept<lb/> on them as they
                    were. In the morning, felt well,<lb/> which is an additional cause of
                    thankfulness for the<lb/> many favours we have received. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-05">5th</date>. <geogName key="detror" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> We have frequent visits from the town, —<lb/> and this day came <persName
                        key="jabbo1">James Abbot</persName>, <persName key="wbo">William
                        Bow</persName>, and<lb/> — Sportsman, in a small sail boat. Our friend<lb/>
                    <persName key="jparr1">John Parrish</persName>, paid a visit to the <orgName
                        key="wyandot">Wyandot</orgName> Indian<lb/> town about four miles from our
                    camp. This night<lb/> was the most general complaint of the musketoes I<lb/>
                    have yet heard since our encamping here. Most of<lb/> us got little sleep either
                    in the house, tents, or on<lb/> ship board. Towards day the weather grew
                    colder<lb/> — wind N. W. which caused an increase of muske-<lb/>toes in our
                    tents. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-06">6th</date>. <geogName key="detror" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> One of the servants of <persName key="celli1">captain Elliot</persName>, called <lb/>
                    <pb n="327"/>
                    <persName key="tob">Toby</persName>, a <orgName key="pawnee">Pawnee</orgName>
                    slave, who has lain near a year in<lb/> a consumption, died about two o'clock
                    this afternoon. </p>
                <p> I was with him for about an hour before he depart-<lb/>ed, and speaking with him
                    about fifteen minutes be-<lb/>fore he breathed his last, found he was sensible
                    of<lb/> death being upon him. He said he understood all<lb/> I said to him, and
                    was glad he was noticed in his<lb/> last moments. I think I never saw before so
                    hasty<lb/> a burial. His coffin was made immediately, and his<lb/> interment
                    took place about sunset, in a grave near-<lb/>by on the bank of the river,
                    attended by about twen-<lb/>ty people, whites, blacks, and Indians. This
                    was<lb/> the end of poor <persName key="tob">Toby</persName>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-07">7th</date>. <geogName key="detror" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> I was at captain <persName key="wcol">William Colwell</persName>'s, and
                    to-<lb/>wards evening walked to <persName key="sgirt1">Simon Girty</persName>'s.
                    At night<lb/> the wind came strong from the south, with much<lb/> rain.<persName
                        key="wcol">William</persName> and I got a little wet again, but are<lb/>
                    preserved in health. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-08">8th</date>. <geogName key="detror" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> Two Indians came from the <geogName key="miamr1">Rapids</geogName>, by whom<lb/>
                    we received letters from <persName key="haupa1">captain Hendricks</persName>, a
                    chief<lb/> of the <orgName key="sxntns">Five Nations</orgName>, announcing his
                    opinion there<lb/> will be peace. This was pleasant, indeed, and we<lb/> sat up
                    this evening, conversing with the commis-<lb/>sioners till past eleven o'clock.
                    Slept well, being<lb/> clear of musketoes. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-09">9th</date>. <geogName key="detror" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p>
                    <persName key="wsave1">William Savery</persName> and myself dined on
                    board<lb/>the ship that rides nearly opposite our camp. This<lb/> evening came
                    in several more Indians from the <geogName key="miamr1">Ra-<lb/>pids</geogName>,
                    whose reports agree in substance with <persName key="haupa1">captain<lb/>
                        Hendrick</persName>s' letters. They were treated with a glass<lb/> a piece,
                    and encamped near by; but a canoe coming<lb/> from <placeName key="detro"
                        >Detroit</placeName> with rum, they were made very noisy.<lb/> This, with
                    the musketoes, caused little sleep. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-10">10th</date>. <geogName key="detror" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> Great looking out for the boat's return from<lb/>
                    <pb n="328"/> the council, for which we are very anxious. The<lb/> season
                    advancing, and the great distance we are<lb/> from home, together with the
                    continued uncertainty<lb/> of succeeding, according to our wishes, in the
                    great<lb/> business we are engaged in, accompanied with other<lb/> unpleasant
                    circumstances, give us at times some very<lb/> disagreeable sensations. Yet on
                    the whole, we are<lb/> preserved in a good degree of patience, still
                    believing<lb/> our coming out was right, be the event as it may. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-11">11th</date>. <placeName key="gisle"/></dateline>
                <p> First of the week. No arrival from the <geogName key="miamr1">Ra-<lb/>pids
                    </geogName> to alleviate our strong desires and anxiety to see<lb/> the Indians.
                    With some difficulty we got to <placeName key="gisle">Grose<lb/>
                        Isle</placeName>, where we held a meeting with some of its in-<lb/>habitants
                    and divers from the main, to a good de-<lb/>gree of satisfaction. This morning,
                        <persName key="jparr2">Jasper Parrish</persName>,<lb/> who had been express
                    to Philadelphia, the second<lb/> time, arrived in the ship Ottoway, from <placeName key="ferie">Fort
                        Erie</placeName>,<lb/> by whom we received many letters from home. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-12">12th</date>. <geogName key="detror" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> Our anxiety and great suspense still con-<lb/>tinue. <persName key="wsave1"
                        >William Savery</persName> and <persName key="jparr2">Jasper Parrish
                    </persName>both<lb/> poorly. At night our rest was much disturbed by<lb/> the
                    musketoes. We have frequent visits from small<lb/> parties of Indians, who
                    sometimes find means to get<lb/> too much rum, and are then troublesome;
                    otherwise<lb/> they are quiet and civil. Fresh provisions are plen-<lb/>ty here;
                    but rate very high. Sheep from four to<lb/> six dollars, not large. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-13">13th</date>. <geogName key="detror" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> No remarkable occurrence. We are still<lb/> looking earnestly for the boats from
                    the great In-<lb/>dian council. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-14">14th</date>. <geogName key="detror" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> This day we had the company of <persName key="cwell2">captain<lb/>
                        Wellbank</persName>, who returned some days ago from <placeName key="niafo"
                        >Nia-<lb/>gara </placeName>. He gave the commissioners much the same <lb/>
                    <pb n="329"/> account we received from him at <placeName key="detro"
                        >Detroit</placeName>the 18th<lb/> ultimo. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-15">15th</date>. <geogName key="detror" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> Felt dull and heavy in body and mind --<lb/>We have a <orgName key="wyandot"
                        >Wyandot</orgName> Indian, who stays much with<lb/> us. He often goes out to
                    hunt, and brings in plenty<lb/> of ducks, &amp;c. for which he gets well paid.
                    He ap-<lb/>pears to be a sensible man, speaks many languages<lb/> in the Indian
                    tongue and some English. Two men<lb/> came from the other side of the river, and
                    informed<lb/> the boats were coming from the council to invite us <lb/>to the
                    treaty. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-16">16th</date>.<geogName key="detror" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> In the afternoon came two young Indian<lb/> men, (<orgName key="wyandot"
                        >Wyandots</orgName>) they looked wild and afraid; one<lb/> of them was
                    introduced to <persName key="glinc1">general Lincoln</persName>, and<lb/> handed
                    him a message in writing, from the great<lb/> council, informing, that the
                    several treaties at <placeName key="fmint">Fort<lb/> M'Intosh</placeName>,
                        <placeName key="miam">Miami</placeName>, <placeName key="musk"
                        >Muskingum</placeName>, &amp;c, where lands<lb/> had been ceded by two or
                    three nations only, were<lb/> not valid, as they had no right to cede lands.
                    And<lb/> as for the large sums of money proposed to be given<lb/> for their
                    country, they did not want it, and a great<lb/> many of them did not know the
                    use of it: therefore<lb/> desired it might be applied with the proposed
                    sala-<lb/>ry, to the indemnification of the settlers north of<lb/> the
                        <placeName key="ohio">Ohio</placeName>. And as they supposed they were
                    mostly<lb/> poor people, or they would not have settled on dis-<lb/>puted lands,
                    they now proposed that government <lb/> should give the money to them. It would
                    be a suf-<lb/>ficient compensation to those settlers, and might in-<lb/>duce
                    them to move quietly somewhere else, out of<lb/> the Indian country — and make
                    the <geogName key="ohior">Ohio</geogName> the bounda-<lb/>ry: for it was their
                    land. And signified, as the<lb/> land to the westward was filled up, they had
                    no-<lb/>where to repair to, and were now determined to lay <lb/><pb n="330"/>
                    their bones in that country. As to the concessions<lb/> the commissioners
                    proposed making, by giving mo-<lb/>ney, they did not want it; and running a new
                    line<lb/> was but giving them a part of their own land. And<lb/> as to
                    disclaiming the right to all their country by<lb/> virtue of the peace made with
                    the king, their father,<lb/> they knew they never were conquered, and the
                    pre-<lb/>emption right agreed on by the British and United<lb/> States,
                    concerning the purchasing of their country,<lb/> could not be binding on them;
                    for they supposed<lb/> they had a right to sell their lands to whom they<lb/>
                    pleased. Upon the whole, it was received as a very<lb/> contemptible speech, by
                    our commissioners — which<lb/> soon appeared to be the case, as the baggage
                    was<lb/> ordered on board, and caused an alarm in our camp. </p>
                <p> Some for safety proposed to lodge on board the ship,<lb/> and divers tents were
                    struck. Some went on board,<lb/> and others took to the house for safety. This
                    pros-<lb/>pect, all on a sudden, looked gloomy, and Friends<lb/> got together to
                    feel if any thing further opened for<lb/> us to do. We felt much shut up; — and
                    as we had <lb/> never been called into council with the commission-<lb/>ers, nor
                    had any public conference with the Indians,<lb/> we were obliged to bear our own
                    burthens, and sub-<lb/>mit the awful subject to the interposition of the
                    Di-<lb/>vine hand, and turn our faces homeward to our dear<lb/> friends and
                    connections, in hopes of reaching our<lb/> Yearly Meeting. </p>

                <p> This evening, two runners who were despatched<lb/> three days ago, returned with
                    a verbal message from<lb/> the <orgName key="sxntns">Five Nations</orgName>, who
                    expected us to come for-<lb/>ward, and were moving six miles down the river
                    to<lb/> meet us. They having all along appeared very<lb/> friendly to the
                        <orgName key="usag">United States</orgName>, this appeared an art-<lb/><pb
                        n="331"/> ful manoeuvre, on one side or the other. It was<lb/> somewhat
                    extraordinary to hear <persName key="glinc1">general Lincoln</persName>
                    ex-<lb/>press, that they had received just such an answer as<lb/> he could have
                    wished. What his meaning was, is<lb/> unknown. Friends slept in their tents as
                    heretofore,<lb/> I believe with little fear. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-17">17th</date>. <geogName key="detror" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> We were hurried on board soon after break-<lb/>fast, with the remainder of "our
                    baggage. Two run-<lb/>ners were dispatched by the commissioners to the<lb/>
                    <orgName key="sxntns">Six Nations</orgName>, the object unknown to us. About
                    ele-<lb/>ven o'clock, we were all on board, and stood down<lb/> the river into
                    the lake. My mind felt sorrowful and<lb/> very heavy, reflecting on the
                    important subject of<lb/> our journey; but I could see nothing material
                    omit-<lb/>ted on our part, to give uneasiness: so I endeavoured<lb/> to rest
                    quiet, leaving the event to Him who judgeth<lb/> righteously. In this part of
                    the world, but little mo-<lb/>rality, law, or religion, appears to govern the
                    peo-<lb/>ple, though the climate is blessed with health and<lb/> there is plenty
                    of the good things of this life; no-<lb/>thing being wanting but industry and
                    thankful<lb/> hearts. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-18">18th</date>. <geogName key="lakee" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> First of the week. We came to anchor<lb/> among a cluster of islands in the west
                    end of the<lb/> lake; of which there is said to be about thirty, great<lb/> and
                    small. Some of them produce abundance of red<lb/> cedar, much used in ship
                    building — there are also<lb/> raccoons and many other wild animals on them.
                    We<lb/> stood out into the open lake with pleasant weather.<lb/> Had a season of
                    solid retirement in the cabin, with <lb/> a few of our fellow passengers, to a
                    good degree of<lb/>satisfaction and comfort; though held in much con-<lb/>tempt
                    by others, who supposed themselves wise and <lb/> good enough already. </p>


                <pb n="332"/>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-19">19th</date>.<geogName key="lakee" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> Light head wind. We have thirty-one pas-<lb/>sengers on board, besides the
                    ship's crew and ma-<lb/>rines. Provisions plenty — poultry, sheep, hogs —<lb/>
                    and two bears belonging to <persName key="cbunb1">captain Bunbury</persName>.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-19">19th</date>. <geogName key="loomh"/></dateline>
                <p> We passed the mouth of <geogName key="cayah">Cayahoga river</geogName>,<lb/> and
                    in sight of the <geogName key="loomh">Looming-hills</geogName> on the south
                    shore,<lb/> land claimed and held by the <orgName key="delaware">Delaware
                        Indians</orgName>. —<lb/>The light and trivial conversation on board,
                    accom-<lb/>panied with such a degree of profanity in language<lb/> and behavior
                    one to another, at times, was truly<lb/> distressing, though otherwise we were
                    as comforta-<lb/>bly accommodated as the nature of our situation <lb/> would
                    admit. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-22">22d</date>. <placeName key="ferie"/></dateline>
                <p> We anchored at <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>. — <date
                        when="1793-08-23">23d</date>. Rainy,<lb/> no goods or baggage could be
                    landed, as the lake<lb/> was rough, which caused a great surf. <date
                        when="1793-08-24">24th</date>. Morn-<lb/>ing fair and calm — a great stir,
                    hoisting out casks,<lb/> trunks, &amp;c. The commissioners preparing to set<lb/>
                    forward, some by water, others by land. <persName key="wsave1">William<lb/>
                        Savery</persName> and <persName key="whart">William Hartshorne</persName>,
                    are to go with <persName key="glinc1">ge-<lb/>neral Lincoln</persName>, by
                        <geogName key="lakeo">Ontario</geogName>.<persName key="jlind1">Jacob
                        Lindley</persName> is pro-<lb/>vided with a horse by the commissioners, and
                    goes<lb/> by land; so that we are all busily engaged fixing our<lb/> baggage
                    each in his own way, clearing off all ex-<lb/>penses for passage, &amp;c. And
                    truly we may say, by<lb/> this time, we became pretty much stript of the
                    con-<lb/>tents of our purses, and a great deal of our stock of<lb/> provisions,
                    &amp;c. <persName key="jelli1">John Elliott</persName> and <persName
                        key="jparr1">John Parrish</persName> went<lb/> on shore in the afternoon, to
                    get to some Friend's <lb/> house. <persName key="jlind1">Jacob
                        Lindley</persName> and myself went in the even-<lb/>ing to the house of
                        <persName key="bwill1">Benjamin Willson</persName>, who had been<lb/> on
                    board with us all the afternoon. I felt myself in<lb/> some measure, like one
                    let out of prison. Here we<lb/> were kindly treated and lodged; proposing to
                    visit a <lb/>
                    <pb n="333"/> number of Friends and friendly people, in and about<lb/> this
                    neighborhood, before we set out for home;<lb/> which seemed annexed to my
                    concern in coming<lb/> forth to this country, to attend the proposed treaty<lb/>
                    with the Indians. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-25">25th</date>.<placeName key="ferie"/></dateline>
                <p> First of the week. We held a public meet-<lb/>ing, and visited a few families —
                    towards evening,<lb/> got to <persName key="ascho1">Asa Schooley's</persName>,
                    where <persName key="jparr1">John Parrish</persName> came to<lb/> us. Here we
                    lodged. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-26">26th</date>.<placeName key="ferie"/></dateline>
                <p>
                    <persName key="jelli1">John Elliott</persName> came to us this morning — so<lb/>
                    that we are now all together again. We went to <persName key="jherr1">John<lb/>
                        Herrit</persName>'s, son-in-law to <persName key="ascho1">Asa
                        Schooley</persName>, had a sitting<lb/> there and returned to <persName
                        key="ascho1">Asa</persName>'s — there had a solid op-<lb/>portunity with his
                    family and the family of <persName key="jcutl1">John<lb/> Cutler</persName>,
                    together; — after which, went to <persName key="dpoun1">Daniel<lb/>
                        Pound</persName> 's and lodged. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-27">27th</date>. <placeName key="ebin"/></dateline>
                <p> We held a public meeting at <persName key="jhave1">Joseph
                    Ha-<lb/>ven</persName>'s, which was large and favoured; at the close,<lb/> we
                    had a select opportunity with such as profess<lb/> with Friends, a number of
                    them being members, to<lb/> whom some interesting matters of advice were
                    com-<lb/>municated. Upon the whole, we thought it a very<lb/> solid and
                    profitable opportunity, many hearts being<lb/>tendered; for whom, in their
                    lonely situation, we<lb/> were brought into near sympathy. We parted from<lb/>
                    them in much love. <persName key="jparr1">John Parrish</persName> and myself
                    went<lb/> to <persName key="ezden">Ezekiel Dennis</persName>'s, up the side of
                        <geogName key="lakee">Lake Erie</geogName> about<lb/> six miles, to
                        <placeName key="ebin">point Ebino</placeName>, where we were kind-<lb/>ly
                    entertained and lodged. I think when the meet-<lb/>ing was select as above
                    mentioned, there was in the<lb/> whole, young and old, about forty — many
                    decent<lb/> looking young people, with innocent countenances,<lb/> were present;
                    on account of whom I felt much con-<lb/>cern for their religious and school
                    education. </p>


                <pb n="334"/>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-28">28th.</date>
                    <placeName key="suga"/></dateline>
                <p> Set out and rode up the beautiful beach on<lb/> the lake shore, about ten miles,
                    to what is called the<lb/>
                    <placeName key="suga">Sugar Loaf</placeName>, a point of land extending out in
                    the<lb/> lake, with a remarkable round hill, at a distance re-<lb/>sembling a
                    sugar loaf. Here we visited seven fami-<lb/>lies, and returned in the evening to
                    our friend <persName key="ascho1">Asa<lb/> Schooley</persName>'s. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-29">29th</date>. <placeName key="ferie"/></dateline>
                <p> With divers other Friends, we went about<lb/> twelve miles to <persName
                        key="jpowe1">esquire Powell</persName>'s, where we had a<lb/> large public
                    meeting of Friends and others, to much<lb/>satisfaction to ourselves, and I
                    believe it was so to the<lb/> auditory. They behaved quiet, and with
                    becoming<lb/> decency. After which many Friends took leave of<lb/> us in much
                    love and tenderness, and departed to<lb/> their several homes. We dined with the
                    squire, be-<lb/>ing freely and liberally entertained. Afterwards I<lb/> rode
                    about four miles to the fort, and went on board<lb/> the Dunmore on a small
                    errand, with our friend <persName key="wlund1">Wil-<lb/>liam Lundy</persName>,
                    who having heard of our being here,<lb/> came about twenty miles to see us, and
                    was at the<lb/> meeting to-day. In the evening went to our friend<lb/>
                    <persName key="bwill1">Benjamin Willson</persName>'s — leaving the other Friends
                    at<lb/> Powell's. <persName key="jelli1">John Elliott </persName>had been very
                    poorly with<lb/> the ague and fever — am fearful he will hardly be<lb/> able to
                    ride very soon, which is now a great trial to<lb/> us, being very desirous to
                    move towards home -- </p>

                <p> Having had the two public meetings above mention-<lb/>ed, and visited most of
                    the families and Friends in<lb/> this country, to wit, <persName key="ascho1"
                        >Asa Schooley</persName>,<persName key="jhave1">Joseph Havens</persName> ,<lb/>
                    <persName key="odenn1">Obadiah Dennis</persName>, <persName key="awebs1">Abraham
                        Webster</persName>, <persName key="jcutl1">John Cutler</persName>,<lb/>
                    <persName key="jhill1">John Hill</persName>, <persName key="bhill1">Benjamin
                        Hill</persName>, <persName key="jmoor2">Jeremiah Moore</persName>, <persName
                        key="alain">(Abra-<lb/>ham Laing</persName>, and <persName key="bcan"
                        >Benjamin Canby</persName>, single men) <persName key="jtayl2">John<lb/>
                        Taylor</persName>, <persName key="jgilh1">Joshua Gillam</persName>,
                        <persName key="jmars1">Joseph Marsh</persName>, <persName key="aburw1">Adam
                        Bur-<lb/>well</persName>, <persName key="dpoun1">Daniel Pound</persName>,
                        <persName key="wlund1">William Lundy</persName>, <persName key="trice1"
                        >Thomas Rice</persName>, <lb/>
                    <pb n="335"/>
                    <persName key="jcraw1">James Crawford</persName>, <persName key="esnig1">Enoch
                        Scrigley</persName>, <persName key="stayl1">Samuel Taylor</persName>,<lb/>
                    <persName key="ezden">Ezekiel Dennis</persName>, and several others. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-30">30th</date>. <placeName key="ferie"></placeName></dateline>
                <p> We now began to prepare to leave this part<lb/> of the country. This morning the
                    other Friends<lb/> came to me at <persName key="bwill1">Benjamin
                        Willson</persName>'s. <persName key="jparr2">Jasper Parrish</persName><lb/>
                    we hear is very poorly at the landing, not able to<lb/> return. We felt loth to
                    leave him, but understand-<lb/>ing <persName key="gchap1">general
                        Chapin</persName>, with whom he has his home, is<lb/> expected to be here in
                    about a week, we were the<lb/> more easy to leave him. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-31">31st</date>. <geogName key="buffc1"></geogName></dateline>
                <p>
                    <persName key="jelli1">John Elliott</persName> now bravely, though weak,<lb/>
                    seems very willing to move forward. We waited<lb/> this morning for <persName
                        key="alain">Abraham Laing</persName>, a young man who<lb/> is going to the
                    States, and is very desirous of our<lb/> company. Then went to <persName
                        key="powel1">Powell</persName>'s, and thence to<lb/>
                    <persName key="wind1">Windecker</persName>'s, the ferryman, where <persName
                        key="alain">Abraham Laing</persName><lb/> came to us — we crossed over and
                    went three miles<lb/> to <persName key="cwin2">Cornelius Winney</persName>'s, at
                        <geogName key="buffc1">Buffalo creek</geogName>. Here we<lb/> stayed, as
                    there is no house between this and the<lb/>
                    <placeName key="genes2">Genesee</placeName>, which is called seventy-five miles.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-01">9th mo. 1st.</date>
                    <geogName key="genes2"/></dateline>
                <p> First-day. Set out early for <placeName key="genes2">Gene-<lb/>see</placeName> —
                    rode about forty miles; night came on, and we<lb/> halted by the side of a small
                    brook, and began to<lb/> make preparation for a shelter, but a cloud came
                    on<lb/> with heavy thunder and rain. We made out to get<lb/> a fire kindled,
                    which was a comfort to us; but we<lb/> got very wet. The wind being high,
                    several trees<lb/> fell near us, which was somewhat alarming. The<lb/> gust held
                    about two hours, and then cleared up with<lb/> bright starlight the remainder of
                    the night. We all<lb/> lay before the fire, in the best manner we could,
                    in<lb/>our wet situation, got some sleep, but were some<lb/>what afflicted with
                    the musketoes. On the whole,<lb/> we thought ourselves much favoured. </p>


                <pb n="336"/>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-02">2d</date>. <geogName key="genes2"/></dateline>
                <p> We were up early, looked out for our horses,<lb/> put on our kettle, and made a
                    good dish of choco-<lb/>late, wherein our friend <persName key="jparr1">John
                        Parrish</persName>, was princi-<lb/>pal director — then set out and rode
                    about thirty-five<lb/> miles to the <geogName key="genes2">Genesee
                        river</geogName>, which we crossed by<lb/> fording, and put up at <persName
                        key="gberr">John Gilbert Berry</persName>'s, where<lb/> we were comfortably
                    entertained. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-03">3d</date>.<placeName key="willi"/></dateline>
                <p> After writing letters to <persName key="ichap2">general Chapin</persName> at<lb/>
                    <placeName key="canan">Canandaigua</placeName>, <persName key="cbunb1">captain
                        Bunbury</persName> at <placeName key="niagaf">Niagara</placeName>, and
                        <persName key="haupa1">cap-<lb/>tain Hendricks</persName>,<lb/> a chief
                    among the <orgName key="sxntns">Five Nations</orgName>, we<lb/> rode sixteen
                    miles to <persName key="jmill4">James Miller</persName>'s, superintendent<lb/>
                    of <orgName key="willif">Williamsburgh farm</orgName>, where we put up for
                    the<lb/> night, there being no place for lodging short of for-<lb/>ty miles
                    further. Among the many Indians resort-<lb/>ing about <persName key="gberr"
                        >Berry</persName>'s, we saw a woman, said to be a<lb/> hundred years old. In
                    conversation with her, and<lb/> admiring her grey hair, she assigned as a reason
                    for<lb/> her long life, that she was always kind and good,<lb/> and against all
                    quarrels; therefore God had spared<lb/> her to see the sun a long time; pointing
                    up to it. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-04">4th</date>. <placeName key="bath" type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p> This morning we took a wrong road and<lb/> had to return, by which we lost about
                    ten miles, so<lb/> that we were not able to reach <placeName key="bath"
                        >Bath</placeName>, and lodged at<lb/> the same old Indian cabin we were at
                    in going up<lb/> in the spring, eleven miles short of the place we<lb/> aimed
                    at. We struck up a fire and slept pretty com-<lb/>fortably. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-03">5th</date>. <placeName key="bath"/></dateline>
                <p> We rode to <placeName key="bath">Bath</placeName>, and late in the evening
                    got<lb/> to <persName key="clind2">colonel Lindley</persName>'s, where we put
                    up, having rode<lb/>about forty miles. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-06">6th</date>. <placeName key="block" type="unattested"></placeName></dateline>
                <p> We were up early, proposing to reach the<lb/>
                    <placeName key="block">Block-house</placeName>, distant about forty miles, but
                    having<lb/> our young friend <persName key="alain">Abraham Laing></persName> in
                    company, with<lb/> a poor little horse that tired on the way, our pro-<lb/>
                    <pb n="337"/> gress was retarded, so that we were benighted in<lb/> very dark
                    thick woods, and were obliged to alight.<lb/> There, tying up our horses to the
                    trees, with much<lb/> difficulty we kindled a fire, and lay on the ground,<lb/>
                    which, with our clothes, were wet with rain. We<lb/> kept up our fire, got a
                    little sleep, wishing for day,<lb/> and were glad when it appeared. We left
                        <persName key="alain">Abraham <lb/> Laing></persName> with his tired horse
                    about eight miles back,<lb/> where there is a small cabin in the woods. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-07">7th</date>. <placeName key="loyal"/></dateline>
                <p> Mounted our horses before sun-rise, and<lb/> rode two miles to the <placeName
                        key="block">Block-house</placeName>, where we took<lb/> breakfast, and gave
                    our horses as much oats as we<lb/> thought would be useful. Being thus
                    refreshed, we<lb/> set out, leaving <persName key="alain">Abraham
                        Laing</persName> to come on as well<lb/> as he could, in hopes that he may
                    overtake us at<lb/>
                    <placeName key="muncy">Muncy</placeName>. We rode seventeen miles to <persName
                        key="jkyle1">James Kyle</persName>'s,<lb/> and dined — thence fourteen miles
                    to our friend<lb/>
                    <persName key="sharr">Samuel Harris</persName>'s, at <placeName key="loyal"
                        >Loyalsock</placeName>, where <persName key="jparr1">John
                    Parrish</persName><lb/> and myself lodged, leaving <persName key="jlind1"/>Jacob
                    Lindley and <persName key="jelli1">John<lb/> Elliott</persName> five miles hack
                    to get their horses shod. —<lb/> Here we heard of great sickness in
                    Philadelphia. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-08">8th</date>. <placeName key="muncy"/></dateline>
                <p> First of the week. After breakfast, <persName key="jlind1">Jacob<lb/>
                        Lindley</persName> and <persName key="jelli1">John Elliott</persName> came
                    up, and we went to<lb/>
                    <orgName key="muncym">Muncy</orgName> meeting. Here we met with a number of<lb/>
                    our dear friends. This seemed very pleasant, and<lb/> we had a solid, favoured
                    time together. After which<lb/> we went to our friend <persName key="swall1"
                        >Samuel Wallace</persName>'s and dined,<lb/> then disposed of ourselves in
                    several places to lodge.<lb/> I went to <persName key="hpark1">Henry
                        Parker</persName>'s. We all felt a little of<lb/> the effects , of lying in
                    the damp woods in our wet<lb/> clothes, and hard travelling for two days past,
                    with<lb/> rough roads, and crossing many creeks; one called<lb/>
                    <geogName key="trout">Trout run</geogName>, we crossed thirty times, and
                        <geogName key="lycom3">Lycoming<lb/> creek</geogName> seven times — with
                    several large mountains, <lb/>
                    <pb n="338"/> one of which was a part of the <geogName key="allemo"
                        >Alleghany</geogName>. The<lb/> sickness in Philadelphia confirmed in every
                    place. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-09">9th</date>. <placeName key="muncy"/></dateline>
                <p> Not feeling quite clear of this neighbour-<lb/>hood, we held another meeting at
                        <orgName key="muncym">Muncy </orgName>meeting<lb/> house, which was larger
                    than yesterday, and much<lb/> favoured. After dinner, went back six miles to
                        <persName key="sharr">Sa-<lb/>muel Harris</persName>'s, over the very large
                    and rapid creek<lb/> called <geogName key="loyac">Loyalsock</geogName>. Here we
                    had a large and satisfac-<lb/>tory meeting. Most of our company returned, but
                    I<lb/> stayed here. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-10">10th</date>. <placeName key="fishi"/></dateline>
                <p> Our friend S. H., an ancient man, has lain<lb/> poorly for some time, and not
                    likely to continue<lb/> long. He seems quiet and calm, and told me this<lb/>
                    morning, he felt bravely refreshed, and much satis-<lb/>fied with the meeting,
                    and the company of his friends.<lb/> I took a solemn leave of him and the
                    family, and pro-<lb/>ceeded to <persName key="swall1">Wallace</persName>'s. We
                    then all set out together,<lb/> and rode to <persName key="welli1">William
                        Ellis</persName>'s, where we settled the<lb/> running accounts we had among
                    ourselves. Our<lb/> friend <persName key="jlind1">Jacob Lindley</persName>
                    concluded here to leave us,<lb/> and proceed home by way of <placeName
                        key="harrisb">Harrisburgh</placeName>. We<lb/> then went on, having
                        <persName key="jcarp1">Joseph Carpenter</persName> for a guide,<lb/>
                    eighteen miles toward <placeName key="catta">Catawissa</placeName>, and put up at
                    our<lb/> friend <persName key="jeves1">John Eves</persName>'s, at <placeName
                        key="fishi">Fishing creek</placeName>, where we were<lb/> kindly
                    entertained. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-11">11th</date>. <placeName key="catta"/></dateline>
                <p> Here we had a meeting with a few Friends<lb/> and divers of their neighbours, in
                    a school house, to<lb/> a good degree of satisfaction and comfort. Set out<lb/>
                    in company with <persName key="ijam2">Isaac James</persName>, brother to
                        <persName key="jjam3">John</persName>, in<lb/> Philadelphia, and rode about
                    twelve miles to <placeName key="catta">Catta-<lb/>wissa</placeName>, crossing the
                    north-east branch of the <geogName key="susqu">Susque-<lb/>hanna</geogName>, and
                    put up at our friend <persName key="jlloy1">John Lloyd</persName>'s. Here<lb/>
                    is a small town of about thirty buildings. I lodged<lb/> at <persName
                        key="jwat2">James Watson</persName>'s, <persName key="jparr1">John
                        Parrish</persName> at <persName key="jwill1">John Lloyd</persName>'s, <lb/>
                    <pb n="339"/> poorly, <persName key="jelli1">John Elliott</persName> stopped
                    about eight miles short<lb/> of this, at <persName key="jwill1">John
                        Willson</persName>'s. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-12">12th</date>. <placeName key="roari"/></dateline>
                <p>
                    <persName key="jelli1">John Elliott</persName> came to us this morning. On<lb/>
                    his way he called to see an ancient Friend, now in<lb/> the ninety-seventh year
                    of her age. We had no<lb/> public meeting here, but visited most of the
                    families<lb/> of Friends in town, wherein our friend <persName key="jparr1">John
                        Par-<lb/>rish</persName> had good service, and was much favoured. In<lb/>
                    the afternoon we rode about nine miles to <placeName key="roarc">Roaring<lb/>
                        creek </placeName>. This part of the country is hilly and moun-<lb/>tainous,
                    — the valleys interspersed with good farms.<lb/> Many Friends are settled
                    hereabouts. Lodged at<lb/>
                    <persName key="mstar1">Moses Starr</persName>'s. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-13">13th</date>. <geogName key="crun1"/></dateline>
                <p> Rode twenty-six miles to <geogName key="crun1">Cold Run</geogName>, and<lb/> put
                    up at <persName key="swebb2">Samuel Webb</persName>'s, having crossed the
                        <geogName key="lmoun">Little<lb/> Mountain</geogName>, <geogName key="mahon"
                        > Mahony</geogName> ,<geogName key="broam">Broad</geogName>, <geogName
                        key="locu"> Locust</geogName>, and <geogName key="tusca">Tuscarora<lb/>
                        mountains</geogName>. Great part of the way very rough and<lb/> stony. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-14">14th</date>. <placeName key="harke"/></dateline>
                <p> Set out and rode seven miles to <persName key="rstep1">Richard<lb/>
                        Stephens</persName>'s — thence to <placeName key="harke"
                        >Harkerstown</placeName>. We here met<lb/> with our friend <persName
                        key="mlee1">Mordecai Lee</persName>, who had heard of<lb/> our coming, and
                    came to meet us. We went home<lb/> with him. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-15">15th</date>. <placeName key="readi"/></dateline>

                <p> First of the week. <persName key="jwrig1">Joseph Wright</persName>, living<lb/>
                    in one part of the house with his family, has lately<lb/> been afflicted with
                    the bloody flux, by which he had<lb/> lost three children. Divers Friends came
                    here to<lb/> see us, viz. <persName key="jstar1">John Starr</persName>,
                        <persName key="twrig1">Thomas Wright</persName>, <persName key="lpilk">Levi
                        Pil-<lb/>kington</persName>, &amp;c. We all attended their sa meeting at
                        <orgName key="maide">Mai-<lb/>den creek</orgName> — and after dinner
                    proceeded nine miles to<lb/>
                    <placeName key="readi">Reading,</placeName> where we put up at <persName
                        key="sjack1">Samuel Jackson</persName>'s. —<lb/> The sickness, and distress
                    in consequence thereof,<lb/> we still hear confirmed, and much talked of, as
                    still<lb/> raging to a great degree in <placeName key="phila">
                        Philadelphia</placeName> — which, I <lb/>
                    <pb n="340"/> expect will be a trying circumstance to many friends<lb/> in the
                    country, in getting to our ensuing Yearly<lb/> Meeting. May the good hand be
                    near to help us. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-18">18th</date>. <placeName key="pottt"
                        type="unattested"/></dateline>
                <p>
                    <persName key="swall1">Samuel Wallace</persName>, from <placeName key="muncy"
                        >Muncy</placeName>, called to see<lb/> us. He left the city yesterday, and
                    confirms the<lb/> accounts of the sickness and mortality to be quite<lb/> equal
                    to what we have heard — and that the principal<lb/> nurses for the sick, and
                    buriers of the dead, are the<lb/> blacks, of whom it is said, very few or none
                    have<lb/> yet taken the disorder. After breakfast we set out<lb/> and rode
                    twenty-three miles to <persName key="jpot">Joseph Potts</persName>'s, <lb/>where
                    we lodged. Here we again heard much of<lb/> the distressed situation of
                        <placeName key="phila"> Philadelphia</placeName>. Our friend<lb/>
                    <persName key="jelli1">John Elliott</persName> left <persName key="jparr1">John
                        Parrish</persName> and myself here, pro-<lb/>posing to ride into town this
                    evening to his family. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-19">19th</date>. <placeName key="germa"/></dateline>
                <p> I have been these two days past, poorly<lb/> with a cold, and very hoarse; but
                    through favour, this<lb/> morning, feel some better. <persName key="jparr1">John
                        Parrish</persName> was taken<lb/> in a carriage by a friend, proposing to go
                    to <placeName key="darby">Darby</placeName>,<lb/> where he understands his wife
                    was gone, intending<lb/> to go by <persName key="jfiel">John Field</persName>'s,
                    who with many others are<lb/> out of town. At the same time I set out with
                    my<lb/> friend <persName key="jpot">Joseph Potts</persName>, and rode nine miles
                    to <placeName key="germa">German-<lb/>town</placeName>. Called at <persName
                        key="hdrin1">Henry Drinker</persName>'s, who with his<lb/> family were here.
                    From thence went with <persName key="hdrin1">Henry</persName><lb/> to <persName
                        key="jpemb1">John Pemberton</persName>'s, who was here also with his
                    <lb/>family. Having heard that <persName key="grand1">Beverly
                        Randolph</persName> was<lb/> at his cousin <persName key="erand1">Edmund
                        Randolph</persName>'s, the attorney ge-<lb/>neral of the United States,
                    about three miles from<lb/> this, and being desirous to see him, towards
                    even-<lb/>ing, <persName key="jpemb1">John Pemberton</persName>, <persName
                        key="hdrin1">Henry Drinker</persName> and myself<lb/> went there in
                        <persName key="jpemb1">John</persName>'s carriage. We were glad to see<lb/>
                    each other again, and after spending about an hour <lb/>and a half together in
                    free conversation, returned to <lb/>
                    <pb n=" 341"/>
                    <placeName key="germa"/>Germantown, where I lodged at my friend <persName
                        key="jjohn5">John<lb/> Johnson</persName>'s. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-20">20th</date>. <placeName key="germa"/></dateline>
                <p> The weather dry and warm — thought to be<lb/> rather unfavorable to the sick in
                    the city, where<lb/> deaths and burials are frequent through the day. —<lb/>
                    Here I met with my friend <persName key="slund1">Sarah Lundy</persName>, who
                    is<lb/> on her way to the Yearly Meeting, and a proposed<lb/> visit to the
                    Southern States. Also, again met with<lb/> my dear friend, <persName
                        key="wsave1">William Savery</persName>, who came in last<lb/> evening, his
                    wife being here, and having taken<lb/> lodgings at <persName key="chain1">Caspar
                        Haines</persName>'s. We were all together<lb/> at their <orgName
                        key="germpm">preparative meeting</orgName>, where divers weighty<lb/>
                    testimonies were delivered by <persName key="slund1">Sarah Lundy</persName>
                    and<lb/> others; and solemn supplication by <persName key="wsave1">William
                        Savery</persName>.<lb/>
                    <persName key="whart">Wm. Hartshorne</persName> returned home from <placeName
                        key="nycit">New York</placeName>, <lb/>well. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-21">21st</date>. <placeName key="phila"/></dateline>
                <p> This being the day for opening our select <lb/><orgName key="pym">Yearly
                        Meeting</orgName>, it was exceedingly trying to many<lb/> Friends, on
                    account of the prevailing and mortal<lb/> disorder raging in the city, where it
                    is said from a <lb/>hundred to a hundred and fifty of a day, have been<lb/>
                    taken to their graves. I was much exercised in<lb/> mind on that account, being
                    yet poorly with my<lb/> cold, which 1 now apprehend to be what is common-<lb/>ly
                    called the influenza; — however, on the whole, I<lb/> thought I felt most easy
                    to go forward, and rode<lb/> into <placeName key="phila"
                        >Philadelphia</placeName>, attended the meeting at Fourth<lb/> street, which
                    was a solid, favoured time, though <lb/>very small. There were some Friends from
                    every<lb/> Quarter, though many of the representatives were<lb/> absent. I think
                    from one meeting there was but<lb/> one answered. The number on the women's
                    side<lb/> of the house, in the whole, twenty-four. I dined at<lb/>
                    <persName key="twist1">Thomas Wistar</persName>'s, and towards evening returned
                    to <lb/>
                    <pb n="342"/>
                    <placeName key="germa">Germantown</placeName>, feeling myself very poorly with
                    great<lb/> debility. While in the city, I had occasion to pass<lb/> by Friends'
                    burial ground, the <geogName key="pfiel">Potter's field</geogName>-, and<lb/>
                    several others. The prospect was awful and alarm-<lb/>ing, to behold the many
                    new graves, and others dig-<lb/>ging, with the hearses standing, and some
                    coming<lb/> and going — most of which were attended by the<lb/> black people,
                    whom it is said the disorder has not <lb/>reached. This is a token of mercy,
                    mixed with<lb/> judgment, both to them and the whites, they being<lb/> the
                    principal nurses and carriers of the dead. I am<lb/> hardly able to describe my
                    feelings on the present<lb/> occasion, believing it to be all in wisdom, and
                    hoping<lb/> it may have a tendency to bring the lofty from their<lb/> seats, and
                    beget greater humility than has of latter<lb/> time appeared in that highly
                    favoured city. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-22">22nd</date>. <placeName key="germ"/></dateline>
                <p> First of the week. The weather much the<lb/> same as many days past. I felt very
                    weak and poor-<lb/>ly; did not go out to meeting, but kept in my quar-<lb/>ters,
                    where I was very kindly and tenderly treated,<lb/> wanting for nothing the house
                    could afford to make<lb/> me comfortable. <persName key="jjohn5">John
                        Johnson</persName> and his wife <persName key="rjohn2"/>Rachel,<lb/> appear
                    to be tender-hearted, sympathizing friends,<lb/> blessed with a plenty of the
                    good things of this life,<lb/> and an open disposition to communicate freely
                    to<lb/> those that are in need. May the Lord reward them,<lb/> as good stewards
                    of the manifold favours received. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-23">23rd</date>. <placeName key="phila"/></dateline>
                <p> This day our general <orgName key="pym">Yearly Meeting</orgName> be-<lb/>gins,
                    at ten o'clock in the morning. I much desired<lb/> to be there; but remaining
                    poorly, concluded to lay<lb/> by another day for rest. I think I now feel the
                    ef-<lb/>fects of hard riding through the wilderness, and ly-<lb/>ing on the damp
                    ground; being stiffened, with sore-<lb/>ness in my bones. <persName key="jelli1"
                        >John Elliott</persName>, I hear, has been <lb/>
                    <pb n="343"/> poorly since his arrival in town. Neither he nor<lb/>
                    <persName key="jparr1">John Parrish</persName> was at meeting on seventh-day.
                        <persName key="jlind1">Jacob<lb/> Lindley</persName>, <persName key="wsave1"
                        >William Savery</persName> and myself were there,<lb/> and glad to see each
                    other again in that place; and<lb/> many friends expressed their gladness at our
                    safe<lb/> return. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-24">24th</date>. <placeName key="phila"/></dateline>
                <p> The weather dry and warm, the roads very<lb/> dusty. This morning felt better.
                    Leaving my horse<lb/> here, I rode into town with my friend <persName
                        key="jjohn5">John John-<lb/>son</persName>, in a chair -- attended two
                    sittings of our Yearly<lb/> Meeting, which was much smaller than usual. Our<lb/>
                    friend <persName key="nwai1">Nicholas Wain</persName>, was again chosen clerk
                    for<lb/> the present year; and the business went on in much <lb/>brotherly love
                    and concord — a good degree of so-<lb/>lemnity and weight attending. I lodged at
                        <persName key="thou1">Thomas<lb/> Hough></persName>'s. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-25">25th</date>. <placeName key="phila"/></dateline>
                <p> The weather much the same. I continue<lb/> tolerable well in health; but weak
                    and some cough.<lb/> Attended the meeting as yesterday. Dined at <persName
                        key="nwai1">N.<lb/> Wain</persName>'s, and lodged at <persName key="jjam3"
                        >John James</persName>'s. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-26">26th</date>, and fifth of the week. <placeName
                        key="phila"/></dateline>
                <p> The meeting assem-<lb/>bledagain at nine o'clock, and the business
                    conclu-<lb/>ded before twelve, in solemn quiet, and, I believe,<lb/> to the
                    satisfaction of all present. After which, I <lb/>dined with my friend <persName
                        key="dbaco1">David Bacon</persName>, and returned to <lb/><placeName
                        key="germa">Germantown</placeName> with my kind friend, <persName
                        key="jjohn5">John Johnson</persName>,<lb/> who had also attended all the
                    sittings of this Yearly<lb/> Meeting. The sickness in town continues as
                    here-<lb/>tofore. Divers friends in the city are paying con-<lb/>stant attention
                    to the sick — providing necessaries,<lb/> nurses, coffins, and carriers of the
                    dead. At which<lb/> I felt glad, and hope they will be rewarded for their<lb/>
                    labours in so great and charitable a work. </p>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
