<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei-print.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" hkey="global.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>Journal of Joshua Evans 1795-1796 (E): Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>Emma Remsberg</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Journal transcribed by</resp>
                    <name>Aaron Brecher</name>

                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Tri-Co Digital Humanities Initiative</sponsor>
                <funder>Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 222 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>This work is the property of the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore
                        College. It may be copied freely by individuals for personal use, research,
                        and teaching (including distribution to classes) as long as this statement
                        of availability is included in the text. It may be linked to freely in
                        Internet editions of all kinds, including for—profit works.</p>
                    <p>Publishers, libraries, and other information providers interested in
                        providing this text in a commercial or non—profit product or from an
                        information server must contact Swarthmore College for licensing and cost
                        information.</p>
                    <p> Scholars interested in changing or adding to these texts by, for example,
                        creating a new edition of the text (electronically or in print) with
                        substantive editorial changes, may do so with the permission of Swarthmore
                        College. This is the case whether the new publication will be made available
                        at a cost or free of charge.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2014">2014</date>
                <idno type="local">SW_JE1796E</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Native Americans and Quakers: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>Joshua Evans Papers</collection>
                        <idno>RG5/190 Journal E</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>81 pp. (1 volume)</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p> The Joshua Evans journal that includes his trip to visit Native Americans in New
                    York State in 1796, Journal E, is housed at Friends Historical Library, on the
                    campus of Swarthmore College. It is one of seven Evans journals that will be
                    published in 2016. The encoding was done as part of the Native Americans and
                    Quakers project.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> The transcribers and editor attempted to render the author’s orthography and
                    grammar as they appear on the page of his journal, even when the author’s own
                    spelling and usage are inconsistent. Additionally, many questions remain about
                    spelling the names of his Quaker acquaintances, individual Native Americans who
                    populate his journal, and Indian villages and towns. The transcribers and editor
                    attempted to remain faithful to the author’s Anglicized spellings in all cases. </p>
                <p>The author of the original journal does not include page numbers on his
                    manuscript; the page numbers have been interpolated by the transcribers to
                    correspond with the manuscript sheets.</p>
                <p> On page 181, there is a marginal note reading "obscurely expressed" that may
                    refer to Evans's original notes, that involves a number of possible
                    substitutions written above two words in the entry. The words may also be edits
                    of Warrington if he felt that that Evans's language was unclear.</p>
            </editorialDecl>

        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written in <date when="1796">1796</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Society of Friends</item>

                        <item>Church and state--New York</item>

                        <item>Indian reservations</item>
                        <item>Indians of North America--Missions</item>
                        <item>New York (State)--Description and travel</item>

                        <item>Philadelphia Yearly Meeting of the Religious Society of Friends</item>
                        <item>Quakers--Pennsylvania--Diaries</item>
                        <item>Quakers--Political activity</item>
                        <item>Seneca Indians</item>
                        <item>Society of Friends--Missions</item>
                        <item>Voyages and Travels</item>


                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>

        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="121" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_01"/>
                <dateline><emph rend="underline"><date when="1795-07">1795. 7th month.</date></emph><lb/>
                    <date when="1795-07-29">29th</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>


                <p>We set forward this Morning a little refreshed, and rode near<lb/>40 Miles
                    through a Mountainous Country; the people seem to live well, and<lb/>appear
                    open-hearted to receive friends, many being weary of their Teachers.<lb/>As I
                    was very weak in body, we hired a Chair to ease me in travelling,
                    &amp;<lb/>reached to our friend <persName key="smoor2">Samuel Moor</persName>'s
                    the <date when="1795-07-30">30th.</date> being about 40 miles; my wea-<lb/>ry
                    body and mind seemed to experience much Comfort. <del>we had two
                    meetings</del></p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-08-03">8th. mo. 3rd.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p> We had two meetings here, one of which was held in <persName key="smoor2"
                        >S.M.</persName>'s House, large<lb/>and satisfactory; and the other on a
                    mountain not far off: I marvelled at<lb/>the kindness of the People, and their
                    openness to receive:<lb/> we set<lb/>forward for <placeName key="annap"
                        >Annapolis</placeName>, and that afternoon had a Meeting at <orgName
                        key="meetrand">Randolph</orgName>,<lb/>and though very rainy, it was large
                    and very satisfactory. The next day<lb/>had a Meeting in a <orgName key="bapt"
                        >Baptist</orgName> Meeting-house near; and another about ten<lb/>miles off;
                    both were favoured seasons, and the people openhearted &amp; kind.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-08-06">6th.</date>
                    <placeName key="annap"/></dateline>
                <p> This day we reached to <placeName key="annap">Annapolis</placeName>, &amp; from
                    thence went to <persName key="ethor1">Edward ~~<lb/>Thorn</persName>'s, who
                    kindly took us in his Boat to <placeName key="digby">Digby</placeName> about
                    nine Miles.<lb/>This is a small Town of about 100 houses, standing on the Bason
                    so called, at<lb/>the Mouth of <geogName key="annri">Annapolis river</geogName>,
                    where that empties through a narrow pas-<lb/>sage into the <geogName key="fundy"
                        >Bay of Fundy</geogName>. Here the tide, it is said, riseth 30 feet. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-08-07">7th.</date>
                    <placeName key="digby"/></dateline>
                <p> A large room in the Tavern where we lodged, was freely offered to<lb/>hold
                    Meetings in; Which was this day occupied, and a large Meeting held<lb/>there to
                    good satisfaction, to the tendering of some hearts. -- We<lb/>were requested to
                    stay longer, &amp; to have more Meetings; but intending to cross <lb/>
                    <pb n="122" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_02"/><date><emph rend="underline">1795. 8th
                            month.</emph></date>
                    <lb/>the <geogName key="fundy">Bay</geogName>
                    <del>that</del> in a Vessel which was to sail that afternoon for<lb/>
                    <placeName key="newbr">New-Brunswick</placeName>; we thought it best to take
                    leave of them, and go<lb/>on board. We were on the water all night, which was to
                    me very<lb/>trying, as the motion of the vessel caused me to be very sick. In
                    about 22<lb/>hours we landed: it is called about forty Miles from <placeName
                        key="digby">Digby</placeName> to this <lb/> place. </p>
            </div>


            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-08-08">8th.</date><placeName key="newbr"/></dateline>

                <p> One who was called a Bishop of the Church of England, was<lb/>with us on board
                    of this Vessel. The man was respectful, and desired to<lb/>see my Certificate;
                    on it's being shewn to him, he commended it, and the<lb/>Order settled among
                    friends; saying, It well agreed with his Sentiments.<lb/>After this his kindness
                    towards me increased; for he came frequently<lb/>to enquire how I was; saying,
                    "Friend Evans, are you any better: And<lb/>when we parted, he gave me his
                    blessing, as also divers others did, in their <lb/>way</p>
            </div>


            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-08-09">9th.</date>
                    <placeName key="newbr"/>
                </dateline>
                <p>At <placeName key="newbr">New Brunswick</placeName> we had two large and
                    fa<lb/>voured <orgName key="meetnb">Meetings</orgName>, to the tendering of many
                    hearts, and bringing as I thought honour<lb/>to the Cause of Truth; many
                    expressed their Satisfaction, and I admi<lb/>red their solid sitting, as there
                    was long silence, and a number of them<lb/>never before at any of our meetings.
                    It was the Lord's mercy; Blessed be<lb/>his great Name; I am but as a worm, and
                    no man. ----</p>
                <p> Many of the People hereaway, have had an education amongst<lb/>Friends, and are
                    friendly; But appear to be as Sheep without a Shepherd<lb/>I felt Love flowing
                    towards them; and I thought great openness appear'd <unclear>in</unclear><lb/>
                    this town towards the Doctrine of Truth: a number expressing their
                        tend<unclear>erness</unclear><lb/>
                    <pb n="123" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_03"/>
                    <lb/>by the flowing of their Tears.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-08-10">10th.</date>
                    <placeName key="newbr"/></dateline>


                <p>On the other side of this <geogName key="fundy">Bay<lb/>of Fundy</geogName>,
                    there was not anything oppressed my mind with more sadness<lb/>than the manner,
                    the former French inhabitants of the Place, which were called<lb/>Neutrals, were
                    forced away from their improved Farms and Estates in this<lb/>Part of <placeName
                        key="novas">Nova Scotia</placeName>, by those acting under British
                    Authority, and Brit-<lb/>tish Subjects coming in to inherit the fruits of their
                    Labor. I mention'd my Sentiments<lb/> freely concerning such injustice taking
                    place, &amp; I am willing to leave it. </p>
            </div>



            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-08-10">10th.</date>
                    <placeName key="newbr"/></dateline>
                <p> As we had to wait for a passage from hence to <placeName key="beavh">Bever
                        Harbour</placeName>, visit-<lb/>ed a few families here, being kindly
                    received by the people where we came.</p>
            </div>


            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-08-11">11th.</date>
                    <placeName key="dippe"/></dateline>
                <p> This Morning, we went on board of a Boat with four Oars, and came about<lb/>20
                    Miles to <placeName key="dippe">Dipper-harbour</placeName>; here we lodged at
                    one Frenches, who <del>to</del> enter-<lb/>tained us kindly &amp; refused taking
                    pay for it: Being yet only about half<lb/>Way to <placeName key="beavh"
                        >Bever-Harbour</placeName>, we went on board early next morning, and<lb/>
                    coming thither, had a <orgName key="meetbeav">meeting in that place</orgName> in
                    the afternoon, which was a<lb/> solid season; <emph rend="underline"
                        >Likewise</emph> the next day we had another meeting, also solid.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-08-14">14th.</date>
                    <placeName key="passa"/></dateline>
                <p> We proceeded then about 20 Miles to <geogName key="passa"
                        >Passomaquady</geogName>, at the mouth<lb/>of the <geogName key="scroi"
                        >river Saint Croix</geogName>; and from thence the next day also by Water to<lb/>
                    <placeName key="machi">Machias</placeName> in the province of <placeName
                        key="maine">Main</placeName>: Here, altho' no member of our Society<lb/>
                    resided in the place, we had two large and satisfactory Meetings. They<lb/>
                    <del>people</del> desired us to stay longer, and have more: But I have found it
                    safest<lb/>to leave the People hungring, rather than to stay to make additions:
                    I wish<lb/>all who travel on Truth's account to guard against the Activity of
                    the<lb/>Creature, lest a good savour be not left among Strangers. Being </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="124" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_04"/>
                <dateline><emph rend="underline"><date when="1795-08">1795. 8th month.</date></emph><lb/>
                    <date when="1795-08-17">17th.</date>
                    <placeName key="penob"/></dateline>
                <p> Being kindly supplied with Horses, &amp; a man to<lb/>take them back, we went on
                    to <geogName key="pleas">Pleasant-River</geogName>, about 20 Miles towards<lb/>
                    <placeName key="penob">Penobscot</placeName>: As heretofore hinted there appears
                    to be much Openness<lb/>amongst the inhabitants of this Eastern Country towards
                    Friends: I thought<lb/>it looked as tho' "the fields were white unto Harvest;"
                    and that many seem<lb/>ed weary of their Teachers: We had a <orgName
                        key="meetpenob">Small solid meeting</orgName> here the<lb/>next day: After
                    which we crossed the <geogName key="pleas">River</geogName> to <persName
                        key="rcoff1">Richard Coffin</persName>'s.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-08-19">19th.</date>
                    <placeName key="penob"/></dateline>
                <p> Hiring Horses and a Man to take them back, we came about<lb/>30 Miles to
                        <geogName key="frenb">French-man's Bay</geogName>, and the next day we
                    reached to the house<lb/>of <persName key="pdudl1">Paul Dudley</persName>, who
                    was a very kind man: He offered his Boat and<lb/>Hands to take us near 30 Miles,
                    but It being rainy we tarried here till<lb/>the day following, <del>day</del>
                    and then were taken down <geogName key="frenb">Frenchman's<lb/>Bay</geogName> to
                    the <placeName key="blueh">Blue Hills</placeName>: </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-08-21">21st.</date>
                    <placeName key="penob"/></dateline>
                <p>On the Way to <placeName key="penob">Penobscot</placeName> we had<lb/>a pleasant
                    Passage; and I had to admire the goodness of the Lord,<lb/>in opening &amp;
                    preparing my Way. Blessed be his excellent Name, doth<lb/>my soul say,
                    tremblingly, in awful fear and Love. -- The next day<lb/>we hired Horses to
                    cross a neck of Land about six Miles; and then went<lb/>by water to <placeName
                        key="penob">Penobscot</placeName>: Feeling Poor in mind, and hearing of an
                    Opportu-<lb/>nity to go on further by Water, We had like to have gone, But
                    perceiv<lb/>ing an Opening unexpectedly for a <orgName key="meetpenob">meeting
                        here</orgName> next day, we concluded <unclear>to</unclear><lb/>tarry,
                    having one in the Morning, and also another in the afternoon,
                        <unclear>so</unclear><lb/>lid and profitable, I hope: The people's behaviour
                    was commendable, I was<lb/>comforted, and some benefit perhaps was received by
                    individuals among them.</p>

            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="125" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_05"/>
                <dateline><emph rend="underline"><date when="1795-08">8th month.</date></emph><lb/>
                    <date when="1795-08-24">24th.</date>
                    <placeName key="penob"/></dateline>
                <p> After leaving <placeName key="penob">Penobscot</placeName> we crossed the
                        <geogName key="penob2">bay</geogName> about 14 Miles to<lb/>
                    <placeName key="duckt">Ducktrap</placeName>, and had a <orgName key="meetduck"
                        >small solid meeting</orgName> among the People there<lb/>that afternoon;
                    they <del>people</del> behaved well; The next day we hired<lb/>a man and horses
                    to take us to <placeName key="camde">Camden</placeName> on <geogName
                        key="penob1">Penobscot bay</geogName>; and on<lb/>the day following had a
                        <orgName key="cammeet">small<emph rend="underline">ish</emph>
                        meeting</orgName> there, which I thought<lb/>was favour'd. Here I bought a
                    Horse, bridle and saddle, and rode<lb/>to <geogName key="broab">Broad
                        Bay</geogName>; where we had a satisfactory meeting at the widow<lb/>
                    <persName key="wchap1">Chapman</persName>'s House; in which deep impressions
                    were made on some<lb/>Minds, and we were brought near to each other, altho'
                    outwardly<lb/>Strangers. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-08-27">27th.</date><placeName key="durha"/></dateline>

                <p>In the afternoon we proceeded about 15 miles<lb/> to the <persName key="wkenn1"
                        >Widow Kennedy</persName>'s, near <geogName key="sheep">Sheepsgut</geogName>
                    Ferry; and on the day follow-<lb/> ing reached to our friend <persName
                        key="jhack1">Jeremiah Hacker</persName>'s at <placeName key="durha"
                        >Durham</placeName>;</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-08-29">29th</date><placeName key="falmo"/></dateline>
                <p>From hence, pro-<lb/>ceeding to <placeName key="falmo">Falmouth</placeName>, in
                    company of several friends, on first day were at<lb/><orgName key="meetfalm"
                        >meeting</orgName> there, which was, as I thought, poor and dull: The
                    weather was warm<lb/>and riding thus on horseback was trying to my shattered
                    condition: Yet I<lb/>am favoured: All praise belongs to the Lord: I have been
                    fully convinced<lb/>in this my pilgrim-like-Journey for the good of Souls, that
                    nothing<lb/>belongs to man, nor the contrivence of Men in putting forward the
                    Lord's<lb/> Work. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-09-02">31st <lb/>9th mo 2nd</date><placeName key="sandw"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>From <placeName key="falmo">Falmouth</placeName> we came to <placeName
                        key="meetsand">Sandwich</placeName>, where we had two<lb/> meetings, one of
                    which was publick; The other with our friends<lb/>selected: These were
                    exercising, but I believe they ended well. Hard labour<lb/>and much Poverty seem
                    to be my allotment: But let me not murmur<lb/>
                    <pb n="126" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_06"/>
                    <lb/> murmur; The Lord has hitherto helped me.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-09-03">3rd</date>.<placeName key="sandw"/>
                </dateline>
                <p> From hence we are to journey to <placeName key="coho1">Cohorse</placeName>, in
                        <placeName key="vermo">Vermont.</placeName></p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-09-05"/>.<placeName key="coho1"/>
                </dateline>
                <p> At which <lb/>place we arrived on the <date when="1795-09-04">4th</date>. I was
                    much weary. We had two <orgName key="meetcoho">Meetings</orgName> the
                    day<lb/>following, being first day; One of them was held in a
                    School-house<lb/>in a good degree solid; the other in a <orgName key="bapt"
                        >Baptist</orgName> Meeting house, large, but<lb/>interrupted by the people's
                    going out and in: It is often so, when we consent<lb/>to hold meetings in the
                    houses which belong to People of other Societies.<lb/>I believe we ought
                    carefully to feel our way, even when their houses are offered<lb/>freely. Here I
                    met with my friend <persName key="hhull1">Henry Hull</persName> from <placeName
                        key="9part1">Nine Partners</placeName>.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-09-07">7th</date>. <placeName key="sharo"/></dateline>
                <p> I had a Meeting in <orgName key="meetsharo">Sharon</orgName> near Bassett's, which was large; but it<lb/>suffered Loss
                    by a friend's speaking rather too much about his own<lb/>Convincement: My Mind
                    was distressed hereby; And my desires are that<lb/>Friends of the Ministry may
                    be well guarded against branching out<lb/>improperly, when silence might be more
                    useful near a Meeting's Conclusion.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>We now set out for <placeName key="danby">Danby</placeName>, through a
                    Mountainous Country, which<lb/><date when="1795-09-09">9th.</date>
                </dateline>
                <p> we reached the next day. My journey since I left my habitation, I<lb/>think
                    amounts to near two thousand Miles by land and Water till<lb/>came to this
                    place; And I am thankful that I feel in good measure<lb/>Comfortable after the
                    Fatigue which has attended such a long Travel.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-09-10">10th</date>. <placeName key="danby"/></dateline>
                <p> At <orgName key="meetdanby">Danby</orgName> we had a meeting that was large, and
                    exercising. I thought<lb/>the people's minds were too much outward, and not
                    attentive to the true founda-<lb/>tion. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-09-11"/>
                    <placeName key="mount"/></dateline>
                <p>The next day had a favoured meeting at <placeName key="mount"
                        >Mountholly</placeName> on the green<lb/>mountain in <placeName key="vermo"
                        >Vermont</placeName>, where no Meeting of Friends was ever held<lb/>
                    <pb n="127" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_07"/> held before: The people sat commendably:
                    several of them<lb/>invited us to their houses; But believing myself clear, I
                    chose ra-<lb/>ther to leave them in the hand of the Lord. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1795-09-12">12th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>Next at Walling's<lb/> valley, a little village, we had a large &amp; good
                    meeting; where there<lb/>had not been any held by friends before: A <orgName
                        key="bapt">Baptist</orgName> Minister<lb/>was present, who seemed to be
                    tendered. --- The height of the<lb/>mountains here seemed awful, exceeding any
                    that I had seen:<lb/>Some people suppose that much more rain and snow fall on
                    them<lb/> then doth in a level country. --- Oh! the sympathy I
                    have<lb/>perceived for those who dwell in these rough places; many of
                    them<lb/>in poor cottages, covered with Bark, or straw.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-09-13">13th.</date>
                    <placeName key="danby"/></dateline>
                <p> I was at <orgName key="meetdanby">Danby meeting</orgName> again, it being the
                    first of the<lb/>week, and seemed to be a dull season; yet some ability to
                    la-<lb/>bour amongst them was afforded; several things opened in my
                    mind<lb/>concerning the free use of distilled Spirits, <del>India Tea</del>, and
                    tobacco,<lb/>and I had to tell the <del>people</del> I was apprehensive these
                    things were<lb/>not introduced amongst us by the dictates of Truth; but that
                    they<lb/>rather came in by stealth, as a thief in the night, and stand
                    behind<lb/>the curtain of custom (as many other evils do; causing weak-<lb/>ness
                    among us as a people: Yet that I believed the Lord's refining work<lb/>would go
                    forward, &amp; prevail over all Opposition, but gradually; And that<lb/>
                    <pb n="128" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_08"/> and that a reformation is begun;
                    Therefore let not the little<lb/>ones be discouraged; For though the first who
                    step forth to change<lb/>evil customs may meet with exercise and sore conflicts,
                    yet<lb/>as they stand simple, &amp; keep humbly resigned to the Lord's
                    disposal,<lb/>their reward will be sure. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="easto"/>
                    <date when="1795-09-14">14th.</date></dateline>
                <p>Leaving <placeName key="danby">Danby</placeName> I came<lb/> to <placeName
                        key="easto">Easton</placeName>; and on the <date when="1795-09-16"
                        >16th</date>, crossed the <geogName key="nrive">North River</geogName> to
                    the <orgName key="meetsara">Week<lb/>day meeting</orgName> at <orgName
                        key="sarat">Saratoga</orgName>; which was a trying season. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-09-17"/><placeName key="easto"/></dateline>
                <p> The day following I went back to their monthly <emph rend="underline"
                        >mo.ly</emph> meeting<lb/>at <orgName key="eastmeet">Easton</orgName>; at
                    the close whereof the Shutters were opened at my re-<lb/>quest, and I was
                    exercised in close labour with Friends of both sexes<lb/>on the subject of a
                    reformation, having to touch on the particular<lb/>things which, as above, were
                    mentioned at <orgName key="meetdanby">Danby</orgName>: Also on the harm<lb/>
                    arising extensive Trade, <del>(with that of declining to use our own coun-<lb/>
                        try produce:)</del> advising that children be brought up to industry:
                    &amp;c.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-09-18">18th.</date>
                    <placeName key="wcree"/></dateline>
                <p> Travelling to <orgName key="meetwcree">White-Creek</orgName>, the following day,
                    I had a large and<lb/>solid meeting there; after which an aged man came to me,
                    and<lb/>said, <said who="undetermined">he had thought much of being a Quaker,
                        yet had been afraid<lb/>to join them, but this day the Truth had been
                        declared to his com-<lb/>fort:</said> and at parting he expressed his wish
                    that the Lord might prosper the<lb/>work in my hand.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-09-20">20th.</date>
                    <placeName key="pitts2"/></dateline>
                <p>The following first day I was at <orgName key="meetpitt">Pitts-town</orgName>
                    Meeting;<lb/>the first which was held in their new Meeting house, being a
                    large<lb/>gathering; I believe the Truth was in Dominion among us; and it
                    see-<lb/>med marvellous to see such a mixed multitude sit so still &amp; solid.
                </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="129" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_09"/>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1795-09-23">23d</date><lb/><placeName key="coeym"/></dateline>
                <p> The next Meeting was among friends of <orgName key="meetcoey">Queman's
                        Patent</orgName>, large and<lb/>solid. At the close of the publick sitting,
                    I had an opportunity with<lb/>friends by themselves; Here way opened for close
                    labour respecting the<lb/>the necessity of reformation, as things amongst them
                    were much out of<lb/>Order, and too much lukewarmness prevalent. I was also at
                    their<lb/>monthly meeting next day, where I was engaged to labour with<lb/>both
                    Sexes, on the necessity of reformation, and had to touch on the<lb/>same
                    Subjects as in other Places, concerning Foreign Trade, Rum, <del>India</del><lb/>
                    <del>Tea</del>, Tobacco &amp;c, exhorting to that of more true moderation,
                    temperance<lb/>&amp;c, with the use of our own country Produce. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-09-26">26th.</date>
                    <placeName key="kline"/></dateline>
                <p> After that I had a Meeting at <orgName key="meetkline">Clineykill</orgName>, a
                    solid favoured<lb/>Season, said to be the largest known to be in that place: A
                    hope<lb/>was expressed by some that the Lord would bless my Labours.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-09-27">27th</date>. <placeName key="newbr1"/></dateline>
                <p>The next day was at <orgName key="meetnewb">New-Britain</orgName>, a large and
                    solid Meeting; and<lb/>another at <orgName key="meetsteph">Steven-town</orgName>
                    in the Afternoon, where power was given<lb/>to labour fervently for the good of
                    souls --- I am this day 64<lb/>years old; and am at times deeply humbled in
                    beholding how my<lb/>way has been opened, and every kindness necessary have I
                    witnessed from all<lb/>sorts of people; with a Capacity to undergo
                    hard-travelling, thru' scenes<lb/>&amp; Places where to human view it seemed
                    impossible: In the Arm<lb/>of the Lord is all Strength &amp; sufficiency. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="130" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_10"/>
                <dateline><date when="1795-09-28">28th</date><placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>This Morning I visited a Settlement of the People called Sha-<lb/>kers, who
                    seem'd to receive me kindly, yet were much reser-<lb/>ved. I informed them I had
                    felt my mind drawn to visit them<lb/>in love, and if they were free to sit down
                    with us, if anything<lb/>arose in any of our minds, we might speak freely;
                    adding also<lb/>that I had often heard of them, but did not see any of their
                    sort<lb/>before now: One of them then said, he expected some things
                    report<lb/>ed of them might be true, and some false: He then leaving us,
                    (I<lb/>suppose he went to consult with his Brethren,) but soon return-<lb/>ing,
                    he asked if I was born in this Country, and of what pro-<lb/> fession I was? I
                    told him I was one of the People called Quakers;<lb/>and shew'd my certificate;
                    After he read it, he asked if he might<lb/>shew it to some in the next room;
                    which I allowed him do:<lb/>He then went in again, where, by that time, I
                    suppose many were<lb/>collected in Council; I heard them read over my
                    certificate, which<lb/>after some time was brought back, and I was told they
                    found I was an<lb/>approved Minister of that Society &amp; was on a long
                    journey; I informed<lb/>him I was on my return; and if he had freedom I should
                    be willing<lb/>to know something of their Principles: He then informed me,
                        They<lb/><said who="undetermined">believed in Christ Jesus, and in his
                        second appearance, and endea<lb/>vored to live up to the Scriptures, and to
                        follow Christ: being Members<lb/>of his Church thro' the baptism of the holy
                        Ghost: and coming under the</said><lb/>
                    <pb n="131" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_11"/> the cross: This, he said, had crucified
                    every fleshly lust, and given<lb/> them power to resist the tempter: That also,
                    they held <del>that</del> it was not right to<lb/>marry, but that the World was
                    wrong, and laid in Sin, &amp;c. He seem'd<lb/>confident in supposing their
                    Tenets to be right in respect to marriage, and that they take up<lb/>the cross
                    to lustful desires, and go beyond others in self-mortification, &amp;c.<lb/>With
                    respect to their Worship, he informed me they came together<lb/>every evening,
                    took a solid pause, and if the Elders feel any thing to<lb/>arise with weight,
                    they were permitted to speak; they also sing the Songs<lb/>of Solomon, use
                    dancing &amp;c. I informed him of our belief concer-<lb/>ning the benefit of
                    Silence, and of Spiritual Worship; and advised him<lb/>to beware of being over
                    confident in supposing they had witnessed grea-<lb/>ter Attainments than others.
                    He told me they believed George Fox to<lb/>have been a good Man, until he mixed
                    with the World; that then he fell<lb/>away, and there had been a falling away
                    among us till this time; and we<lb/>had lost our gift of discerning, &amp; had
                    in our Church many rotten, or defected Members,<lb/>But they (the Shakers) he
                    said, had that Gift, &amp; had sought out some of<lb/>the most deep &amp; hidden
                    Sins, &amp;c: -- I let him know I feared they were<lb/>mistaken, not being so
                    whole as they thought themselves to be. --- This man<lb/>appear'd to be sober
                    &amp; well-behaved. He said they all lived in Love, and in<lb/>one family, and
                    portion'd out each one's labour, according to their ability:<lb/> They have many
                    Mechanicks, and some are appointed to inspect the work<lb/> before it is Sold;
                    appearing to maintain Credit by honest dealing, &amp;c. -<lb/>They seem
                        <del>appear</del> to be much United, do not act without consulting together,
                    and -<lb/>move as in a body, This Man told me farther, they did not receive any
                    as Mem-<lb/>bers if they had wronged any person, until they had returned
                    fourfold: and when<lb/>any one joined them, his Property is put into public
                    Stock; &amp; if he should leave <lb/>
                    <pb n="132" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_12"/> leave them, he is to take out what he
                    first put in, &amp; no more. They ap<lb/>pear to be a decent industrious people;
                    and on the whole, I thought better<lb/>of them, than before I went to see them. </p>
                <p> I understand the women among these People, were much by themselves;<lb/>They
                    spin, knit, sew, weave, and manage the Houshold Affairs. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-09-29">29th.</date>
                    <placeName key="hoosi"/></dateline>
                <p> Moving forward to <orgName key="meethoosi">East Husack</orgName>, I was at a
                    very large Meeting there;<lb/>This was almost held in silence, yet the people
                    sat quiet and solid: I<lb/>told them I much commended that, and wished them not
                    to be discouraged;<lb/>also that, as God was a Spirit, we believed he might be
                    worshipped in<lb/>Spirit and in Truth, even where no vocal Sound or Voice is to
                    be heard.<lb/>It being a Season of mortality here, I visited several sick
                    persons and<lb/>Families, of which our valued friend <persName key="rnisb1"
                        >Robert Nisbet</persName>'s was one, who<lb/>deceased soon after: many
                    others also were called off here about that time.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-10-01">10th. Mo. 1st.</date>
                    <placeName key="hoosi"/></dateline>
                <p> The monthly Meeting at <orgName key="meethoosi">East Husack</orgName> being held
                    now, I attended<lb/>it, being a large gathering &amp; a favoured season in the
                    fore part: I sat<lb/>with Women friends while they answered the queries: where a
                    deep search was<lb/>made into the State of Things, to my comfort: I then sat
                    with the Men in<lb/>the like Exercise: But life seem'd to be wanting: I thought
                    there was a dis<lb/>position to answer evasively, and unless they were more
                    weighty in the<lb/>business, The queries might become a snare to them. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-10-02">2nd</date>. <placeName key="tyrin"/></dateline>
                <p>At one place <del>I confess</del> I was grieved, at seeing so large preparations
                    for<lb/>making Cyder: doth it not tend to promote Excess in drinking? The
                    next<lb/>day had a small dull meeting at a friend's house; and to me, mournful.
                    Then<lb/>went on our Way towards <placeName key="tyrin">Tyringham</placeName>.
                    We </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="133" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_13"/>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1795-10-03">3rd.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>We visited another settlement of those called Shakers: after a<lb/>solid
                    conferrence we were permitted to see the women, who appeared<lb/>plain and
                    sober; one of them, and antient Woman, spake in a free<lb/>and friendly way,
                    asking several questions: She seemed well satisfied<lb/>with my answers, and
                    invited me to come again. Their Head-dress was<lb/>much the uniform: and
                    although I had some satisfaction in the visit, I feared<lb/>they were too much
                    unacquainted with the Cross of Christ; yet they<lb/>speak of living under the
                    cross. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-10-04">4th.</date>
                    <placeName key="tyrin"/></dateline>
                <p>Had a large and satisfactory Meeting at <orgName key="meettyrin"
                        >Tyringham</orgName>; after which<lb/>I was in Conferrence with a Committee
                    from <orgName key="meethoosi">East Husack Mo.ly Meeting</orgName>,<lb/>in
                    respect to holding a meeting at this place, as the number is small,<lb/>and the
                    State of things but low. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-10-06">6th</date><placeName key="goshe"/></dateline>
                <p>The next day travelled on<lb/>a rough road through a mountainous Country to
                        <persName key="crich1"> Charles Richards's</persName><lb/>House at <orgName
                        key="meetgosh">Goshen</orgName>; and the <del>next</del> day following a
                    large and solid Meeting was<lb/> held there: It may be remarked the people in
                    those parts are long in ga-<lb/>thering to assemblies for Worship. <persName
                        key="crich1">C. Richards</persName> seems to be a singu-<lb/> lar man in
                    almost all his conduct; and yet in the main, I esteemed<lb/>him
                    honest-hearted.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-10-08"/><placeName key="wbran"
                    >Branch</placeName></dateline>
                <p>The day following in the afternoon, we<lb/>had a dull heavy Meeting at a place
                    called the <orgName key="meetwbran">Branch</orgName>, and the 8th.<lb/> had one
                    at <orgName key="meetnewmi">New-milford</orgName>; which was low in the
                    forepart; untill some<lb/> gay people not of our perswasion came in; unto whom I
                    believe<lb/>the Lord had regard, for ability was received to extend gospel
                    labour<lb/>for their benefit: as a lukewarm drowsy spirit was to be felt <lb/>before<lb/>
                    <pb n="134" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_14"/> before they came in. This was the
                    preparative Meeting day<lb/>at <orgName key="meetnewmi">New-Milford</orgName>,
                    But matters appeared to be in a low State. --<lb/>At the close of the first
                    Meeting, I felt a desire to have a<lb/>meeting with the inhabitants of
                        <placeName key="newmi">New-Milford</placeName> next day, which<lb/>was
                    united with on being mention'd, and the time and place proposed;<lb/>and those
                    gay people above hinted proposed to spread the notice.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-10-09">9th.</date>
                    <placeName key="newmi"/></dateline>
                <p> Agreeable to which proposal, a pretty large number assembled of<lb/>those not of
                    our society in a private house near the town, which was <lb/>a favoured season,
                    not soon to be forgotten.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-10-10">10th.</date>
                    <placeName key="peach"/></dateline>
                <p>Going Forward, I<lb/>had a pretty large and satisfactory Meeting at <orgName
                        key="meetvall">Friends Meeting-<lb/>house in the Valley</orgName>, so
                    called: And next day at <orgName key="meetpeach">Peach Pond</orgName>, was at
                    a<lb/>small meeting, where poverty was felt; yet I had some labour.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-10-12">12th.</date>
                    <placeName key="oblon"/></dateline>
                <p> Next I attended the Monthly Meeting at <orgName key="meetoblon"
                    >Oblong</orgName>, which was an<lb/>exercising time; I fear'd barrenness
                    prevailed; the crowding Cares of<lb/>the World &amp; the deceitfulness of Riches
                    choaking the good seed: I had <lb/>some close labor which appeared to be well
                    taken; The day follow-<lb/>ing I attended the select Meeting at the same place,
                    which was dull &amp;<lb/>exercising: </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-10-14">14th</date>. <placeName key="9part1"/></dateline>
                <p>From hence I went to <placeName key="9part1">Nine Partners</placeName> to their
                        <orgName key="meetnp">monthly<lb/> Meeting</orgName>; which was very large,
                    and somewhat lively, I thought; I per-<lb/>ceived some ability to labour
                    satisfactorily. ~~ Next day I met<lb/>with a Committee on the Subject of a
                    Boarding School at the same<lb/>place: I thought I was led to see more clearly
                    than ever before, into <lb/>the <lb/><pb n="135" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_15"/> the
                    nature or right manner of educating Children, which I men-<lb/> tioned, and left
                    with them. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1795-10-16">16th.</date><placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>Next I attended the <orgName key="meetcreek">Creek Monthly Meeting</orgName>:
                    which, I thought was an exercising poor-time.<lb/>The day following I had a
                    large Meeting, which was at my desire<lb/>appointed for the young people at the
                        <orgName key="meetcreek">Creek Meeting-house</orgName>; This<lb/>was a
                    season of Divine Favour: The Youth felt more pleasant to me<lb/>separated from
                    others; I fear the unlawful love of lawless things is<lb/>a great Snare, in
                    which the Enemy hath caught many, who have appear'd<lb/>to be well-disposed
                    Members of our Society, up and down in this land.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-10-18">18th.</date>
                    <placeName key="lnine"/></dateline>
                <p>Had a Meeting at <orgName key="meetlnine">Little nine Partners</orgName>, so
                    large that the house could<lb/>not contain all the people; It was exercising,
                    yet blessed be the God<lb/>of all power; he gave ability to labor in his cause,
                    to the tendering of<lb/>some hearts. Returning to <placeName key="9part1">Nine
                        Partners</placeName>, I was at a <orgName key="meetnp">Meeting</orgName>
                    <lb/>appointed for the Youth, at my desire: which was a solid favoured
                    time:<lb/>some of these appeared to be of the naughty rebellious Ones: Oh!
                    may<lb/>the opportunity be as <quote type="biblical">bread cast upon the Waters'
                        to be found hereafter.</quote></p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-10-20">20th.</date>
                    <placeName key="9part1"/></dateline>
                <p>I had also at the same place a large and solid Meeting with<lb/>the Parents and
                    Heads of Families of the <orgName key="meetnp">Monthly Meeting</orgName>; I had
                    to<lb/>revive among them the Sense of our Primitive friends, respecting
                    fine<lb/>houses, Rich furniture, a Worldly spirit, &amp;c, also my sentiments
                    concern-<lb/>ing the free use of Tobacco, &amp; other things heretofore
                    mention'd, which <lb/><pb n="136" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_16"/> which (as it seems
                    to me) have stole in upon us as a thief in the night,<lb/>and which in a measure
                    occasion dimness and weakness with respect to<lb/>a faithful Support of the pure
                    testimony of Truth. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-10-21">21st.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>And the next day at the <orgName key="meetcreek">Creek</orgName>, or stone,
                    house, a meeting of the same<lb/>kind was held with heads of families, large,
                    and owned by the Truth, as many<lb/>Friends expressed; for many hearts were
                    tendered, &amp; many tears dropt.<lb/>Here also the example &amp; Care of our
                    Predecessors, for punctuality in<lb/>dealings, true moderation in living &amp;c,
                    was brought into view; and a weigh-<lb/>ty Care urged in the education of
                    Children: also the ruinous Effects of a<lb/>neglect of that Care was mention'd.
                </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-10-22"/>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>The day following I had<lb/>a large &amp; solid Meeting at <persName key="sdean1"
                        >Stephen Dean</persName>'s house; And one at<lb/>
                    <persName key="ititu1">Israel Titus</persName>'s house in the afternoon, which
                    was likewise satisfactory.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-10-23">23rd.</date>
                    <placeName key="osweg"/></dateline>
                <p> At <orgName key="meetosweg">Swago</orgName> also I had a pretty large Meeting,
                    which was thought<lb/> to be favoured. --- On my way the next day to <placeName
                        key="apoqu">Appoquage</placeName>, I saw a<lb/>shameful sight, a Bull tied
                    up, and dogs allowed to worrey him in that<lb/>condition: <del>and</del> those
                    looking on, who (no' doubt) professed Christianity.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-10-25">25th.</date>
                    <placeName key="apoqu"/></dateline>
                <p> Attending <orgName key="meetapoqu">Appoquage meeting</orgName> on first day, it
                    was so large<lb/>the house was too small for the people: but too many of them
                    see-<lb/>med to be a bad sort, yet they sat commendably for such a mixed
                    num-<lb/>ber; and I was concerned to lay things close, &amp; scarcely got
                    relieved in the<lb/>meeting: In the afternoon I had but little strength to hold
                    up my head,<lb/>believing this is a poor place, &amp; the faithful number but
                    few.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-10-26" type="unattested"/>
                    <placeName key="oblon"/></dateline>
                <p> I went from hence to <placeName key="oblon">Oblong</placeName> again; thro' a
                    rough mountainous Country.<lb/>A friend who was educated in the <orgName
                        key="presby">Presbyterian</orgName> profession informed me <lb/>that
                        <lb/><pb n="137" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_17"/> that he was convinced of the
                    truth, on hearing some little Children<lb/> using the plain language of thee, to
                    one another; and they appearing<lb/>so lamblike, he believed it was Truth's
                    language: I thought, from<lb/>this instance, how much effect simple Plainness
                    hath, even when observ-<lb/>able in children: and how much more if grown people
                    &amp; Parents were<lb/>properly concerned to live up the pure inward principle
                    of Truth? We<lb/>should then be teachers, instead of stumbling blocks, to honest
                    enqui-<lb/>rers; and like the <quote type="biblical">Salt of the earth</quote>,
                    the savour whereof would be perceived<lb/>for miles round, in a neighborhood
                    where it was retained. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-10-28">28th.</date>
                    <placeName key="oblon"/></dateline>
                <p> I attended the Quarterly Meeting at <orgName key="meetoblon">Oblong</orgName>;
                    it was very large,<lb/>and comfortable to my mind: Gospel Truths were declared
                    to the tendering<lb/>of many hearts: The next day the Youth's Meeting was said
                    to be the<lb/>largest known in this place; a solid and favour'd season I
                    believe; The<lb/>people sat quiet, although crowded; and I sat in silence, being
                    comforted<lb/>in Christ our Lord. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-11-01"/><placeName key="9part1"/></dateline>
                <p>The day following I travelled<lb/>towards <placeName key="9part1">Nine
                        partners</placeName> again, their <orgName key="meetnp">Qu.ly
                        Meeting</orgName> being near, and on the way Stopped at the <orgName
                        key="ridge">Ridge Meeting</orgName><lb/>held the <date when="1795-11-01">1st
                        of the 11th month</date>, <placeName key="checkPlace"/> which was very
                    large, solemnity prevailing,<lb/>tho' many had to stand up for want of seats.
                    The day before I staid at a<lb/>Friend's house, whose wife was in a weak State
                    of health: she appeared to be<lb/>of an innocent spirit, and expected much
                    satisfaction in the right.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-11-02">2nd.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>This morning considering how well I fared among my friends, I feared
                    the<lb/>danger of forgetting the Lord, who had so remarkably favour'd, &amp;
                    prepared my<lb/>way; Let him have the praise of his own Works, who is alone
                    worthy, forever.</p>
                <p> I had a solid opportunity with a naughty young man, the only <lb/>Son <lb/>
                    <pb n="138" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_18"/> Son of his father; I intreated him to
                    forsake evil company, and<lb/>in so doing he would be likely to find Comfort,
                    otherwise he would not, either<lb/> here or hereafter: using much freedom with
                    him, as one who resembled the<lb/> prodigal Son the parable, he appear'd to take
                    it well, and said, he hoped he<lb/>should not forget my advice.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-11-03">3rd.</date>
                    <placeName key="9part1"/></dateline>
                <p>Being at the select Quarterly meeting at <orgName key="meetnp">Nine
                        Partners</orgName>, I was led to<lb/>mention my sense of there being no
                    necessity for much school learning<lb/>for a gospel minister; that the knowledge
                    of Latin, Greek, &amp; Hebrew, is more likely<lb/> to hinder, then to help a
                    gospel Minister: Truth being a simple Thing, not<lb/> needing learned languages
                    to explain it &amp;c.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-11-04"/>
                    <placeName key="9part1"/></dateline>
                <p>The <orgName key="meetnp">Quar.ly meeting</orgName><lb/>for business the next day
                    was very large; and I thought, was favoured with<lb/> power from on high to
                    labour for the good cause in a way that is uncommon.<lb/>I felt my mind
                    impressed with concern to sit with both men friends and the<lb/>women, first in
                    one Meeting, &amp; then in the other, whilst the Business of reading<lb/>the
                    Queries &amp; the Answers to them is attended to: Which being mentiond, my
                    re-<lb/>quest was united with by both men and women friends: It was a season of
                    fa-<lb/>vour, as I had an opportunity in both Meetings to clear myself
                    respecting<lb/>the trust which I apprehended the Lord reposed in me, to the
                    Satisfaction of my self<lb/>and my friends: <del>And</del> many hearts were
                    tendered, &amp; minds instructed and edi-<lb/>fied; which divers freely and
                    openly expressed: So that we parted in near<lb/>Love, a sense of which I hope
                    will not soon be forgotten: Let the Name of<lb/>the Lord be blessed. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-11-05"/>
                    <placeName key="9part1"/></dateline>
                <p> The day following was a publick <orgName key="meetnp">Meeting</orgName> at
                    the<lb/>same place, larger than their large Meeting-house could contain;
                    in<lb/>which a good degree of solidity prevailed. Yet I thought the Meeting was
                    hurt <lb/>
                    <pb n="139" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_19"/> hurt by too much preaching: It is
                    necessary a deep travail of<lb/>spirit, should take place for the arising of
                    that <emph rend="underline">Spirit and</emph> life<lb/>which gives victory over
                    lightness and airy dispositions; without which<lb/>preaching is vain. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-11-06">6th.</date>
                    <placeName key="goshe"/></dateline>
                <p>Inclining now to go towards <placeName key="hartf">Hartford</placeName> in
                        <placeName key="connt">Con-<lb/>necticut</placeName>, I travelled about 20
                    miles, and in the afternoon had a Meeting<lb/>near <placeName key="goshe"
                        >Goshen</placeName> in a <orgName key="bapt">Baptist</orgName>
                    Meeting-house; it was remarked that the<lb/>meeting was solid &amp; quiet. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-11-08">8th.</date>
                    <placeName key="ehart"/></dateline>
                <p>Coming to <placeName key="ehart">East Hartford</placeName> where a number
                    dwell<lb/> who by convincement have of late been joined to our Society, I
                    attended<lb/>their <orgName key="meetehart">Meeting</orgName> on first day
                    forenoon; Also in the afternoon when notice was<lb/>further spread, we had a
                    large and favoured Meeting: but it was somewhat<lb/>injured by the publick
                    appearance of one towards whom<lb/>Care was extended.</p>
                <p> In the evening also we had the largest meeting ever seen at this<lb/>place; and
                    tho' the crouding of the people was some hindrance to its'<lb/>Settlement in
                    quietude, yet the seasoning virtue of Truth was perceived<lb/>by many: insomuch,
                    that near a hundred persons, after the Meeting<lb/>concluded, were loth to
                    depart from the house; I felt my mind engaged in<lb/>exercise on their account;
                    but went to lay down, that I might rest a little;<lb/>After they had conferred
                    together, a solid young man came, and told me<lb/>they desired another
                    oppertunity, as the evening meeting was so crouded. This<lb/>proved to be a time
                    of much favour: to shew them that I was no Impostor<lb/>I caused my Certificate
                    to be read near the close: This lasted till near<lb/>midnight: such a solemnity
                    prevailed, that it seemed not easy to separate.<lb/>I did believe the Truth came
                    into dominion this evening: May the Lord be<lb/><pb n="140"
                        facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_20"/> praised who is alone worthy, saith my Soul.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-11-09">9th.</date>
                    <placeName key="whart"/></dateline>
                <p>Feeling a draught in my mind to go and visit a Clergyman named <persName
                        key="perki1">Perkins</persName> in <placeName key="whart">West
                        Hartford</placeName> who<lb/>had shewn some bitterness towards friends; and
                    although some thought<lb/>it was likely he would treat me with contempt, I was
                    most easy to go,<lb/>being accompanied by two friends: when we went to him, he
                    treated us<lb/>friendly beyond our expectation, saying he had attended at
                        <del>one</del> one Mee-<lb/>ting, and was well satisfied with what I said: I
                    replied, if thou wouldest<lb/>lay aside forms and ceremonies, I think we shall
                    be likely to agree in<lb/>the parts which are essential: he then said, he
                    believed the Scriptures to<lb/>be the only rule of faith and practice, and that
                    revelation had ceased. I en-<lb/>deavoured to open my Sentiments to him in
                    freedom, That the Scriptures<lb/>appeared to be a sealed book, and the true
                    meaning of many parts not to be ob-<lb/>tained, except thro' the assistance of
                    the same Spirit which gave them forth,<lb/>That the divine principle of Light
                    and Grace which we preach up, and<lb/>testify unto, is that, which if attended
                    to, brings to the knowledge of<lb/>God; That the Spirit of Wisdom which inspired
                    the Penmen who<lb/>wrote the Scriptures, is surely to be preferred before that
                    which was<lb/>written under its' Influence, &amp;c, altho' he said he believed
                    in free grace<lb/>yet he continued to urge the Scriptures being the only Rule,
                    other Con-<lb/>versation followed, yet it appeared he was loth to yield to any
                    Sen-<lb/>timent different from what he had been accustomed to endeavour
                    to<lb/>uphold, according to their Creed: I let him know before we parted, that
                    I<lb/>thought he knew better than he spake. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-11-10">10th.</date>
                    <placeName key="hartf"/></dateline>
                <p> The next day I had a Meeting with Friends of <gap/><orgName key="meethartf"
                        >Hartford</orgName> by them- <lb/>
                    <pb n="141" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_21"/> themselves, to my comfort and
                        <del>their</del> theirs. I saw there was great need<lb/>of care in this
                    place, as they are but newly convinced, and their number-<lb/>small. They hold
                    Meetings under the Care of <orgName key="meetoblon">Oblong monthly
                        meeting</orgName><lb/>in the government of <placeName key="newyo">New
                        York</placeName>. This viz. <placeName key="hartf">Hartford</placeName>
                    appears to have been a dark place<lb/>of formal Professors of Religion. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-11-12">12th.</date>
                    <placeName key="goshe"/></dateline>
                <p> Leaving <placeName key="hartf">Hartford</placeName>, and returning<lb/>westward
                    bout 40 miles, I had a solid &amp; satisfactory meeting at <orgName
                        key="meetgosh">Goshen</orgName>:<lb/>where some attended that never had been
                    at one of our Meetings before:<lb/>with one of whom I had solid conversation:
                    She was in a tender State,<lb/>&amp; expressed herself not satisfied with their
                    hireling Teachers, believing they<lb/>ought to work for something towards their
                    own maintenance; without spend-<lb/>ing their time from week to week in an idle
                    way, &amp;c:.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-11-14">14th.</date>
                    <placeName key="schag"/></dateline>
                <p> I went from hence to see a Settlement of Indians at <placeName key="schag"
                        >Scatecook</placeName>, about<lb/>30 in number, with whom I had a meeting:
                    and afterwards visited them<lb/>in their families, in which I had
                    satisfaction.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-11-16">The next day </date><placeName key="wbran"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> I was at<lb/>that called the <orgName key="meetwbran">Branch Meeting</orgName>,
                    being <del>on</del> first day, which was dull and exer-<lb/>
                    <date when="1795-11-16">16th.</date> cising. ---- At the Monthly Meeting at
                        <orgName key="meetoblon">Oblong</orgName> I also attended, and<lb/> had a
                    solid season both among men and women; many of the young peo-<lb/>People were
                    present, to whom, as well as to Parents &amp; others I endeavored to discharge
                    my<lb/>self honestly: reminding them of the Indians above mention'd, for whom I
                    was<lb/> concerned, as much of the land had been obtained from that
                    People<lb/>under value, &amp; some of it very unfairly, That now it was right,
                    kindness<lb/> towards them should be remembred; Friends uniting with my Concern,
                    a Commit-<lb/>tee was appointed to visit the Indians, &amp; administer to their
                    help if need-<lb/>ful. This days exercise &amp; Labour yielded me Comfort, and,
                    I believe tended to<lb/>the Glory of God; Blessed be his great Name; He is the
                    Helper of his People.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="142" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_22"/>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1795-11-17">17th.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p> Travelling homewards about 30 miles, I had in the Evening at a<lb/>Friends house
                    some edifying conversation: I fear it is too often other-<lb/>wise, and that the
                    Cause of Truth is at times hurt, and perhaps honest enqui-<lb/>rers stumbled,
                    and friends weakened, when they come together, by light<lb/>conversation on
                    worldly, or trifling Subjects. Had a Meeting at<lb/><persName key="rrand1">Rob.t
                        Randel</persName>'s house, which was thought to be solid and
                    comforting,<lb/>as well as pretty large.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-11-19">19th.</date>
                    <placeName key="amawa"/></dateline>
                <p>Next at <orgName key="amamm">Ammawock</orgName>, had a large Meeting in<lb/>the
                    forenoon, which was exercising: and in the afternoon another at <orgName
                        key="meetcoleb">Cole-<lb/>bark</orgName>; This was a comfortable
                    heart-tendering season, wherein many eyes<lb/>dropped tears. Blessed be the Name
                    of the Lord, who helpeth.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-11-20">20th.</date>
                    <placeName key="chapp"/></dateline>
                <p> I likewise had pretty large Meeting in the forenoon at <orgName key="meetcm"
                        >Shappaqua</orgName><lb/>where Life was not permitted to rise high; And
                    another in the after-<lb/>noon at <persName key="iquim1">Isaiah
                        Quimby</persName>'s, which was more Satisfactory. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-11-22">22nd.</date>
                    <placeName key="nycit"/></dateline>
                <p>Coming on to <placeName key="nycit">New-York</placeName>, I was on first day,
                    fore, and afternoon<lb/>at <orgName key="meetny">Meeting</orgName> with my
                    friends there, which I thought were the most<lb/>afflicting Meetings I had sat
                    in for some time: It was near the close<lb/>of a season of Mortality wherewith
                    that city had been visited; which<lb/>should have produced humility, turning
                    peoples' minds from the pursuit of<lb/>earthly riches, to that treasure which is
                    durable: But to my grief, I was<lb/>afraid the inhabitants (when the late rod
                    was withdrawn) too many were<lb/>turning, like the Sow, to that of wallowing in
                    the mire again.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-11-23">23d.</date>
                    <placeName key="nycit"/></dateline>
                <p>Next day I visited a few families in the <placeName key="nycit">City</placeName>,
                    and had close conversation<lb/>with <lb/><pb n="143" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_23"/>
                    a Formalist, whose Eyes, I thought were blinded by the God of this<lb/> world. I
                    told him in Substance, nearly on this Wise, that it grieved me to think,
                        <del>that</del> while a remnent were<lb/> trying to prevail with Young
                    people &amp; others to come into the Practice of<lb/>more plainness and true
                    moderation consistent with the simplicity of our<lb/>Profession, those in high
                    Station for worldly interest, should be keeping,<lb/>and holding up Articles
                    &amp; Things for Sale as a temptation to others to<lb/>branch out in purchasing,
                    to deck themselves with Superfluities, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-11-26">26th.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p> In about three days after this time I reached to my own habita-<lb/>tion again
                    after a journey which took up near eight Months: and<lb/>in which I had to
                    travel about 4,000 Miles; and have now cause<lb/>to praise &amp; magnify the
                    Name of the Lord, who in a marvellous man-<lb/>ner prepar'ed my way, &amp;
                    carried me through; and now vouchsafeth<lb/>the Sense of a reward which is
                    sufficient for all my Trials &amp; Labours;<lb/>That of finding my Wife &amp;
                    near Connections alive &amp; in pretty<lb/>good health was esteemed by me an
                    additional Cause for<lb/> humble thanksgiving. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-12-05">12th. mo. 5th.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>At our select <orgName key="haddoqm">Quarterly Meeting</orgName>, my mind was
                    closely exer-<lb/>cised concerning superfluities that appear; and
                    particularly<lb/>I had to mention large Looking-glasses; whether having
                    them<lb/>in friends houses was not one cause of keeping pride alive in
                    the<lb/>hearts of those who spend time in standing before them to view
                    their<lb/>dress, and to have all appear delicate &amp; nice; and whether such
                    scrupulous <lb/>
                    <pb n="144" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_24"/> nicety in t <emph rend="underline"
                        >trigging</emph> of the body, doth not add to the Soul's un-<lb/>fitness to
                    approach the presence of a heartsearching God, when<lb/>we go to places for
                    solemn worship.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-11-07">7th.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>Drowsiness in times of worship was complained of in our<lb/>Answers brought in to
                    the <orgName key="haddoqm">Quar.ly Meeting</orgName> of business;
                    whereupon<lb/>I was concerned to bring into consideration, whether high,
                    luxurious<lb/>eating &amp; drinking Cider, Wine &amp;c, plentifully, with
                    smoking tobacco,<lb/>did not tend in some measure to alter the state of the
                    body, and thereby<lb/>add to the causes of heavy dullness when friends come to
                    sit down in our religious Meetings.</p>
                <p> That of paying a kind attention to the Situation of the Native<lb/>Indians who
                    dwell near us, by visiting them, &amp; inspecting as well as helping their
                    neces-<lb/>sities, as winter is approaching, and we much indebted to them, as
                    such<lb/>who possess the Land which was theirs, &amp; obtained from them at a
                    cheap<lb/>rate, was at this time urged to friends Observation as a
                    Christian<lb/>duty; My mind is often concerted for that people. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-12-11">11th.</date>
                    <placeName key="evesh"/></dateline>
                <p>I was at <orgName key="meetevesh">Evesham Mo.ly Meeting</orgName> in company with
                    several<lb/>ministring friends: I have often thought that the time in our
                    meetings for business<lb/>ought to be occupied in attending thereto, and not
                    taken up with com-<lb/>munications in the way of preaching; Life and power far
                    exceed<lb/>words.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1795-12-12">12th.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/>
                </dateline>
                <p>My mind was turned in feeling sympathy towards<lb/>the poor and afflicted, divers
                    of whom I visited: one of them was<lb/>antient, whose time seemed nearly over,
                    and I feared his days work was<lb/>not done; I urged him to use all
                    diligence.</p>

                <pb n="145" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_25"/>
                <p>At another house, I went to see an afflicted woman, and her<lb/>mother who was a
                    widow, they rejoiced at being visited; and I<lb/>tho't they appear'd much in the
                    innocency, like favourites of<lb/>Heaven.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-12-13">13th.</date><placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>At a neighboring Meeting, I thought insensibility, and<lb/>forgetfulness of God
                    prevailed; with a worldly spirit to my grief.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-12-17">17th.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>At our week day meeting, I hoped for an increase of living<lb/>Faith and life
                    among us; Friends seem to bring out more of the youth<lb/>to meetings then
                    heretofore. ---- I visited a number more of the<lb/>poor and afflicted, who
                    appeared thankful in being remembred.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-12-24">24th.</date>
                    <placeName key="piles"/></dateline>
                <p>At <orgName key="meetpiles">Pilesgrove Mo.ly Meeting</orgName> was a trying time;
                    I seemed almost<lb/>ready to give out, the appearance was gloomy, and the
                    floods<lb/>ready to swallow me up; I feared also the Lord was about to
                    hide<lb/>his face from me: ---- I said, Suffer me not, O Lord, to fall
                    a<lb/>prey to mine Adversary: I know my help is in thee. -----<lb/>Next day I
                    visited some in deep affliction of body, who<del>m</del> I thought<lb/>were in
                    favour with God, a comfortable feeling. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1795-12-27">27th.</date>
                    <placeName key="salem"/></dateline>
                <p>At <orgName key="salempm">Salem Meeting</orgName> I had close <del>doctrine</del>
                    doctrine to deliver which<lb/>seemed well taken, At their Monthly Meeting <date
                        when="1795-12-28">next day</date>, my<lb/>bow seemed to be renewed in
                    strength; and I had close labour to discharge<lb/>both amongst Men friends and
                    the Women, to my own satisfaction, and to<lb/>theirs, as far as appear'd. I was
                    led to treat on the pernicious Effects<lb/>of a worldly Spirit, and a sumptuous
                    way of living, aiming at fine<lb/>Houses, rich furniture, particularly large
                    looking-glasses &amp;c, &amp;c:. <lb/>Returning <lb/>
                    <pb n="146" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_26"/> Returning home I visited several sick
                    persons to our mutual<lb/>Joy. At our week day meeting, were a large number of
                    Youth; a good<lb/>Meeting crowned with the divine presence. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">

                <dateline>
                    <date when="1796-01">1796 1st. month.</date><placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>For six days I have been about home, &amp; done little good.<lb/>Instead of
                    attending with other Friends the <orgName key="pymind">committee on In-<lb/>dian
                        Affairs</orgName>, I let in reasoning, that I was of so little
                    conse-<lb/>quence, I might as well stay away; and thus have lost time.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-01-08">8th.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>My mind was inclined to attend a neighboring Mo.ly Meeting, but<lb/>the Adversary
                    endeavour'd to defeat me here also: I was kept lingering<lb/>about home till it
                    was almost too late; when trembling seized<lb/>me; &amp; I said, <quote
                        type="biblical">let me not fall by the hand of Saul</quote>; I was
                    favoured<lb/>with a little Strength to press thro': and my bow was renewed,
                    so<lb/>that I had a favoured Opportunity, both amongst Men and Women
                    friends.<lb/>I was engaged to speak to Parents and Children concerning a<lb/>
                    worldly spirit, and the inconsistency of Superfluity in dress and<lb/>
                    furniture; and had to press in plain Language the evil of these<lb/>Things;
                    believing it was not a time for speaking smooth Words. It was<lb/>thought the
                    meeting ended well. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-01-09"/>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>

                <p> I also attended another Monthly Meeting next day where my<lb/>service was pretty
                    much in the same line; And I can say in<lb/>truth, Blessed be the name of the
                    Lord; He is a rich rewarder<lb/>of those who serve him faithfully.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-01-11">11th.</date>
                    <placeName key="haddo"/></dateline>
                <p>I was at our Monthly Meeting at <orgName key="meethaddo">Haddonfield</orgName>,
                    Where the<lb/>Minutes of our <orgName key="pym">Yearly Meeting</orgName> were
                    revived which advise against <lb/>
                    <pb n="147" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_27"/> a worldly Spirit, &amp; mention it's
                    weakening effects in leading to the<lb/>vain customs of the World in dress
                    &amp;c: I was led on this oc-<lb/>casion to speak plain, and closely urge my
                    friends to a proper<lb/>attention to this advice, with other matters
                    recommended; It appear'd<lb/>evident to me that giving way to fleshly ease, and
                    a worldly Spi-<lb/>rit, was the ground cause of a defection in our Society,
                    &amp; a depar-<lb/>ture from that Simplicity which the dictates of the blessed
                    Truth,<lb/>if strictly observed, would lead into. Some of the rich can
                    scarce-<lb/>ly bear this kind of doctrine, especially Parents; The
                    Children<lb/>sometimes appear most tender. -- I had also to express my
                    fears<lb/>respecting the dangerous consequence of friends mixing with
                    others<lb/>in promoting a School at <placeName key="haddo"
                        >Haddonfield</placeName> for instructing Youth in the<lb/>French Language:
                    as it might be a snare to entangle some of<lb/>the dear Youth, &amp; expose them
                    to the Company of those of a loose<lb/>conduct &amp;c. Tho' some seemed to
                    disapprove of my freedom in this<lb/>respect, several both Old and young united
                    with my Sentiments. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-01-12">12th.</date>
                    <placeName key="woodb"/></dateline>
                <p>I was at <orgName key="meetwoodb">Woodberry Monthly Meeting</orgName>: where a
                    worldly spirit<lb/>was again treated on, with its' effects: I opened my
                    Sentiments on what<lb/>relates to extortion; and had to advise my friends not to
                    seek the largest<lb/>Prices when they were about to sell, Meat or other produce,
                    especially to<lb/>those in low circumstances: This appear'd to be a low time:
                    and I was<lb/>afraid my friends in this place had lost ground.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-01-18">18th.</date>
                    <placeName key="woodb"/></dateline>
                <p>At our <orgName key="meethaddo">Meeting</orgName> lately we had the company of
                    four friends who were <lb/>Ministers, <lb/>
                    <pb n="148" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_28"/> Ministers. It came into my mind that in
                    a season of drought, <del>we</del><lb/>we looked to the clouds for rain;
                    sometimes many clouds produce but little -<lb/>rain, so when divers preachers
                    are in the gallery, &amp; the minds of the<lb/>people turned towards them, &amp;
                    not to the bishop of Souls, a disappointment<lb/>often happens.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-01-24">24th.</date>
                    <placeName key="woodb"/></dateline>
                <p>I have done no good thing.</p>
                <p> For several days after this, I was closely engaged in visiting<lb/>the sick, and
                    in assisting, and pleading the cause of the poor, to my<lb/>comfort, and I hope,
                    to their benefit.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-02-01">2nd month 1st.</date>
                    <placeName key="burli"/></dateline>
                <p>I was at <orgName key="meetburl">Burlington Mo.ly Meeting</orgName>, &amp; had
                    some service<lb/>both amongst Men friends &amp; the Women, tho' it seemed hard
                    work, because<lb/>of lukewarmness, and I feared the World was likely to gain
                    Ascendancy.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-02-02">2nd.</date>
                    <placeName key="chesf"/></dateline>
                <p>Attending also the <orgName key="meetchesf">Mo.ly Meeting at
                        Chesterfield</orgName>, it appeared to be<lb/>a low season, &amp; part of
                    the time unprofitably spent; Some who had more<lb/>of the form than substance
                    urging sentiments to carry their Point, I thought<lb/> it was distressing to
                    some younger persons, &amp; so it was to me.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-02-03">3rd.</date>
                    <placeName key="sprin"/></dateline>
                <p><orgName key="meetsprin">Springfield Monthly meeting</orgName> held to day, I
                    thought was a more<lb/>favour'd time in the management of their business;
                    Friends seemed to<lb/>be united, &amp; the Youth sat solidly, which was pleasant
                    to observe.<lb/>I had a comforting time in a Family yesterday evening; the
                    Chil-<lb/>dren appear'd in a good degree of innocence. (<persName key="cnewb1"
                        >C. Newbolds.</persName>) </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-02-04">4th.</date>
                    <placeName key="mount1"/></dateline>
                <p>At the <orgName key="mthomeet">Monthly Meeting of Mount-holly</orgName>, I
                    thought matters<lb/>were in a low condition, scarcely managed to the honour of
                    Truth:<lb/>as life seem'd wanting. -- In the evening I visisted one who<lb/>had
                    been an old Professor, hurt by taking strong drink to excess; I
                    dealt<lb/>closely with him, as I took him to be deceiver.</p>
                <pb n="149" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_29"/>
                <p>I visited a family of <orgName key="metho">Methodists</orgName>, who seemed well
                    disposed: they were<lb/>tender &amp; expressed satisfaction.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-02-05">5th.</date>
                    <placeName key="evesh"/></dateline>
                <p>I likewise attended <orgName key="meetevesh">Evesham Mo.ly Meeting</orgName>, and
                    was afraid friends<lb/> were rather on the decline, as to the ground work of
                    religion. The spirit<lb/>of the world often gets too much place in the hearts of
                    Professors, and then<lb/>the good seed is choked, so that it cannot flourish to
                    the honour of the<lb/>Great Husbandman. --- I felt much stripping after I came
                    home,<lb/>but on visiting some of the Poor, &amp; those in Affliction, I was
                    comforted;<lb/>and had cause to bless, &amp; praise the Name of the Israel's
                    God. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-02-08">8th.</date>
                    <placeName key="newto"/></dateline>
                <p>At our <orgName key="meethaddo">Monthly Meeting</orgName> I opened my concern to
                    visit<lb/>the Families belonging to our Meeting of <orgName key="meetnewto"
                        >Newtown</orgName>; and to hold<lb/>a few Meetings near the river side,
                    which my friends united with,<lb/>I was induced to express my Concern also,
                    about so great a Con-course<lb/>of People coming to our <orgName key="haddoqm"
                        >Quarterly Meeting</orgName>, &amp; the disorders often seen<lb/>among them.
                </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-02-14">14th</date>. <placeName key="newto"/></dateline>
                <p>On first day we had a favoured Meeting<lb/>at <orgName key="meetnewto"
                        >Newtown</orgName>: a searching testimony was delivered by our
                    friend<lb/>S.S. many hearts both of young and old were tendered.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-02-15">15th</date>. <placeName key="newto"/></dateline>
                <p> -- I thought I had some clear openings, respecting the manner of<lb/>holding our
                    Meetings for discipline, in the authority of Truth.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-02-18">18th.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>Being at a Meeting held in a School House near the River, I was<lb/>concern'd on
                    the subject of dwarfishness, which is apt to overtake<lb/>Friends both Men and
                    women, in a religious Sense; where the Spirit<lb/>of the World is allowed to
                    gain Place: O how it hinders the Growth<lb/>of the blessed Truth! </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1796-02-21">21st.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p> In visiting the poor and afflicted, I find some who <lb/>are <lb/>
                    <pb n="150" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_30"/> are in a good degree tender &amp;
                    sweet-spirited: one of whom I thought<lb/>had too much confidence in the doctor,
                    which gave me concern. Doctors<lb/>we see are often men of loose principles, not
                    fit for religious Minds<lb/>to place reliance on. On further visits to some in
                    straitned Circum-<lb/>stances, I find Comfort: I am often tried with great
                    poverty of Spirit,<lb/>I therefore own those as my brethren and sisters in
                    tribulation,</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-03-13">3rd. month, 13th</date><placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>I have for near two weeks been engaged in visiting the fami-<lb/>lies mention'd
                    before, to my satisfaction; many of the visited also -<lb/>express the same:
                    more friends are observed to attend Meetings than<lb/>were seen a while past, or
                    before this Visit.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-03-14">14th.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>I thought our<lb/><orgName key="meethaddo">Monthly Meeting</orgName> at this time
                    was pretty well conducted.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-03-15">15th.</date>
                    <placeName key="moore"/></dateline>
                <p>I attended the Meeting at <orgName key="meetmoore">Moorestown</orgName>, &amp;
                    sat with a Committee<lb/>who had under Consideration the subjects mention'd in
                    the Yearly Meetings<lb/>minutes relative to a worldly Spirit &amp;c: I had some
                    close labour touch-<lb/>this <quote type="biblical">root of all evil,</quote>
                    the Love of money; It seems to go hard with<lb/>some old folks, &amp; those who
                    are eagerly pursuing outward wealth: So<lb/>secure were some, they were ready to
                    say, "Touch me not:" But I told<lb/>them, <quote type="biblical">Joseph, or
                        little David, was yet alive; Therefore let no man's<lb/>heart fail
                        him.</quote></p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-03-16"/>
                    <placeName key="ueves"/></dateline>
                <p>The next day at <orgName key="meetueves">Upper-Evesham Meet-<lb/>ing</orgName>, I
                    had to speak of dangers that may happen, if the Watchmen<lb/>fall asleep, and
                    give not the alarm at the approach of the<lb/>enemy. It appear'd that now
                    worldly spirit was advancing fast<lb/>into our Society, &amp; for want of
                    faithful, wakeful, Watchmen, <lb/>many <lb/>
                    <pb n="151" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_31"/> many with their sons and their
                    daughters, are likely to be taken captive;<lb/>the rich are getting more riches;
                    but the poor are oppressed; and I be-<lb/>lieved the time loudly called for an
                    Alteration; and that now Rye<lb/>and Corn sold for so high a price, and other
                    things high also, Friends<lb/>example in moderation might be loud preaching;
                    even if we<lb/>could submit to supply the poor at one third lower than the<lb/>
                    highest price; what a pleasant Savour it would yield in the<lb/>country round
                    us. These sentiments it seemed right for me to<lb/>press home to my friends
                    closely.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-03-17">17th.</date>
                    <placeName key="haddo"/></dateline>
                <p>Attending <orgName key="meethaddo">Haddonfield Meeting</orgName>, I had to
                    mention the manner<lb/>in which we ruled the Ox and the Ass, which are bought
                    with<lb/>our money, &amp; therefore - ought to be subject under us; to come or
                    go at<lb/>our bidding: But ourselves, who are bought at a higher price,
                    by<lb/>the Saviour of the world, do not obey him as our Great Master,<lb/>nor
                    keep his holy Law: Thus, are we not more stubborn than the brutes?<lb/>If the
                    brutes obey not, we give them stripes: And must not the<lb/>Lord chastise us for
                    disobedience? -- We may consider for our-<lb/>selves; As we whip harder for the
                    second Offence, may we not look<lb/>for the same measure ourselves, if still
                    disobedient? As the inhabi-<lb/>tants of this place have been lately visited by
                    the rod of Sickness,<lb/>and many numbered to the silent Grave, of different
                    Ages &amp; sexes:<lb/>and have not some been raised as from the grave, and
                    spared longer,<lb/>who have made promises of amendment in the affliction, yet
                    have<lb/>not kept them? Will not the Lord visit again, by Sword, Famine <lb/>or <lb/>
                    <pb n="152" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_32"/> or pestilence? I had to press these
                    things for close consideration.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-03-19">19th.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>I have several times visited a sick friend, who said she felt a sweet<lb/>calm;
                    that she had all she could look for; death was no terror; adding,<lb/>Oh how
                    trying would a wounded conscience be, at such a time as this!</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-03-24">24th.</date>
                    <placeName key="piles"/></dateline>
                <p> I was at <orgName key="meetpiles">Pilesgrove Mo.ly Meeting</orgName> as poor and
                    low, I thought,<lb/>as I ever felt myself. Next day at our <orgName
                        key="haddoqm">Quarterly Meeting</orgName>, I thought<lb/>it right to mention
                    the situation of two old Jersey Indians near us; one of whom<lb/>is about 80
                    years old, &amp; the other blind, about 60, for whom I have been<lb/>concern'd
                    that they may be properly cared for: a committee was appointed to<lb/>attend to
                    their Case. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-03-26">26th.</date>
                    <placeName key="phila"/></dateline>
                <p> Attending our <orgName key="checkPlace">General Spring Meeting</orgName> in
                        <placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName>, I be-<lb/>lieve it was a
                    favoured Season, remarkably so. Our English friends <persName key="ddarb1"
                        >Debo-<lb/>rah Darby</persName> &amp; <persName key="ryoun1">Rebecca
                        Young</persName> attended, being nearly ready to return<lb/>after
                    accomplishing their religious visit in America; Our Friends <persName
                        key="semle1">Sam.l<lb/>Emlen</persName>, <persName key="wsave1">Will.m
                        Savery</persName>, &amp; two Women friends, going over with them;
                    they<lb/>all obtained Certificates at this Meeting.</p>
                <p> Sitting with the <orgName key="pymind">Committee on Indian Affairs</orgName>, I
                    was concerned<lb/>to open my Sentiments concerning the propriety of taking the
                    situa-<lb/>tion of our Jersey Indians, under care, as well as those more
                    re-<lb/>mote from our dwellings: as I remember to have heard my father<lb/>
                    often mention the Indians Kindness to our Predecessors in the Jer-<lb/>seys,
                    when they were few, &amp; the Indians many. </p>

            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="153" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_33"/>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1796-04-03">3rd.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p> I attended a Meeting held in a School-House over <geogName key="coope">Cooper's
                        Creek</geogName>,<lb/>a large and solid Meeting, which ended well. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1796-04-05"/>
                    <placeName key="glouc"/></dateline>
                <p>On the 5th I had a Meeting<lb/>at a School-house near <placeName key="glouc"
                        >Gloucester</placeName>, not very large on account of a<lb/>Burial, &amp;
                    visited four families afternoon; and the next day five fami-<lb/>lies, which
                    closed our Visit to families of <orgName key="meetnewto">Newtown
                        Meeting</orgName>; about<lb/>90, to our comfort, &amp; the satisfaction of
                    those visited, for ought that<lb/>appear'd. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-04-10">10th.</date>
                    <placeName key="glouc"/></dateline>
                <p>I have visited several other sick persons, not with-<lb/> out a reward, &amp; had
                    two pretty large Meetings in School-houses to good<lb/>satisfaction.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-04-11">11th.</date>
                    <placeName key="haddo"/></dateline>
                <p>At our <orgName key="meethaddo">monthly Meeting</orgName> I laid before my
                    friends the continu-<lb/>ance of a concern to pay a farther Visit within the
                    Governments of<lb/>
                    <placeName key="newyo">New-York</placeName> &amp; <placeName key="canad"
                        >Canada</placeName>, which was referred to the next meeting.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-04-13">13th.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>Visiting sick people, of whom there are many; and some die<lb/>at short Warning:
                    to me the season seems alarming, &amp; I fear hard-<lb/>ness of heart
                    increaseth; with extortion in high prices, as though there<lb/>would not be a
                    living for the poor: Oh the Worldly spirit which prevails;<lb/>Will not the Lord
                    be angry, &amp; stretch forth his hand more severely?</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-04-15">15th.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>Again, I have visited several who were under deep bodily<lb/>infirmity; the State
                    of whom caused serious contemplation concern-<lb/>ing some circumstances: Some
                    are falling out with one another by the<lb/>way, contending about things which
                    appear to be of so little worth<lb/>in a dying hour, that there is no name of a
                    small enough Value to<lb/>call them by. Oh that all would try to be rich in good
                    Works!</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="154" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_34"/>
                <dateline><date when="1796-04">1796. 4th mo.</date><lb/>
                    <date when="1796-04-17">17th.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>I thought I saw the enemy had made an inroad amongst us<lb/>by stirring up
                    discord, and setting friends at variance with one a-<lb/>nother in strong
                    parties, both pleading they were right: when it appear'd<lb/>to me, both were
                    wrong, &amp; gave way too much to thinking evil; For this I<lb/>was grieved, and
                    laboured with both, to be at peace. The love of the<lb/>world was the beginning
                    of this: When that prevails, such are its' fruits.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-04-19">19th.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>I have been visiting the sick: was humbled under a sense of the<lb/>speedy calls
                    from time to eternity, in this day of too general depravity.<lb/>Many trying
                    days I have to pass through; perhaps all for my good:<lb/>these are not joyous;
                    but if they the better prepare me for the Lord's<lb/>work, his Will be done.
                </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key="piles"/><date when="1796-04-21"/>
                </dateline>
                <p>At <orgName key="meetpiles">Pilesgrove meeting</orgName> the 21st I was
                    enabled<lb/>to do what I believed to be my part, faithfully. The same day was
                    at<lb/>a place where a marriage dinner was soon to be provided for my
                    young--<lb/>est son, I had to open my mind on the subject of such
                    entertainments<lb/>freely, &amp; with some weight: pressing the necessity of
                    true Moderation, and<lb/>advising against what has crept in relating to the
                    ceremony of particular<lb/>waiting on the Bride &amp; Groom so called, My advice
                    had a Place in the --<lb/>minds of those concerned; The company at that marriage
                    was small, I attend-<lb/>ed, and was pleased to see a good degree of right order
                    observed. Much loose<lb/>and disorderly conduct at might be prevented by timely
                    care, which<lb/>should be exercised, by friends rightly concerned, whether elder
                    or younger.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-04-25">25th.</date>
                    <placeName key="salem"/></dateline>
                <p>For some days, Sorrow, triels and grievous temptations have<lb/>attended; Yet I
                    believe I had some service amongst the poor, afflicted<lb/>Widows and Fatherless
                    Children, in and near <placeName key="salem">Salem</placeName>, whom I have
                    visited.<lb/>At <orgName key="salempm">Salem Mo.ly Meeting</orgName> next day, I
                    had much Labour both in<lb/>Men's and Women's apartment to good satisfaction.
                        I<lb/><pb n="155" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_35"/> I have had to review the
                    Vanity which prevails with the young<lb/>People of our time, and the Avarice
                    &amp; Extortion that seem visible among<lb/>older Ones, which produce mournful
                    feelings. Nor has it felt pleasant to<lb/>my exercised mind to observe so much
                    of the free use of Silk <del>in</del>
                    <del>for</del><lb/>for clothing in our Country, which is so plentiful for Wool
                    and flax; Might not<lb/>these seem to be sufficient on many occasions, without
                    showing the desire<lb/>of over much delicacy. --- I have been at <orgName
                        key="meetgreew">Greenwich</orgName> and <orgName key="meetwoodb"
                        >Woodberry</orgName><lb/> Meetings, where Poverty was perceived, I fear the
                    Truth is at a low<lb/> ebb among too many of us. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-05"/>5th mo<placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>I have apprehended the Hearts of many professors resemble the sto-<lb/>ny ground;
                    So that altho' favour to them is renewed, for want of depth in<lb/>root they
                    fall into old customs again.</p>
                <p> Close work on answering the Queries in our <orgName key="meethaddo">Preparative
                        Meeting</orgName>; I<lb/>feared that evasive answers to them, would be
                    likely to become a Snare.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-05-08">8th.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>I had to minister Sound Truths, tho' it seemed hard work; and<lb/>hard for people
                    to hear; yet I hope our Meeting ended Well to day. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-05-09"/>
                    <placeName key="haddo"/></dateline>
                <p>Next day was our <orgName key="meethaddo">Monthly Meeting</orgName>: where my
                    Concern mention'd last<lb/>month was united with, and a certificate granted
                    according to my<lb/>prospect, signed with Unanimity.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-05-10"/>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>The day following I had a desire<lb/>to See a number of friends come together at
                    a suitable time &amp; place, who had<lb/>let in hardness one against another;
                    which desire prevailed, so that a time<lb/>was fixed, all uniting therewith
                    except one person who had lost his right<lb/>amongst us: He went to the others,
                    with a view to discourage their attending, and <lb/>
                    <pb n="156" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_36"/> and then told me he had seen them; that
                    they did not purpose to attend<lb/>neither did he: I said, he might use his
                    Pleasure: I intend to go to<lb/>the place, and if none came, I could sit quietly
                    by Self, and had <del>nothing</del><lb/>nothing prepared to say. Yet at the set
                    time, the Friends all came, except<lb/>that Man's Wife, and we had a favourd
                    season which had a uniting ten-<lb/>dency; I could say I was thankful for it,
                    that I loved them, and did -<lb/>believe they loved me.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-05-12">12th.</date>
                    <placeName key="borde"/></dateline>
                <p>The time is near approaching that I must <del>leave</del> leave near connections
                    and all,<lb/>again, and be come as a Pilgrim, which I think is for the cause of
                    Truth, &amp;<lb/>good of souls; Taking leave of my friends in much love at
                    our<lb/>week day meeting, many tears were shed; After I left home I found<lb/>
                    my mind secretly turned, to try to be at <placeName key="borde"
                        >Bordentown</placeName>, and getting there, I had<lb/>cause to believe it
                    was right; though I see but little way before me. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-05-15">15th.</date>
                    <placeName key="borde"/></dateline>
                <p>On first day I was at a pretty large <orgName key="meetbord">Meeting
                        there</orgName>; and at <orgName key="meettrent"
                    >Trenton</orgName><lb/>another, in the afternoon: The last especially was a
                    favoured season.<lb/>I was now a little revived, believing I was in my proper
                    place thus far.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-05-16"/>
                    <placeName key="lambe"/></dateline>
                <p>The next day at <placeName key="lambe">Lamberton</placeName>, where is no
                    religious Meeting held,<lb/>nor Meeting house of any Sort, I had a large Meeting
                    in an empty<lb/>store-house, and feeling my heart so much enlarged in love to
                    the<lb/>People, I seem'd constrained to stand near two hours on my feet;
                    which<lb/>almost surprised me: it having been uncommon with me to stand
                    above<lb/>half so long; This was a highly favoured season, and many
                    hearts<lb/>were tendered; my mind was also bowed in thankful reverence before
                    my<lb/>divine Master: Many of different Ranks, both black and White came to <lb/>
                    <pb n="157" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_37"/> to take leave of me, with tears
                    trickling down: my tears also were min-<lb/>gled with theirs. It truly was a
                    comfortable time. A more solid mee-<lb/>ting, or greater attention, I think I
                    never saw before at any time<lb/>or place, than what was observable here on this
                    occasion.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-05-17"/><placeName key="rahwa"/></dateline>
                <p>Next day, travelling to <persName key="rahwa">Rahaway</persName>, I thought none
                    had to feel<lb/>more of inward poverty than poor me: yet as the Lord is not
                    wanting<lb/>to assist his devoted ones in the needful time, there is no
                    cause<lb/>for murmuring.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-05-18">18th.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>At a kind friends house, there was sent in the afternoon a fine<lb/>riding waggon
                    with nice horses, for that friends wife and me to<lb/>ride in to visit her
                    mother and some others. I told her I had no ob-<lb/>jection to going, yet was
                    not free to ride in that carriage, nor<lb/>with such Horses; but I could go on
                    foot, and she might ride in it,<lb/>as a late rain caused the roads to be wet
                    &amp; unpleasant walking.<lb/>This was a trial to us both, as she appear'd to be
                    a good spirited<lb/>woman: but I believed it best for me to hold forth my
                    testimony<lb/>for simplicity, and lowly mindedness. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-05-19">19th.</date>
                    <placeName key="rahwa"/></dateline>
                <p>I was at <orgName key="meetrahwa">Raha-<lb/>way</orgName> Monthly Meeting, and at
                    an evening Meeting appointed by my<lb/>Friend J. S. held here; These seemed to
                    be laborious Seasons<lb/>though attended by many friends on their Way to
                        <orgName key="nym">Yearly Meeting</orgName> at <placeName key="nycit">N.
                        Y.ork</placeName><lb/>Reaching to that city next day, I was somewhat
                    comforted: many<lb/>Friends kindly came to see me.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="158" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_38"/>
                <dateline><date when="1796-05-21">21st.</date>
                    <placeName key="nycit"/></dateline>
                <p>The <orgName key="nym">Yearly Meeting</orgName> of Ministers and Elders began, at
                    wch<lb/>were our Friends <persName key="jwigh1">John Wigham</persName> and
                        <persName key="mrout1">Martha Ro<del>w</del>uth</persName> from Europe,
                    with<lb/>others out of other Parts; a second sitting thereof was in the
                    afternoon,<lb/>low times to me: I thought many of us were got into a state of
                    easy<lb/>indulgence in many things, and are not soon to be removed from<lb/>
                    Beds of Ease: I tried at it a little, yet not to much purpose. I hinted<lb/>
                    that the benefit &amp; well ordering of this large <orgName key="nym">Yearly
                        Meeting</orgName>, wou'd<lb/>much depend on the wise Conduct of those in
                    high Stations: guarding<lb/>well their own Example &amp; Conversation, and then
                    watching over younger<lb/>People carefully; checking their going on formal
                    visits from house<lb/>to house; that if favoured to receive a little good, they
                    might lose it's Sa-<lb/>vour, or learn bad fashions or unprofitable Customs, by
                    getting into Com-<lb/>panies, and indulging Vanities, so as to be in danger of
                    returning<lb/>from such a Solemnity worse than when they came to it: That of
                    sitt-<lb/>ing up late in the Evenings, &amp; laying in bed late in the mornings
                    I had also to<lb/>mention my belief, it was unprofitable for Body and Soul. I
                    thought<lb/>this kind of Doctrine seemed rather hard or close for me to
                    deliver<lb/>among Brethren &amp; Sisters of high rank in a large City, and
                    though<lb/>lately visited with alarming mortality, I fear too many are not
                    enough<lb/>humbled. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-05-23">23d.</date><placeName key="nycit"/></dateline>
                <p>The meeting of Business began, which in most of it's Sittings<lb/>seem'd times of
                    exercise, the Stream being low, as I thought; Members being<lb/>too generally
                    tinctured more or less with a Worldly Spirit, know not the<lb/>proper value of
                    the precious Truth, &amp; thus become captivated,<lb/>barren &amp; dwarfish.
                    <lb/>At </p>

            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="159" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_39"/>
                <dateline><date when="1796-05-25"/><placeName key="nycit"/></dateline>
                <p>At one Sitting of the select Meeting, on 4th day morning, The truth<lb/>appeared
                    to have comfortable dominion: My mind in the liberty thereof was<lb/>emboldened
                    to inform my brethren and Sisters of my exercise on observing a<lb/>custom to
                    prevail in the <placeName key="nycit">City</placeName> which I thought was not
                    right; and if I differed from<lb/>all my friends in Sentiment I hoped I might be
                    excused; It was that of employ-<lb/>ing men to do women's Work in houses,
                    &amp;c: That I did not doubt there being wo-<lb/>men enough, healthy, &amp;
                    capable of business if their minds were applied<lb/>thereto, to do all that was
                    necessary in Families: And as provisions were dear,<lb/>and men's labour high
                    rated, they had better be imployed in the fields, or<lb/>out door business, than
                    at Womens work; If the young Women were to be<lb/>brought up in a course of
                    family industry, and to rise early in the<lb/>morning, I believed it might
                    contribute to health, and tend to fit many of<lb/>them better for business,
                    &amp; the managing houshold affairs, if they should<lb/>come to need that, than
                    if brought up in an easy delicate Manner: having<lb/>seen some such in my time
                    who have been reduced to great hardship and<lb/>unable then to minister to their
                    own necessities; and perhaps there may<lb/> be instances of this kind proceeding
                    out of Families where men had<lb/>been employ'd to do women's Work, and children
                    indulged in a delicate idle<lb/>life. Tho' my testimony on this head seemed to
                    go hard with some<lb/> to whom it might seem applicable, Yet I found it had the
                    concurrence<lb/>of many friends who expressed unity therewith. It was also
                    proposed by<lb/>one friend that a Minute of the substance of the concern be
                    taken on<lb/>their book which was <del>also</del> agreed to. -- This was a
                    memorable time, the<lb/>Power of Truth in dominion, lofty Spirits chained down,
                    the rich &amp;<lb/>great having to submit to the simple discipline prevalent in
                    the present sea-<lb/>son <lb/><pb n="160" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_40"/> In a
                    following sitting of Ministers &amp; Elders the same<lb/>concern was
                    strengthened by others and friends in the city &amp; country closely
                    ad<lb/>vised to attend to the Contents of what was taken on minute at the
                    former<lb/>Sitting. The Bow seemed (as I believed) to be at this season, renewed
                    &amp;<lb/>strengthened by the Lord's Power, in the hands of some little
                    Ones,<lb/>who had to shoot their Arrows against the Queen of Pride. I did
                    not<lb/>find my self clear without also hinting my exercise on the growing
                    Custom<lb/>of friends having fine Carpets, and flowery Things in their rooms;
                    which<lb/>I believed were not brought into use by the dictates of simple Truth,
                    and that<lb/>a number of such matters might well be spared, and thus help
                        <del>might</del> be<lb/>administerd towards warming and covering many of the
                    Poor. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-05-28">28th.</date>
                    <placeName key="nycit"/></dateline>
                <p>The <orgName key="nym">Yearly Meeting</orgName> ended the <date when="1796-05-28"
                        >28th</date> with a publick Meeting.<lb/>I was exceedingly stripped that
                    Evening; having to confess with the<lb/>Prophet of Old, "I am a Worm, and no
                    man." So great was my poverty<lb/>that I feared I should murmur; there seeming
                    to be no sense of good left.<lb/>But I tried to get into quietude, therein to
                    know what further the<lb/>Lord had for me to do. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-05-29"/>
                    <placeName key="nycit"/></dateline>
                <p>Next day being the first of the Week, there<lb/> were held 3 meetings in the
                        <placeName key="nycit">City</placeName>: The last of which was
                    appointed<lb/>for the Youth of all descriptions: These were large and
                    I<lb/>thought ended well, yet not so highly favoured as some have been.</p>
                <p> Here I parted with my beloved Friends <persName key="jwigh1">J.
                        Wigham</persName> and <persName key="mrout1">M. Routh</persName>.<lb/>each
                    turning to our own Allotments in the Master's work, <persName key="jwigh1"
                        >John</persName>, to<lb/>
                    <placeName key="longi">Long-Island</placeName>, <persName key="mrout1"
                        >Martha</persName> to the Northern Meetings in this Govern-<lb/>ment, and I
                    towards the Genesee Country &amp; <placeName key="canad">Upper
                        Canada</placeName>.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-05-30">30th.</date>
                    <placeName key="nycit"/></dateline>
                <p>Musing on the State of Things, I fear'd that since the late<lb/>mortality, The
                    People in this City are grown rather Worse than <lb/>better <lb/>
                    <pb n="161" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_41"/> better: This is cause of grief to many
                    as well as myself,<lb/>tho' I do not see I have any further to do in the Place.
                </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-05-31">5th mo. 31st</date>. <placeName key="nycit"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>Next day I left <placeName key="nycit">New-York</placeName>, as one having none
                    Inheritance on earth;<lb/>travelled about 40 miles to <geogName key="croto"
                        >Croton River</geogName>, and had a pretty<lb/>large meeting that evening on
                    Short Notice, which proved reviving, and satis-<lb/>factory, believing it ended
                    to the honor of Truth.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-06-01">6th. mo. 1st</date>
                    <placeName key="osweg"/></dateline>
                <p>I went about 40 miles further to a friend's House near the<lb/>
                    <geogName key="nrive">North River</geogName>: and the next day, was at their
                    week day Meet-<lb/>at <orgName key="meetosweg">Swago</orgName>, which was small,
                    yet in measure favored; after<lb/>which I visited an aged friend under bodily
                    affliction: <del>of body</del><lb/>but in a heavenly frame of mind: Who,
                    although his Pain was<lb/>great, refused the taking of Laudanum as a medicine,
                    lest it<lb/>might tend to stupify his Senses, near the close of Life, by
                    it's<lb/>benumbing Effects; I much approved of his religious Caution
                    herein:<lb/>fully believing it has often been handed out by Doctors in an
                    unrigh-<lb/>teous manner; which in some instances may injure the
                    clear<lb/>understanding of departing Souls, in their last Moments.</p>
                <p> I am informed by a friend who says he had it from the<lb/>Mouths of two
                    merchants in <placeName key="nycit">N. York</placeName> who were in Partnership,
                    That<lb/>in the Summer of last year, they imported from the East Indies<lb/>
                    Teas, and Silks: on which the duties which were to be paid, amounted<lb/>to more
                    than one hundred thousand Dollars. And as it is<lb/>said much of those Duties
                    goes towards defraying the expences of<lb/>War, I do not see How friends can
                    consistent with a clear testimony<lb/>to that pure principle which stands
                    against all cruelty and<lb/>bloody measures, freely purchase and use the Goods,
                    on which such Duties <lb/><pb n="162" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_42"/> duties are
                    laid; it being (as I take it,) generally agreed that<lb/>those who use or
                    consume the Articles so circumstanced, do<lb/>pay the Duties. Such are my tender
                    scruples &amp; Testimony;<lb/>and so I leave it for others to look at, perhaps
                    when I am<lb/>dead and gone; believing it to be what was given me to bear,
                    and<lb/>attend to in simplicity and integrity of heart. <lb/>
                    <persName key="jevan1">Joshua Evens</persName>.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-06-03">The 3rd.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p> I proceeded on my Way and came to <persName key="zgree1">Z. Green</persName>'s:
                    had a solid<lb/>time in his family: several young Women were there, &amp; it was
                    a satis-<lb/>factory season. I also visited an aged woman friend, of a
                    heavenly<lb/>mind as I believed. I have to wait a little for a companion;
                    feeling<lb/>inward Calmness: This I take to be a divine Gift, to support
                    a<lb/>tottering mind. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-06-05">5th</date><placeName key="9part1"/></dateline>
                <p>I was at the <orgName key="meetcreek">Creek Meeting</orgName> (<placeName
                        key="9part1">Ninepartners</placeName>), where strength was<lb/>given me to
                    labour (I believe) to the honour of Truth, and my<lb/>own comfort: next day, my
                    companion<lb/>coming, we rode to <placeName key="lnine">Little nine
                        Partners</placeName>, and the day after that<lb/>upon short notice, had a
                    pretty large Meeting to good satisfac-<lb/>tion, at <placeName key="catsk1"
                        >Cattskil</placeName>, amongst the <orgName key="presby"
                        >Presbyterians</orgName>.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-06-08">8th</date><placeName key="unadi"/></dateline>
                <p>Crossing the <geogName key="nrive1">North River</geogName> here, we proceeded
                    westward toward <placeName key="unadi">Unedilly</placeName>:<lb/>I felt myself
                    as a Stranger in a strange land; yet perceived a<lb/>little something which
                    inwardly sweeten's the mind: The next day<lb/>we went much the same Course,
                    thro' a Wilderness, where the<lb/>mountains were admirably high, which seemed
                    awful; and travel-<lb/>ling was very difficult among Roots, Rocks and Mire:
                    Sometimes we <lb/>seemed <lb/>
                    <pb n="163" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_43"/> seemed to be surrounded in such a manner
                    with mountains as -<lb/>though there would be no way. Here it was hinted to
                    mind, "Look not<lb/>outwardly, but to the Lord, &amp; the Path:" I then felt
                    more easy, scarcely<lb/>daring for a while to raise my head, or look about me.
                    The Road -<lb/>also continued difficult the next day, but I was favour'd with a
                    sweet<lb/>calm: -- I thought perhaps many of my friends were in another<lb/>way
                    toiling themselves, in trying to get riches, &amp; leave their Children<lb/>
                    rich, and I struggling along thus might <del>migh</del> come to die out-<lb/>
                    wardly poor: But my mind was touched on this wise; Thy Riches<lb/>come another
                    way; if thou art faithful, thy reward shall be sure,<lb/>and sufficient. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-06-10">10th</date><placeName key="unadi"/></dateline>
                <p>We crossed the River <geogName key="susqu">Susque-<lb/>-hanna</geogName> near
                        <placeName key="unadi">Unedilly</placeName>: Enquiring for a friend's house
                    we had heard of:<lb/> it being also near night, and receiving no account of him,
                    it seemed a<lb/>discouraging circumstance in a wilderness place; But going a
                    little further on<lb/>we obtained lodging; &amp; were informed he lived about
                    fifteen Miles dis-<lb/>tant. --- The following day about noon, we reached to
                        <placeName key="ghalls">Green Halls</placeName>:<lb/> Having now travelled
                    near 160 Miles through a remarkable road<lb/>for difficulties. I have no cause
                    to murmur, feeling the Lord to be near<lb/>as a kind Master. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>On the <date when="1796-06-12"/>
                    <placeName key="ghalls"/></dateline>
                <p>On the 12th. we had a <orgName key="meetghall">Meeting</orgName> at this house;
                    and<lb/>in the afternoon another in a School-house, which were
                    consider-<lb/>able gatherings, and might be called Seasons wherein divine
                    Good-<lb/>ness was dispensed; The solid &amp; quiet Sitting of the People,
                    was<lb/>comforting to me to behold. --- <date when="1796-06-13">13th.</date> Had
                    a Meeting at <persName key="zsmit1">Zeb.n Smith</persName>'s<lb/>by the
                        <geogName key="unadr">Unedilly River</geogName>, among a People who were
                    much unac-<lb/>quainted with friends. There was an appearance of much
                    tender-<lb/>ness in these Meetings: and my heart was affected on hearing of
                    the<lb/>Cries of some of the Poor for want of bread; It seems they have an
                    <lb/>extortionate <lb/>
                    <pb n="164" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_44"/> extortionate teacher, or Priest, to
                    maintain, and a great scarcity<lb/>of grain here; Some have been (they say)
                    several days without bread.<lb/>Also some who went 30 miles to buy, &amp;
                    brought the Corn home on their<lb/>backs. We called at one place, where was a
                    woman and three Chil-<lb/>dren besides one at her breast; whose husband was out
                    seeking bread.<lb/> She said they had been two days without, and knew not
                    when<lb/>he would return. It was almost more than I could bear to hear
                    of,<lb/>&amp; observe the situation of these poor Children; That called
                    the<lb/>House they sheltered in, was, a few logs put up, and brush thrown<lb/>
                    on the top; When it rained they suffered much, having to stand<lb/> or sit the
                    whole night, some times in the wet, and without fire.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-06-14">14th</date><placeName key="chena"/></dateline>
                <p>Had a Meeting in a place called <orgName key="meetchena">Shenang</orgName>, at
                        <persName key="tlion1">T. Lions</persName>, about<lb/>five Miles west of the
                        <geogName key="unadr">Unedilly River</geogName>, among a People
                    not<lb/>acquinted with friends; the gathering was so large, I wonder'd
                    where<lb/>all the People came from; In the afternoon, another at <orgName
                        key="meetghall">Green-<lb/>Halls</orgName>; these were favour'd seasons; in
                    the last especially, the hearts of<lb/>many were melted into tenderness. With
                    respect to <persName key="ghall1">G. Hall</persName> &amp; <persName
                        key="lhall1">Lydia</persName><lb/>his wife, I had reason to believe (if they
                    were faithful) the Lord would<lb/>prepare them for usefulness in this wilderness
                    Country. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-06-16">16th.</date>
                    <placeName key="otego"/></dateline>
                <p>We now took leave of our friends of this place in much near-<lb/>ness: it seemed
                    hard for them part with us: and travelled<lb/>through a rough way to <placeName
                        key="otego">Ottego</placeName>: here I met with some of my kinsfolk<lb/>and
                    acquaintance, and we were kindly received by a Son of <persName key="jslee1"
                        >John<lb/>Sleeper's</persName>: The next day had a pretty large Meeting to
                    good satisfaction <lb/>in <lb/><pb n="165" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_45"/><lb/>in a
                    new barn of <persName key="bslee1">Bn. Sleeper</persName>'s: The day following
                    at the same place<lb/>we had one with those who professed, or had a friendly
                    education,<lb/>which ended to my comfort and theirs also: We found them in<lb/>a
                    tried Spot: Some who had come hither to settle, appearing in
                    measure<lb/>friend-like, had conducted in a shameful, dishonest way, rather
                    drunken,<lb/>and disposers of goods which were sent here damaged &amp; of
                    small<lb/>value; endeavouring to cheat, &amp; take advantage of Poor People
                    &amp;c:<lb/>Such had left a stink behind them, and caused the way of Truth<lb/>
                    to be evilly spoken of, to the grief of some tender spirited little ones.<lb/>O
                    the mischief and wrongs some Traders are guilty of, profess what<lb/>they may,
                    who send into those new Countries, Old Shops Goods, not<lb/>easily to be sold in
                    more populous Places; in this manner defraud-<lb/>ing &amp; oppressing Poor
                    people &amp; new Settlers; Will not the Cry of these<lb/>corrupt deeds reach the
                    ears of Heaven's King, and call for a scourge<lb/>on the workers of such
                    Iniquity. Having been an Eye wit-<lb/>ness &amp; mourner on these accounts, or
                    having cause to believe the<lb/>Truth of such Complaints, I think I shall not
                    stand clear in my<lb/>duty, without making, and leaving remarks as things occur.
                </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-06-19"/><placeName key="otego"/>
                </dateline>
                <p> On first day the 19th. had a Solid quiet Meeting in the barn<lb/>above mention'd
                    which I thought ended to the honour of Truth: This<lb/>was supposed to be the
                    largest gathering ever known in these parts</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="166" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_46"/>
                <dateline><date when="1796-06-20">20th.</date><placeName key="otego"/></dateline>
                <p>Visited several families, &amp; had a Meeting in <persName key="sslee1">Sl.
                        Sleepers</persName> Grist Mill,<lb/> pretty large, but long in gathering,
                    which hurt the service; it ended<lb/>well. The people for quiet orderly sitting
                    were remarkable.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-06-21">21st</date><placeName key="otego"/></dateline>
                <p>We went to see some families, two of which were my eldest Sis-<lb/>ters
                    daughters, they live at <placeName key="otego">Otego</placeName>: Also had a
                    Meeting about eight<lb/>miles up the creek at <persName key="ncogg1">Nicho.s
                        Coggeshal</persName>'s, remarked for a time of<lb/>favour. A deacon of the
                        <orgName key="bapt">Baptist</orgName> Society at the conclusion, said<lb/>he
                    could say, Amen, to the testimony which was preached; that not<lb/> a word had
                    been spoken but what he united with; and altho' he<lb/>was old, he never had
                    been at a friends' meeting before. I then<lb/>return'd to my beloved friends
                    near <placeName key="otego">Otego</placeName>, named <persName key="jbrig1">John
                        Brightman</persName>,<lb/><persName key="jmatt1">John Matthewson</persName>
                    &amp; <persName key="icarr1">Isaac Carr</persName>, who had Families; with
                    others there<lb/>who I think deserve the notice of friends: These have
                    suffered<lb/>much by the misconduct of some (as before hinted) who proved
                    dishonest,<lb/>and as stumbling blocks to tender enquirers.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-06-23">23d.</date><placeName key="otego"/></dateline>
                <p>We had a farewell Meeting in <persName key="bslee1">Sleeper</persName>'s barn;
                    satisfactory.<lb/>This being a time near our parting, we visited other
                    families:<lb/>some with tears expressed their Sorrow at our leaving them.
                    -<lb/>Here are some tender-spirited little Ones, who felt near and
                    dear,<lb/>whose Condition for reasons aforesaid hath been trying. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-06-24">24th.</date>
                    <placeName key="coopt"/></dateline>
                <p>I was this day in a low state of mind: Rode to <placeName key="coopt"
                        >Cooper's-town</placeName><lb/>on the east end of <placeName key="otego"
                        >Otego</placeName>; a Spot beautiful for Situation. Here<lb/>unexpectedly,
                    we were kindly received by <persName key="wcoop1">Wm. Cooper</persName>, then
                    Judge<lb/>of the Court, &amp; his sister , altho' Strangers. He queried whether
                    I stood <lb/>in <lb/><pb n="167" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_47"/> in need of Money,
                    and if I did, he was willing to supply me, he said.<lb/> also unknown to me, he
                    wrote an Order, that if at any time, whilst<lb/>in these northern parts, I
                    should have occasion, I might draw<lb/>on him, which he would cheerfully answer.
                    -- Finding the roads<lb/>very difficult, here I sold my waggon, &amp; some other
                    things, and<lb/>provided myself to ride on my mare, with the kind assistance of<lb/>
                    <persName key="wcoop1">Judge Cooper</persName> &amp; his sister; having cause to
                    remember them both:<lb/>we had a solid, good meeting at this place, which to
                    some, was a<lb/>tendering season. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-06-25"/>
                    <placeName key="coopt"/></dateline>
                <p>The 25th. in the morning we left <placeName key="coopt"
                    >Cooper's-town</placeName>,<lb/>and travelled near 50 miles to <placeName
                        key="duane">Duane's-Bush</placeName>; This was as try-<lb/>ing as my nature
                    could well bear: Towards the latter part we came<lb/>to a family of poor Irish
                    people: Here we got down to rest ourselves &amp;<lb/>horses a little, it being
                    very warm weather; and I much fatigued; Here tho'<lb/>not at all agreeable, I
                    thought we must stay that night: Yet were, <del>af-</del><lb/>
                    <del>ter</del> after resting awhile, favour'd to reach <persName key="wbrig1"
                        >Walter Briggs</persName>'s, our desired<lb/>Place. -- The next day, had two
                    pretty large Meetings held in<lb/>a Barn at <placeName key="duane"
                        >Duanes-bush</placeName>; one of which was a favour'd time; the other<lb/>
                    more exercising, the minds of the People being outward. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-06-27">27th.</date>
                    <placeName key="duane"/></dateline>
                <p> We had a meeting at <persName key="wbrig1">W. Briggs</persName>'s, in a new
                    framed house, which was<lb/>large, &amp; ended well; the people appearing solid.
                    We have no cause to<lb/>murmur: we want for nothing, The Lord being good, and
                    doth marvel-<lb/>lously open the way: Unto whom be all Glory &amp; Praise,
                    forever, Amen.<lb/>We now propose to go up the <geogName key="mohaw">Mohock
                        river</geogName>; but how far, we cannot say. <lb/>This <lb/>
                    <pb n="168" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_48"/> This <persName key="wbrig1">W.
                        Briggs</persName> is a friendly man; he lives near that <geogName
                        key="mohaw">River</geogName>.<lb/>I have been fearful on the account of
                    some, who seem likely to ac-<lb/>quire a large Share of outward wealth, whether
                    it will not choke<lb/>the good Seed in their minds, except great Care is taken
                    to keep humble.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-06-28">28th</date><placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>This day we rode about 25 Miles to <persName key="talmy1">Thomas
                    Almey</persName>'s; and the next, had<lb/>a smallish meeting in his barn, yet
                    very quiet: The People were<lb/>strangers to our Meetings and manner of Worship;
                    as there never had<lb/>been a meeting of the kind here before; and I believe
                    this did not<lb/>cause any dishonour to the <del>cause of</del> Truth: I am now
                    in a<lb/>poor state of health; but with kind friends, resting a little; and
                    feel<lb/>my mind very calm: resigned to the divine Will.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-07-01">7th. mo 1st.</date>
                    <placeName key="white"/></dateline>
                <p>Travelling near 50 miles towards <placeName key="white">Whitstown</placeName>,
                    pretty comfort-<lb/>ably, we reached that place on the <date when="1796-07-02"
                        >2nd</date> before noon. There I met<lb/>with my neighbor <persName
                        key="jcoop1">J. Cooper</persName>, &amp; other friends appointed to visit
                    the<lb/>Indians: And finding freedom to join them, we went in Company<lb/>that
                    afternoon to an Indian Settlement called <placeName key="broth"
                        >Brotherton</placeName>: I under-<lb/>stand the number of these Indians is
                    about 200, They have Cows,<lb/>Horses, Oxen &amp;c: <del>and</del> hold as yet a
                    Tract of good Land, about ten thou-<lb/>sand acres, and have an yearly income
                    paid by <placeName key="newyo">New-York</placeName> Go-<lb/>vernment of 2000
                    dollars for Lands sold thereto. ---<lb/>We were comfortably entertained by an
                    Indian named <persName key="gcros1">George<lb/>Crosley</persName>; this is a
                    kind family, speaking our language, and we find their daugh-<lb/>ter can read
                    and write pretty well. </p>
                <p> As I have from my young years, been friendly disposed towards<lb/>the Native
                    owners of our American Lands, and especially since Reli-<lb/>gion began to have
                    place in my mind, have been often concerned on ac-<lb/>count <lb/>
                    <pb n="169" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_49"/> count of the wrongs and unfair dealings
                    of my brethren the white<lb/> Settlers of different Ranks, with Traders &amp;c,
                    which have, I fear,<lb/>taken Place in too many instances, to the great injury
                    of the poor<lb/>Indians; I have therefore thought it right to leave some remarks
                    to<lb/>posterity, here, and in other parts of my simple notes, of my
                    Senti-<lb/>ments which have occured on this subject. ~ It appears that<lb/>in
                    years back, some of the Indian Lands in this govern-<lb/>ment where I now am,
                    were by them rented to some white-<lb/>people who settled thereon: After thus
                    obtaining possession,<lb/>it seems those professed Christian white settlers
                    refused to go off their rented lands:<lb/>also those who were in stations of
                    government supposing, or<lb/>pretending they could not easily remove them, even
                    if the In-<lb/>dians were the sufferers; <del>and</del> therefore advised that
                    the lands<lb/>be sold to the government; and to promote a Sale, perhaps
                    an<lb/>offer was made to the Indians, that an interest tho' much less than their
                    Value or yearly<lb/>Income should be paid them in lieu of their Lands: Now to
                    turn<lb/>the scale, &amp; look at the treatment they have met with heretofore
                    in<lb/>some places; How do we suppose the White people would remove<lb/>Indians,
                    if they were to come intruding and settle on the real property of the
                    Whites?<lb/>Would it not be likely that the Method of expelling them<lb/>by
                    sword and gun would be adopted, without endeavoring to convince<lb/>or shew
                    them, that the mild spirit of Christianity leads men to do<lb/>justly &amp;
                    strictly, to observe Equity one towards another in every nation<lb/>where it
                    prevails. To me it remains a serious cause of real Concern <lb/>
                    <pb n="170" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_50"/> that in a Country of Professing
                    Christians, whose predecessors<lb/>were permitted to come and settle on a part
                    of the soil, allotted by<lb/>Divine Providence to native owners who are our
                    brethren of his Creation: Who have been<lb/>renowned both before &amp; since the
                    corruption they imbibed through<lb/>the Fraud &amp; bad example of white men, to
                    be in general, kind and<lb/>hospitable, as well as remarkably punctual to their
                    engagements: That<lb/>these poor natives in so many instances should justly have
                    cause to com-<lb/>plain of wrongs, impositions, &amp; unchristian treatment,
                    through breach<lb/>of contracts, unjustly grasping after and obtaining their
                    Lands, besides<lb/>the great abuse and disadvantage they have received by the
                    hateful<lb/>practice of introducing strong Liquor, Whisky &amp;c, among a weak,
                    unguar-<lb/>ded &amp; uncivilized People: And that these Complaints should
                    undeniably<lb/>fix upon Men more knowing &amp; civilized, who if the Spirit of
                    the religion they profess was attended to<lb/>would find it incumbent on them to
                    shew forth a very different Conduct, or a<lb/>treatment and Disposition much
                    more likely to instruct, civilize and convert<lb/>those whom they term a savage
                    &amp; barbarous People. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-07-03">7th. mo. 3rd</date><placeName key="broth"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> ... To day we had two comfortable meetings at <placeName key="broth"
                        >Brotherton</placeName>,<lb/>attended by many of the Indians, both men and
                    women. This People,<lb/>or many of them appear'd to have a deep sense of Favour.
                    We parted<lb/>with them in much Love, and went to another Indian Settlement called<lb/>
                    <placeName key="stock">Stockbridge</placeName>, lodging at the house of a Chief
                    called <persName key="haupa1">Captain Hendricks</persName>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-07-04">4th.</date>
                    <placeName key="stock"/></dateline>
                <p>The Committee having agreed to hold a Council with the <orgName key="stockbridge"
                        >Stockbridge<lb/>Indians</orgName><lb/><pb n="171" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_51"
                    /> Indians, I attended also. This was in consequence of Friends concern<lb/> for
                    their benefit &amp; advancement in civilized life, and a desire to aff-<lb/> ord
                    them some assistance by giving them impliments such as axes, <emph
                        rend="underline">howes</emph>,<lb/>&amp;c. This conference was not so
                    satisfactory as we could desire; these In-<lb/>dians then shewing rather a
                    coveting disposition, or looking for larger<lb/>gifts from friends than was
                    proper to expect, or for them to be supplied<lb/>with so hastily: perhaps their
                    expectations had been by some means<lb/>imprudently raised before our coming to
                    see them. --- Before we<lb/>parted from this Council, so called, the Indians
                    were informed that at<lb/>two hours from that time, I proposed to have a meeting
                    at the same place<lb/>where we now met them. --- In consequensce of which notice
                    a large<lb/>Number of them, men and women came together; It proved to be
                    an<lb/>exercising Season, life was much wanting; many of them were
                    ignorant<lb/>in our language, so that an interpreter was made use of, and I felt
                    my<lb/>self poor at parting. -- I understand that the Portion of Land
                    wch<lb/>these <orgName key="stockbridge">Stockbridge Indians</orgName> possess,
                    is said to be 23,000, Acres, and their<lb/> number is about three hundred: Also
                    that their yearly income from<lb/>the Government is 600 dollars; which might
                    yield them more benefit<lb/>if a considerable part of it went not, or was not
                    spent in Strong<lb/>drink, which I suppose has manifestly been too often the
                    Case. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-07-05">5th.</date><placeName key="stock"/></dateline>
                <p>Passing thro' the Town of the <orgName key="tuscarora">Tuscarora Tribe</orgName>
                    (who are but few or about 60 in num-<lb/>ber) we went to the settlement of
                        <orgName key="oneida">Oneida Indians</orgName>, where was held a<lb/>Council
                    so called. Things here were not very pleasant, The Indians seem<lb/>
                    <pb n="172" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_52"/> seem at times unsteady &amp; fickle; by
                    some means they were not plea-<lb/>sed, &amp; the interpreter disordered with
                    strong drink; these circumstan-<lb/>ces were very trying; But we informed them
                    we were willing to have another<lb/>meeting, which was proposed for religious
                    worship in the afternoon.</p>
                <p> This happened to be more trying still; for the Intepreter was so drun-<lb/>ken
                    &amp; poor a creature, I had but little freedom to speak by him, if suit-<lb/>
                    able matter had opened; so that my Sorrow was increased on seeing so<lb/>much
                    drunkenness among Indians. -- From hence we returned to<lb/>
                    <placeName key="stock">Stockbridge</placeName>, &amp; tarried there again that
                    night; <persName key="haupa1">Captain Hendricks</persName> seems to<lb/>be a
                    chief of some consequence &amp; reputation, &amp; his wife a well behaved<lb/>
                    woman so far as I saw. The <orgName key="oneida">Oneidas</orgName> being<lb/>the
                    largest of those Nations, are computed six hundred in number.<lb/>The Land they
                    hold, called 150 thousand Acres, &amp; their income from<lb/>government yearly,
                    five thousand dollars. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-07-06">6th</date><placeName key="stock"/></dateline>
                <p>The committee having goods to distribute among the Indians, the<lb/>business was
                    finished this morning at <placeName key="stock">Stockbridge</placeName>: and
                    many both men and women com-<lb/>ing to take leave; we had a favoured
                    opportunity with them, wherein<lb/>greater tenderness appear'd, than in any
                    other Season since we came to<lb/>visit them. --- We then went to the Place
                    where three friends<lb/>propose staying a while among the <orgName key="oneida"
                        >Oneidas</orgName> to instruct them; with<lb/>whom we had a solid parting
                    season: after this, as many Indians<lb/>were come together near our departure
                    from the Place, My desire<lb/>was<lb/><pb n="173" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_53"/>
                    was mention'd of sitting under yonder Trees a little while with as<lb/> many of
                    them, both men and women as were willing to come toge-<lb/>ther there, (shewing
                    the place;) Upon which about 150 came; some<lb/>of whom being painted Red, black
                    &amp;c, seemed to make a frightful<lb/><del><gap/></del>Show as they sat on the
                    ground; yet on the whole, their appear-<lb/>ance was then more solid that at the
                    former times when we were with<lb/>them: so that our parting with the <orgName
                        key="oneida">Oneidas</orgName>, was in a way Mostly<lb/> friendly: -- And
                    yet as a portion of Death and darkness was per-<lb/>ceived rather than a
                    pleasant feeling among them on these Visits:<lb/>altho' perhaps in their way of
                    civility, their custom of saying,<lb/>Yough, is to give <del>of</del>
                        assent<del>ing</del> to what they hear deliver'd to them, yet to me<lb/>it
                    was unpleasant at this time; and I have my doubts concerning some
                    things.<lb/>This afternoon we went on about 12 miles towards the <placeName
                        key="onond">Onon-<lb/>dagoes</placeName>; and having to lodge at an Indian
                    Tavern, it seemed to<lb/>be a poor time: Yet I felt my mind quiet in a good
                    degree, which<lb/>I esteem a high favour in these times of Trial. </p>
                <p> The <orgName key="tuscarora">Tuscaroes</orgName> hinted of before, live on the
                        <orgName key="oneida">Oneidas</orgName> Land, and<lb/>have about two hundred
                    acres allotted them: and it is said a proportion<lb/>of 4,500 dollars, perhaps,
                    annually from the government. I understand that<lb/>murdering one another when
                    involved in drunkenness, frequently happens<lb/>among Indians in these parts. Oh
                    that White People may be concern'd to con-<lb/>duct so towards them, as not to
                    be found chargeable with Guilt on account of<lb/>the Sins of Indians. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="174" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_54"/>
                <dateline><date when="1796-07-08">8th.</date><placeName key="onond"/></dateline>
                <p>After riding about 18 Miles further, a Council (as they<lb/>call it) was held
                    among those called <orgName key="onondaga">Onondago Indians</orgName>:
                    These<lb/>seemed not well pleased; as we found they upon some grounds had
                    ex-<lb/>pectations of larger gifts or help from friends than they were now<lb/>
                    likely to obtain; This was trying again, and my feelings were un-<lb/>pleasant
                    &amp; mournful; O the necessity of prudence and wise steering,<lb/>if we propose
                    to be useful to these uncultivated fellow Men.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-07-09">9th.</date><geogName key="cayug"/></dateline>
                <p>We now set forward towards the <geogName key="cayug">Cayuga Lake</geogName> on a
                    visit to those<lb/>called <orgName key="cayuga">Cayuga Indians</orgName> living
                    there, who seemed poor and miserable<lb/>&amp; like the others, disappointed in
                    their expectations; We found their chiefs<lb/>were not at home, and that the end
                    of our coming could not be answered to day,<lb/>we proposed tomorrow to have a
                    meeting with some White People dwell-<lb/>ing near.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-07-10">10th.</date><placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>So it being first day, we met, &amp; sat comfortably with a<lb/>little gathering;
                    it being a favoured season: here were some of the<lb/>scattered little ones,
                    with whom my heart was tenderly affected.<lb/>In the afternoon we went to meet
                    with the Indians, having spoken to<lb/>them on the subject the day before: and
                    altho' none came at the time<lb/>proposed, we sat down, and I may say I was
                    comforted in our Sitting<lb/>&amp; concluded we had done well, though these poor
                    creatures were very much igno-<lb/>rant of what we mean by Worship. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>On the <date when="1796-07-11"/>
                    <placeName key="genev"/></dateline>
                <p> On the 11th. a few Indians met with us in Council, who appeared misera-<lb/>ble,
                    and some of them, I thought, then disorder'd with strong drink: we<lb/>had but
                    little satisfaction, as they were looking for Gifts &amp;c. </p>
                <p> Parting with them, I went from hence down the <geogName key="cayug">Cayuga<lb/>
                        lake</geogName>, &amp; crossing the ferry, came to a small Village, called
                        <placeName key="genev">Geneva</placeName>,<lb/>where we lodged at a <lb/>
                    <pb n="175" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_55"/>
                    <date when="1796-07">1796.<lb/>7th mo</date>. <lb/>a tavern. --- From thence
                    next day, to <emph rend="underline"><placeName key="canan"
                            >Canadocway</placeName></emph>;</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-07-12">12th.</date><placeName key="canan"/></dateline>
                <p>and tarrying a while at <persName key="ichap1">Israel Chapin's</persName> (who is
                    the Indian<lb/>Agent) we went on to <persName key="ncoms1">Nathan
                        Cumstock's</persName>, near <geogName key="mudcr"
                    >Mud-Creek</geogName><lb/>in the <placeName key="genes">Genesee
                        Country</placeName>. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-07-14">14th.</date>
                    <placeName key="genes"/></dateline>
                <p>At this place we had a <orgName key="meetgenes">Meeting</orgName> in the
                    forenoon, and one in<lb/>the afternoon which were pretty large; &amp; solid
                    favour'd seasons.<lb/>Then we went on to <persName key="alaph1">Abm.
                        Lapham's</persName>. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-07-15">15th</date>. <placeName key="genes"/></dateline>
                <p>We visited seve-<lb/>ral families at, and near <geogName key="mudcr"
                        >Mud-Creek</geogName>. Then to <persName key="naldr1">Nathanl.
                        Aldridges</persName>.<lb/>This seems to be a low flat Country, the water
                    unwholsome,<lb/>&amp; the Place sickly. -- Some asked me if I was not afraid
                    of<lb/>being sick; I told them I thought I was not for I enjoy'd a
                    quiet<lb/>mind, which I esteemed a great blessing; more especially when<lb/>- I
                    am in the Lord's service.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-07-15">15th.</date>
                    <placeName key="canan"/></dateline>

                <p>Next day at <persName key="jsmit4">Jonn. Smith's</persName>, we<lb/>had a large
                    and favoured Meeting, in which much tenderness ap-<lb/>peared among both old and
                    young, a comfortable season to many.<lb/>This was about four Miles from <emph
                        rend="underline"><placeName key="canan">Canadocwey</placeName></emph>. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-07-16">16th.</date>
                    <placeName key="canan"/></dateline>
                <p>At <persName key="wingl1">Willm. Ingle's</persName> in the forenoon we had a
                    pretty large mee-<lb/>ting, which was comfortable. And in the afternoon (<emph
                        rend="underline">in the</emph>)<lb/>at <emph rend="underline"><placeName
                            key="canan">Canadocwy</placeName></emph> we had another, in the
                    Court,house, not so<lb/>large, nor so much favour'd; yet it was agreeable to
                    observe the<lb/> people sat commendably quiet and attentive. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-07-17">17th.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>Leaving this place, we travelled for five days towards<lb/>
                    <placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName>, through an unpleasant
                    mountainous Country, met with poor<lb/>fare for men &amp; horses, &amp; mean
                    lodging; sometimes on the floor,<lb/>with swarms of fleas, &amp;c; a Scarcity of
                    bread was also apparent. </p>
                <pb n="176" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_56"/>
                <p>Expences in travelling mount high; the road uneven and<lb/>mirey in Places: We
                    are all favourd with health, being five in<lb/>number &amp; have travelled in
                    the five days near two hundred miles.<lb/>Many of the people through this back
                    Country of late seemed to be<lb/>of the ungodly sort; and less room to receive
                    the Principles<lb/>of Truth, than I have seen in my eastern Travels of near
                    7,000<lb/>miles; Tho' we have among them met with some who were more<lb/>
                    Friendly. On looking back over my travels, I believe I have endea-<lb/>vour'd
                    honestly to discharge the trust the Lord reposed in me, thro'<lb/>the ability he
                    afforded: Blessed forever be his great and holy Name,<lb/>who faileth not to
                    help in the needful times, and rewards with the<lb/>answer of sweet peace. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-07-24">24th.</date>
                    <placeName key="muncy"/></dateline>
                <p>We are now at <placeName key="muncy">Munsy</placeName> in <placeName key="penns"
                        >Pennsylvania</placeName>; have attended a<lb/>large <orgName key="muncym"
                        >Meeting</orgName> among my friends &amp; others, and had close Labour,
                    wch.<lb/>seems to be well received. At <placeName key="bloom"
                        >Blooming-Grove</placeName> (or Pine-Grove)<lb/>the <date when="1796-07-25"
                        >next day</date>, we visited a few friends who are lately come there:<lb/>
                    they appear thoughtful in some degree, &amp; have a pretty large<lb/>flock of
                    youth &amp; innocent Children; This is N. Westward of <placeName key="muncy"
                        >Munsy</placeName>, to-<lb/>wards the <geogName key="allmo">Alleganey
                        Mountain:</geogName> Here the <date when="1796-07-26">day following</date>
                    we had<lb/>two <orgName key="meetbloom">meetings</orgName>: one of them with our
                    friends selected; and the other<lb/>for all that pleased to come; which, tho'
                    attended with close Labor<lb/>were measurably satisfactory: much openness
                    appear'd amongst<lb/> them to hear the world preached, &amp; many signified
                    their Unity.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-07-27">27th.</date>
                    <placeName key="muncy"/></dateline>
                <p>Visited some families at <placeName key="muncy">Muncy</placeName> to
                    satisfaction. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="177" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_57"/>
                <dateline><date when="1796-07-28">28th.</date><placeName key="muncy"/></dateline>

                <p>At <orgName key="muncym">Muncy</orgName> we had a Meeting, the largest (they say)
                    ever seen at<lb/>that Place, many more people than the house held, and one
                    the<lb/>same day with friends by themselves; I had much labour<lb/>this day, my
                    Shirt being wet with sweat, It was an humbling<lb/>season: Visited some families
                    also. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-07-29">29th</date> -- <geogName key="fishi"/></dateline>
                <p>We travelled hard to reach to the Meeting at <orgName key="meetfishi"
                        >Fishing-creek</orgName>, near<lb/>20 Miles; it was large and solid, being
                    the first held in their<lb/>new house. In my wearisom travel I have in many
                    places<lb/>found that Truth was at a low ebb, though People have sat
                    com-<lb/>mendably quiet, yet some raw &amp; uncultivated have attended. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-07-30">30th.</date><placeName key="berwi"/></dateline>
                <p>Travelled hard again to reach <placeName key="berwi">Berwick</placeName>, a
                    little village on<lb/>the N. East branch of <geogName key="susqu"
                        >Susquehanna</geogName>, where in the afternoon, had<lb/>a <orgName
                        key="meetberwi">Meeting</orgName>: it was pretty large, and held in the
                    Court-house<lb/> Chamber (<placeName key="north">Northumberland
                        County</placeName>:) the People appear'd well satis-<lb/>fied. A few friends
                    dwell here, but no meeting settled. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-07-31">31st.</date><placeName key="catta"/></dateline>
                <p>We went down the river in a boat which friends provided<lb/>to go to meeting at
                        <orgName key="meetcat">Catawissey</orgName> town to which they belong,
                    the<lb/>distance called 15 miles. This boat had in it 30 people, &amp; would
                    carry more.<lb/>They frequently attend their meeting in this way, and have to
                    push back<lb/>up stream when they return: I mention this to encourage
                    others,<lb/>that they may not let small matters prevent their diligence in
                    divine<lb/>Worship. -- This being first day, we were at Meeting with friends and
                    others<lb/>at <orgName key="meetcat">Catawissey</orgName>, which was not so
                    favoured a season as many others. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-08-01">8th mo. 1st.</date><placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>The next day we met with friends selected from others: It was a<lb/>humbling
                    season to many, tending to unite us nearly in Love to each <lb/>other<lb/>
                    <pb n="178" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_58"/>other. After meeting visited some, sick,
                    aged &amp; infirm people<lb/>to my comfort &amp; theirs. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1796-08-02">2nd</date>. <placeName key="roari"/></dateline>
                <p>The next day we went to <orgName key="meetroar">Roaring-<lb/>creek
                        meeting</orgName>; a solid and favoured time. Near it's conclusion
                    I<lb/>requested Friends not to go out when others did, for I thought a
                    little<lb/>fragment remained for them. Here was a considerable number of
                    Young-<lb/>people, who sat solidly, as did the Parents. A time not soon to
                    be<lb/>forgotten, I hope.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1796-08-03">3rd</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>After visiting some aged people, and<lb/>tender little ones acceptably, I
                    returned to <placeName key="catta">Catawissey</placeName>. &amp; the
                    day<lb/>following, attended their week-day meeting: I thought it was a<lb/>solid
                    season, also visited some aged &amp; infirm people.</p>
                <gap/>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1796-08-07">7th</date><placeName key="maide"/></dateline>
                <p> (I was this day at the week day meeting at <orgName key="meetcat"
                        >Catawissey</orgName> which was<lb/>a comfortable time;) The next Morning
                    leaving this Place in two days, I<lb/>travelled through those called <geogName
                        key="bluem">Blue Mountains</geogName>, (a rough road, &amp;<lb/>I was poorly
                    &amp; much fatigued, the distance near fifty Miles) <lb/>to <lb/>
                    <pb n="179" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_59"/> to <placeName key="maide"
                        >Maiden-Creek</placeName>: On first day I was at that <orgName key="maidem"
                        >Meeting</orgName>; it<lb/>was not very large, but an humbling season to
                    many hearts of the<lb/>Youth and others; I believe it is not one that will be
                    forgotten soon, by<lb/>the youth especially: This is mention'd to the Lord's
                    praise; I know that not<lb/>any thing is due to mortal man: It is often my lot
                    to enter the<lb/>meeting-houses as an empty vessel; my joints nearly trembling,
                    for<lb/>fear any thing through me should give occasion for the holy<lb/>cause to
                    be lightly spoken of: Let not the Lord's faithful servents<lb/>or Handmaids fail
                    of being watchful, &amp; dependent on him in the<lb/>most stripping seasons; so
                    shall we know an establishment on the sure<lb/>rock, further and further. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-08-09">9th.</date><placeName key="readi"/></dateline>
                <p>From <placeName key="maide">Maiden-creek</placeName> I went to a meeting in the
                    town of <orgName key="meetread">Reading</orgName>,<lb/>in <placeName key="berks"
                        >Berks County</placeName>; which was large, and I may say, solid: Here,
                    (as<lb/> has been common where I have travelled) were all sorts that chose
                    to<lb/>come; some from curiosity to see, &amp; to hear a man who wears his
                    beard.<lb/>This circumstance has given me as large opportunity to see the
                    people<lb/>whom I should not otherwise have seen. This Meeting, I
                    believe<lb/>ended well; Let the praise be given to him who is our Holy
                    Helper.<lb/>The next day, I was at <placeName key="robin">Robinson</placeName>
                    meeting on the west side of<lb/><geogName key="schri">Schuylkill
                        river</geogName>; Tho' it was not large, it was a solid &amp; favoured
                    sea-<lb/>son; many hearts being tendered. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-08-11">11th</date>.<placeName key="exete"/></dateline>
                <p>I was next at <orgName key="meetexete">Exeter</orgName>; not a large meeting, and
                    long in the<lb/>gathering; when assembled it was but a poor low time. I <lb/>
                    <pb n="180" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_60"/> I thought I was sensible of a dry
                    lukewarm state; which is but too<lb/> common amongst the highly favour'd People
                    called Quakers: O how<lb/>the customs, the love and the spirit of the world have
                    caused dim-<lb/>ness in some places. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1796-08-12">12th</date>. <placeName key="pottt"/></dateline>
                <p> The following day I had a small meeting<lb/>at <orgName key="meetpottt"
                        >Potts-town</orgName>; I thought the number of Women was largest here,
                    &amp;<lb/>they the most tender. I had close labour amongst them, which was<lb/>
                    well received, and I thought the meeting ended to the honour of the good<lb/>
                    cause: Divers gay people attended &amp; sat solidly. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-08-13">13th</date>. <placeName key="richl"/></dateline>
                <p>From hence I travelled to <placeName key="richl">Richland</placeName> in
                        <placeName key="bucks">Bucks County</placeName>, in an exercised
                    &amp;<lb/>low state of mind, and was at two pretty large meetings there on
                    first<lb/> day, though I thought the truth was not permitted to come much
                    into<lb/>dominion, either in the fore - or afternoon. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1796-08-15">15th.</date>
                    <placeName key="plums"/></dateline>
                <p>From this place<lb/>I went to <orgName key="meetplums">Plumstead</orgName>, and
                    had a meeting, pretty large; but so poor<lb/> and low a time, I was almost ready
                    to think all was over with me:<lb/>I had less opinion of preaching; desiring the
                    people might have time<lb/>to think of their condition, and to seek for renewing
                    of Strength: Are<lb/>not many under our name in a self secure state, Seeming to
                    need<lb/>nothing.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1796-08-16">16</date><placeName key="bucki"/></dateline>
                <p>The next Meeting I went to was at<lb/><orgName key="meetbucki"
                        >Buckingham</orgName>, which was very large, but laborious indeed;
                    Here<lb/>I was sunk very low in my mind, began to think I was worse off<lb/>than
                    in remote parts, or amongst the Indians: and near ready to say,<lb/>Are we the
                    worst of all People, who above al, have been so pecu-<lb/> liarly favored of the
                    Lord. Oh, Ease, lukewarmness and worldly Spirit, <lb/>what <lb/>
                    <pb n="181" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_61"/> What havok have ye made! It almost
                    seemed to day as though I<lb/>had done with preaching. Yet there is a little
                    hope that I am not forsaken. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-08-17">17th.</date>
                    <placeName key="bucki"/></dateline>
                <p>I next day attended a Sitting of select members at the same place, who<lb/>belong
                    to that <orgName key="meetbucki">Monthly Meeting</orgName>: which ended well; I
                    believe the Truth<lb/>reigned over all. Here I was helped to Labour in the
                    Lord's Cause, with<lb/>Weapons of his own preparing; The Arrows came so sharp
                        <del>against</del> a-<lb/>gainst wrong things, that at length there was a
                    yielding and confessing,<lb/>until hidden matters were laid open: Glory to his
                    great Name now &amp;<lb/>forever.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-08-18">18th.</date>
                    <placeName key="plums"/></dateline>
                <p>I went the next day from <placeName key="plums">Plumstead</placeName>, to a
                        <orgName key="checkPlace">Monthly<lb/> Meeting,</orgName> (not belonging to
                        <orgName key="buckqm">Bucks Quarter</orgName>) Here, observing the
                    State<lb/>of their Business and the management of it, there was really
                    cause<lb/>of lamentation: When life and Power is wanting, but little can be
                    done<lb/>to the Lord's honour, in the affairs which relate to discipline in his
                    church.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-08-19">19th</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>obscurely expressed.</p>
                <p>I also attended a <orgName key="checkPlace">general Meeting</orgName> held there.
                    At this time I thought<lb/>it was given me to see clearly, there was a danger in
                    being too free<lb/>in the use of A liberal flow of words in ministry; I fear
                    there is a<lb/>possibility <emph rend="underline">of</emph> that some, <emph
                        rend="underline">except</emph> unless they are better guarded, and speak
                    not<lb/> without the Spirit's pure influence, <emph rend="underline">that
                        they</emph> will be in danger of uttering Words<lb/>in publick resembling
                    common talk, or of gratifying itching<lb/><unclear>Ear</unclear>, instead of
                    raising the witness of life in the Souls of the luke-<lb/>warm &amp;
                    disobedient. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-08-20">20th</date>
                    <placeName key="wrigt"/></dateline>
                <p>Travelling towards <placeName key="wrigt">Wrightstown</placeName>, I was poor,
                    wading as in the<lb/>deeps: Thinking that as I now feel, I can scarcely ever
                    open my <lb/>
                    <pb n="182" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_62"/> my mouth in the Lord's cause any more.
                </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-08-21">21st</date><placeName key="wrigt"/></dateline>
                <p>Coming to <placeName key="wrigt">Wrightstown</placeName>, I attended their
                        <orgName key="meetwrigt">Meeting</orgName> on first<lb/>day. Preaching seems
                    to be looked for by many People, and<lb/>that of a smooth kind pleases best;
                    this makes hard labour for<lb/>those who singly seek to serve the great Master
                    uprightly: I<lb/>think I have not been more sensible of this, than since I
                    came<lb/>nearer home: Those are large Meetings: but I have been at<lb/> some
                    much smaller, comparable to the two or three, with Minds tru-<lb/>ly turned
                        <del>turned</del> to seek the fountain of life in themselves, which<lb/>
                    have been much more favored with the divine presence.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-08-22">22d.</date><placeName key="makef"/></dateline>
                <p>The next day, had a Meeting at <orgName key="meetmakef">Makefield</orgName>: A
                    very<lb/>comfortable season it was to myself, and to friends in general,<lb/>I
                    believe. My mind has not been favour'd with such a sweet<lb/>enjoyment of divine
                    Goodness since I came into this County: Blessed<lb/>be the Great Shepherd of
                    Israel: If the tender-hearted little<lb/>ones hold on their Way, I believe there
                    will be a growth in the<lb/> truth to some in this Meeting. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-08-23">23d</date><placeName key="middl"/></dateline>
                <p>At <orgName key="meetmiddl">Middletown</orgName> there was held a large Meeting
                    which ended<lb/> well; and tho' laborious, I believe the Truth was in
                    domi-<lb/>minion over all, to the tendering of many both Young and<lb/>Old. I
                    had a pleasing prospect of some being brought forward into<lb/>usefulness who,
                    if they keep their places may be made as Pillars<lb/>that shall go no more out.
                    ---- This </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="183" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_63"/>
                <dateline><date when="1796-08-24">24th</date><placeName key="falls"/></dateline>
                <p>This was the select Meeting held at the <orgName key="fallmm">Falls</orgName> for
                        <orgName key="buckqm">Bucks Quar-<lb/> ter</orgName>, at which I attended.
                    It appeared to be a lively time: and I<lb/>thought that many things were well
                    handled: It was agreed as<lb/>the general Sense of friends to form the answers
                    in the Meeting which are to be<lb/>sent forward to our Queries; Pausing
                    weightily on each query,<lb/>after reading it, and then endeavouring to
                    represent the real<lb/>State; not seeking to hide or screen ourselves by evasive
                    Answers.<lb/>The impropriety was opened of friends making too great
                    provision<lb/>at Qu. Meetings &amp;c, by preparing many Sorts of dishes,
                    often<lb/>changing Plates, causing needless Work: The necessity was also
                    hin-<lb/>ted of the foremost rank beginning to prepare, &amp; lead the way
                    towards true<lb/>moderation and temperance, their example being likely to have a
                    power-<lb/>ful influence.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-08-25">25th</date>. <placeName key="falls"/></dateline>
                <p>On the day following was held their <orgName key="buckqm">Qu.ly Meet-<lb/>ing for
                        Business;</orgName> wherein at this time the Stream of Truth's
                    discipline<lb/>was low, as I believed: and I was ready to say, Alas, Alas; and
                    so<lb/>to almost give out trying to labor for the benefit of the Cause I<lb/>I
                    had been engaged in. -- But going to see some poor little Ones<lb/>in the
                    afternoon, I was a little comforted, and strength renewed; for<lb/>I believe we
                    were own'd by the Master in some of our conferences,<lb/> on weighty subjects.
                </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-08-26">26th</date><placeName key="falls"/></dateline>
                <p>I likewise attended their Youth's Meeting at the <orgName key="fallmm"
                        >Falls</orgName>: poor<lb/>and low to some of us; yet no lack of preaching.
                    I did believe<lb/>a weighty Silence might have done more good at that time,
                    perhaps. <lb/>And </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="184" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_64"/>
                <dateline><date when="1796-08-26">26th</date><placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>And yet I leave these things to the Judge of all the Earth.<lb/>That evening I
                    crossed <geogName key="delaw">Delaware</geogName> to my son in law's; and the
                    next day came<lb/> home, finding my family in health; which with many other
                    fa-<lb/>vours I have witnessed in my absence from them, I feel there is
                    great<lb/>Cause of humble thankfulness to the God and Father of all
                    our<lb/>mercies. --- Though, with respect to my outward home, I<lb/>feel myself
                    but as a Sojourner or Pilgrim, Because of a<lb/>Prospect having been weightily
                    opened to me, relating to a religi-<lb/>ous visit toward the Southern Parts of
                    this Continent before Long, <del><gap/></del><lb/><del><gap/></del> if my health
                    admits, and the way should be prepared<lb/> with Clearness.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-08-28">28th</date><placeName key="haddo"/></dateline>
                <p> At <orgName key="meethaddo">our meeting</orgName> on first day, tho' I with my
                    friends rejoice<lb/>to see each other, (I believe never more so,) as I have been
                    ab-<lb/>sent three months and more; yet we sat in silence, a degree
                    of<lb/>mutual sympathy being felt. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-08-31">31st</date><placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>I have visited several friends; have had serious thoughts<lb/>concerning
                    reformation; and have believed those who go fore-<lb/>most in the work to real
                    Profit, must pass thro' great exercises<lb/> for self must become of no
                    reputation, before we can bear the<lb/>cross, &amp; despise the shame for Jesus
                    Christ's sake; And as it was<lb/>with our worthy fore-fathers, Great trading,
                    and many worldly<lb/>concerns, then "will be a great Burden": Fine houses and
                    rich furni-<lb/>ture an Eyesore," with Sumptuous liveing, rich Tables, many
                    dishes,<lb/>great attendance, and a lordly way of getting thro' the World
                    &amp;c, &amp;c.</p>
                <pb n="185" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_65"/>
                <p>In much sympathy with my fellow-members, my Spirit<lb/>hath for some years been
                    deeply exercised on account of the state<lb/>of things in our society: And I
                    have sometimes feared that wrong<lb/>things of late have grown fast among
                    friends in a time of Peace<lb/>plenty and Ease. Surely if we let hurtful weeds
                    grown, they check<lb/>the growth of good seed; So will wrong things, if we
                    entertain them, check<lb/>our Progress in the narrow Way that leads to life: In
                    that way, though<lb/>strait &amp; narrow, there is liberty enough: And when we
                    through a patient<lb/>coming to wear the Cross of Christ, come to experience the
                    Liberty of the<lb/>blessed Truth, we may be then freed from that worst of all
                    Burdens, the<lb/>world, and the idolatrous love thereof. ---- Oh that, if by
                    here<lb/> leaving a few sentences of my earnest desire, as a call to the
                    beloved<lb/> Youth of our day, I could prevail with many of them to come
                    taste<lb/>and see how good the Lord is, to those who fully surrender
                    their<lb/>hearts to his service; Then would your experience of his
                    matchless<lb/>Love be sweet, and this language would often breathe forth, "Thy
                    Ways<lb/>are ways of pleasantness, O Lord, and all thy Paths are Peace:"
                    At<lb/>thy right hand are rivers of Pleasure, forevermore: For although<lb/>the
                    Lord may see meet to hand unto you some of the Wormwood and<lb/>the Gall to
                    partake of, Yet he will so sweeten the Cup to his little<lb/>Ones who are his
                    sincere followers, that you will scarcely per-<lb/>ceive the Bitters: My soul in
                    deep reverence can say, his Sweet<lb/>Peace for obedience for submitting to his
                    requiring, has been sweeter than the <lb/>Honey <lb/>
                    <pb n="186" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_66"/> Honey-comb. --- Oh that it was the happy
                    experience of all<lb/>people, to submit to the refining Operations of the Grace
                    which is<lb/>inwardly revealed; Then might they come to know the
                    in-dwelling<lb/>of the peaceable Spirit of holy Jesus: This would put an<lb/>end
                    to the quarrelling, &amp; Jarrs, to hard thoughts and hard Speeches,
                    and<lb/>introduce in us the coming of his Kingdom: Men would thus be
                    taught<lb/>and enabled to love enemies, &amp; to bear reviling for Christ's
                    sake:<lb/>without reviling again: They would find no better way to gain
                    <lb/>Victory, than by overcoming evil with good. However hard this
                    doc-<lb/>trine may seem to be to the natural <emph rend="underline">will</emph>
                    of Man, many living<lb/>Witnesses certainly know, that a state of this kind is
                    attainable:<lb/>Therefore let no man's or Woman's heart fail them: All have
                    the<lb/>offer of divine Grace and Assistance to overcome the evil part,
                    &amp;<lb/>none are excluded who are willing to close in, &amp; obey the
                    teachings<lb/>thereof; working while their day of Visitation lasteth; and often
                    bearing<lb/>in mind, that "The night cometh, wherein no man can work." --<lb/>O
                    that this might in some degree serve as a loud, loving<lb/>call, to my
                    fellow-pilgrims, and sojourners throughout the Land. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-09-03">9 mo. 3d.</date>
                    <placeName key="mount1"/></dateline>
                <p>I Attended the monthly meetings at <orgName key="mthomeet">Mount-holly</orgName>
                    and <orgName key="meetevesh">Evesham</orgName><lb/>in this Month: I thought it
                    seemed to be low Times, especially at the<lb/>first of them. At the select
                    Meeting for <orgName key="meetevesh">Evesham</orgName> on the <date
                        when="1796-09-10">10th</date> I had<lb/>close labour in true Love,
                    respecting the things which have <lb/>appear'd <lb/>
                    <pb n="187" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_67"/> appear'd to me superfluous, and
                    inconsistant with <del>respect to</del> our<lb/>ancient testimony, relative to
                    eating, drinking, wearing, using, &amp;c,<lb/>similar to what I have free to
                    hint of elswhere in the minutes<lb/> I have made; and my present concern was
                    well received as I believe.</p>
                <p> The same day I visited a couple newly married, who had both of them<lb/>former
                    companions; The woman was poor, &amp; the Man deemed rich;<lb/>I was concerned
                    to speak closely on the snares and disadvantages<lb/>which have frequently
                    attended second marriages, and the Necessity<lb/>there is for such Persons
                    living steadily in the Lord's fear; and guard-<lb/>ing against tempers, &amp;
                    party views about worldly interest, where they<lb/>had children by former
                    marriage: The woman was tender-spirited and<lb/>shed many tears: and I warned
                    the man to beware of cramping her.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-09">12th</date><placeName key="haddo"/></dateline>
                <p>I returned my certificate at our <orgName key="meethaddo">Monthly
                        Meeting,</orgName> and gave my<lb/>Friends some account of my late journey
                    &amp; exercises. I also let<lb/>them know that as I returned homewards, a
                    Prospect had opened<lb/>afresh, which I had a glimpse of before, &amp; had told
                    my wife, Yet it<lb/>seemed taken away from me after that: which was, of paying a
                    reli-<lb/>gious visit to the Meetings of friends, &amp; such service otherwise
                    as way might open<lb/>for in the Southern parts, the <emph rend="underline"
                        >Carolina</emph>'s, &amp;c. Wherewith my Friends con-<lb/> curred, and
                    directed a certificate to be prepared, the meeting ad-<lb/>journing for the
                    purpose.</p>

            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="188" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_68"/>
                <dateline><date when="1796-09">1796. 9th mo,</date>
                    <date when="1796-10">10th</date>.<lb/><placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>About this time there was were many sickly, a number of whom<lb/>I visited. One
                    woman being in great distress of mind, expressed her-<lb/>self after this
                    manner, (expecting her stay on earth would not be long)<lb/><said
                        who="undetermined">I did not think I had been so great a sinner until
                        now.</said> May it<lb/>serve as a warning to many: I have heard piercing
                    lamentations<lb/>near their End, from others before I heard this womans
                    expressions: The<lb/>cry of some has been, <said who="undetermined">Alas! Alas!
                        What shall I do.</said> O the benefit of rightly<lb/>making use of precious
                    time. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-09-19">19th.</date>
                    <placeName key="haddo"/></dateline>
                <p>My certificate was sign'd by a large number of my friends, and at<lb/>our
                        <orgName key="haddoqm">quar.ly Meeting</orgName> it was indorsed with
                    approbation of friends there.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-09-23">23d</date><placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>After that I prepared for my journey: tho' at times I was under great<lb/>poverty
                    of spirit; had the company &amp; sympathy of several friends<lb/>who came to See
                    us; and in the midst of my exercised, I feel the Lord<lb/>near for my strength
                    and Support, Blessed be his name, who is the God of<lb/>Abraham, of Isaac and
                    Jacob. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-10-04">4th. of 10th mo.</date><lb/><placeName key="phila"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> Now I had to take an affectionate leave again of my dear wife<lb/>and all my
                    outward connections, in obedience to the Master's call, as<lb/>I believe, and
                    though poor in Spirit, was favourd with a sweet calm.<lb/>I crossed the
                        <geogName key="delaw">Delaware</geogName> to <placeName key="phila"
                        >Philadelphia</placeName>, proced'd <unclear>by</unclear>
                    <placeName key="wilmi">Wilmington</placeName>,<lb/>towards the <geogName
                        key="susqu">Susquehanna river</geogName>; When I crossed the ferry there
                    two<lb/>black men who were Slaves took me over: my mind enclined to pay<lb/>
                    them also, after paying ferriage to their Master. I reached to <placeName
                        key="balti1">Bal</placeName>- <lb/>
                    <pb n="189" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_69"/>
                    <placeName key="balti1">timore</placeName> on the <date when="1796-10-07"
                        >7th</date>. The <orgName key="bym">Yearly Meeting</orgName> of Ministers
                    and<lb/> Elders began next day: </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-10-08">8th</date>. <placeName key="balti1"/></dateline>
                <p>It was thro' the Course of it's Sittings<lb/>&amp; the Sittings for business in
                    the next Week a time of suffer-<lb/>ing to me; &amp; I believe I had brethren
                    and Sisters in like Situation,<lb/>not perceiveing the Truth to rise into hight
                    &amp; dominion. I had a<lb/>little Strength to discharge my trust in the way I
                    am led, in speak-<lb/>ing among the Select Members on the liberal use of Wine
                    and smo-<lb/>king Tobacco; this was in the first sitting, and I believe was
                    not<lb/>rejected by a remnent, after which I bore my burden mostly in
                    si-<lb/>lence through the Sittings. O Lord, be pleased to keep my head<lb/>above
                    the Waters, &amp; leave me not in the most trying Seasons, wch<lb/>thou mayest
                    permit to come, and then my soul shall bless and praise<lb/>thy adorable Name.
                </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-10-16">16th</date>
                    <placeName key="alexa"/></dateline>
                <p> Perceiving my mind drawn to endeavour if I can to attend<lb/>the <orgName>yearly
                        Meeting</orgName> in <placeName key="ncaro">North-Carolina</placeName>, I
                    left <placeName key="balti1">Baltimore</placeName> (having<lb/>(company
                    provided) and went thro' a storm to a poor little Meeting<lb/> at <orgName
                        key="meetelkri">Elk-ridge</orgName>. That afternoon &amp; next day reached
                    to <placeName key="alexa">Alexandria</placeName><lb/>in <placeName key="virgi"
                        >Virginia</placeName>, and had a <orgName key="meetalex">large
                        meeting</orgName> in the evening: where divine<lb/>favour was witnessed;
                    &amp; I believe the Truth was over all. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-10-23">23d</date><placeName key="roano"/></dateline>
                <p>Passing forward to <orgName key="meetroano">Roen Oak</orgName>
                    <del>I had a Meeting there, or</del> was at Meeting<lb/>there on first day, at
                    which were a large number of black People<lb/>who sat solidly: On discoursing
                    after meeting with several of<lb/>them, I found the manner they are treated as
                    to food, Clothing &amp; otherwise <lb/><pb n="190" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_70"/>
                    was mean, &amp; attended with considerable hardship and diffi-<lb/>culty. my
                    mind was touched with Sympathy and a tender feel-<lb/>ing for their
                    Condition.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1796-10-25">25th</date>.<placeName key="burle"/></dateline>
                <p>Reaching to <orgName key="meetburle">Burleigh</orgName> we were fa-<lb/> voured
                    with a solid comfortable Meeting there. Since I left <placeName key="balti1"
                        >Bal-<lb/>timore</placeName> until I came here, my friend <persName
                        key="ccook1">Charity Cook</persName> &amp; her Sister <persName key="scook1"
                        >Su-<lb/>sanna</persName> from <placeName key="scaro">South
                        Carolina</placeName> have been in Company with me, to good<lb/>Satisfaction,
                    we now parted: and with the friend who bore me Comp-<lb/>
                    <date when="1796-10-26">26th</date> any I had a Meeting at <orgName
                        key="meetblack">Black-Water</orgName>, which was in measure solid<lb/>and
                    pretty large.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-10-28"/>
                    <placeName key="seaco"/></dateline>
                <p>On the 28th. we also had a pretty comfortable<lb/>meeting at a Place called
                        <orgName key="meetseaco">Seacock</orgName>; And the day following one
                    at<lb/>the <orgName key="meetwbran">Western Branch</orgName>; this was a time of
                    very close searching per-<lb/>haps to some profit: I understood that two young
                    men here<lb/>who never had been at one of our Meetings before, were
                    consi-<lb/>derably reached &amp; Affected.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-10-30">30th</date>. <placeName key="ncaro"/></dateline>
                <p>We now came to <geogName key="little">Little River</geogName> in <placeName
                        key="ncaro">North-Carolina</placeName> and attend-<lb/>ed a <orgName
                        key="meetlittle">meeting</orgName> there: &amp; the next day began their
                        <orgName key="ncym">Yearly Meeting</orgName><lb/>of business at the same
                    place; The first sitting appear'd to me a low season<lb/>but in the next I
                    thought business was conducted rather better,<lb/>&amp; in the Sittings of this
                    yearly Meeting, <del>I thought</del> there was much<lb/> condescention among
                    friends. The testimony against the im-<lb/>proper use of Distilled Spirits &amp;
                    the making such Liquors hath<lb/>not risen high in this Meeting, altho' friends
                    had the subject before them.<lb/>I was with a Committee on the revival of their
                    discipline and <lb/><pb n="191" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_71"/> and had some
                    satisfaction, perceiving room to deliver my Sentiments<lb/>in a close way, on
                    several subjects. nevertheless it was rather a suffer-<lb/>ing Season thro the
                    Week. But there a considerable number of the tender, honest-hearted Friends.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-11-03">3rd</date><placeName key="pasqu"/></dateline>
                <p>I had a large <orgName key="meetnewbe">Meeting</orgName> at <geogName key="newbe"
                        >New-begun Creek</geogName> in <placeName key="pasqu">Pasquo-<lb/>tank
                        Coty</placeName>: many of the people could not get seats in the
                    house.<lb/>Many of the blacks or Slaves were at the meeting who sat<lb/>in a
                    solid manner; appearing more humble than many of<lb/>the whites: Yet I believe
                    it was a season of divine favour.<lb/>I understand the slaves in these <del>in
                        these</del> parts, though<lb/>they fare hard with those who hold them, are
                    commonly of<lb/>longer lives than the white People, who live sumptuously<lb/>on
                    the fruits of their Toil: The Slaves allowance for a<lb/>week is in many
                    instances confined to a peck of indian Corn<lb/>for one grown person, to cook it
                    as they can, without meat, fat<lb/>or other addition; My heart was often
                    tenderly affected at<lb/> -- their condition.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-11-05">5th</date>.<placeName key="pasqu"/></dateline>
                <p>Next I had a large <orgName key="meetnarro">Meeting</orgName> at
                        the<lb/><geogName key="narro">Narrows</geogName>
                    <geogName key="pasqr">Pasquotank</geogName>, mostly not Friends. The people sat
                    solid, and the meeting<lb/>ended to satisfaction.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-11-06">6th</date><geogName key="symon"/></dateline>
                <p>On first day I was at a very<lb/>large Meeting at <orgName key="meetsymon"
                        >Symonds-Creek</orgName>; one third part was sup-<lb/>posed to be of Blacks;
                    a number were here of people who had<lb/> not been at one of our Meetings
                    before. It was a solid Season,<lb/>ending well, and appeared to general
                    Satisfaction. After this Meet<lb/>ing we visited a Member of the Legislature:
                    &amp; treated on the<lb/> subject of slavery, and their unrighteous Law which
                    justifies <lb/>the <lb/><pb n="192" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_72"/> the taking up
                    and selling such for Slaves again, who are<lb/>set free, altho' by conscientious
                    Persons who are not free to hold<lb/>them in Slavery: It afforded me comfort
                    that he acknowledged<lb/>that Law to be unjust, hoped for its alteration, &amp;
                    proposed to use<lb/>what influence he had for it's repeal. <del>or
                        alteration.</del></p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-11-07">7th</date><geogName key="sutto"/></dateline>
                <p>Our next Meeting was at <orgName key="meetsutto">Sutton's-Creek</orgName>, large,
                    solid and<lb/>satisfactory: In these meetings I have been engaged in
                    close<lb/>Service, which seems well received. From place to place I par<lb/>take
                    of spiritual Poverty, Yet am not left with out a Hope<lb/>in the Lord, who
                    putteth forth and goeth before: Blessed be his<lb/>glorious Name forever</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1796-11-08">8th</date>. <placeName key="pasqu"/></dateline>
                <p>The next day two large Meetings,<lb/>in <placeName key="pasqu">Pasquotank
                        County</placeName>, one at <persName key="well1">Wells</persName>'s and
                    another at <orgName key="meetbeach">Beach<lb/>Spring</orgName>: so large that
                    the houses did not near hold the people.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>On the <date when="1796-11-09"/><placeName key="piney"/></dateline>
                <p>On the 9th. we were at <orgName key="meetpiney">Piney-woods Meeting</orgName>;
                    This also<lb/>was large, and to me exercising. -- At these Meetings
                    many<lb/>black people attended, who behaved solidly. -- I then had to
                    turn<lb/>back into <placeName key="virgi">Virginia</placeName> again, about 36
                    miles to <persName key="jcowp1">Jesse Cowpland</persName>'s.<lb/>On our way
                    thither, it was affecting at different Places, to<lb/>observe the situation of
                    the poor Slaves, Men, Women and<lb/>Children: a number of little ones quite
                    naked, many others who were<lb/>grown up nearly so, or their covering little
                    better then tat-<lb/>tered rags; It seems as though a continuance in Scenes of
                    <lb/>Cruelty <lb/>
                    <pb n="193" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_73"/> Cruelty hardens the hearts of
                    unrighteous Slave-holders;<lb/>But how they will answer for the Sins attending
                    this odious<lb/>Business, when brought to the bar of a righteous Judge, is a
                    Subject<lb/>that occasions awfulness to serious Christian minds.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-11-11">11th</date>. <placeName key="somer"/></dateline>
                <p>We were now at a pretty large Meeting at <orgName key="meetsomer"
                        >Somerton</orgName>, nearly<lb/>one third, were black people, &amp; they, as
                    well as others sat solid: this<lb/>was a satisfactory season, and many appeared
                    tendered; close doc-<lb/>trine was delivered on behalf of Truth's cause, &amp;
                    seemed to be well re-<lb/>ceived.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>The <date when="1796-11-12"/><placeName key="somer"/></dateline>
                <p>The 12th. attended a select Meeting of the Quarter<lb/>held at <orgName
                        key="meetwbran">Western-Branch</orgName>, in much poverty. I believed there
                    was<lb/> a want of more living zeal amongst it's Members.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-11-13">13th</date>. <placeName key="suffc"/></dateline>
                <p>Then had a large Meeting composed of people of different<lb/>Colours, which was
                    held in <placeName key="suffc">Suffolk Courthouse</placeName>, many more
                    came<lb/>than the house did hold. It was a solid &amp; favour'd Season;
                    satisfactory<lb/>in general I believed; But one family of friends dwelt here at
                    this time.<lb/>From hence we returned to the <persName key="ascot1">Widow Ann
                        Scotts</persName>', near the Western<lb/>Branch. Who being able &amp;
                    open-hearted, is about building a new<lb/>Meeting-house at her own expence. My
                    affectionate desire for her<lb/> is that she may be preserved, so as to retain a
                    blameless character in<lb/>the important Station she stands. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>The <date when="1796-11-14">14th</date>. <placeName key="suffc"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> was their Quar.ly Meeting for business here: dull and exer-<lb/>cising <lb/>
                    <pb n="194" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_74"/> cising: I had close labour with Men and
                    Women, perceiving barren-<lb/> ness among them: I hope it had some good effect
                    on some of the youth<lb/>&amp; others, but I leave it. That Evening had a
                    meeting for the<lb/>black people in a School-house near the <persName
                        key="ascot1">Widow Scotts</persName>': It was the first<lb/>of this kind
                    that was ever held in these parts, being large; One of the Jus-<lb/>tices
                    attended, &amp; some other Masters of Negroes. It was a solid favoured
                    time<lb/>and these spake well of the Meeting: some of them said they should be
                    very<lb/>free their Negroes should be at such meetings, and were glad they
                    had<lb/>been there themselves, uniting with what was spoken, and wishing
                    it<lb/>might be observed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-11-15">15th</date>.<geogName key="benne"/></dateline>
                <p>We next travelled from hence to <geogName key="benne">Bennets<lb/>
                        Creek</geogName>, near the sea shore; and the next day had a large and
                        favour'd<lb/><orgName key="meetbenne">Meeting</orgName> there; Also the same
                    afternoon another at the <persName key="wbufk1">Widow<lb/>Bufkins</persName>,
                    likewise large for the place, as well as solid and satisfactory.<lb/>Some of the
                    people seemed rejoiced, not having much opportunity to be<lb/>at friends
                    Meetings. We parted with them very lovingly.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-11-17">17th</date>.<placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>Our next Meeting was at the <orgName key="meetsbran">South Branch</orgName>, a
                    very exercising<lb/>Season: I thought the desire of some was, that smooth
                    things, or peace<lb/>might be spoken to them, believing they were too much in a
                    whole<lb/>State, &amp; that there was but little room for labour. --- But
                    how<lb/>can there be peace, where Pride and Oppression abound; The
                    slaves<lb/>having to bear the burden; many of them sorely oppressed,
                    with<lb/>want of proper Clothing, Food &amp;c, under Taskmasters, whose religion
                    seems<lb/>to be in talking; The Land Barren or nearly worn out, and
                    their<lb/>manner of Cultivation and Management but poor: So that the <lb/>
                    <pb n="195" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_75"/> Prospect of Things here looks gloomy
                    every Way. It is a trying<lb/> circumstance to me, to See the naked Bodies of
                    slaves and cold wea-<lb/>ther near, Whilst the Sons of their Oppressors, in an
                    idle life, ap-<lb/>pear so different; and their haughty daughters with stretched
                    forth<lb/>necks and wanton looks, their long-tailed gowns, trailing, as
                    tho'<lb/>some of them might spare something to put on the naked bodies
                    of<lb/>those who wait upon them. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-11-18">18th.</date><placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>We next had a small meeting near the great bridge at <persName key="rpool1"
                        >Robert<lb/>Pool's</persName> to Satisfaction: After which I had solid
                    Conversation with some<lb/>gay women respecting their manner of dress, at a
                    house where we<lb/>were kindly entertained; <unclear>my</unclear> Freedom with
                    them seemed to be well ta-<lb/> ken: They appeared somewhat religious, but I
                    thought they wanted depth.<lb/> they were not acquainted with friends, nor our
                    principles. One thing<lb/>I mention'd for them to consider was, Whether some of
                    the Stuff in their<lb/>Gown tails, &amp; the price of superfluous ribbonds,
                    might not well be<lb/>spared to put something on the naked bodies of little
                    blacks, &amp;c. It was a<lb/>solid season, and not resented, though I suppose
                    they never heard such sentiments<lb/> before; We parted very friendly;
                        <del>and</del> rode in the Evening about 15 Miles,<lb/>and had a solid time
                    with E.D. who said he was born at <placeName key="eggha">Egg-harbor</placeName>
                    in<lb/>Jersey.</p>

            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><pb n="196" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_76"/>
                    <date when="1796-11-22">22d</date><placeName key="camco"/></dateline>
                <p>We had a large and solid meeting at the <persName key="wbrit1">Widow
                        Britts</persName>', in <placeName key="camco">Cam-<lb/>den
                        County</placeName>, <placeName key="ncaro">N. Carolina</placeName>, a place
                    where never had been held one of our<lb/> Meetings, and but few of the people
                    who ever had attended at one.</p>
                <p> The next day also we had a large and favoured meeting in the same<lb/>County, at
                    the <persName key="wrich1">widow Richardson</persName>'s; These seemed a kind
                    people, much<lb/>unacquainted with our way, and many hearts were tendered: I
                    believe it was<lb/>a time not to be forgotten by some.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-11-24">24th</date><placeName key="piney"/></dateline>
                <p>At <orgName key="meetpiney">Piney-Woods</orgName>, we attended Friends
                    preparative meeting: Here I had close<lb/>Labour, things appearing in a low
                    state: I endeavored to stir them up to a<lb/>more lively Zeal for the cause and
                    Testimony of truth; which they ap-<lb/>peared to receive well. On the next day
                    was the Select Meeting at<lb/>the same place, for their Quarterly Meeting. My
                    concern was to stir<lb/> up to the pure part on the right education of Children
                    and Families,<lb/>that becoming plainness might be kept to, and they be good
                    examples<lb/>themselves, in their houses, furniture &amp;c. --- The day
                    follow-<lb/>ing was held their Qu.ly Meeting for business: Here, I believe the
                    State of<lb/>my friends in a religious sense was poor, but little life &amp;
                    power: I lab-<lb/>oured both amongst Men and women in my small ability, for
                    their help,<lb/>and I hope it ended to some profit at last: tho' a trying time.
                </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-11-27">27th</date><placeName key="pasqu"/></dateline>
                <p>I went from hence to <orgName key="meetlittle">Little-River</orgName>, being a
                    second time: and was at Meeting<lb/>there on first day, which I believe ended
                    well. And in the after-<lb/>noon had a Meeting in the Court-house of <placeName
                        key="pasqu">Pasquotank County</placeName>; at<lb/>which were many people, of
                    black and White; It was a season of <lb/>general <lb/>
                    <pb n="197" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_77"/> general satisfaction. Many in great
                    tenderness signified their U-<lb/> nity with me &amp; my service; and some
                    sincerely craved for my staying<lb/> that night in their town: but I was easiest
                    to leave them, as in the<lb/>hand of the Lord. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-11-28">28th</date><placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>Had a meeting at the <orgName key="meetoldn">Old-neck</orgName>, somewhat small,
                    yet favour'd and<lb/>still.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-11-30">30th</date><placeName key="piney"/></dateline>
                <p>Leaving <placeName key="piney">Piney-Woods</placeName>, we travelled to
                        <placeName key="richs">Rich-Square</placeName>, and<lb/>the next day, had a
                    large <orgName key="meetrichs">Meeting</orgName> there, which to me was very
                    exercising.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-12-01">12th mo. 1st.</date>
                    <placeName key="richs"/></dateline>
                <p>On the day following at the request of some of the <orgName key="bapt"
                        >Baptists</orgName>,<lb/>we had a Meeting in their Meeting-house; which was
                    satisfactory, &amp;<lb/>I believe ended well; being larger than I expected, in
                    wet weather, and the<lb/>notice given being but small.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-12-03">3rd</date><geogName key="jacks"/></dateline>

                <p>Next, we were at a Monthly Meeting<lb/>at <orgName key="meetjacks">Jack's
                        Swamp</orgName>; rgIt was but small: some solid friends dwell here:<lb/>who
                    seem rather in a weak State, and are in need of help: I laboured<lb/>among them
                    according to measure, &amp; they expressed unity with my Service.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-12-04">4th</date><placeName key="halif"/></dateline>
                <p>We tarried at their first day meeting which was large, and
                    mercifully<lb/>favoured: then went forward to <placeName key="halif"
                        >Hallifax</placeName>; The day following riding near<lb/>50 Miles towards a
                    town called <placeName key="ralei">Rawleigh</placeName>, the day after that we
                    came<lb/>to it, Where the <orgName key="ncgen">General Assembly</orgName> for
                        <placeName key="ncaro">North-Carolina</placeName> were sitting;<lb/> &amp;
                    we found some friends at the place, desiring to endeavor for an alte-<lb/>
                    ration the cruel Laws relative to the Negroes. Having felt my mind much<lb/>
                    concerned on the subject, I was willing to join my endeavours to theirs.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-12-07">7th</date>.<placeName key="ralei"/></dateline>
                <p>We attended the House of Common Council, had many private<lb/>Conferrences with
                    Members, who received us friendly, yet seemed mostly op-<lb/>posed to the
                    freedom of black People. </p>

                <pb n="198" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_78"/>
                <p>I was endow'd by my Great Master with an innocent boldness, in which<lb/>I could
                    use great freedom in solid conversation with the most leading men; for<lb/>they
                    mostly quartered where we did; which gave me a full opportunity to re-<lb/>lieve
                    my oppressed mind. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-12-08">8th</date>. <placeName key="ralei"/></dateline>
                <p>The prospect seems gloomy, whether any<lb/>thing can be done at this time for the
                    Relief of our distressed fellow Men,<lb/>yet I would not have my friends here be
                    discouraged: The Cause is Surely<lb/>good; And I have no doubt but way will be
                    made for this poor people's libe-<lb/>ration, but what way, or how Soon must be
                    left to the Lord. My mind was<lb/>turned to think of trying for a religious
                    public Meeting in the place<lb/>which some of those we conversed with, spake in
                    favour of, if the Way<lb/>should be opened, and the Business they were met on,
                    would admit of it: It was<lb/>also thought the house where they sat in would be
                    the most suitable place; But after wait-<lb/>ing a while to see how matters
                    would turn with respect to a publick<lb/>opportunity, it seemed scarce likely to
                    be obtain'd in the present Circumstances.<lb/>I was therefore the more free to
                    make use of private opportunities<lb/>with the Members of the Legislature and
                    others; which was to my own<lb/>satisfaction &amp; to theirs, as far as I saw:
                    There being here now a<lb/>large collection of those of the first rank,
                    Gentlemen, so called: most of<lb/>them being Men in some Office, Civil or
                    military. I thought the res-<lb/>pect they shewed me was marvellous: For my
                    simple Appearance, singular<lb/>as it was, some of them confessed it was
                    instructive to them; that their own Conduct<lb/>and way of living was luxurious,
                    &amp; they allow'd much might be spared; Saying that<lb/> I looked as well s
                    they did, altho' they had great variety of roasted, baked,<lb/>&amp; boiled
                    provisions &amp;c; whilst mine was about half a pint of milk and <lb/>as <lb/>
                    <pb n="199" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_79"/> as much water, morning, noon and night
                    without any flesh; Boarding at one house, we<lb/>generally sat at one Table.
                    Some at first looked at me with astonishment,<lb/>and tho' they had never seen
                    the like, said they believed, or did not know,<lb/>but it was the right way of
                    living, but it would be hard for them to sub-<lb/>mit to. -- As they had private
                    Rooms, a number of them invited<lb/>me (as it was at a tavern we were, &amp;
                    near 50 boarders all men of Note.) that if at<lb/>anytime I was weary of noise
                    &amp; craved to me more retired, I might freely<lb/>come into their rooms, &amp;
                    sit with them; &amp; that they should be pleased if I<lb/>would make so free.
                    All this seemed to be in my favour to furnish<lb/>me, when my mind was so
                    engaged, with opportunities to touch on their<lb/>cruel Laws, the hardships
                    &amp; inhuman cruelties to which the poor blacks<lb/>were Subjected in that
                    Government &amp;c. I queried of them Why Things should<lb/>be in such a severe
                    Way here, more than in any other Place that I had<lb/>heard of: For I had been
                    thro' each of the Governments Eastward, as well as <placeName key="maryl"
                        >Mary-<lb/> land</placeName> and <placeName key="virgi">Virginia</placeName>
                    lately, and had not heard of any Cruelty of the kind<lb/>sanction'd by any other
                    Legislative Body on the Continent: Some of them<lb/>spake of other States not
                    having so many Slaves in them, and less occasion for<lb/>fear of their rising
                    &amp;c; my answer to that was, Those who so cruelly oppress<lb/>the Slaves, have
                    more occasion to fear their rising, &amp;c: My treating with them<lb/>on the
                    subject was in a way of plain dealing, and so well received that<lb/>many of
                    them kindly invited me to come and see them, if I should come near<lb/>their
                    dwellings, for that it would give them pleasure (as they said) to entertain<lb/>
                    me: It was unexpected also to my Companion &amp; myself, when he came<lb/>to
                    Settle for our Tavern Expences whilst there, the Man would take<lb/>no pay for
                    my Boarding, he was so well pleased with the visit. </p>

            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="200" facs="SW_JE1796E_Page_80"/>
                <dateline><date when="1796-12-09">1796. 12th. mo. 9th</date><lb/><placeName
                        key="ralei"/></dateline>
                <p>This morning we proposed to leave <placeName key="ralei">Rawlegh</placeName>. My
                    companion had bought<lb/>him a new horse, who was rather wild, &amp; threw him
                    after he mounted,<lb/>at which I was concern'd fearing he was hurt; &amp; could
                    not proceed with me,<lb/>but through favour we found he was not so much hurt as
                    we had expected<lb/>and we travelled near forty Miles that day; &amp; the two
                    days following<lb/>so much as to make near 150 to <geogName key="cores">Core
                        sound</geogName>. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>The <date when="1796-12-13">13th</date>, <geogName key="cores"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>we met with the<lb/>Ministers &amp; Elders of that <orgName key="meetcores"
                        >Monthly Meeting</orgName>, to confer on the Subject of<lb/>visiting their
                    families, which was united with, and two friends agreed to<lb/>join me in the
                    service; which we proceeded in, and in less than four days<lb/>visited about 14
                    families, mostly to good satisfaction, besides attending<lb/>their Meeting at
                        <geogName key="cores">Coresound</geogName>, (which is near the
                    Sea-Coast).</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1796-12-17">17th</date>. <geogName key="cores"/></dateline>
                <p>We had af<lb/>ter that a comfortable &amp; satisfactory <orgName key="meetcores"
                        >Meeting</orgName> there, amongst our friends<lb/>by themselves; in which we
                    were favoured with a measure of the<lb/> Divine Presence owning us together.
                    Here is a hopeful number of<lb/>youth of both Sexes; and their appearance more
                    in the Simplicity<lb/>as to their Dress &amp; otherwise: their apparel (I mean
                    the Womens) was<lb/>mostly Homespun, no black silk Cloaks nor Bonnets among
                    them, I was<lb/>comforted in their Company &amp; parted with them in near love
                    and fel-<lb/>lowship; after which visited two other Families, &amp; went on to
                    my friend<lb/><persName key="hhowa1">Horton Howards</persName>, whose Wife lay
                    ill with the Consumption; I perceived her<lb/>to be innocent, laying in a quiet
                    frame of mind, as nearly fit to leave<lb/>the World.</p>
            </div>


        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
