<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei-print.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" hkey="global.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>Joshua Sharpless' Journal [Visit to Upper Canada and Parts Adjacent], 1797:
                    Electronic Version</title>
                <author>Joshua Sharpless</author>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by </resp>
                    <name>Emma Remsberg</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcribed by</resp>
                    <name>David Fialkow</name>
                    <name>Epiphany English</name>
                    <name>Keat Murray</name>
                    <name>Sarah Scheub</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Tri-Co Digital Humanities Initiative</sponsor>
                <funder>Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 162 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>This work is the property of the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore
                        College. It may be copied freely by individuals for personal use, research,
                        and teaching (including distribution to classes) as long as this statement
                        of availability is included in the text. It may be linked to freely in
                        Internet editions of all kinds, including for—profit works.</p>
                    <p>Publishers, libraries, and other information providers interested in
                        providing this text in a commercial or non—profit product or from an
                        information server must contact Swarthmore College for licensing and cost
                        information.</p>
                    <p> Scholars interested in changing or adding to these texts by, for example,
                        creating a new edition of the text (electronically or in print) with
                        substantive editorial changes, may do so with the permission of Swarthmore
                        College. This is the case whether the new publication will be made available
                        at a cost or free of charge.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2014">2014</date>
                <idno type="local">SW_JS1797</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Native Americans and Quakers: Electronic
                    Collection</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>Sharpless Manuscripts</collection>
                        <idno>Mss040 Journal 7</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>87 pages (1 volume)</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>


        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The manuscript of Joshua Sharpless’ “Journal [Visit to Upper Canada and Parts
                    Adjacent]” (1797) is housed at Friends Historical Library, on the campus of
                    Swarthmore College. In the spring semester of 2012, Swarthmore students enrolled
                    in English 57A (“Early American Literature Through A Traveler’s Eyes”)
                    transcribed Sharpless’s manuscript as part of a larger project to make the
                    library’s rich store of Quaker journal writings more accessible to researchers.
                    The project was designed by Christopher Densmore, curator of Friends Historical
                    Library, and Keat Murray, Visiting Associate Professor of English. Transcribers
                    included: David Fialkow (1-14), Epiphany English (15-42), Keat Murray (43-51),
                    and Sarah Scheub (52-87). Students’ transcriptions were compiled and edited in
                    the present form by Professor Murray.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Because the manuscript does not include page numbers, the transcribers have
                    interpolated page numbers. The transcribers and editor attempted to render
                    Sharpless’s orthography and grammar as they appear on the page of his journal,
                    even when Sharpless’s own spelling and usage are inconsistent. </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written in <date when="1797">1797</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                        <item>Quakers</item>
                        <item>Indian reservations</item>
                        <item>Indians of North America--Missions</item>
                        <item>New York (State)--Description and travel</item>
                        <item>Pennsylvania--Description and travel</item>

                        <item>Philadelphia Yearly Meeting of the Religious Society of Friends</item>
                        <item>Quakers--Pennsylvania--Diaries</item>
                        <item>Quakers--Political activity</item>
                        <item>Seneca Indians</item>
                        <item>Society of Friends--Missions</item>
                        <item>Voyages and Travels</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>

        <body>

            <div type="entry">

                <pb n="1" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_01"/>
                <dateline><date when="1797-10-12"/><placeName key="ebrad"/></dateline>
                <p>On the <date when="1797-10-12">12th day of the 10th Mo 1797</date> after <lb/>an
                    humbling time with my dear Wife<lb/> and Children, I left home in order to<lb/>
                    Join a Committee of our last Yearly<lb/> Meeting appointed <del>the</del> to
                    Visit some friend<lb/> in <placeName key="upcan">upper Canada</placeName> and
                    parts adjacent,<lb/> my Dear Wife bearing me company<lb/> as far as my soninlaw
                        <persName key="bcoop1">Benjamin<lb/> Cooke</persName>’s, I went that Evening
                    to <unclear>Na</unclear><lb/> then <persName>Sharples’s</persName> where by
                    agreement<lb/> I met with <persName key="jlind1">Jacob Lindley</persName> and
                        <persName key="jwils1">James<lb/> Wilson</persName> two of the
                    aforementioned Com-<lb/>-mittee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-10-23">13th</date>
                    <placeName key="maide"/>
                </dateline>
                <p> a pleasent Morning the Wind South-<lb/>-erly, dined at <persName key="jscar1"
                        >John Scarlet</persName>s in the<lb/> forest 20 miles, pased over a
                    rough<lb/> hilly country up the waters of the <geogName key="brand"
                        >Brandy-<lb/>-wine</geogName>, much of the Land thin tho che-<lb/>-quered
                    with some good plantations<lb/> pretty well improved, pased through<lb/>the East
                    end of <placeName key="lconn">Little Connestoga Valley</placeName>
                    <lb/>a fruitful spot, the hills about the forest <lb/>very steep, and in places
                    covered with <lb/>stones, from <persName key="jscar1">scarlet’s</persName> to
                        <geogName key="schri">Schuylkill</geogName> 5 mil<unclear>es</unclear>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="2" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_02"/> continued very rough, thence up the
                        <lb/><geogName key="schri">Schuylkill</geogName> to <placeName key="readi"
                        >Reading</placeName> 4 miles, the town is situ<lb/>-ated on a low piece of
                    Ground near <lb/>the sd river, surrounded with high hills <lb/>the place is by
                    no means elegant. nei-<lb/>-ther did the town look thriving or <lb/>lively, from
                    thence to <persName key="pwile1">Pennose Wiley</persName>’s <lb/><del>goes,
                        over</del> near <placeName key="maide">Maiden Creek</placeName> where we
                    <lb/>lodged, over a pretty fruitful Coun-<lb/>-try and beautiful road 9
                    miles.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-10-14">14 and 1st of the week</date>
                    <placeName key="maidi"/></dateline>
                <p> a Northwest Wind and plesant day, <lb/>attended <orgName>Maiden creek
                        Meeting</orgName>, <del>who</del>
                    <lb/>which upon the whole was a refresh-<lb/>-ing time, Dined at <persName
                        key="jstar1">John <unclear>Starrs</unclear></persName> near <lb/>the
                    Meetinghouse, having me last <lb/>Evening with <persName key="opaxt1">Oliver
                        Paseton</persName>, and <lb/>this Morning with <persName key="jlang1">James
                        Lang<lb/>staff</persName> two friends of our Number <lb/>making up now five
                    in all, after <lb/>a comfortable Opportunity at <persName key="jstar1">John
                        <lb/>Starrs</persName>, we off towards <placeName key="muncy">Munsy
                    </placeName><lb/> in about three Miles, upon a con-<lb/>-siderable eminence, we
                    had a <lb/>bold and noble view of the <geogName key="bluem">Blue
                        <lb/>Mountain</geogName> at about 8 miles distance.<lb/>
                    <pb n="3" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_03"/> with an elegant Valley between, the
                    <lb/>View was truly beautiful and pic-<lb/>-terisque as far as the Eye could
                    <lb/>reach, both to the East and West, and <lb/>the <geogName key="bluem"
                        >Mountain</geogName> in front raising its <lb/>lofty head in a Majestick and
                    de-<lb/>-lightful Manner, thence 5 miles to <placeName key="hambu"
                        >ham-<lb/>-burgh</placeName> now <unclear>Carters</unclear> a smart town,
                    thence among <lb/>the <geogName key="bluem">Mountain</geogName> up the Side of
                    the <lb/><geogName key="schri">Schuylkill</geogName> where the prospect was
                    <lb/>will and romantick and in 5 or 6 <lb/>miles opened to a fine plantation
                    <lb/>on one branch of the <geogName key="schri">Schuylkill</geogName>
                    <lb/>where we took up our quarters in <lb/>a good habitation in the possession
                    of <lb/><persName key="mmasy1">Michal Mosyer</persName> the road for the most
                    <lb/>part pretty good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-10-16">16</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> Started by brake of day, a clear<lb/> white-frosty-morning, 7 miles <lb/>of good
                    road, come to the second <lb/><geogName key="bluem">Blue Mountain</geogName>,
                    passed through <lb/>a gap where a small branch of <lb/>the <geogName key="schri"
                        >Schuylkill</geogName> has it course, the gap <lb/>in places was narrow, and
                        <del>the</del>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="4" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_04"/> on each side very steep and <lb/>high,
                    covered with a thick crust <lb/>of Stones, thence in some 2 or 3 miles
                    <lb/>crossed the <geogName key="tusca">Tuscarora Mountain</geogName>, <lb/>on
                    the North Side of which there is <lb/>an amazing prospect, a very <lb/>great
                    Valley in front extending <lb/>from east to West as far as the Eye <lb/>could
                    reach, about 2 or three miles <lb/>off over said Valley there was a <lb/>lofty
                    towring Mountain, or one <lb/>Mountain upon the top of a-<lb/>-nother whose
                    proud <del>crest</del> tops reach-<lb/>-ed the Sky, the appearance was
                    <lb/>truly Magestick and Bold, and <lb/>so diversifyed with many
                    enliv-<lb/>-ening coulours that the pros-<lb/>-pect was picturesque and
                    beau-<lb/>-tiful, we then passed the <gap/><lb/> Mountain which was very high,
                    <lb/>next the <geogName key="broam">Broad Montain</geogName> which<lb/> was
                    inferior to none, then<lb/>
                    <pb n="5" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_05"/> we came to the <geogName key="mahan"
                        >Mahony Moun-<lb/>-tain</geogName>, the prospect from the <lb/>Northside of
                    which was much<lb/> like that of <geogName key="tusca">Tuskorora</geogName>, tho
                    the abiss<lb/> or Valley was deeper and more di<lb/>rectly down beneath our
                    feet, per<lb/>haps 400 feet, the next <del>Mountain</del>
                    <lb/>was called the <geogName key="lmoun">little Mountain</geogName>
                    <lb/>tho thought to be higher then any <lb/>of the rest, the Assent and decent
                    <lb/>from those mountains are not very steep <lb/>tho couvered with large and
                    <lb/>small stone, the road from <lb/>thence to <placeName key="catta"
                        >Catewissee</placeName>is most of <lb/>it very rough, lodged at <persName
                        key="jlloy1">John Loyd</persName>s <lb/>40 miles, the Land from <placeName
                        key="hambu">Hamburgh</placeName>
                    <lb/>to this place is chiefly Mountanious, <lb/>Poor, and Stony, and very little
                    set-<lb/>-tled, there are a number of Settle<del>me</del><lb/>-ments
                        <del>about</del> in <placeName key="roari"><unclear>Roring</unclear> Creek
                        Valley</placeName>
                    <lb/>yet the face of Ground, appears thin <lb/>Stony, and not desirable.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="6" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_06"/>
                <dateline><date when="1797-10-17">17</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>

                <p>Crossed <geogName key="susqu">Susquehanna</geogName> at <placeName
                        key="checkPlace">Catewissee</placeName> in the <lb/>boat, the <geogName
                        key="susqu">River</geogName> 80 <unclear>pearches</unclear> wide, <lb/>the
                    Land from the River to <geogName key="fishi">fishing <lb/>Creek</geogName> is
                    more desirable than on the <lb/><placeName key="checkPlace"
                        >Catewisee</placeName> side, it is pretty clear of <lb/>Stones, and mostly
                    such as will do <lb/>to settle on, and in some places, <lb/>particularly toward
                        <geogName key="fishi">Fishing Creek</geogName>
                    <lb/>is considerably improved, Dined <lb/>at <persName key="jhain1">Jessee
                        Hains</persName>’s 15 miles, the tim-<lb/>-ber for 7 or 8 miles after we
                    crossed <lb/>the <geogName key="susqu">River</geogName>, is mostly Pine, thinly
                    scat-<lb/>-tered with very little undertimber, <lb/>about Fishing Creek very
                    heavy <lb/>timber, from <persName key="jhain1">Jessee Haines</persName>’s on
                    <lb/>towards <placeName key="muncy">Munsy</placeName> generally White <lb/>Oak,
                    for 6 or 7 miles the Land leavel<lb/> and pretty good with a number <lb/>of good
                    improvement, from thence <lb/>to <del>the</del>
                    <geogName key="muncr">Muncy <del>Creak</del> Creek</geogName> Mountainous,
                    and<lb/> poor, the <placeName key="munva">Muncy Valley</placeName> is pretty
                    good <lb/>Land, Lodged at <persName key="welli1">William Ellises</persName><lb/>
                    <pb n="7" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_07"/> three Miles over <geogName key="muncr"
                        >Muncy Creek</geogName>, 33 <lb/>Miles this day, this days travel pretty
                    <lb/>good Roads and clear of Stones </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1797-10-18">18</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> a fine morning, and pleasant day <lb/>for traveling, stoped, and took an
                    ear-<lb/>-ly Dinner at the <persName key="wharr1">Widdow Harreses</persName>* at <lb/>
                    <emph rend="asterisk">*On Roasted and Baked Venison, persons having
                            <unclear>killed</unclear> 3 the day before and 20 this fall</emph>
                    <lb/><placeName key="loyal">Loyalsock</placeName> 9 miles, thence up the Banks
                    <lb/>of <geogName key="susqu">Susquehanna</geogName> to <geogName key="lycom"
                        >Lycomun</geogName> 6 miles, <lb/>then we turned a North Coarse
                        <del>of</del> up the sd. <lb/><geogName key="lycom">Lycomun</geogName> 10
                    miles to <unclear>Skylers</unclear>, among the <lb/>Mountains, where we Lodged,
                    the Road<lb/> from <persName key="welli1">William Ellis</persName>’s to
                        <geogName key="lycom">Lycomun</geogName>, is <unclear>thr</unclear><lb/>
                    Level, clear of Stones, and very good, the <lb/>timber a Mixture of White Oak,
                    Pitchpine, <lb/>&amp;c, and the Land in general <del>very</del> good. <lb/>Up
                    the <geogName key="lycom">Lycomun</geogName> the road to this place <lb/>crossed
                    the Creek 7 times, the bottom we <lb/>went up Deep and furtile, with
                        <del>some</del> a <lb/>few Cabbins &amp; a little improved in places
                    <lb/>the valley was narrow with high moun-<lb/>-tains on each side, this bottom
                    was <lb/>very heavy timbred abundance of <lb/>lofty White pine, butternut,
                    button <lb/>Wood, Sugar Maple &amp;c. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-10-19">19</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <pb n="8" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_08"/>
                <p>Set of[f] Just at breck of day, a fine morn-<lb/>-ing, <unclear>fed</unclear> at
                    the foot of the <geogName key="laure">Laural hill</geogName>
                    <lb/><del>on the uppermost branch of <geogName key="lycom"
                        >Lycomun</geogName></del>
                    <lb/>9 miles the Road deep and Miry up <lb/>a Branch of the <geogName
                        key="lycom">Lycomun</geogName>, which we <lb/>crossed upwards of 20 times, I
                    have <lb/>had this morning to admire the produc-<lb/>-tions of nature the
                    remarkable Lofty towring <lb/>pines, the Hemlock, spruce, Sugar <lb/>Maple, and
                    a Variaty of other Lofty <lb/>timber, no man to recieve and carry<lb/> them
                        <del>it</del> of so that they fall into their Mother <lb/>lap, the earth,
                    and the multitudes of trunks of <lb/>Trees that lye across one another is
                    <lb/>truly admiral, many of the White <lb/>pine trunks appears to have lain
                    <lb/>in that Situation for more than half <lb/>a Century, grown over with moss,
                    the <lb/>Seeds of the trees falling <del>of</del> on the Moss<lb/> have taken
                    Root, grew to be trees 5 or 6 <lb/>Inches over, while the Log under them<lb/>
                    remained, the Valley through which we <lb/>passed is narrow with very high
                    moun-<lb/>-tains on each they all appear <del><unclear>very rich</unclear></del>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="9" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_09"/>
                    <del>and</del> Cloathed with an Admirable load <lb/>of Timber, so that a person
                    who <del>have</del> has not <lb/>been acquainted with such an Appearance<lb/>
                    would scarcely be able to form a Just Idea. <lb/>We <del>now</del> then mounted,
                    the <geogName key="laure"> Laural Hill</geogName>, which proved <lb/>Very high.
                    we first passed through a Ches[t]-<lb/>- nut Ridge about 2m then entred a
                    <lb/>Vast Forrest of Hemloch, Spruce &amp;c<lb/> so thick that tho a clear day
                    yet it ap-<lb/>-peared like the Dusk of the Even-<lb/>-ing, we
                        <del>presently</del> in a few miles <lb/><del>came unto</del> passed through
                    a very great Quantity <lb/>of Sugar Maple, many of them from <lb/>2 to 3 or 3½
                    feet over 40, 50, and 60 <lb/>feet fit for Sawing, also a vast Quanty <lb/>of
                    beach and Berch, fed at the <lb/><placeName key="block">Blockhouse</placeName> 9
                    miles on a Branch <lb/>of <geogName key="pinec">Pine Creek</geogName>, from
                    thence to <lb/>a Branch of <geogName key="tioga">Tyoag River</geogName> where
                    <lb/>we [?] 10 miles thence to Lambs <lb/>on the side of sd. <geogName
                        key="tioga">River</geogName> 15 miles <lb/>
                    <pb n="10" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_10"/> the timber continuing Very <del>so</del>
                    <lb/>heavy all the way, great over<gap/><lb/>grow Hemlacks, many of which
                        <del>whom</del> would <lb/>make 5 or 6000 feet of Boards <lb/>and great
                    Burdens of White <lb/>pine in place many <del>of Whose</del> where <lb/>100 feet
                    high with out Limbs, the <lb/>curiosity through this days tra-<lb/>-vel in
                    beholding the timber, and <lb/>face of the ground was such, that <lb/>I could
                    scarcely keep mine Eyes <lb/>from runing too and frow in <lb/>beholding the
                    Wonders of nature, <lb/>many places the Trunks of Trees <lb/>were laying across
                    one another 3 or four feet high so that it ap-<lb/>-peared impossible to ride
                    through <lb/>the Woods, this day has been fatague<lb/>-ing both to Man and
                    Beast, the Roads <lb/>were <del>chief</del> mostly very miry
                        <del>particular</del><lb/>
                    <pb n="11" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_11"/>
                    <del>ly</del> in places very stony, <gap/> full of Roots <lb/>particularly the
                    first 27 miles, night <lb/>overtook us before we got into <gap/>
                    <lb/>and the Road being covered with thick <lb/>Pines it was very dark, so that
                    we <lb/>were truly thankful when <del>we saw</del>
                    <lb/>the glimmers of Light at our dis-<lb/>-tined part made their appearance,
                    tho we found it a very <lb/>Poor Tavern, having <del>little</del> nothing but
                    Mush <lb/>and Milk the Mush made of meal <del>for</del>
                    <lb/>Pounded in a Mortar, and the fare of <lb/>our Horses not much better yet we
                    were<lb/> thankful we fared so well in the Wilderness <lb/>having this day in
                    the Course of 43 miles <lb/>passed by but three cottages and them mean,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-10-20">6th day 20</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p> met with a trial this morning <lb/>two of our horses having broke out of our
                    <lb/>poor Stable, but in three Miles rid-<lb/>-ing they were taken and brought
                    <lb/>back, a Cold frosty morning and <lb/>like for snow, but grew warmer
                    <lb/>and rained a little in the evening <lb/>this has been a pleasant days
                    travel<lb/> the road led down by the side of <lb/>
                    <pb n="12" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_12"/> of the <geogName key="tioga">Tyago
                        River</geogName> through a very <lb/>furtile Vally with a few Cabbins and
                    <lb/>some little improvements for the first <lb/>twelve Miles, the <geogName
                        key="tioga">River</geogName>, we <del>Crossed</del>
                    <lb/>frequently crossed as the Road suit-<lb/>-ed, <del>the</del> it
                        gl<del>a</del>ides along in a Most <del>be</del>
                    <lb/>beautiful manner, not impeaded <lb/>by Rocks, or Cataracks, we finally
                    <lb/>crossed it about <del>one</del> two miles above the <lb/><persName
                        key="mlind1">Widow Lindsly’s</persName>, and in less than <lb/>one Mile we
                    crossed <del>nearly</del> another <lb/>Branch as beautiful and nearly as
                    <lb/>large called the <gap/> as the former and got our Breakfast we then stoped
                    <lb/>&amp; fed our <del>selves and</del> horses at the Wi-<lb/>-dows,
                        <del>and</del> were much pleased with <lb/>our repast, having had
                    nothing<lb/> since we Left the <persName key="wharr1">Widow Harresses</persName>
                    <lb/>besides what our bags afforded except <lb/>two indiffirent suppers, here we
                    <lb/>got Excellent green Tea, and Loaf <lb/>Sugar, with Some choice Venision
                    <lb/>Stakes, taken out of a famous fat <lb/>Buck which had been just killed
                        <del>not yet could</del>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="13" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_13"/>
                    <del>since killed</del> to this stage 12 miles. <lb/>We still went down sd
                        <geogName key="tioga">River</geogName>, over <lb/>very fine fat bottoms, in
                    about 8 <lb/>miles crossed <geogName key="canis">Cannost<del>o</del>
                        <gap/></geogName> a very beau<lb/>tiful <del>strem</del> stream, then in 4
                    miles <lb/>more we crossed <geogName key="cohoc">Conhocton</geogName> as
                    beau<lb/>tifull a stream as <del>another</del> any of <lb/>the former, the
                    smallest of those stream†<unclear>s</unclear><lb/> are <del>nearly as</del>
                    large>r <del>as</del> than <geogName key="brand">Brandywine</geogName><lb/>
                    Stoped to feed at the <placeName key="ppost">painted Post</placeName> 12 miles
                        <lb/><del>but</del> but had nothing Suitable, thence <lb/>to <geogName
                        key="mudcr">Mud Creek</geogName> to <persName key="jdols1">John
                        Dolso’s</persName> where <lb/>we Lodged 12 miles the Road has been
                    <lb/>in the main pretty good, to the <placeName key="ppost">paint<lb/>-ed
                        post</placeName> very good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-10-21">21</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> Stoped and took breakfast at <lb/><persName key="wkers1">William
                        Kerseys</persName> 5 miles, he had nei<lb/>ther Hay, Corn, or Oates for our
                    horses Lives in <lb/>a small Log house in the Woods by <lb/>a Curious Lake, of
                    about 50 acres it <lb/>is surrounded by a hard gravelly bank, <lb/>has no Stream
                    that runs either in>to it <lb/>or out, continues nearly the same <lb/>fulness of
                    all Seasons, and abound[s] <lb/>with various kinds of Fish, went to
                        <lb/><placeName key="bath">Bath</placeName>
                    <gap/> miles there fed our horses <del><unclear>2 mile</unclear></del>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="14" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_14"/> within two miles of this Town
                    seve-<lb/>-ral Large and elegant Buildings made <lb/>their appearance, which
                    after passing <lb/>through more than 100 miles of Wil/-<lb/>-derness where there
                    were but a few <lb/>stragling Cabbons <del>to be seen</del>, where<lb/>
                    enlivenings, the town of <placeName key="bath">Bath</placeName> stands on <lb/>a
                    low piece of Ground <del>near</del> on the <lb/>North Side of <geogName
                        key="cohoc">Conhocton Creek</geogName> consisting of<lb/> about 60 dwellings
                    some of which are <lb/>no discredit to the place, here we fed <lb/>our Horses 6
                    miles, the Road from <geogName key="mudcr">mud <lb/>Creek</geogName> runs pretty
                    much under the <lb/>South side of a Mountain is in places <lb/>Stony, and other
                    places very Miry <lb/> the <del>and</del> Land thin at <placeName key="bath"
                        >Bath</placeName> we <del>council<lb/>led</del> enquired of <del>with</del>
                    some knowing men which <lb/>way we had better take for the best <lb/>to go to
                        <placeName key="niaga">Niagara</placeName> haveing it in <lb/>prospect to go
                    through <placeName key="willi">Williams-<lb/>-burgh</placeName> it being out
                    nearest Rout, <lb/>but they informed us there was only <lb/>a small Indian path
                    that way and <lb/>that we had better go by the way of <lb/>
                    <pb n="15" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_15"/>
                    <placeName key="canan">Canadarque</placeName> and <del>at that</del> the
                    directest <lb/>road there, was so Miry <del>that</del> we had <lb/>better go by
                        <persName key="jwilk1">Jemima Wilkinson’s</persName>
                    <lb/>settlement, which was so far round <lb/><del>that</del> our minds became
                    closely <lb/>exercised to know what was best <lb/>to do, but upon closely
                    attending <lb/>to the subject, and taking <del>the</del>
                    <lb/>that part of our appointment of<lb/> Visiting those of our society about
                        <placeName key="canan">Can<lb/>adarque</placeName>
                    <del>and parts</del> &amp; parts adjacent into view are <lb/>felt most easy to
                    turn our Course <lb/>towards what is called <persName key="jwilk1"
                        >Jemima</persName>'s <del>the friends</del><lb/> settlement, tho it was much
                    about, <lb/>it was a solitary road, there being <lb/>but a few settlements , and
                    those two or three <lb/>expected, were within four Miles of <lb/><placeName
                        key="bath">Bath</placeName> the rest of the way an entire <lb/>Wilderness,
                    the Land for a few Miles<lb/> from <placeName key="bath">Bath</placeName> was a
                    high dry soil and thin the <lb/>Timber Chiefly pitch pine <del>the soil
                        <lb/>thin</del> thence through a low fat Bottom <lb/>very swampy, thence
                    over the North end of <lb/>Mountain’ beautifully Timbered, not very <lb/>
                    <pb n="16" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_16"/> stony but excellent Wheat Land, to
                    Sanfords <lb/>15 miles, where we got Hay, and very indif.<lb/>-firent Oates in
                    the sheaf, thence along the <lb/>East side of the <geogName key="crook">Crooked
                        Lake</geogName> ever a level <lb/>Country, and for the most part good
                    <lb/>Land, for miles togather, a deep Rich <lb/>Soil abounding with Sugar Maple,
                    <lb/>Shelbark Hickory, Ash, Elm, White Oak <lb/>&amp;c: mostly a White Oak
                    Timber the Last <lb/>20 Miles, a few White Pine in pplaces, <lb/>to <persName
                        key="tlee1">Thomas Lees</persName> a kind friendly Family <lb/>16 miles,
                    this has been a hard days, tra-<lb/>-vel for our Horses, and there fare very
                    poor, <lb/>there was no place to Quarter, short <lb/>of where we arrived, that
                    we were <gap/>
                    <lb/>Obliged to travel hard, this has been <lb/>a dark Cloudy day tho not much
                    rain </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1797-10-22">1st day of the week 22nd</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> a rainy Morning &amp;<lb/> drisley day, in conference this Morning <lb/>it was
                    thought best, not to travel <lb/>till afternoon, and as there was no
                    <lb/>friends Meeting in these parts, we felt <lb/>an Opening to sit down with
                    the <lb/>family in which we were, with <del><gap/></del> such <lb/>
                    <pb n="17" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_17"/> of the neighbors who were free to
                    <lb/>come, there being but a few within <lb/>reach, the Opportunity was sensibly
                    <lb/>owned, the Lords Heavely Power <lb/>Overshadowing to our Comfort &amp;
                    <lb/>the Contrition and humbling of <lb/>most that were present were we
                    parted<lb/> with them in much nearness, went to one <lb/><del>Potters</del>
                    <persName key="wpott1">Judge Potters</persName> who kindly <lb/>took us in, he
                    lives in a very <lb/>Elegant <del>House</del> Building which after riding <lb/>5
                    or 6 Miles without seeing scarcely a house:<lb/>
                    <del>to see</del> such a Supurb one rising <lb/>in the Woods begot admiration.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-10-23">2nd day 23</date>
                    <placeName key="canan"/></dateline>
                <p>a pleasant Morning, set of[f]<lb/> for <placeName key="canan"
                        >Canadarque</placeName>, the road mostly throu gh<lb/> the Woods, and in
                    places deep, stoped an[d] <lb/>fed at Gilberts 8 miles, in 5 miles farther
                    <lb/>we came on the bank of <geogName key="canla">Canadarque
                        <lb/>Lake</geogName>, which was enlivening, and look<lb/>ed beautiful thence
                    up the side of the Lake <lb/>to the place <del>where it ran out</del> of its
                    outlet which stream <lb/>was as Large as a pretty <del>Creek</del> Clever Creek<lb/>
                    <pb n="18" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_18"/> thence up a beautiful ascending
                    stre†[ch]<lb/> about a mile <del>stands</del> to <placeName key="canan"
                        >Canadarque</placeName>
                    <del>thou[gh] <lb/>is</del>
                    <gap/> it contains a Number of <del>well built</del> Houses perhaps so some <lb/>
                    <del>of us <gap/></del> elegant, and supurb, here we fed >10 mil†[es?] <lb/>upon
                    confering together we thought <lb/>best of going to see some of our mem<lb/>bers
                    hereaway <del>upon</del> and enquiring of our <lb/>Landlord he informed us of
                    one or <del>one</del> more <lb/>who Lived at <geogName key="mudcr">Mud
                        Creek</geogName> about 10 or 12 m<unclear>iles</unclear><lb/> off, we then
                    turned our faces that way <lb/>and in about 9 m <del><gap/></del> traveling
                    <lb/>we stoped at a certain <persName key="jhowl1">Job Howlings</persName>
                    <lb/>to enquire the way, he told us it was <lb/>to far to reach that evening and
                        <del>a</del> kind-<lb/>-ly invited us to stay all night, which we
                    <lb/>accepted of, found his Wife a Member and very kind <lb/>we had a sitting
                    with them that even-<lb/>ing, the Land from <persName key="tlee1">Thomas
                        Lees</persName> to <lb/><placeName key="canan">Canadarque</placeName> is in
                    some places very <lb/>rich strong land in other places thin, <lb/>much of the
                    way is Low flat Country <del>Land</del>
                    <lb/>to wet for Wheat, but little pine for <lb/>20 m past the mostly heavy
                    timbered. <lb/>From <placeName key="canan">Canadarque</placeName> to this place
                    very <lb/>Deep, rich Land, for the most part, the <lb/>
                    <pb n="19" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_19"/> Very flat and wet, <del>the greater body
                        <lb/>of</del> Timber chiefly Elm, breech, &amp; Sugar maple <lb/>27 miles.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1797-10-24">3d 24</date>, <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> in conferrence this Morning it open-<lb/>-ed with greatest clearness to appoint
                    a Meeting <lb/>to be held next day at <persName key="nherr1">Nathan
                        Herringdan</persName>’s a <lb/>Friendly Man about 11 miles from thence, we
                    <lb/>then went to <persName key="ncoms1">Nathan Cornstalk</persName>’s, 5 miles
                    sat with <lb/>his family, his Wife a Member; thence to <persName key="alaph1"
                        >Abraham <lb/>Lapham</persName>’s 2 miles had a refreshing Oppertunity
                    <lb/>with his family Lodged there, 7 miles</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-10-25">4 day 25</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> attended the Meeting at <persName key="nherr1">Herringdan’s</persName>
                    <lb/>9 miles tho it was not a time of reigning, yet an<lb/> instructive
                    Opportunity, Dined with the fami-<lb/>-ly where the meeting was held, Lodged at
                        <persName key="jsmit2">Jeremiah <lb/>Smiths</persName> over <geogName
                        key="mudcr">Mud Creek</geogName>, his Wife a Member<lb/> he was one of the
                    first settlers in these parts, <lb/>his Cabin remains Covered with bark, the
                    <lb/>logs of his house are Chunked but not plastered <lb/><del>I</del> we had
                    pretty good Beds, otherwise I thought <lb/>the Openness of the House was a
                    prepa-<lb/>-ration to our Lying in the woods, which we <lb/>expect shortly to
                        <del><gap/></del> encounter the Land in these parts <lb/>mostly flat, a deep
                    rich soil, so that the roads <lb/>are <del>mostly</del> wet and heavy, the chief
                    body of <lb/>the Timber is Poplar, some of them the <lb/>finest I ever saw, Ash,
                    Beech, and Sugar Maple <lb/>9 miles </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="20" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_20"/>
                <dateline><date when="1797-10-26">5th day the 26</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>

                <p> attended an appointed Meeting <lb/>at <persName key="ncoms1">Nathan
                        Cornstalks</persName>, 2miles, it was a Solid <lb/>favoured Opportunity, at
                    the Close of which <lb/>we desired that those in religious pro-<lb/>-fession
                        <del>with</del> and those who had their<lb/> minds turned towards friends
                    would <lb/>keep their seats, to whom Council and<lb/> instruction was
                    administered, the num<lb/>-bers who staid was <del>not</del> perhaps 40, one
                    <lb/>half of whom were not in membership <lb/>but divers of them appeared a
                    ten<lb/>-der seeking people, went in the <lb/>Evening to <persName key="jsmit1"
                        >Jacob Smith’s</persName> on <geogName key="mudcr">Mud Creek</geogName>
                    <lb/>6 miles here we had a religious Op-<lb/>-portunity with his and his Brother
                        <lb/><persName key="jsmit3">Joseph Smith</persName>’s family this Closed our
                    <lb/>religious services in these parts</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-10-27">6th day 27</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> set of for <placeName key="niaga">Niagara</placeName>, fed at
                        <unclear>Thayers</unclear><lb/> 16 miles got to the <geogName key="niagr"
                        >River</geogName> 8 miles here we<lb/> expected to have been supplyed with
                    Oates<lb/> to take carry us to <placeName key="buffa">Buffaloe</placeName>
                    <del><gap/> 80 miles</del> but could neither get Corn or Oates, we <lb/>then
                    went back about one mile and <lb/>with difficulty got one corn, we had <lb/>
                    <pb n="21" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_21"/> intended to have stayed all night <lb/>at
                    the <geogName key="niagr">River</geogName>, but finding there was a house <lb/>8
                    miles on our way &amp; <del>at</del> that it was at least <lb/>80 miles to
                        <geogName key="buffc1">buffalow Creek</geogName>, we thought best <lb/>to
                    try to get there, but the Prospect was very <lb/>discouraging, as it was like to
                    be a dark <lb/>Rainy Evening and the sun not above an <lb/>hour high when we got
                    over the <geogName key="niagr">river</geogName>, <lb/><del>yet we set off</del>
                    and their proving several<lb/> Roads in the Course of <del><gap/></del> 2 miles
                    we took <lb/>a wrong one and after 2 miles traveling <lb/>upon enquiry found we
                    were wrong, <del>and</del> then had 7 miles<lb/><del><gap/></del> to our
                    intended <del>Quarters</del> point a good house <lb/>was a little to the left
                    but upon trying <lb/>could not get Quarters there, it was now near <lb/>dusk, a
                    dark Rainy evening and 7 miles <lb/>of a small path in a unknown Woods <lb/>to
                    traverse, we had a little Moon in our favour <lb/>yet in about 5 miles it grew
                    so <lb/>dark that we frequently missed our path <lb/>and <del>we</del> had but
                    little prospect of getting <lb/>to our port, the thoughts of having to <lb/>get
                    by the side of a tree and hold our <lb/>horses in the rain without fire until
                    <lb/>day Break was trying, yet through mer-<lb/>-cy we got safe in <del>to our
                        Quarters</del> but there was <lb/>neither hay nor <del>father fore</del>
                    fodder for our <lb/>
                    <pb n="22" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_22"/> horses we let them out to pick a little
                            <del><unclear>grass</unclear></del> while <lb/>then tyed them up till
                    Morning, the hay <lb/>afforded no provision for ourselves, <lb/>the Land from
                        <persName key="jhowl1">Job Howlings</persName> around throu[gh] <lb/>the
                        <del>the</del> settlement of friends is deep, Rich, <lb/>black Soil, mostly
                    pretty level, inclinable <lb/>to be wet, the Surfice of the ground very
                    <lb/>uneven, by trees being blown up from <lb/>time immemorial, the timber
                    pretty <lb/>Large and very thick, chiefly Poplar, Ash, <lb/>Sugar Maple, Elm,
                    Shelbark Hickory and <lb/>some White Oak, from <persName key="jsmit1">Jacob
                        Smith</persName>s to the <lb/><geogName key="niagr">River</geogName> about 2
                    or 3 miles in our first seting <lb/>off excepted, mostly
                            <del><unclear>matly</unclear></del> on open Country <lb/>very little
                    timber either great or small, <lb/>the Land for the most part a sandy loam,
                    an[d] <lb/>the Country pretty thick settled</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-10-28">7th day 28th</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> to up very early and set off as soon<lb/> as we could see the path, in hopes of
                    a pretty <lb/>pleasant day, the sun made its appearance <lb/>about 9 or 10 yet
                    it presently hid its face and the <lb/>Clouds grew thick so that <del>and</del>
                    the Close wood we <lb/>were in <del>was</del> looked like evening, &amp;
                    presently <del>the snow</del><lb/> >it began to snow <del>fall</del>, and in a
                    few hours the <lb/>Limbs, and young timber became <del>so</del> Loaded <lb/>
                    <pb n="23" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_23"/> >so that it was difficult getting along,
                        <del>over</del>
                    <lb/>the Woods continuing remarkably thick<lb/> of under stuff, and abundances
                    of wind fall Timber <del>that</del> it was a trying day <lb/>to ride, for near
                    20 miles of our road was <lb/>through a Beech and Sugar Maple Land, which
                    <lb/>is mostly deep rich soil, and wet, much <lb/>of the way was very swampy, so
                    that be-<lb/>-tween the snow and the Mud, we were <lb/>in a wet dirty condition,
                    and the pros-<lb/>-pect of siting down when Night came, upon <lb/>the Snow
                    without Shelter looked very try-<lb/>-ing, yet we went on pretty Chearful,
                    tak-<lb/>-ing a bit of Victuals in our hands wet <lb/>and could as we were,
                    while our horses <lb/>eat their Corn out of pieces of Bark <lb/>that Lay in
                    places by our path, when <lb/>Evening came we espyed a Large Rock,<lb/> near the
                    Road, which projected 6 or 7 <lb/>feet over at one side and the Back part<lb/>
                    sufficiently secured from the Storm, <lb/>have upon viewing it we concluded to
                    take<lb/> up our Quarters some of us went to gather-<lb/>-ing Wood, which was
                    wet and Snowy, but<lb/> to our great disappointment, after we <lb/>had got our
                    time so forward of the blaize<lb/>
                    <del>through an accident</del> by an accident it was <lb/>
                    <pb n="24" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_24"/>
                    <del>it</del> scattered went out, and having but little <del>for</del>
                    <lb/>punk we were not able to renew it. <lb/>here we were in the midst of a
                    desso-<lb/>-late Wilderness, wet and could, without <lb/>fire, without Shelter
                    or Beding, more <lb/>than what a Rock afforded, yet we com-<lb/>-forted our
                    selves in being so happy as to find <lb/>so good a Shelter, we felt as much for
                    our <lb/>Horses, as for ourselves, the Woods afford<lb/>-ed but little
                    provision, and that was cover-<lb/>-ed with Snow, so that after giving them<lb/>
                    some Corn, we tyed them up till Morning <lb/>and Changing some of our Wet
                    Clothes, we <lb/>endeavoured to take some rest, and <lb/>tho it was Cold, we
                    Lodged more com-<lb/>-fortable than could be expected, slept <lb/>pretty well,
                    took little or no cold, and <lb/>set our Journey chearfully next Morn-<lb/>-ing
                    <gap/> 36 miles </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-10-29"> 1st day 29</date>, <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> it snowed a little all night, and<lb/> continued this Morning yet by 8 or 9
                    <lb/>O Clock the Sun, to our great Joy, made <lb/>its appearance, and our road
                    for the <lb/>most part good, we pursued our Journey <lb/>
                    <pb n="25" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_25"/> with Livelyness and by 3 O Clock arived
                    <lb/>at <geogName key="buffc1">Buffaloe Creek</geogName> in full view of
                        <geogName key="lakee">Lake<lb/> Erie</geogName> 36 Miles.—--- after we
                    Crossed the <lb/><geogName key="genri">Genesee River</geogName> the first 10
                    miles, mostly an<lb/> open plain, the timber for the next 8 or 10 <lb/>miles
                    increased, it being pretty much <lb/>Oak, Shelbark Hickory, some beech, and
                    <lb/>Sugar Maple, the next 20 or more miles<lb/> a Very thick Wood mostly Beech,
                    and <lb/>Sugar Maple with some Beautiful White<lb/> Oaks, and Poplars, from
                    thence to the <lb/><geogName key="lakee">Lake</geogName> is in the general an
                    open Country <lb/>for 15 or more miles very little timber <lb/>either great or
                    small, the Cuntry is ve-<lb/>-ry level <del>the whole 80 miles</del> a few hills
                    <lb/>excepted about some waters <del>Creeks</del>, there <lb/>being 4 or 5
                    Creeks in this last 80 m<lb/> nearly as large as <geogName key="brand">Brandy
                        wine</geogName>, the <lb/>fording place of some of them was <lb/>one entire
                    smothe Rock nearly as <lb/>level as an house floor, so that the water <lb/>did
                    not vary in depth more than 2 or 3 Inches <lb/>for side to side and fell within
                    two yards †<lb/> [an entire line is cut off the bottom of the page]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="26" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_26"/>
                <dateline><date when="1797-10-30">2nd day 30</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>


                <p>set of early to cross the <geogName key="niagr">Niagara</geogName>
                    <lb/>went 100 or more Pearches down the <geogName key="buffc1"
                        >Buf<lb/>-faloe</geogName>, a beautiful stream to its Confluence<lb/> with
                    the <geogName key="lakee">Lake</geogName> which <geogName key="lakee"
                        >Lake</geogName>
                    <del>afforded</del> had a Majestick <lb/>appearance, the breakers roling on the
                    <lb/>Shore like those <del>that More</del> of the <geogName key="atlan"
                        >Atlantick</geogName>. <lb/>we rode down the Beach 3 or 4 miles <lb/>to the
                    Narrows of the <geogName key="niagr">Niagara</geogName>, there
                        <lb/><del>were</del> was neither Boat nor House on the <lb/>Side we were,
                    but by waiting an hour <lb/>or more, the Boat came, which took <lb/>three of us,
                    and by ten we all got safe <lb/>over, it is a bold rapid stream half <lb/>a Mile
                    over were we Crossed, &amp; about 16 feet deep <del>and</del> it appeared
                    dangerous <del>and</del> we <lb/>were informed that a few hours of <lb/>high
                    Westerly Winds would blow the <lb/>the Water off the <geogName key="lakee"
                        >Lake</geogName> so to the end <lb/>where the <geogName key="niagr"
                        >River</geogName> essued, that <lb/>it would raise it immeadiately 4 or 6
                    <lb/>feet, tho not altered perceptable in its depth by Rains we rode down the
                    shore upon<lb/>
                    <pb n="27" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_27"/> The <placeName key="upcan"
                        >Canada</placeName> side several Miles, a plea<lb/>-sant ride being
                    beautifyed with the <geogName key="niagr">River</geogName><lb/> on one hand and
                    good improvements on <lb/>the other, <del>and</del> in some 3 or 4 miles we
                    left<lb/> this delightful Prospect to encounter a mis-<lb/>-erable swampy road,
                    with some firm<lb/> stony Land, and in 8 or 10 miles arrived <lb/>at <persName
                        key="ascho1">Asa Schuylies</persName> one of our friends which <lb/>was
                    truly satisfactory to us all, being <lb/>weary, dirty, and wanted recruitive
                    <lb/> >our coming was unexpected to our friends yet truly <lb/>acceptable and we
                    were received <lb/>with open hearts 14 miles </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-10-31">3rd day the 31</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> sat at <persName key="jcutl1">John Cutlers</persName>
                    <del>Gilberts</del> who appear<unclear>ed</unclear>
                    <lb/>to be an Innocent examplary friend, has <lb/>5 children at Home three of
                    whom are nearly <lb/>grown up and are hopeful, and three <lb/>are from home who
                    are in their Mino-<lb/>-rity, he has latterly buried his Wife &amp;
                        <lb/><del>he</del> is a member of <orgName>Buckingham Monthly<lb/>
                        Meeting</orgName> we have since met with one of <lb/>his sons who was from
                    home, he is an<lb/> apprentice to a friend, and is an hope-<lb/>-full young
                        <del>friend</del> Man <lb/> thence sat at <del>to</del>
                    <persName key="jherr1">John Herit</persName>s neither him <lb/>nor his Wife are
                    in Membership, they <lb/>are thoughtful persons, and profess no other <lb/>way<lb/>
                    <pb n="28" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_28"/> Then sat at <persName key="dpoun1">Daniel
                        Pound</persName>s, <del>him</del> he and <lb/>his Wife are examplary friends
                    and have <lb/><del>nine</del> seven pretty Inocent Children who are<lb/> all
                    small, <del>him</del> he and his Wife were dis<lb/>-owned by <orgName>Plainfield
                        Monthly Meeting</orgName>
                    <lb/>they appear to be in a tender thought<lb/>-ful condition and are desirous
                    to <lb/>make up with friends, and have sent acknowledgments by us none of their
                    Child<lb/>-ren have a right <lb/> we then sat at <persName key="jmorr1">Joel
                        Morrises</persName>, he <lb/>has never had a right among friend <lb/>but we
                    think he is hopeful and in a <lb/>thoughtful tender state, his wife was
                    <lb/>disowned by <del>Shrewsberry</del>
                    <orgName>Rahway Monthly Meeting</orgName>
                    <lb/> they have 4 small children <lb/>is <del>in</del> a tender thoughtful
                        <del>State</del>, woman here we <lb/>met with <persName key="alane1">Abraham
                        Lane</persName> a Single Man <lb/>and a Member, <del>and</del> who may do
                    Well, he <lb/>is a Member of <orgName>Shrewsbury Monthly Meeting</orgName>
                    <lb/> Sat at <persName key="ascho1">Asa Schuylies</persName>
                    <del>him</del> he and his Wife <lb/>are examplary friends, and, Members <lb/>of
                        <orgName>KingWood Monthly Meeting</orgName>, they have <lb/>several hopeful
                    Children but none of them<lb/> have a right of membership, Lodged here </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="29" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_29"/>
                <dateline><date when="1797-11-01">4th day 11th Mo 1st</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>


                <p>Sat with <persName key="jhave1">Joseph Haven</persName>s, <del>him</del> he
                    <lb/>and his Wife appear to be steady examplery<lb/> Friends, they have two
                    Children grown <lb/>to Manhood, who are hopeful, the Son<lb/> Married <persName
                        key="jhill1">John Hills</persName> Daughter as near to the <lb/>common
                    Practice of Friends as circumstances <lb/>would permit, he lives home with his
                    <lb/>Father and they are an hopeful Couple <lb/> our next Oppertunity was at
                        <persName key="jmars1">Joseph Marsh</persName><lb/>-es, his Wife never had a
                    right amongst friends <lb/>but is a tender, Open, Inocent Woman, and a <lb/>real
                    friend in Principle, Joseph was disown<lb/>-ed by <orgName>Plainfield Monthly
                        Meeting</orgName> for Marri-<lb/>-ing, he is desirous to condemm his
                    out-<lb/>-going and we hope from a right concern<lb/> the have seven pretty
                    Innocent Children <lb/>the Oldest not ten <lb/> we sat at <persName key="awebs1"
                        >Abraham Webster</persName>’s who with his <lb/>Wife are Members of
                        <orgName>Kingwood Monthly <lb/>Meeting</orgName>, they have <del>eight</del>
                    seven Children who are <lb/>in membership, <del>they</del>
                    <del>who</del> they appear Innocent <lb/>and hopefull<lb/> then sat at <persName
                        key="aburr1">Adam Burrell</persName>’s neither <del>him</del> he <lb/>nor
                    his Wife ever had a right among <del>frien</del><lb/>friends, they attend
                    Meetings, <del>and</del> are look<lb/>-ing toward friends, and appear hopeful<lb/>
                    <pb n="30" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_30"/> the have nine Children, Several
                        <unclear>Vierging</unclear>
                    <lb/><del>on</del> towards young women who have the <lb/>Stamp of Innocency on
                    their Countenan-<lb/>-ces, were very much tendred, and parted <lb/>with near
                    affection, ---- Our horses <lb/>being tired, and the Roads in these parts
                    <lb/>flat and Swampy, we went on foot yes-<lb/>-terday and today, traveled about
                    20 <lb/>Miles, and Lodged at <persName key="ascho1">Asa Schuylies</persName>,
                    who <lb/>bore us company to the families we <lb/>have visited, <del>lodged at
                            <persName key="ascho1">Asa Schoolys</persName></del>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-11-02">5th day 2nd of the mo</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> Attended a Meeting that <lb/>we appointed to be held at <persName key="ascho1"
                        >Asa Schoolys</persName>
                    <lb/>the friends &amp; friendly People generally attend<lb/>-ing, it was pretty
                    Large, <del>it</del> was an Open <lb/>time, and Gospel truths were delivered
                    <lb/>from good Authority, <del>and</del> Some time was <lb/>spent in endeavoring
                    to strenghen and <lb/>Assist them in <del>in</del> bringing things into
                    <lb/>order, and in the holding of their Meet-<lb/>-ings to the reputation of our
                    profession <lb/>many of them parted with us in near <lb/>affection, being much
                    Contrited <lb/>
                    <pb n="31" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_31"/> went in the afternoon up the Northwest
                    <lb/>side of <geogName key="lakee">Lake Erie</geogName> to <persName
                        key="odenn1">Obediah Denniss</persName>’s <lb/>who lay very low,
                        <del>him</del> he and his Wife are <lb/>members of <orgName>Kingwood Monthly
                        Meeting</orgName>
                    <lb/>with their five Children who are under<lb/> 15, we had a beautiful ride
                    about four <lb/>Miles on the Beech up the Side of the <geogName key="lakee"
                        >Lake</geogName>, the <lb/>Sand near the Water is very Hard and <lb/>Smoothe
                    and is an excallent road, and what to me appeared very <lb/>curious was the
                    ellevations that were<lb/> frequent along the side of the <geogName key="lakee"
                        >Lake</geogName>, some <lb/>of them 40 or 50 feet high 10 or more
                    pearch<lb/>-es broad covered with Timber, and yet <lb/>we were informed they
                    were perfect sand <lb/>hills blown out of the Lake, which upon <lb/>inspection
                    appeared to be realy the case <lb/>Lodged at <persName key="dpoun1">Daniel
                        Pounds</persName> 10 miles </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-11-03">6th day third</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> a warm smoky Morning <lb/>and so thick an Air for several days <lb/>past that
                    the sun scarcely made it appear<lb/>-ance, went to <persName key="ascho1">Asa
                        Schoolies</persName> 2 ½ miles, hav-<lb/>-ing visited the families of
                    Friends, and <lb/>such who profess with us in those parts we <lb/>set of to see
                    the four families down the <lb/>
                    <pb n="32" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_32"/> in a Northward direction from hence
                    <lb/>in about 8 miles we came to the great <lb/><geogName key="niagr">River
                        Niagara</geogName>, thence went down it <lb/>close on its Banks about 16
                    miles, the <lb/>Ride was delightful, having the beau<lb/>-tiful stream on our
                    right, which glid-<lb/>-ed Smoothly along, a good Road un<lb/>-der our feet, and
                    mostly improved <lb/>and checkquered on our Left with <lb/>pretty good
                        <del>improvements</del> dwellings, in about <lb/>12 miles we crossed a Large
                    Stream called <lb/><geogName key="chipp">Chippaway</geogName> a number of good
                    improv-<lb/>-ments are planted near its mouth, a <lb/>little below the mouth of
                    this Water the <lb/><geogName key="niagr">River</geogName> begins to hasten its
                    pace, and <lb/>in about 1 mile it became considerably <lb/>Rapid, the road kept
                    nearly on a level <lb/>but the bed of the <geogName key="niagr">River</geogName>
                    gradually <lb/>decended until it became very Roman<lb/>-tick so that I have no
                    words to ex-<lb/>-press its grand, and Majestick appear<lb/>-ance, its boldness,
                    its rapidity, its <lb/>dashing, and flying appearance, so that<lb/>
                    <pb n="33" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_33"/>
                    <del>Its dashing that</del> it <del>appeared</del>
                    <del>looked</del> was all in a <lb/>foam flying in places twenty or more
                    <lb/>feet high, <del>looking as</del> as white as a sheet <lb/>and all this, and
                    ten times as much <lb/>more before we came to the grand <lb/><del>and
                        perpendicular falls</del> Catarack, the day be-<lb/>-ing very Smoky, and a
                    little rainy we <lb/>had not so full a view of the great falls <lb/>as we
                    desired, <del>on</del> proposing if the day suited to <lb/>spend a little more
                    time when we re-<lb/>-turned, as near as I could compute, <lb/>this very wild,
                    romantick, and <lb/>foming condition of the river it began <lb/>about ¾ of a
                    Mile above <del>to</del> the great preci-<lb/>-pice, we left the <geogName
                        key="niagr">River</geogName> and in about two <lb/>miles <del>and</del> got
                    to <persName key="wlund1">William Lundy’s</persName>
                    <lb/>who was once a Member of <orgName>Kingwood month<lb/>-ly Meeting</orgName>
                    but for many years past, disowned, his <lb/>Wife and Children never had a right,
                    we <lb/>were friendly entertained, <del>but</del> there is bu[t] <lb/>little
                        <del><gap/></del> prospect in sd. family of any <lb/>Strength to the society
                    arising therefro[m] </p>
                <p> 25 Miles</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-11-04">7th</date> of the week <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p>a rainy morning, went <lb/>to <persName key="jmoor2">Jeremiah Moore’s</persName>
                    3 ½ miles, who <lb/>were much Joyed in th seeing us <lb/>
                    <pb n="34" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_34"/>
                    <del>him</del> he and his Wife are concerned <lb/>examplary friends from
                        <orgName>Sadsbury Monthly Meeting</orgName>, they have at <lb/>home seven
                    Innocent affectionate<lb/> Children. -- <lb/> hen sat at <persName key="bhill1"
                        >Benjamin Hills</persName>, 5 miles he is <lb/>a Member of
                        <orgName>Buckingham Mo.ly Meeting</orgName><lb/> and his Wife of
                        <orgName>Sadsbury <del>Monthly Meet-<lb/>-ing</del></orgName>, they are
                    young, and I hope maybe <lb/>usefull friends, they have four small Children
                    <lb/> Went to <persName key="jhill1">John Hills</persName>, 1 mile were <lb/>we
                    lodged <del>him</del> he and his Wife are <lb/>members of <orgName>Buckingham
                        Monthly<lb/> Meeting</orgName> they have two Children at <lb/>home, members,
                    ---- the Land <lb/>from <persName key="wlund1">William Lundy</persName>’s to
                        <persName key="jmoor2">Jeremiah<lb/> Moore</persName>’s is a high, dry,
                    Sandy loam, <lb/>mostly improved, from thence to this <lb/>place for 2 or 3
                    miles the same sort <lb/>but thinly Timbered, the remainder<lb/> flat, heavy
                    Timbred and appeared <lb/>
                    <pb n="35" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_35"/> kindly for 3 miles a White Oak Timber the
                    most <lb/>beautiful, both for Quantity and Quality <lb/><del>that</del> I have
                    seen since I left home. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-11-05">1st day the 5th</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> a wet stormy Morning and <lb/>increased with the day, snowed in the
                    <lb/>afternoon, attended an appointed meeting at <persName key="jhill1">John
                        Hills</persName>
                    <lb/>with the few friends in this Neighbourhood <lb/>it was a solid instructive
                    Opportunity, <lb/>Heavenly goodness was near, and the <lb/>meeting closed, to
                    general Satisfaction, we <lb/>had a tendering time in the afternoon <lb/>in
                    Conference <del>with them</del> concerning <lb/>their situation in which I hope
                    they gained <lb/>some strength, they have not as yet <lb/>been in the practice
                    of hold any mee[t]<lb/>-ings for Worship, <del>they</del> being but few <lb/>in
                    number and very scattered <del>but</del>
                    <lb/>we felt our minds Strengthened t[o?] <lb/>encouraged them to press
                    throu†[gh] <lb/>difficulties and meet together to <lb/>wait upon and Worship the
                    Lor[d] <lb/>Almighty, believing it would a<unclear>dd</unclear>
                    <lb/>to their strength and would if<lb/>
                    <pb n="36" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_36"/> rightly performed, be of a good
                    <lb/>Savour in the neighborhood </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-11-06">2nd of the week the 6</date>,
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> a frosty Morning and Snow<lb/>-ed the latter part of the day, set of to see
                    <lb/>friends at the <placeName key="short">Short Hills</placeName>, stoped and
                    sat <lb/>at <persName key="jdarl1">John Darlin</persName>’s 6 miles, his Wife
                    was<lb/> disowned by the <orgName>falls Monthly meeting</orgName>
                    <lb/>and her Husband never had a right, <lb/>they were kind, but not much
                    professed <lb/>of their ading strength to friends, >they have 6 Children <lb/>
                    then sat at <persName key="jgilh1">Joshua Gillam</persName>’s 5 miles he was
                    <lb/>Disowned by <orgName>Middletowon Monthly meet<lb/>-ing</orgName> for
                    marrying, his Wife a Member of <orgName>Sadsbury Monthly Meeting</orgName>
                    <lb/>they have three small Children, Joshu<unclear>a</unclear>
                    <lb/>is thoughtful about his situation and <lb/>desirous to be united to friends
                    which <lb/>we encouraged, we also here met with <lb/><persName key="tgill1"
                        >Thomas Gillam</persName> he was disowned by <lb/><orgName>Middletown
                        Monthly Meeting</orgName>, his wife <lb/>never had a right <lb/>
                    <pb n="37" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_37"/> then sat at <persName key="trice1">Thomas
                        Rice</persName>’s, <del><gap/></del>he was <lb/>brought up among friends but
                    has <lb/>no right, his Wife was disowned by <lb/><orgName>Buckingham Monthly
                        Meeting</orgName>, they are<lb/> examplary, and I hope thoughtfull, and
                    <lb/>have eight Children mostly small<lb/> thence to <persName key="jtayl2">John
                        Taylors</persName>, ½ a mile he was dis-<lb/>owned by the <orgName>Falls
                        Monthly Meeting</orgName><lb/> his Wife and two hopefull Children <lb/>are
                    members of <orgName>Sadsbury Monthly <lb/>Meeting</orgName>, she appears to be a
                    Motherly <lb/>concerned friend— <lb/> the face of the Country from <persName
                        key="jhill1">John Hill</persName>s <lb/>mostly flat and miry till within one
                    <lb/>mile of <persName key="jdarl1">John Darlin</persName>s, then commences<lb/>
                    the <placeName key="short">Short Hills</placeName> which produces
                    remark-<lb/>-ably steep pitches we then pased over <lb/>2 or more Miles of the
                    most beautiful <lb/>Chesnut Timber I remember to have <lb/>ever seen, the Woods
                    had been lately <lb/>burned to clear the leaves out of the way <lb/>of gathering
                    the Chesnuts, they we saw them lay ing very <lb/>
                    <pb n="38" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_38"/> thick on the ground as we rode along
                        <lb/>the<del>ir</del> Pigs are not allowed to run in the<lb/> Woods at this
                    season for fear of the <lb/>Bears and Wolves, we then for se-<lb/>-veral miles
                    passed <del>the effects</del> through the <lb/>effects of the greatest
                        Hi<unclear>o</unclear>rican mine<lb/> Eyes ever beheld, it was a very
                    <lb/>heavy Timbered Land about ¾ <lb/>of <del>it</del> the timber was torn up by
                    the Roots, the <lb/>other ¼ broke of by the Middle, the <lb/>Prospect was truly
                    awfull, <del>and</del> and tremendious. <lb/>the last five miles hilly though
                    not stony. the land good. <lb/>We are now got among the White <lb/>Pines, not
                    having seen many for<lb/> the last 30 miles </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-11-07">3 of the week and 7</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> sat at <persName key="stayl1">Samuel Taylors</persName>
                    <lb/>he was disowned by <orgName>Sadbury Monthly<lb/> Meeting</orgName> and his
                    Wife by <orgName>Kingwood</orgName>
                    <unclear>do</unclear>. <lb/>they appear pretty hopefull, and sent<lb/>
                    acknowledgements with us to their seve-<lb/>-ral Monthly Meeting to Condemn
                    their <lb/>out goings, they have 4 small children <lb/>
                    <pb n="39" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_39"/> thence back to an appointed Meeting at
                        <lb/><persName key="jtayl2">John Taylor</persName>s, it was an open favoured
                    <lb/>time <lb/> Thence to <persName key="jmoor1">Jacob Moore</persName>’s 2
                    miles he Married <lb/>his first-Cousin and <del>they were</del> was disowned
                    <lb/>by <orgName>Sadsbury</orgName>, his wife never was a Member they have two
                    small Children <lb/> intending to have sat at <persName key="smoor1">Soloman
                        Moore</persName>
                    <lb/>who lives Just by but neither <del>him</del> he nor <lb/>his Wife were at
                    home, he also mar-<lb/>-ried his first Cousin and <del>they</del>
                    <del>he</del>stands dis-<lb/>owned, they have three small Children <lb/> this
                    have been a Cold unpleasant day <lb/>began to snow about 10 O Clock and
                    con<lb/>-tinued till Evening, the prospect look<lb/>-ed discouraging to be near
                    500 miles from <lb/>home 300 of which was through what may <lb/>be called a
                    Wilderness the road small <lb/>that not much used, yet it felt a good
                    <lb/>degree of resignation — Lodged at<lb/>
                    <persName key="esnig1">Enoch Snigley</persName>’s 1 mile he has <del>not</del>
                    never had <del>a full</del> a right <lb/>right, <del>the friendly</del> his wife
                    was disowned by <orgName>Bucking<lb/>-ham</orgName>, they are friendly people
                    and have <lb/>six Children the Oldest perhaps <del>18</del> 20 <lb/>
                    <pb n="40" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_40"/> Some of our Company went to <persName
                        key="jcraw1">James Craw-<lb/>-ford</persName>’s who is a friendly Man, his
                    Wife <lb/>was disowned by <orgName>Richland Monthly Meet<lb/>-ing</orgName>
                    <del>they have five small Children</del>
                    <del>and</del>
                    <del>She</del><lb/>She is an exa mplery thoughtful Woman, have
                    <del>the</del><lb/>sent an Acknowledgement by us to the <lb/>Meeting she was
                    testifyed against to <lb/>condemm her out goings. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-11-08">5th day the 8</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> a pleasant day, the snow <lb/>nearly gone by evening, the Roads very <lb/>wet,
                    about six miles deep and heavy <lb/>like the breaking up of the frost,
                    stop-<lb/>-ed at <persName key="jhill1">John Hills</persName> and got dinner,
                    &amp; <lb/>Lodged at <persName key="jmoor2">Jeremiah Moores</persName>, 12
                    miles</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-11-09">5th day the 9th</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> a pleasant day, walked <lb/>1 ½ miles to <persName key="tmerc1">Thomas
                        Mercer</persName>’s, a person <lb/>who came out of <persName key="jlind1"
                        >Jacob Lindley</persName>’s <lb/>neighborhood about one year ago <lb/>they
                    were much pleased with <lb/>our Company, and gave us a Breakfast <lb/>exceeding
                    any we met with in <lb/><placeName key="upcan">Canada</placeName>, having
                    excellent Green <lb/>
                    <pb n="41" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_41"/> Tea and Loaf Sugar, Bread eaqual <lb/>to
                    any made in <placeName key="chest1">Chester County</placeName> &amp;c <lb/>We
                    then went to the <geogName key="niagr">River Niagara</geogName> >½ a mile
                    <lb/>to View a remarkable whirlpoole about 3 miles below the great Catarack
                    <lb/>the <geogName key="niagr">River</geogName> was not more than 20 pearches
                    <lb/>wide both above and below sd. poole the depth unknown<lb/>and it runs in a
                    romantick and ra-<lb/>-pid condition, the banks on each side perhaps 1000 feet
                    high got our horses shod <lb/>this Morning, Dined at <persName key="jmoor2"
                        >Jeremiah <lb/>Moores</persName>, attended an appointed meet<lb/>-ing held
                    in an house near the great <lb/>falls, built by the neighbors in ge-<lb/>-neral
                    for any who Choose to hold a <lb/>meeting in it, it was a Quiet well<lb/>
                    conducted Meeting, and Gospell Truths <lb/>delivered with good Authority, the
                    <lb/>meeting was held chiefly for those of other so-<lb/>-cieties Lodged at
                        <persName key="wlund1">Willam Lundyes</persName> 4 m </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-11-10">6th day the 9th [sic]</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> a Cold Frosty night, cloudy <del>mor</del>
                    <lb/>morning and like for now, set off for <placeName key="black">Black
                        <lb/>Creek</placeName>, stoped to View the great falls, the wind
                    <lb/>Southeast blew the fog or mist that arose from <lb/>the fall of the water
                    over us which fell <unclear>in</unclear>
                    <unclear>small</unclear><lb/>
                    <pb n="42" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_42"/> Rain <del>so</del> that it made it very
                    unpleasant <lb/>and the bank, or hill down to the Table <lb/>Rock where we
                    intended to have decended <lb/>was so Sleeted over with Ice <del>that</del>
                    <del>which</del>
                    <del>proceeded</del> that was produced <lb/>from the damp of the falls
                        <del>that</del> it appear<lb/>-ed unsafe to go down, we had a pretty
                    <lb/>fair prospect where we stood, being per-<lb/>-haps 50 feet above the water
                        <del>higher than where the great <lb/>pitch of the falls decended,</del> it
                    is hard <lb/>to discribe the appearance and motion <lb/>of the water it came
                    down with great <lb/>rapidity to where it projected off, <del>tho</del>
                    <lb/> we were informed that the sheet<lb/>
                    <del>was not the same thickness but appeared</del>
                    <lb/>in places was 16 feet thick <lb/><del>in places to be 16 or more
                        feet,</del> I could <lb/>>not see the <del>place</del> bottom of the sheet
                    by reason <lb/>of the fog or mist that arose from the great fall of water,
                        <del>the</del> we were informed that <lb/>one part of the pitch <del>was
                        within six</del> is 4 or 5 pearches<lb/>
                    <del>feet</del> father up the stream than it was <lb/>nine years ago and appears
                    to be <lb/>gradually wearing, stoped at the <persName>Widow
                        <lb/>Birchels</persName> who has an extraordinary Mer-<lb/>-chant and Saw
                    Mill on the rapids about <lb/>80 pearches above the great falls, the <lb/>race
                    is 80 pearches long taken out of the <lb/>
                    <pb n="43" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_43"/>
                    <geogName key="niagr">great River</geogName>, and has in that distance <lb/>ten
                    feet Head and Fall, it is truly an<lb/> awful sight to View the <geogName
                        key="niagr">River</geogName> from the <lb/>Mill door, now Leaving this Wonderfull<lb/>
                    <del>Phinonamy</del> Phinonima, we had a cold <lb/>ride up the River, and got to
                        <persName key="ascho1">Asa <del>School</del>
                        <lb/>Schoolies</persName> where we Lodged 21 miles—</p>
                <p>we have now Visited all the families, <lb/>or nearly so, of friends or such as
                    once <lb/>had a right, had four Meetings amongst <lb/>them, feel easy to set our
                    Faces homeward <lb/>but how we shall get along must be left <lb/>as it has been
                        <del>tret</del> threttening all day <lb/>for snow, and this evening it is
                    fall-<lb/>-ing very fast</p>
                <p> we found residing at <placeName key="black">Black Creek</placeName> pretty
                    <lb/>compact, tho two families were about 4 or 5 <lb/>miles from the rest, 7
                    families, who were in <lb/>Membership with friends, and appeared <lb/>pretty
                    orderly, with a number of hopeful <lb/>Children divers nearly or fully grown up
                    <lb/>making the Whole 33 persons, and <lb/>five families who profess with
                    friends <lb/>
                    <pb n="44" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_44"/> and are pretty hopefull, some of whom
                    <lb/>have sent acknowledgments by us to the<lb/> Meeting that disowned them,
                    they have a <lb/>number of tender Inocent Children, the<lb/> whole number of
                    both Parents and Child-<lb/>-ren are thirty eight many of them if <lb/>they keep
                    their places will add strength <lb/>to the little handful of friends in that
                    place, <lb/>we found at the <placeName key="short">Short Hills</placeName> and
                    in that <lb/>neighbourhood five families of Friends <lb/>who live at present
                    pretty wide per-<lb/>haps 12 or more miles tho some of them have it in prospect
                    to move nearer together for the Benefit of society, making in the whole
                    <lb/>twenty seven persons, and eight fami-<lb/>-lies of such who have mostly
                    been dis-<lb/>-owned, several of whom are desirous <lb/>to Condemn their
                    outgoings, <del>and</del> have <lb/>sent acknowledgments along with us, <lb/>and
                    I hope will make useful members. <lb/>The Parents and Children of this Class
                    <lb/>make 53 <del>persons and</del> who live pretty <lb/>compact, the way the
                    road now goes <lb/>makes it near 40 miles from the <placeName key="short">short
                        <lb/>Hills</placeName> to the settlements of friends at <lb/><placeName
                        key="black">Black Creek</placeName>, but there is reason<lb/>
                    <pb n="45" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_45"/> to expect that before long there will
                    <lb/>be a road opened between these places <lb/>not which will
                        <del>containing</del> be more than 14 or 15 <lb/>miles</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-11-11">7th of the week 11th</date>
                    <placeName key="buffa"/></dateline>
                <p> a rainy Morning not <lb/>more Snow fell last night than about <lb/>two inches
                    deep, wrote a number of <lb/>Letters to some friends in this
                    neighbour-<lb/>-hood, and feeling our minds easy to <lb/>return, we made
                    preparations to pass <lb/>homewards, the had not the season been <lb/>so far
                    advanced we would have been <lb/>easy to have stayed a few days longer,
                    <lb/>about 11 OClock we left our tender friends <lb/>at <placeName key="black"
                        >Black Creek</placeName> with Hearts full of <lb/>Gratitude that we had been
                    amongst <lb/>them, and some of them bore us Compa-<lb/>-ny as far as the
                        <geogName key="niagr">River</geogName>, where we ar-<lb/>-rived about ½
                    after two OClock, havin[g] <lb/>rode about 8 miles down the Beech<lb/> on
                        <geogName key="lakee">lake Erie</geogName>, we were <gap/>ise in
                    num-<lb/>-ber, and the Wind blowing high and<lb/>
                    <pb n="46" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_46"/> the <geogName key="niagr">River</geogName>
                    Rough, we were Obliged <lb/>to go two at a time, which took <lb/>near three
                    hours to get over, and <lb/>it Raining hard made it disagree-<lb/>-able,
                        <del>and</del> we were truly thankful <lb/>when we got safe on our own shore
                    Lodged <lb/>at <placeName key="buffa">Buffoaloe</placeName> 15 miles</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-11-12">1st day of the Week 12th</date>, <placeName
                        key="buffa"/></dateline>
                <p> we lay last Evening<lb/> next the Roof, and their falling much <lb/>Rain, it was
                    so plainly heard, that the<lb/> difficulty of passing through the <geogName
                        key="genri">Genesee</geogName>
                    <lb/>where there are a number of large<lb/> Creeks, without bridges, and no
                    house to <lb/>stop at provided we could not Cross,<lb/> presented with all its
                    discouragements, <lb/>which led into an enquiry whether we <lb/>had too much
                    hurried out of <placeName key="upcan">Can ada</placeName>
                    <lb/>and upon the most strict <del>enquiry</del> exa-<lb/>-mination, nothing
                    remained painful <lb/>as an Omission, but it would have been <lb/>more easy to
                    most of our Minds <lb/>
                    <pb n="47" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_47"/> if we had stayed over first day, feering
                    <lb/>our leaving them 7th day and next day this little meeting coming on
                    <lb/>least <del>it</del> should administer some discou-<lb/>-ragement <del>to
                        the few friends there</del><lb/> however resignation was our best
                    expe-<lb/>-dient, and when Morning came, the <lb/>rain still continuing very
                    heavy, we <lb/><del>can</del> thought it most safe, and felt most <lb/>easy to
                    remain in our Quarters, about <lb/>noon the rain abated, the wet a little
                    till<lb/> evening</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-11-13">2nd day the 13</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> rose early this morning to pur-<lb/>-sue our Journey, still Cloudy, from the
                    best <lb/> information we could get, were in hopes <lb/>the Waters, except
                        <geogName key="tonaw">Tawnywanty</geogName>, would be <lb/>fordable, but in
                    about four Miles travel-<lb/>-ing we were disappointed, for we came <lb/>upon a
                    very rapid Stream, which upon<lb/> examining, we believed not safe to Cross
                    <lb/>and to 18 hours since the rain abated<lb/> it appeared still to be rater
                    rising, this <lb/>was a fresh trial, but patience was our <lb/>best expedient,
                    for if we had ventured <lb/>and got safe over this stream, there was ano- <lb/>
                    <pb n="48" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_48"/> another much larger 6 or 7 miles ahead
                    <lb/>we therefore, upon holding a Council, agreed as <lb/>the most safe
                    expedient to return to our <lb/><gap/> Quarters, and wait until tomorrow
                    <lb/>Our Landlords house stands on a pleasant <lb/>elevated spot having a rich,
                    furtile Meadow <lb/>in front, enlivened by the <geogName key="buffc1"
                        >Buffaloe</geogName> to its Con-<lb/>-fluence with <geogName key="lakee"
                        >Lake Erie</geogName>, the stream is <del>perhaps <lb/>as</del> Large>r than
                        <del>of</del>
                    <geogName key="brandy">Brandywine</geogName>, and the <geogName key="lakee"
                        >Lake</geogName> its<lb/>self opens in full view as far as the Eye can
                    reach, when <lb/>the Wind is high in the West, it so raises <lb/>the Water in
                    this end of the <geogName key="lakee">Lake</geogName>, that it <lb/>flows up the
                        <geogName key="buffc1">Buffaloe</geogName> like a flood tide <lb/>our
                    accomodation here has been pretty <lb/>good, except our Lodging, which was a
                    <lb/>narrow frame scarely room for two to <lb/>lay on their Back, with Boards
                    instead of <lb/>Sackingbottom <del>with</del> and a very thin Strawbed <lb/>yet
                        <persName key="opaxt1">Oliver Paxton</persName> and myself has
                    Occupy-<lb/>-ed it three nights pretty comfortably and <lb/>expect to try it the
                    fourth, it is in an <lb/>upper Chambers next the Roof</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="49" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_49"/>
                <dateline><date when="1797-11-14">3rd day 14</date>, <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>

                <p>a blustry night, but pretty pleasant<lb/> Morning, all in health, and wit an
                    early <lb/>start set off cheerfully homewards, came <lb/>to the water that
                    turned us back Yesterday <lb/>the very rapid Crossed pretty readily, here
                    <lb/>Lay a poor family in distress, they came <lb/>from <placeName key="bucks"
                        >Bucks County</placeName> and were going into <lb/><placeName key="upcan"
                        >Canada</placeName>, Rain, and high waters had <lb/>detained them several
                    days in this <lb/>Wilderness, their Journey had been tedi-<lb/>-ous and their
                    Money spent, and what<lb/> was more trying their provision was <lb/>run out, and
                    no place to supply it un-<lb/>-til they got through, they were encamped <lb/>by
                    the side of the rapid stream that we <lb/>had Just Crossed, we endeavoured to
                    Com<lb/>fort them, leting them know they were <lb/>nearly through, where there
                    was provi-<lb/>-sion to be had, and for an immediate <lb/>relief spared them a
                    small Loaf of Bread, <lb/>and gave the Children some <del>piece</del> pieces
                    <lb/>of Cake, and for their further <del>relief</del> supply gave <lb/>them two
                    Dollars, our sympathy and kind-<lb/>-ness very much Affected the Poor Woman
                    <lb/>and we parted with her in bathed in <lb/>
                    <pb n="50" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_50"/> Tears, feeling thankful that we had
                    <lb/>it in our Power thus far to admini-<lb/>-ster relief, we cheerfully
                    proceeded on <lb/>our Journey, hoping the large Creek <lb/>ahead would be
                    fordable, but on our <lb/>arrival our hopes appeared frustrat<lb/>-ed, for it
                    was very high and appeard <lb/>still to be rising, and it was too wide <lb/>to
                    make a Bridge aCross by falling a Tree, <lb/>we explored the stream up <lb/>and
                    down but discovered no place <lb/>more eligiable than the common <lb/>fording,
                    and there, tho not much <lb/>above belly deep, we believed not <lb/>safe to
                    pass, by reason of its great <lb/>rapidity, and some 20 or 30 pearches
                    <lb/>below a <del>mightily</del> mightiy fall of perhaps 50 or <lb/>60 feet, to
                    sit down by it to wait for <lb/>the Water to fall, was trying, <del>as</del> and
                    their <lb/>was no house nigher than 12 miles <lb/>and we had but Just Provision
                    with <lb/>
                    <pb n="51" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_51"/> us, to carry, without detention, ourselves
                    <lb/>and horses to the <geogName key="genri">Genesee River</geogName>, and to
                    <lb/>turn back 12 miles felt unpleasant, how<lb/>-ever, thought best to stay
                    till towards <lb/>evening to see if their would be any <lb/>change in the Water,
                    and in about <lb/>3 or 4 hours there came up a Company <lb/>of Men who had been
                    out a surveying <lb/>they had a number of axes with them <lb/>and we went down
                    the streem about <lb/>half a Mile, where it was divided into <lb/>four
                        <del>branches</del> streams having small Islands <lb/>between, and here, tho
                        the<del>y</del> water ran surpris<lb/>-ingly swift, and the bottom unknown
                    <lb/>yet we thought best to try to get over <lb/>the Men with Axes fell Trees
                    across <lb/>which would reach <del>at these</del> from Island to
                        Island<del>s</del><lb/> and explored the banks and Depth <lb/>of the Streams
                    at the Opposite side, we<lb/> attempted and through mercy got all <lb/>safe
                    over, for which favour we felt<lb/> humblingly thankful, we then tra<lb/>veled
                    on, making no less a band than<lb/>
                    <pb n="52" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_52"/> 19 in number and in 10 miles pitch<lb/>-ed
                    our Camps on the <del>West</del> east side of a <lb/>lively brook, where we
                    could regale <lb/>ourselves with water and our bags <lb/>supplyed us with
                    Provisions, we <lb/><del>fortunate</del> fortunately in this spot <lb/>found a
                    pretty comfortably Indian <lb/>Wigwam, <del>being</del> covered with bark
                    <lb/>on the top and three sides, the front <lb/>being open, here we erected a
                    very <lb/>hospitable Fire, and with thankful<lb/> Hearts for so good a retreat,
                    enjoyed<lb/> a Comfortable Nights repose, and <lb/>tho in the Wilderness
                        <del>yet </del> we had <lb/>our Neighbours, their being no <lb/>less than
                    four Fires within 40 <del>pear</del>
                    <lb/>pearches distance <del>to</del> >two of which were <lb/>surrounded by
                    Indians who were on their way to <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>,
                    the <lb/>Night was clear and Cold, and we <lb/>hoped we should be favoured with<lb/>
                    <pb n="53" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_53"/> dry Weather till we got into the
                    set-<lb/>-tlement 22 miles</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-11-15">4th day the 15</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p>a cold frosty morning and <lb/> a little Cloudy, set of very early and <lb/>in 5
                    or 6 miles we had a smart snow<lb/> shower, and shortly after another the
                    <lb/>wind at North and very Cold, the<lb/>
                    <placeName key="tonaw">Tonewanty</placeName> we were informed by an <lb/>Indian,
                    was by far too deep to be rid<lb/> we then thought best to go be the <lb/>Indian
                    Village which stood on the <lb/>
                    <del>East</del>Westside of said stream, and was <lb/> perhaps 4 miles
                        <del>more</del>further, we were in <lb/> -formed there
                    <del>was</del>wereabout 150 Indians <lb/> in said Village, the have but a few
                    houses <lb/>for that number, there were two hew-<lb/> -ed log houses pretty neat
                    an tight <lb/>&amp; perhaps 40 or50 feet long, <del>and</del>they were <lb/>
                    stowed full, with several other small <lb/>huts near by, after some small
                    refresh-<lb/> -ment at a dirty Frenchmans house<lb/> on the bank of the said
                    river, we proceeded<lb/> to Cross, he having a small Canoe<lb/>
                    <pb n="54" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_54"/> took us over one by one with our
                        <del>bug<lb/>gage</del> baggage, and Cold as it was <lb/>we swam our horses
                    through, and in <lb/>about 16 miles traveling we came <lb/>to an Indian Wigwam,
                    not so good <lb/>as we met with last night, yet, tho <lb/>we had an hour of Son,
                        <del>we</del> thought<lb/><del>it</del> best >of <del>to </del> tak>ing up
                    our Quarters, <del>we</del> here <lb/>having had a <del>frozen</del> frozen day
                    to <lb/>ride and likely to be a very cold <del>snow</del>
                    <lb/>snowy night, time was necessary to <lb/>provide with wood &amp;c: which we
                    got <lb/>Compleated and ready to set down <lb/><del>before</del> to a
                    Comfortable refreshing<lb/> fire, before dark, here we passed <lb/>a very Cold
                    night, as chearfull and pleasant,<lb/> as could be expected, feel<lb/>-ing more
                    for our horses, than our<lb/>-selves, the Woods afforded little <lb/>but Snow
                    and Leaves, we therefore <lb/>both last night, and this, after giv-<lb/>-ing
                    them some Oates tyed them up <lb/>
                    <pb n="55" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_55"/> till Morning</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-11-16">5th day the 16</date>, <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> a Cloudy Frozen Morning <lb/>tho but little snow fell Last night <lb/>we found
                    the Frost added to the dif-<lb/>-ficulty of traveling about 25 or more miles of
                    <lb/>the road between <placeName key="buffa">buffaloe</placeName> and the
                        <lb/><geogName key="genri">Genesee</geogName> is through a succession of
                    <lb/>deep swamps, and this morning <lb/>our our first sitting of[f] we had
                        <del>one</del> several of <lb/>those difficulties to encounter this <gap/>
                    be-<lb/>-ing in places between belly and <lb/>knee deep, and <del>being</del>
                    Froze over <lb/>almost hard enough to bear, <lb/>it was exceeding
                        <del>exceed</del> difficult and tryin[g]<lb/> to the Horses, fed at Wilbords
                    14 miles. <lb/>There to the <geogName key="genri">Genesee</geogName> 12 miles
                    Lodged <lb/>at Foxes near by, here we got good <lb/><del>entertainment</del>
                    accommodations for <lb/>Man and horse which was very gr<gap/><lb/>ful after
                    so trying a Journey.</p>
                <p> the Country from <placeName key="buffa">Buffaloe</placeName> to <geogName
                        key="genri">Genesee</geogName>
                    <lb/>I discribe as of follows from <placeName key="buffa">Buffaloe</placeName>
                    <lb/>to <geogName key="tumbl">tumbling Creek</geogName> 4 miles mostly <gap/>
                    <lb/>heavy timbered, to <geogName key="stony">Stony Creek</geogName> 8 miles <lb/>
                    <pb n="56" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_56"/> mostly plains, thence to a small
                        <del>stre</del>
                    <lb/>stream at the east end of the large <lb/>plains 10 miles, thence to The
                    Indian <lb/>Village at <geogName key="tonaw">Tonewanty</geogName> 14 miles
                    abou[t] <lb/>½ way plains the remainder heavy <lb/>timbered land and some of it
                    a-<lb/>-mazingly rich, there are Black <lb/>Walnuts about the <geogName
                        key="tonaw">Tonewanty</geogName>
                    <lb/>four feet over, 50 or more feet <lb/>high holding their Thickness clear
                    <lb/>of limbs, thence 8 miles to the plains <lb/>again through <del>are</del>
                    heavy Timbered <lb/>Land in places swampy, some of it<lb/> pretty high and very
                    good, <lb/>thence over 4 or 5 miles of White Oak plains, thence <lb/>to the side
                    of <geogName key="tonaw">Tonewanty</geogName>, <del><gap/></del> heavy
                    tim<lb/>-bred, deep, and <del>in</del> frequently swampy <lb/>land, 6 miles,
                    thence 14 miles through <lb/>Land similar to the last discribed, <lb/>thence 10
                    miles to the <geogName key="genri">Ganesee</geogName> mostly <lb/>a barren
                    plains </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="57" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_57"/>
                <dateline><date when="1797-11-17">6 day the 17</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>


                <p>a Cold frozen night, and <lb/>a snowy day, this Morning was trying <lb/>and
                    discouraging, set of by the way of <lb/><placeName key="willi"
                        >Williamsburgh</placeName> 14 miles through a beautiful <lb/>wheat Country,
                    not much under timber <lb/>here we got Coffee for breakfast for <lb/>the first
                    time since we left <placeName key="muncy">Munsy</placeName>
                    <lb/>thence to <placeName key="danvi">Danville</placeName> 17 miles over a very
                    <lb/>Beautiful rich country we thought <lb/>much of it superior to any we passed
                    <lb/>over and very Curiously situated hav<lb/>-ing an high steady ridge or
                    Mountain <lb/>on our left, and the <geogName>Connesscragy</geogName> a
                    <lb/>branch of the <geogName key="genri">Genesee</geogName> on our <del>left
                        and</del> right with <lb/>a Beautiful Vale, the <del>high</del> hill and
                    <lb/>Vale was like a dunghill, for richness abounding <lb/>with very large
                    Walnut, Shellbark <lb/>Hickory with a Mixture of White Oak <lb/>Ash &amp;c. the
                    whole of the 17 miles abounds <lb/>with lively streams rushing with
                        <lb/><del>great</del> rapidity down from the sd.<lb/>mountain that every
                    Plantation ma[y]<lb/> be sufficiently supplyed with Water and taken of the land
                    with pleasure<lb/> lodged at <persName key="sfaul1">Samuel Faulkner</persName>s,
                    where <lb/>we met with very good accommodations </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="58" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_58"/>
                <dateline><date when="1797-11-18">7th day the 18</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>

                <p>a Cold frozen Morning <lb/>but we were Cleaned with a Clear <lb/>sun the most of
                    the day, which we <lb/>esteemed a favour, having but few <lb/>such days for near
                    three Weeks, there <lb/>are two Roads from this place to<lb/>
                    <placeName key="bath">Bath</placeName>, one flat, much of the way down the
                    <lb/>Waters of the Cohocton <del>tho</del> and is very <lb/>deep and Miry, and
                    scarcly at this <lb/>time passable, the other called the <lb/>Mountain Road, and
                    was rightly <lb/>denominated, we thought it would <lb/>be better to encounter
                    the Mountains <lb/>than the Mud, but truly such a Road <lb/>I never rid, it was
                    about 15 miles <lb/>we had to encounter this Wild and<lb/> romantick
                        <del>sen</del> scene which with all <lb/>the Industry we could use cost us
                    six <lb/>hours hard Traveling, the whole <lb/>way was <del>one</del> continued
                    Mountains <lb/>one after another, perhaps half or more <lb/>of a Mile up, and
                    almost immedi-<lb/>-ately as far down, generally so steep <lb/>
                    <pb n="59" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_59"/> that it was with the greatest
                    dif-<lb/>-ficulty our horses kept their feet <lb/>and I found myself frequently
                    un-<lb/>-der the necessity of taking hold of <lb/>my horses tail to help me up,
                    ma-<lb/>-ny of these Mountains where so load-<lb/>-ed with spruce and hemlock
                    that <lb/>at noon day, tho a bright sun and <lb/>the ground covered with snow,
                    it <lb/>looked like twilight to look up the <lb/>North side of them, and in many
                    <lb/>places there were such a number <lb/>of tress blown across the path
                    <lb/>that it was with the greatest diffi-<lb/>-culty we got round or over some
                    <lb/>of them, and in <del>some</del> other places tho high <lb/>up on the
                    mountains, we were<lb/> nearly to the horses bellies in Mud and Ice <lb/>and for
                    18 miles in this Wild roman-<lb/>-tick scene not so much as one Cabin <lb/>was
                    to be found, nor I suppose ever will tho it abounded with <lb/>Deer, Bear, and
                    Wolf Tracks, with other Wild Beasts we got <lb/>to <placeName key="bath"
                        >Bath</placeName> with great industry in the<lb/>
                    <pb n="60" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_60"/> dusk of the Evening weary, <lb/>Could, and
                    hungry, but lighting at <lb/>the foremost Tavern, could get <lb/>no hay for our
                    Horses, which upon <lb/>enquiry was the situation of the <lb/>other Public
                    Houses, in <gap/> town tho the Capital of <placeName key="steub">Subend
                        County</placeName> we therefore <lb/>were under the Necessity of Riding
                    <lb/>Six Miles further to <geogName key="mudcr">Mud Creek</geogName> 32m </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1797-11-19">1st day the 19</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> still continued cold and <lb/>snowed betimes all day, went to <lb/>the Post 12 m
                    where we got our Break-<lb/>-fast thence up the waters of the <geogName
                        key="susqu">Sus-<lb/>-quehanna</geogName> to the <persName key="mlind1"
                        >Widow Lindsly’s</persName>
                    <lb/>where we intended to have taken up <lb/>our Quarters, but they had no
                    Oates, <lb/>very little corn, and but poor hay, <lb/>we therefore proceeded 5
                    miles <lb/>further up the <geogName key="tioga">Tyoga</geogName> to Salsbury’s
                    <lb/>tho but poor accommodations, yet <lb/>they were very kind, in this days
                    travel <lb/>we have seen 4 deer near <lb/>by and a Multitude of their tracks <lb/>
                    <pb n="61" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_61"/> we have Crossed four Large Streams <lb/>of
                    the <geogName key="susqu">Susquehanna</geogName> in 14 miles each of them<lb/>
                    we Judged as large again as <geogName key="brandy">Bran-<lb/>-dywine</geogName>
                    they were all of them more <lb/>than Belly deep, and we felt truly <lb/>thankful
                    Considering the great <lb/>fall of Rain that we are safely <lb/>over them 29
                    miles ---</p>
                <p> here we met with two travelers <lb/><del>that</del> who had Just come from the
                        <placeName key="block">Block-<lb/>-house</placeName>, they informed us the
                    Road <lb/><del>there</del> was so bad that it cost them two <lb/>days >hard
                    traveling, <del>which</del> and that we <lb/>could not reach <del>there</del> it
                    in one day tho <lb/>but 35 miles, this information was ve-<lb/>-ry discouraging,
                    for their was no stage <lb/>or house short of 23 miles of sd. <placeName
                        key="block">Blockhouse</placeName> yet upon <lb/>considering the
                    circumstances we <lb/>concluded to make a trial of going <lb/>through in one
                    day, and if we failed <lb/>to lye in the Woods, Cold and Snowy as <lb/>it was
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="62" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_62"/>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1797-11-20">2nd day the 20</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>

                <p>Started Just as day ap-<lb/>-peared, a Cold frozen Morning.<lb/><del>We wanted a
                        loaf of bread to make <lb/>use of provided</del> not knowing but we should
                    <lb/>have to lie on the Woods, were desirous to be provided with some bread we
                    tried our <lb/>Landlord, and nearly every house <lb/>we came by for ten Miles,
                    but <lb/>they unanimously informed us <lb/>they had no Bread <del>baked</del>,
                    by them, <lb/>we Stoped at Lambs 10 miles the Last house <lb/>but one, in that
                    settlement fed our horses and got <del>our</del><lb/> Breakfast, and then with
                    Industry <lb/>reached the <placeName key="block">Blockhouse</placeName> by
                    sunset <lb/>our living of Late has been poor, both <lb/>for ourselves and
                    horses, this is the <lb/>second night out of four that they <lb/>have had to do
                    without hay, and we have <lb/>had no wheat or Indian Bread for tw[o] <lb/>days,
                    and <del>when</del> often to drink our <lb/>Tea Without Sugar, we could get
                    no<lb/> milk this Evening, not so much <lb/>as to put a Little in our Coffee,
                    nei- <lb/>
                    <pb n="63" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_63"/> -ther had we butter to eat with our
                    <lb/>Buckwheat Cake, and our Vaneson was fryed without fat, and Last Evening
                    <lb/>there was nothing on the Table but <del>mu</del>
                    <lb/>Mush and Milk, this has been a trying <lb/>day to our horses, as I
                    mentioned the <lb/>Morning was Cold and Frozen, and <lb/>our Road led up by the
                    side of <geogName key="tioga">Ty-<lb/>-ago</geogName> River, <del>and</del>
                    which we <del>had it to</del> Cross ed <lb/>eleven times to day and once
                    yes-<lb/>-terday, in 25 miles frequently Belly deep and <lb/>sometimes deeper
                        <del>More</del>
                    <del>in</del>
                    <del>25 miles</del> and where <lb/>we crossed <del>last</del> it last, it was
                    nearly as large as <lb/><geogName key="brand">Bandywine</geogName>, I had like
                    to have forgot to note <lb/><del>that after</del> we had fed the second time
                    <lb/>which was at petersons camp 15 miles, from the last stage <lb/>where there
                    is no house, having to clean<del>ing</del> the snow <lb/>of the Grass to give
                    our horses their Oates <lb/>which was trying to us thus to wait in <del>as</del>
                    our Cold a Con-<lb/>-dition <del>as</del>
                    <del>we were in, to</del>
                    <del>be</del>
                    <del>thus in the Snow</del>
                    <lb/>and pertake of our little Morsall, I say <lb/>a few miles after this, when
                    we were ente-<lb/>-ring on our discouraging road, we <lb/>met a poor distressed
                    family, being <lb/>a Man and his Wife, and five small <lb/>Children, two of whom
                    rode with the Mother <lb/>
                    <pb n="64" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_64"/> one with the Father on a large pack
                    <lb/>of something, and who by themselves, <lb/>some of them were without
                    Stockings Cold as <lb/>it was, to see that those in their distressed, <lb/>much
                    helpless, and Cumbred condition, <lb/>had surmounted all the difficulties
                    <lb/>as to badness of Road, &amp;c that were before <lb/>us, we felt our hearts
                    animated, to pursue our Journey and I <lb/>thought we had no cause in our well
                    <lb/>provided <del>state</del> condition to entertain the least<lb/>
                    discouragement, the family above noted <lb/>had lain in the Woods last night
                    without<lb/> any Camp, the Ground five Inches deep <lb/>with snow, and the
                    weather so Cold that<lb/> abundance of Ice was floating on the <lb/>Waters we
                    had lately Crossed, and they would <lb/>have to encounter the same trials this
                    <lb/>Night as they could reach no house. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-11-21">3rd day the 21</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> set off as soon <del>this Morning</del>
                    <lb/>as was safe, in hopes we should be able <lb/>to reach a friends House this
                    Evening, <lb/>which was very desirable, the Morning <lb/>was Cloudy and very
                    Cold, and we had a <lb/>rough high Country for 10 miles to travel<lb/>
                    <pb n="65" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_65"/> over, on which there were <del>three</del>
                    two remarkable <lb/>eminences the first was so thickly enclosed <lb/>with
                    Hemlock that it afforded very little<lb/> Prospect, beneath our feet, tho
                    through some openings the top of the mountains around appeared the other was
                    Just as <del>you</del> we be-<lb/>-gan to defend from off the <geogName
                        key="laure">Lawrel Hill</geogName>. <lb/>This Prospect was truly grand, we
                    appeared <lb/>to be above the tops of the <geogName key="allem"
                        >Allegenies</geogName>, which <lb/>rose up in a very romantick and wild
                    <lb/>appearance, the View was very extensive <lb/>and these ellevations being
                    white with snow appeared to be almost <lb/>without Timber, so that with the help
                    of fan-<lb/>-cy they looked like improved Farms, hav-<lb/>-ing many places the
                    appearance of square <lb/>Fields, with hedge rows, and divisions, but <lb/>I
                    have no expectation that these inhospital<lb/> regions will ever be <del>a</del>
                    the habitation of man <del>for any</del><lb/><del>thing</del> but for the Wild
                    Beasts of the Forest and the <lb/>Fowls of the Air, fed at the
                        <unclear>foot</unclear> of the <geogName key="laure">Laurel <lb/>
                        hill</geogName> 9 miles in the snow, there being no house, here our
                    <lb/>Road led us down a beautiful Branch of the <lb/><geogName key="lycom"
                        >Lycoming</geogName> tho very much choaked with <lb/>drift wood, some of our
                    company had the <lb/>curiosity to count how many times we <lb/>crossed it in
                    eight miles, where it united <lb/>with the main branch, and the made it about
                    <lb/>28 <del>times</del>, and the <geogName key="lycom">Lycoming</geogName>
                    itself we Crossed<lb/>
                    <pb n="66" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_66"/> perhaps ten times more, these waters make
                    <lb/>a brake through what is called the <geogName key="allem"
                        >Allegenies</geogName>
                    <lb/>and the vale in many places, particularly be-<lb/>fore we come to the main
                        <geogName key="lycom">stream</geogName>, is not more <lb/>than 8 or 10
                    pearches Wide and the <geogName key="allem">Mountains</geogName>
                    <lb/>rise on each hand remarkably high &amp; steep <lb/>so that our traveling
                    was almost litterally<lb/> sneaking under the Hills and Mountains, fed at
                        <lb/><persName key="jkyle1">Kyle’s</persName> 10 miles here we got our
                    dinner, hav-<lb/>-ing Bear Meat and Veneson fryed up to<lb/>gether, Tea without
                    sugar, with good Wheat <lb/>Bread &amp; Butter, in nine Miles from hence <lb/>we
                    finally left the <geogName key="lycom">Lycoming</geogName> a beautiful
                    <lb/>Stream, we thought about as large as two <lb/>of <geogName key="brand"
                        >Brandywine</geogName>, and in six Miles we <lb/>Crossed the <geogName
                        key="loyal">Loyalsock</geogName> a lovely stream, per-<lb/>-haps nearly as
                    large as two of <geogName key="lycom">Lycomon</geogName>
                    <lb/>and got to <persName key="swall1">Samual Wallice’s</persName>, weary, where
                    <lb/>we were kindly, and Hospita<del>bly</del>belly enter-<lb/>-tained, and the
                    Contrast was very great <lb/><del>was very great</del> between our
                    entertain-<lb/>ment here and what we have latterly <lb/>met with, our Beds ever
                    since we came <lb/>from <persName key="ascho1">Asa Schoolies</persName> in
                        <placeName key="upcan">Canada</placeName>, have been <lb/>a small proportion
                    of straw mostly on <lb/>
                    <pb n="67" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_67"/>
                    <del>of straw, except</del> Boards instead of socking <lb/>Bottom, except when
                    we lay in the Woods on <lb/>Bark, they mostly appeared dirty, uniformly
                    <lb/>without any sheet over us, but in lieu thereof <lb/>a Rough Course Blanket,
                    our meal has been <lb/>steadily fryed Veneson sometimes pretty good, <lb/>our
                    Bread for 100 <gap/> miles, with some small <lb/>exceptions, has been
                    indifferent Buckwhea[t] <lb/>cakes, our drink almost ever since we <lb/>left
                    home has been water, Bohea Tea is <lb/>much used in <placeName key="upcan"
                        >Canada</placeName>, which they drink <lb/>very strong, with or without
                    Sugar, as their <lb/>store holds out, they have a great Plenty of <lb/>Sugar
                    Maple, of which some of the Inhabi-<lb/>-tants make a sufficiency for themselves
                    <lb/>but we found a number of them out, not<lb/>withstanding this was their
                    situation, they <lb/>could lay the Teatable for their friends, &amp; <lb/>sit
                    down with as much composure as <lb/>if all were compleat, which I counted <lb/>a
                    piece of Philosophy worth Labouring after</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1797-11-22">4th day the 22</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> a Northeast Wind, and a <lb/>Cold Wet morning, our horses, and our <lb/>selves
                    being weary and wanted <del>some</del> rest <lb/>and being among friends here
                    upon <lb/>
                    <pb n="68" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_68"/> upon Conferrence we thought we should
                    <lb/>feel most easy to see friends in most of the <lb/>meetings on this side the
                        <geogName key="allem">Mountains</geogName>, ex<lb/>-cept <persName
                            key="opaxt1">Oliver Paseton</persName>, who felt his mind <lb/>bound to get
                    home to their Quarterly <lb/>Meeting, and <persName key="jlang1">James
                        Langstaff</persName>, was free<lb/> to go with him for Company, we parted
                    <lb/>with great nearness &amp; heart felt Affecti-<lb/>-on, having traveled in
                    much Brotherly <lb/>love, united in the same cause, Brethren <lb/>in Jeopardy,
                    and Perils, both in the <lb/>Wilderness and among great Waters, &amp; <lb/>now
                    having got thus far safly through <lb/>and among our friends, our hearts<lb/>
                    were enabled to bless the Lord for his <lb/>manifold favours, and under a
                    Sense<lb/> thereof to bid each other farewell. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1797-11-23"/><placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>
                    <del>5th day the 23 a rainy wet day</del></p>
                <p> at <persName key="welli1">William Ellises</persName>, where we arrived <lb/>this
                    Morning 3 miles</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-11-23">5th day the 23</date>
                    <placeName key="fishi"/></dateline>
                <p> a rainy, wet day, attend-<lb/>-ed <orgName key="meetmuncy">Munsy
                        Meeting</orgName>, dined at <persName key="welli1">William
                        <lb/>Ellises</persName> 2 miles, went to <placeName key="fishi"
                        >Fishing</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="69" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_69"/>
                    <placeName key="fishi">Creek</placeName> that evening, William and Wife
                    <lb/>bearing us company, Lodged at <persName key="jclat1">Jacob
                        <lb/>Cleytons</persName> 16 miles </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1797-11-24">6th 23 [sic]</date>
                    <placeName key="fishi"/></dateline>
                <p> a Northwest Wind and pretty <lb/>clear, Went to <orgName key="meetfishi">Fishing
                        Creek Meeting</orgName><lb/> 2 ½ Miles, which was a comforting
                    <lb/>refreshing Opportunity, and my soul <lb/>was enabled to Worship in secret
                    <lb/>dined at <persName key="jeves1">John Eveses</persName> near the Meeting
                    <lb/>house, and with industry got to <placeName key="checkPlace"
                        >Cate-<lb/>-wissee</placeName> that Evening, having the <lb/><geogName
                        key="susqu">Susquehannah</geogName> to Cross <del>15 mile</del>,
                    lod-<lb/>-ged at <persName key="jlloy1">John Loyds</persName> where we were
                    kindly<lb/> entertained, his <del>Wife</del> companion being a neat <lb/>house
                    wife, both <del>the</del> our supper and<lb/> Bed evinced it </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-11-25">7 day the 24 [sic]</date>
                    <placeName key="catta"/></dateline>
                <p> attended the <orgName key="meetcatta">Monthly Meeting <lb/>at
                        Catewissee</orgName>, which was a low exercising <lb/>time in the forepart,
                    but life gradually <lb/>rose under the Ministry of <persName key="jlloy1"
                        >J.L.</persName> till I <lb/>thought I had <del>ever</del> seldom
                    experienced the like, <lb/>it was a memorable time, and ended <lb/>well, and the
                    Business of the Monthly <lb/>
                    <pb n="70" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_70"/> Meeting was transacted in a good degree
                    <lb/>of right order, there are a large num-<lb/>-ber of pretty exemplary
                    concerned <lb/>friends belonging to this Meeting, I<lb/> believe there is no
                    monthly Meeting <lb/>within the compass of our yearly Meet<lb/>-ing that takes
                    in so large a scope of <lb/>Country as this, and the members <lb/>are still
                    spreading wider, we <lb/>were informed there are upwards <lb/>of one hundred and
                    Eighty families <lb/>within its Compass, and I fully be-<lb/>-lieve it will be
                    right, and will conduce <lb/>to the promotion cause of Truth and
                    righte-<lb/>-ousness for a division of the Month-<lb/>-ly Meeting to take place
                    before long, also <lb/>for a preparative meeting to be established at
                        <lb/><placeName key="fishi">Fishing Creek</placeName>, dined at <persName
                        key="jlloy1">John Loyd</persName>’s<lb/> and lodged at <persName
                        key="cchap1">Charles Chapman</persName>s <lb/>2 miles</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1797-11-26">1st day the 26</date>
                    <placeName key="roari"/></dateline>
                <p> a clear day and northWest <lb/>Wind, we had the Opportunity of <lb/>seeing three
                    Wild Deer, out of the <lb/>friends Poarch where we lodged, they <lb/>
                    <pb n="71" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_71"/> passed very Quietly along, we also
                    <lb/>saw another large Buck coming up the <lb/>road toward us, as we were riding
                    to <lb/><orgName>roring Creek Meeting</orgName>, which we at-<lb/>-tended, 4
                    miles it was large, and I hope pro-<lb/>-fitable dined at <persName key="nlee1"
                        >Nathan Lee</persName>s near the <lb/>Meeting house, and Lodged at <persName
                        key="bhayh1">Bezelleel<lb/> Hayherst</persName> 4miles he lives on the edge
                    of <lb/>what is called the <geogName key="lmoun">little Mountain</geogName>, his
                    <lb/>House is the last we came to in <placeName key="roari">Roring <lb/>Creek
                        Settlement</placeName>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-11-27">2nd day the 27</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> a Clear Cold Morning, soon after<lb/> we set off we ascended what is called the
                        <lb/><geogName key="lmoun">little Mountain</geogName>, of which to the
                    Westward <lb/>there is a grand, and very extensive <lb/>prospect, we overlook
                    all <placeName key="roari">Roring<lb/> Creek Valley</placeName>, the <geogName
                        key="susqu">Susquehannah</geogName> down <lb/>as low as <placeName
                        key="numbe">Northumberland</placeName>, and over <lb/>the Tops of <geogName
                        key="munmo">Munsy Mountains</geogName> Quite <lb/>to the <geogName
                        key="munmo">Allegenies</geogName>, we were fully con-<lb/>-vinced when on
                    the top of this Moun<lb/>-tain that we were in a Colder Re-<lb/>-gion, than when
                    on the Plains, for <lb/>
                    <pb n="72" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_72"/> when we left <persName key="welli1">Wiliam
                        Ellises</persName> we pre-<lb/>-sently assended the <geogName key="munmo"
                        >Munsy Mountain</geogName>
                    <lb/>it was a Cold Northeast rain, but not <lb/>in the least Froze on the Trees
                    until <lb/>we began to asscend this eminence <lb/>where the trees became more or
                    less <lb/>Cloathed with Ice, and when we got <lb/>to its <del>highest
                        eminence</del> sumit the young <lb/>Pines were as loaded that many <lb/>of
                    their Tops were bent to the <del>gro</del>
                    <lb/>ground, and when we desended into <lb/>the Valley the Ice on the Limbs was
                    <lb/>not to be seen, but when we got <lb/>on the Top of this Mountain, which
                    <lb/>was two days after, and both clear, <lb/>yet the twigs of the Trees were
                    still <lb/>much covered with sleet, and the<lb/> snow much <del>more</del>
                    deeper than in the Vales <lb/>we got to <persName key="mmasy1">Michal
                            <unclear>Masyers</unclear></persName> that even<lb/>-ing 34 miles, he
                    keeps pretty good accom-<lb/>-modations, and the Cheapest by near one <lb/>half
                    of any that we met with, </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="73" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_73"/>
                <dateline><date when="1797-11-28">3rd day the 28</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>

                <p>a Clear Cold Morning <lb/><geogName key="schri">Schulkill</geogName> nearly
                    Covered with floating <lb/>Ice, went to <persName key="mlee1">Mordica
                        Lees</persName> to Break-<lb/>-fast 15 miles were we were kindly
                    <lb/>hospitabelly entertained Lodged here <lb/>15 miles </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-11-29">4th day the 29</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> attended the <orgName key="">Monthly of <lb/>Maiden Creek</orgName> which was a
                    time of refresh-<lb/>-ment to my Mind, lodged at <persName key="pwile1">Pennose
                        Wily’s</persName>
                    <lb/>1 ½ miles. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-11-30">5th day the 30</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> set off early this Morning <lb/>homewards, a Clear Cold day, stoped to <lb/>see
                        <persName key="fparv1">Francis Parvin</persName> who was very unwell
                    <lb/>when we came to <geogName key="schri">Schulkill</geogName> it looked very
                    <lb/>trying to ride it, by reason of its depth, and of the great<lb/> Quantity
                    of Floating Ice <del>that</del> which covered the <lb/>surfice of the <geogName
                        key="schri">Stream</geogName>
                    <del>and the depth of <lb/>the water</del> , we waited near half an hour
                    <lb/>from the Boat, but the Ferryman after <lb/>considerable exertion failed
                    geting <lb/><del>the boat</del> it over by reason of the ice so that we had at
                    last to encoun-<lb/>-ter the Frozen rugged stream, and through <lb/>mercy got
                    safe <del><gap/></del> >through my mind was <lb/>
                    <pb n="74" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_74"/> was much comforted, as I Rode
                    home-<lb/>-wards this day, with Heavenly consolation
                        <del>good</del><lb/><del>ness</del>, and on looking over our Jour-<lb/>-ney,
                    felt thankful that I had given <lb/>up to the Service, and <del>on</del>
                        ><del>now</del>
                    <del>returning felt</del> feeling <lb/>the sweet reward of Peace therefore
                        <del>fufil</del> bow-<lb/>-ed my Mind into Contrition, and filled it with
                    true<lb/> thankfulness for the present favour. <lb/>got to <persName
                        key="icoat1">Isaac Coates</persName> a little within <lb/>Evening where we
                    were received <lb/>with Open hearts 18 miles.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1797-12-01">12mo 1st</date>
                    <placeName>checkPlace</placeName></dateline>
                <p> after a tendering opportu-<lb/>-nity this morning, wherein we had <lb/>to
                    experience Ancient goodness <lb/> near and to acknowledge that we had <lb/>been
                    helped through many difficul-<lb/>-ties and so far brought safely<lb/> back, had
                    been made near and <lb/>dear to each other, under a fresh <lb/>and renewed sense
                    of so great a <lb/>sorrow we bid each other farewell<lb/>
                    <pb n="75" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_75"/> and set of to our several habitations
                    <lb/>where I arrived in the afternoon &amp; <lb/>was Lovingly received by my
                    Dear <lb/>Wife and Children whom I found <lb/>enjoying a good state of health,
                    for <lb/>which favour, and my own preser-<lb/>-vation while out, I feel truly
                    thank-<lb/>-ful, having been from home Just <lb/>Seven Weeks, and traveled by
                    com-<lb/>-putation near one thousand miles.</p>
            </div>



        </body>
        <back>
            <pb n="80" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_78"/>
            <div type="itinerary">
                <table cols="2">
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">Big spring</cell>
                        <cell role="data">8</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">Buttermilk fall</cell>
                        <cell role="data">6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data"><placeName key="whoak">White Oak Plains</placeName></cell>
                        <cell role="data">20</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">Through the <unclear>Lo</unclear></cell>
                        <cell role="data">5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">To <geogName key="tonaw">Tonewanty</geogName></cell>
                        <cell role="data">8</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">To the plains</cell>
                        <cell role="data">6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">To <geogName key="stony">Stony Creek</geogName></cell>
                        <cell role="data">28</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">To <placeName key="buffa">Buffaloe</placeName></cell>
                        <cell role="data">12</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>----</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>83</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
            <div type="undetermined">
                <pb n="81" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_79"/>
                <p>on Boards instead of Socking Bottom <lb/>except when we lay in the Woods on bark,
                    <lb/>the mostly appeared dirty, uniformly with <lb/>out any Sheet <del>on</del>
                    over us, but in its place <lb/>a rough Coarse Blanket, our meal has been
                    <lb/>steadily fryed Veneson, sometimes pretty good <lb/>nor Bread for 100 or
                    more Miles with some small <lb/>exception has been indifferent Buckwheat
                    <lb/>cakes, our drink almost ever since we left <lb/>home, Water, Bohea Tea is
                    much used in <placeName key="upcan">Canada</placeName>
                    <del>and</del>
                    <lb/>which they drink very strong, they have plenty of sugar Ma-<lb/>-ple and
                    make their own Sugar, tho in many <lb/>places were out, that our Tea was
                    frequently drank <lb/>without, which was our situation in many <lb/>places
                    Since<lb/> --------------------<lb/>
                    <date when="1797-11-22">4th day the 22</date> a Northeast Wind and a Cold
                    <lb/>Wet Morning, feeling our Minds drawn f <lb/>to do, we concluded to attend
                    the Meetings <lb/>belonging to <orgName>Catewissee Monthly Meeting
                    </orgName><lb/>and our horses as well as ourselves wanting <lb/>rest we lay by
                    to day, tomorrow being their <lb/>meeting at <placeName key="muncy"
                        >Munsy</placeName> in Coarse, the, next day to be at <placeName key="fishi"
                        >Fising Creek</placeName>
                    <lb/>and 7 tho to attend their <orgName>Monthly Meeting at<lb/>
                        <placeName key="catta">Catewissee</placeName></orgName>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="accounts">
                <pb n="82" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_80"/>
                <table cols="2">
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data"><unclear>Ex</unclear>
                            <persName key="slee1">Samuel Lee</persName></cell>
                        <cell role="data">4 . 6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data"><unclear>do</unclear>
                            <persName key="jlang1">James Langstaff</persName></cell>
                        <cell role="data">1: 10 . 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data"><unclear>do</unclear>:<persName key="jwils1">James
                                Wilson</persName></cell>
                        <cell role="data">0. 6 . 8</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data"><unclear>do</unclear>: <persName key="opaxt1">Oliver
                                Paseton</persName></cell>
                        <cell role="data">1:17:6</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>


                <p><persName key="jlind1">Jacob Lindley</persName> at <unclear>Pattes</unclear></p>

                <table cols="2">
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">York Money</cell>
                        <cell role="data">1: 2: 6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">for 2 ½ Bushels of Corn</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0. 13: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">do 5 ferridges over <unclear>Cherely</unclear></cell>
                        <cell role="data">0 .. .6. 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">do 18 Quarts of Corn and Buck-<lb/>wheat</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0. 9 : 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">horses at some <unclear>picking</unclear></cell>
                        <cell role="data">0 .2. 6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">Lodging</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 1 :0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at <placeName key="buffa">Buffalo</placeName> 5 suppers
                            and Lodging<lb/> horses at hay one night and 8 Quarts<lb/> of
                            Corn</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0 : 19: 6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">Crossing <geogName key="niagr">Niagara River</geogName>
                            4/each</cell>
                        <cell role="data">1 : 0 : 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">For Oates at the River</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 3: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>--------</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>4:16 :6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data"><persName key="jlind1">Jacob Lindly</persName></cell>
                        <cell role="data">4: 10: 5 ½</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Settled all the above accounts </p>

                <pb n="83" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_81"/>
                <table cols="2">
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data"><persName key="mmasy1">Michal Mosyers</persName></cell>
                        <cell role="data">1 : 2 . 3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">Geo: <unclear>Raver</unclear> 16 quarts of oates</cell>
                        <cell role="data">4: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">1 pint of Cyder Royal</cell>
                        <cell role="data">1 --</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at <persName key="jkyle1">James Kyles</persName> all
                            night</cell>
                        <cell role="data">1: 16 :4</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data"><del><persName key="jlang1">James Langstaff</persName>
                                paid L.1:10</del></cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">16 <gap/> of Oates at the <placeName key="block"
                                >Blockhouse</placeName></cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 6 . 8</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at <persName>Samuel Bartlets</persName>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data">1: 15 . 7</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>-----------</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>5:5 10</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>

                <table cols="2">
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at Lindleys York money</cell>
                        <cell role="data"> 0 14 . <gap/></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at the <placeName key="ppost">Painted Post</placeName> for
                            4 sheaves<lb/> of Oates</cell>
                        <cell role="data"> 0 . 2 . 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at <geogName key="mudcr">Mud Creek</geogName></cell>
                        <cell role="data">1: 13 . 4</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at Bath 19 quarts of Oates at 6 :</cell>
                        <cell role="data">9 . 5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at <persName>Ephraim Sanfords</persName> hay and
                            Oates</cell>
                        <cell role="data">5: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at <persName key="tlee1">Thomas Lees</persName></cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 8: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at <persName key="wpott1">Judge Potters</persName> all
                            night</cell>
                        <cell role="data">1: 2: 6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at Gilberts for ½ bushel of corn</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0 : 2:6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at <placeName key="canan">Canadarque</placeName> ½ do: of
                            oats</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0. 3: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at Thayer’s ¼ of Corn</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0.1.6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at the River for 2 Bushels of Corn</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0 13: -</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at 20 quarts of Oates at <unclear>4</unclear></cell>
                        <cell role="data">0 .6 .8</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">a <unclear>hatched</unclear></cell>
                        <cell role="data">0 : 3:0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">5 ferredges over Chengly River</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 6: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at the river for Oates</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 3: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>--------</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><gap/></cell>
                    </row>

                </table>

                <pb n="84" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_82"/>
                <table cols="2">
                    <row>
                        <cell><gap/></cell>
                        <cell role="data">6 11 <gap/></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at <placeName key="buffa">Buffaloe</placeName> all
                            night</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 19 :0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">Crossing the <geogName key="niagr">Niagara
                                River</geogName></cell>
                        <cell role="data">1: 0: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>----------</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>8: 11: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Settled all the above accounts</p>
                <p>---------------------------------------------------------------------------</p>

                <p>an account of what money I have<lb/> received since we set our faces
                    home-<lb/>wards</p>
                <table cols="3">
                    <row>
                        <cell>11mo 10</cell>
                        <cell role="data">of <persName key="opaxt1">Oliver Paseton</persName> six
                            dollars</cell>
                        <cell role="data">2:30</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell role="data">of <persName key="jlind1">Jacob Lindley</persName> at the
                            river</cell>
                        <cell role="data"> 1: 0 <gap/></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell role="data">of <persName key="jwils1">James Wilson</persName> for 1 ½
                            B of Corn</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0:12</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell role="data">of <persName key="jlind1">Jacob Lindley</persName> at
                                <geogName key="tonaw">Tonewany</geogName></cell>
                        <cell role="data">0:14</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell role="data">of <persName key="jhill2">Joseph Hill</persName></cell>
                        <cell role="data">1: 7: 7</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell role="data">of <persName key="jlind1">Jacob Lindley</persName> at
                            Foxes</cell>
                        <cell role="data">1:14:0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell role="data">of do: at <placeName key="willi"
                            >Williamsburgh</placeName></cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 15: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell role="data">of <persName key="jlang1">James Langstaff</persName> 5
                            dollars</cell>
                        <cell role="data">2: 0 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell role="data">of <persName key="jlind1">Jacobs Lindley</persName> at
                                <geogName key="mudcr">Mud Creek</geogName></cell>
                        <cell role="data">1: 12. 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell role="data">of Do at the Post</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0 : 18 :0</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>

                <table cols="3">
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell role="data">of <persName key="jwils1">James Wilson</persName></cell>
                        <cell role="data">0 . 7: 6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell role="data">of <persName key="jlind1">Jacob Lindley</persName></cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 10 . 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell role="data">of <persName key="jlang1">James
                            Langstaff</persName></cell>
                        <cell role="data">1: 10: 9</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell role="data">of <persName key="opaxt1">Oliver Paseton</persName></cell>
                        <cell role="data">0 : 15 : 0</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>


                <pb n="85" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_83"/>
                <p>An account of what expenses we were <lb/>from <placeName key="upcan"
                        >Canada</placeName> homewards</p>
                <table cols="2">
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">for 4 bushels of Oats at <persName key="ascho1">Ala
                                Schooly’s</persName></cell>
                        <cell role="data">1:4: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">gave his son for care of our horses</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0 . 4. 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">the daughter for Washing</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0 . 6. 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at the river ½ a Bushel Oates</cell>
                        <cell role="data"> 0 : 3: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">5 ferridges across the river</cell>
                        <cell role="data">1: 0 :0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>-------</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at the <placeName key="buffa">Buffaloe</placeName> 6
                            suppers at 2/6</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0 . 15. 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">6 Breakfasts at 2/6</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0. 15.0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">6 Dinners … .at . . 2/6</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0.15.0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">6 Lodgings 2 nights at 6d</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0. 6. 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">6 horses at hay at 6d</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0 . 3 . 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">½ a Bushel of Corn</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0 . 4. 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">1 ½ Bushels of Corn at 8/</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0 . 12 . </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at Lanes 6 horses at hay 24 hours</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0. 12. 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at Lanes do:</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0. 12. 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">still at <placeName key="buffa">Buffaloe</placeName> 6
                            Breakfasts at 2/6</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0.15.0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">6 suppers at . … .2/6</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0.15.0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">6 Lodgings at 6d</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 3: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">5 pecks of Corn at 2/ . . . </cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 10: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">to a poor family in distress </cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 16: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at <geogName key="tonaw">Tonewany</geogName> 6 ferridges
                            at 6d</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 3:0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">5 pints of milk at 6d</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0 .2 .6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">Corn 3 strings</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0 : 9 : 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">1 do: </cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 3: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data"> At Wilbords for Corn and Stalks </cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 8: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>

                <pb n="86" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_84"/>
                <table cols="2">
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">At Fox’s 5 suppers at 2/6 </cell>
                        <cell role="data">0. 12. 6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">horses 2/6</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0.12.6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">1 Bushel of Corn 6/8</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0. 6. 8</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">5 Lodgings . . . at 6d</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0.2.6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at <placeName key="willi">Williamsburg</placeName> ½
                            Bushel of Oates</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 5: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">5 Breakfasts at 2/ar</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0. 10: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at <persName key="sfaul1">Samuel Faulkners</persName>, at
                                <placeName key="danvi">Danville</placeName><lb/> 5 horses all night
                            at 2/6 </cell>
                        <cell role="data">0.12.6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">32 Quarts of Corn and Oates at <unclear>4d</unclear>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data">0:10:8</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">5 suppers 2/ each </cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 10: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">5 breakfasts 2/each </cell>
                        <cell role="data">0:10: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">2 beds </cell>
                        <cell role="data">0. 2. 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at Mr. Wharton 15 quarts of Oates at </cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 5: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at <geogName key="mudcr">Mud Creek</geogName> at
                            Dalsons<lb/> 5 horses at hay at 2/each</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 10: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">32 Quarts of Corn at 4d </cell>
                        <cell role="data">0:10:0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">5 suppers at 2/each </cell>
                        <cell role="data">0:10:0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">Lodging </cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 2: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at the Post one Bushel of Oates </cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 8:0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">5 Breakfast 2/each</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0:10:0</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>

                <table cols="2">
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">At Salsburys 5 horses at hay </cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 8 : 4</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">5 suppers at 9d bedings 3 each </cell>
                        <cell role="data">0 : 5: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">1 Bushel of Corn </cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 6: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">29 quarts at 4</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0:9:8</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at Lambs 5 Breakfasts </cell>
                        <cell role="data">0:10:0</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>

                <pb n="87" facs="SW_JS1797_Page_85"/>
                <p>at the <placeName key="block">Blockhouse</placeName></p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">5 suppers at 2/6 </cell>
                        <cell role="data">0. 12 <gap/></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">36 Quarts of Oates at 5d </cell>
                        <cell role="data">0. 15. 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">7 Sheaves of Straw</cell>
                        <cell role="data">1: 9</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">Lodging </cell>
                        <cell role="data">2. 6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">at <persName key="jkyle1">Kyles</persName> 5 dinners at
                            1/10 ½ each </cell>
                        <cell role="data">0 . 9 : 4 ½</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">16 quarts of Oates at 3d</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 4 : 0</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>


                <table cols="2">
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">3 ferridges over <geogName key="susqu"
                                >Susquehannah</geogName></cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 3: 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">9 quarts of Oates at Leadenburgh</cell>
                        <cell role="data">2: 3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">9 quarts of do: and 1 pint of Cyder</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 2 :3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">Royal at Geo: Ravers </cell>
                        <cell role="data">0. 0 .9</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">At <persName key="mmasy1">Michal Mosyes</persName> 1
                            Bushel of Oates</cell>
                        <cell role="data">3. 9</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">5 horses at Hay</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0 . 3 . 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">3 Suppers 3/9 Lodging 6d</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 4: 3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">one quart of Cyder</cell>
                        <cell role="data">0: 0 : <unclear>5</unclear></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>

            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
