<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei-print.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" hkey="global.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>John Peirce Notes, on a visit to Several Tribes of Indians, 1796: Electronic
                    Edition</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>Cara Ehlenfeldt</name>
                </respStmt>

                <sponsor>Tri-Co Digital Humanities Initiative</sponsor>
                <funder>Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 177 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>This work is the property of the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore
                        College. It may be copied freely by individuals for personal use, research,
                        and teaching (including distribution to classes) as long as this statement
                        of availability is included in the text. It may be linked to freely in
                        Internet editions of all kinds, including for—profit works.</p>
                    <p>Publishers, libraries, and other information providers interested in
                        providing this text in a commercial or non—profit product or from an
                        information server must contact Swarthmore College for licensing and cost
                        information.</p>
                    <p> Scholars interested in changing or adding to these texts by, for example,
                        creating a new edition of the text (electronically or in print) with
                        substantive editorial changes, may do so with the permission of Swarthmore
                        College. This is the case whether the new publication will be made available
                        at a cost or free of charge.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2014">2014</date>
                <idno type="local">SW_JP1796</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Native Americans and Quakers: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>Miscellaneous Manuscripts</collection>
                        <idno>Mss003/111</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>261 pp. (1 volume)</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The John Peirce journal is housed at Friends Historical Library, on the campus of
                    Swarthmore College. In the fall semester of 2010, Swarthmore students enrolled
                    in English 50A (“Reading Red, White, and In-Between in Early American
                    Literature”) transcribed this manuscript as part of a larger project to make the
                    library’s rich store of Quaker Indian mission writings more accessible.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> The transcribers and editor attempted to render the author’s orthography and
                    grammar as they appear on the page of his journal, even when the author’s own
                    spelling and usage are inconsistent. Additionally, many questions remain about
                    spelling the names of his Quaker acquaintances, individual Native Americans who
                    populate his journal, and Indian villages and towns. The transcribers and editor
                    attempted to remain faithful to the author’s Anglicized spellings in all cases. </p>
                <p>The author of the original journal does not include page numbers on his
                    manuscript; the page numbers have been interpolated by the transcribers to
                    correspond with the manuscript sheets.</p>
            </editorialDecl>

        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written in <date when="1796">1796</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Society of Friends</item>

                        <item>Church and state--Ohio</item>

                        <item>Indian reservations</item>
                        <item>Indians of North America--Missions</item>
                        <item>New York (State)--Description and travel</item>
                        <item>Pennsylvania--Description and travel</item>

                        <item>Philadelphia Yearly Meeting of the Religious Society of Friends</item>
                        <item>Quakers--Pennsylvania--Diaries</item>
                        <item>Quakers--Political activity</item>
                        <item>Seneca Indians</item>
                        <item>Society of Friends--Missions</item>
                        <item>Voyages and Travels</item>


                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>

        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>

        <body>
            <div type="undetermined">
                <pb n="preliminary" facs="SW_JP1796_001"/>
            </div>

            <div type="narrative">

                <pb n="1" facs="SW_JP1796_002"/>
                <head>Notes, on a visit to Several Tribes of Indians. 1796<lb/></head>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-05-30">Fifth month 30th</date><placeName key="germa"
                        /></dateline>
                    <p>about<lb/> ten in the morning left<lb/> my Habitation at <placeName
                            key="darby">Darby</placeName>;<lb/> was accompanied by my<lb/> Friends
                            <persName key="jhump1">John Humphreys</persName><lb/> and <persName
                            key="jhunt1">John Hunt</persName> as far as<lb/>
                        <persName key="chain1">Casper Hains’</persName> in <placeName key="germa"
                            >German<lb/>-town</placeName>, where our Company<lb/> had appointed to
                        meet;<lb/> who accordingly attended,<lb/> being as follows, viz. <persName
                            key="irowl1">Isaiah<lb/> Rowland</persName>, <persName key="jcoop1"
                            >James Cooper</persName>,<lb/>
                        <persName key="jsans1">Joseph Sansom</persName>, <persName key="hsimm1"
                            >Henry<lb/> Symmons</persName> &amp; <persName key="ewalk1">Enoch
                            Walker</persName>;<lb/>
                        <pb n="2" facs="SW_JP1796_003"/> here we dined; and after Dinner,<lb/>
                        taking Leave of our Friends,<lb/> we proceeded on to <persName key="dcumm1"
                            >David Cum-<lb/>min</persName>’s this Evening; where<lb/> we lodged.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-05-31">31st</date><placeName key="kingw"/></dateline>
                    <p>Proceeded on, dined at <persName key="opaxt1">Oliver<lb/> Paxtons</persName>,
                        near <placeName key="cofer">Curruls Ferry</placeName><lb/> on <geogName
                            key="delaw">Dalaware</geogName>, from <placeName key="phila"
                            >Phila-<lb/>34.delphia</placeName> about 34 Miles. -<lb/> Thence up the
                        River, and<lb/> crossed at <placeName key="mifer">Michel’s
                        Ferry</placeName>,<lb/> 16.and thence to <placeName key="kingw"
                            >Kingwood</placeName>, 16<lb/> Miles, lodged at <persName key="hclift1"
                            >Henry<lb/> Clifton</persName>’s and <persName key="jalle2">Jon
                            Allen</persName>’s.</p>
                    <p>Between the last mentioned<lb/> Stages crossed a commanding<lb/> Eminence,
                        called <placeName key="calvi">Calvin’s Hill</placeName> which,<lb/>
                        <pb n="3" facs="SW_JP1796_004"/> which I supposed to rise more<lb/>
                        than 200 Feet in perpendi-<lb/>cular Height, and what was<lb/> remarkable,
                        on the Top, or<lb/> near it, was a nearly level<lb/> Meadow, which appeared
                        to be<lb/> a cold <unclear>sour</unclear> Swamp.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-01">Sixth mo. 1st.</date><placeName key="kingw"
                            type="unattested"/></dateline>
                    <p>This Day crossed<lb/> several considerable Moun-<lb/>tains; on some of which
                        we had<lb/> a grand prospect of the ma-<lb/>jestic works of Nature, in
                        an<lb/> extended view of a large Coun-<lb/>try, variegated with less,
                        and<lb/> greater Hills, Valleys, and<lb/> Plains; producing
                        Reflecti-<lb/>ons humbling to my<lb/> Mind <lb/>
                        <pb n="4" facs="SW_JP1796_005"/> we stopped twice at Inns to<lb/> feed
                        our Horses, at one of<lb/> which got some dry victuals<lb/> which served us
                        for a Dinner,<lb/> and arrived in the Evening<lb/> at <persName key="jlund1"
                            >Jacob Lunday’s</persName> in Hard-<lb/>wick County, in
                                <del><unclear>the</unclear></del> Jersey;<lb/> 35.from <placeName
                            key="kingw">Kingwood</placeName> about 35 Miles.</p>
                    <p> This Friend is seated in a<lb/> fertile Valey almost surround<lb/>-ed with
                        Barren Mountains,<lb/> his Wife is public, and has<lb/> visited many of the
                        Meetings<lb/> in this Continent; by which<lb/> means she was both known<lb/>
                        and nearly esteemed by some<lb/> of us; that meeting with<lb/>
                        <pb n="5" facs="SW_JP1796_006"/> her here under her own and<lb/>
                        Husband’s hospitable Roof was<lb/> reviving.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-02">2nd.</date><placeName key="chest"/></dateline>
                    <p>Continued up a kind of a<lb/> Valey, between two considerable<lb/> Mountains,
                        stoped twice at<lb/> Inns to feed, at one of which<lb/> dined, and got to an
                        Inn at<lb/>
                        <placeName key="chest">Chester</placeName> in <placeName key="orang">Orange
                            County</placeName>, in<lb/>50. the Evening; where we lodged 50<lb/>
                        Miles.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-03">3rd.</date><geogName key="nrive"/></dateline>
                    <p>This morning concluded<lb/> to turn a little out of our direct<lb/> Course,
                        for the purpose of fall-<lb/>ing in with some of our Friends,<lb/> rode
                        about 7 Miles to <unclear>Breakfast</unclear>,<lb/> and about 13 more to
                            <persName key="dburn1">Daniel<lb/> Byrns’</persName> on the <geogName
                            key="nrive">North River</geogName>,<lb/>
                        <pb n="6" facs="SW_JP1796_007"/> where we dined, and rested<lb/>
                        ourselves Several Hours; –– -<lb/> Thence up the River about<lb/> 12 Miles,
                        to <persName key="ehall1">Edward Halluck’s</persName>,<lb/> where we lodged,
                        and were<lb/> kindly entertained, he being an<lb/> Ancient Friend of a very
                        kind<lb/> and hospitable Disposition.<lb/> 32.Travailed this Day but 32
                        miles.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <p> Here we Stand two Days &amp;<lb/> rested ourselves, wrote some Letters Home,
                        and attended<lb/> their Meeting on first Day.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-06">6th.</date><placeName key="catsk1"
                        /></dateline>
                    <p>Being Second Day, left our<lb/> agreeable Quarters, and pro-<lb/>ceeded on
                        our Journey, our Gd.<lb/> Friend <persName key="ehall1">Edward
                            Halluck</persName>, accom-<lb/>paning us Several Miles;<lb/>
                        <pb n="7" facs="SW_JP1796_008"/> 20.dined at <placeName key="esopu"
                            >Eusopus</placeName>, about 20 Miles;<lb/> This Town was <del
                            rend="crossout">entirely</del> burnt<lb/> by the English in 1777;
                        and<lb/> has now a Considerable Num-<lb/>ber of good Houses; then<lb/> rode
                        to <placeName key="catsk1">Cats.kill</placeName> where we<lb/>24. Lodged; 24
                        Miles. </p>
                    <p> Here we were entertained<lb/> at a private House; for com-<lb/>ing to the
                        Creek after Night,<lb/> and finding no Inn on this<lb/> Side; the Creek not
                        rideable,<lb/> and no Boat to be had, things<lb/> wore a disagreeable
                        Appearance,<lb/> but a friendly Man, <persName key="jboga1">Jacob<lb/>
                            Bogarder</persName>, being privy to<lb/>
                        <pb n="8" facs="SW_JP1796_009"/> our Distress, very compli-<lb/>santly
                        offered us Entertain-<lb/>ment, which we gratefully<lb/> accepted; and found
                        him<lb/> to be a Man of Intelligence,<lb/> and some Consequence,
                            <del>and</del>living<lb/> in considerable State, for this<lb/> part of
                        the Country.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-07">7th.</date><placeName key="alban"/></dateline>
                    <p>Staid Breakfast this<lb/> Morning at our Lodgings,<lb/> and while it was
                        preparing,<lb/> took a walk with our Land-<lb/>lord to view the following
                        curious Phaeno-<lb/>menon, on his Farm, from<lb/> 60 to 100 Perches from his<lb/>
                        <pb n="9" facs="SW_JP1796_010"/> dwelling House; A Hill<lb/> which laid
                        in the Northwest<lb/> Angle, formed by the Meeting of the <geogName
                            key="nrive">North River</geogName> &amp;<lb/>
                        <geogName key="catsk2">Cats.Kill Creek</geogName> which raised,<lb/> as I
                        supposed from 100 to 150<lb/> feet of perpendicular Height,<lb/> from the
                        Bed of said Waters, three<lb/> Days since, broke near the Extre-<lb/>mity of
                        the Ellivation; and one<lb/> part of it sunk almost perpen-<lb/>dicularly
                        down between 50 &amp;<lb/> 60 feet, next adjoining the great-<lb/>est
                        Elevation, and gradually up<lb/> toward the Declivity of<lb/> the Hill,
                        leaving the ground<lb/> almost level; the Quantity<lb/> moved was about two
                        Acres; we<lb/> walked over the Ground, and<lb/>
                        <pb n="10" facs="SW_JP1796_011"/> indeed it was an amazing and<lb/>
                        Solemn Sight, the Stupendous<lb/> Cracks and broken Earth made<lb/> an awful
                        appearance; The<lb/> Inhabitants of a small town over the Creek saw it
                        going, and<lb/> were much alarmed, supposing<lb/> it to have been the
                        Beginning<lb/> of an Earthquake, but they<lb/> heard no rumbling, nor
                        discovered<lb/>any Shock: there was also on this<lb/> Hill when it sunk a
                        flock of<lb/> Sheep grazing, which appeared<lb/> much frighted with the
                        first<lb/> Motion of the Earth, <del>and</del>(as it<lb/> sunk gradually)
                        and ran vio-<lb/>lently several Courses at first,<lb/> but quickly gathered
                        all close<lb/>
                        <pb n="11" facs="SW_JP1796_012"/> together, near the Center, and<lb/>
                        went down with the Ground,<lb/> and received no hurt. </p>
                    <p> After Breakfast ferried over<lb/> this Creek, and proceeded on,<lb/> dined
                        at <persName key="ehall2">Edward Halluck Junr.</persName><lb/> at a small
                        Town, on the<lb/>
                        <geogName key="nrive">North River</geogName>, called <placeName key="balti"
                            >Baltimore</placeName>,<lb/> from our Last Stage about 22 miles<lb/>
                        42.thence to <placeName key="alban">albany</placeName>, about 20 miles,<lb/>
                        here we put up our Horses<lb/> at an Inn, and lodged some<lb/> of us at a
                        Friend’s House, and<lb/> others of us at a friendly Man’s<lb/> named
                            <persName key="tspen1">Thomas Spencer</persName>, where<lb/> we were
                        kindly entertained. </p>
                    <p> This we are informed is<lb/> the oldest City in the Conti-<lb/>nent, but it
                        appears a poor<lb/>
                        <pb n="12" facs="SW_JP1796_013"/> place; they have no regular<lb/>
                        Market; the Streets are ex-<lb/>tremely irregular, crooked and<lb/> dirty;
                        the walks on each Side,<lb/> are paved with very indifferent<lb/> Stone, the
                        middles generally<lb/> not paved at all: They Say<lb/> there are better than
                        1000<lb/> Houses in this place, and<lb/> some of them are three<lb/> Stories
                        and otherways good<lb/> and handsome Buildings;<lb/> but the greater part
                        appear<lb/> to be old &amp; inconvenient, of one,<lb/> one and an half and
                        two sto-<lb/>ries, mostly of brick on <emph rend="underline"
                        >Wood.</emph></p>
                    <pb n="13" facs="SW_JP1796_014"/>
                    <p> Here we received Informa-<lb/>tion from a Man who had<lb/> been in the
                        Indian Coun-<lb/>try that the greater part<lb/> of the <orgName key="oneida"
                            >Oneida</orgName>, <orgName key="onondaga">Onondaga</orgName> &amp;<lb/>
                        <orgName key="cayugaind">Cayuga</orgName> Reservations had<lb/> been lately
                        purchased by<lb/> the State of New York:<lb/> This Information a little<lb/>
                        alarmed us, and we concluded<lb/> it expedient to wait on the<lb/> Surveyor
                        General at his Office<lb/> in this Town; and two of us<lb/> being named for
                        that Ser-<lb/>vice, we accordingly went to<lb/> his Office, and found
                        him<lb/> a very obliging and inteligent<lb/> man,<lb/>
                        <pb n="14" facs="SW_JP1796_015"/> Man, and he marked out on<lb/> our
                        Map, what had been pur-<lb/>chased, and what was still<lb/> reserved; by
                        which we were<lb/> fully satisfied with Regard<lb/> to the Quantity of Land
                        still<lb/> in possession of the Indians:<lb/> This Interview was on the<lb/>
                        Morning of the 8th Instant;<lb/> and in the Afternoon we<lb/> concluded to
                        move forward;<lb/> and accordingly rode to <placeName key="schen"
                            >Sche-<lb/>nectady</placeName> a Town on the<lb/>14. <geogName
                            key="mohaw">Mohawk River</geogName> 14 Miles<lb/> from <placeName
                            key="alban">Albany</placeName>.</p>
                    <p> Here we lodged at a good Inn<lb/> kept by English people; our<lb/>
                        <pb n="15" facs="SW_JP1796_016"/> Entertainment and Attendance<lb/>
                        excited Admiration, being equal,<lb/> especially in the Womans
                        de-<lb/>partment, to almost any thing<lb/> in that way, in the City of<lb/>
                        <placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName>: This is a<lb/> Smart Town
                        containing, as they<lb/> say, about 600 Houses many<lb/> of them good
                        Buildings: from<lb/> here the <geogName key="mohaw">Mohawk</geogName> is
                        boatable<lb/> upwards of 100 Miles; but the<lb/> Navigation is so
                        extremely<lb/> difficult, by reason of Shoal<lb/> Water and Rapids, that, if
                        the<lb/> Roads were good, Land Carriage<lb/> would be preferable:
                        Between<lb/> here and the <geogName key="nrive">North River</geogName><lb/>
                        is a large falls, which occasions<lb/> a<lb/>
                        <pb n="16" facs="SW_JP1796_017"/> a carrying place from Albany<lb/>
                        here of 14 miles.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-09">9th.</date><placeName key="cagna"/></dateline>
                    <p>This Morning crossed the <geogName key="mohaw">Mo-<lb/>hawk</geogName> in a
                        Boat, continued up<lb/> the River between two Moun-<lb/>tains; the flats on
                        each Side<lb/> the River appeared fertile,<lb/> but narrow; in about 20
                        miles<lb/> came to old general <persName key="wjohn3"
                        >Jonstons</persName><lb/> Seat; it was a large Stone House,<lb/> for this
                        part of the Country; and<lb/> had Some out Houses of a curious<lb/>
                        Structure; dined at <emph rend="underline"><placeName key="cagna"
                                >Cagnawago</placeName></emph>,<lb/> 25. from <placeName key="schen"
                            >Schenectady</placeName> 25 miles: This<lb/> is an Indian Name, the
                        Etymology<lb/> of which is, <emph rend="underline">Cag</emph>
                        <emph rend="underline">in</emph>
                        <emph rend="underline">the Wagon.</emph></p>
                    <p> Here <persName key="jjohn4">John Jonston</persName>, son of<lb/> old
                            <persName key="wjohn3">William Jonston</persName>, with about <lb/><pb
                            n="17" facs="SW_JP1796_018"/> 600 Indians and Regulars,<lb/> did
                        much mischief, in the<lb/> Time of the American War;<lb/> they burnt the
                        Country for<lb/> about 40 Miles up and down<lb/> the River, and many of
                        the<lb/> Inhabitants lost their Lives,<lb/> amongst which was the
                        parents,<lb/> and other Connections of our<lb/> Present Landlady, which
                        has<lb/> tended <del><gap/></del>to embitter her<lb/> Mind against the
                        Natives<lb/> to this Day.</p>
                    <p> Thence up the River to<lb/>
                        <persName key="jspra1">Jacob Spraker</persName>’s, who keeps a ferry<lb/>
                        over the <geogName key="mohaw">Mohawk</geogName>, where we<lb/> lodged: He
                        has a gracious<lb/> House<lb/>
                        <pb n="18" facs="SW_JP1796_019"/> House on the Outside, but<lb/>
                        within, in most respects, below<lb/> indifferent; from our last<lb/>10.
                        Stage 10 Miles.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-10">10th.</date><placeName key="white"
                        /></dateline>
                    <p>Crossed the River in a<lb/>9. Boat, and rode about 9 Miles<lb/> to Breakfast:
                        here, and for<lb/> Some Miles back, the<lb/> fertile Flats are much<lb/>
                        wider than they were for<lb/> Some Distance, where we<lb/> rode yesterday
                        morning:</p>
                    <p> In the Course of this Stage,<lb/> riding up the River, and ob-<lb/>serving
                        the fertility of the Land,<lb/> and particularly that of the<lb/>
                        <pb n="19" facs="SW_JP1796_020"/> Flats on each Side of the River,<lb/>
                        which a few years ago were<lb/> occupied by the Indians, my<lb/> Mind was
                        tendered in reflecting<lb/> on their Situation; how they<lb/> are tossed
                        from place to place,<lb/> and deprived of their Lands,<lb/> almost as soon
                        as their<lb/> fertility becomes known to<lb/> the white people; and it<lb/>
                        settled in my Mind, that<lb/> it could hardly be the Will<lb/> of the great
                        Founder of the<lb/> Universe, that this valu-<lb/>able Country should
                        remain<lb/> unimproved; and that therefore,<lb/> the only Means, whereby the<lb/>
                        <pb n="20" facs="SW_JP1796_021"/> Natives can secure to
                        them-<lb/>selves their possessions, is<lb/> to endeavor to improve<lb/> in
                        Civilization, and in the<lb/> holy fear of the Lord; becoming<lb/> gradually
                        a religiously organ-<lb/>ized Body.</p>
                    <p> Thence up the River about<lb/> 18 Miles further and dined<lb/>18. at a place
                        called the <placeName key="gefla">German<lb/> Flats</placeName>; here we
                        were informed,<lb/> that these Flats, for Several<lb/> Miles back of this
                        place, have<lb/> been settled with white peo-<lb/>ple for near 80 years,
                        and<lb/> we observed in the Course of<lb/> our last stage several old<lb/>
                        <pb n="21" facs="SW_JP1796_022"/> Houses, and Orchards, the
                        Ap-<lb/>pearance of Which accorded<lb/> with this Information:</p>
                    <p> We also saw many Sugar<lb/> Maples in this Day’s ride, one<lb/> of which was
                        four feet over;<lb/> but generally from <emph rend="underline">one</emph> to<lb/>
                        <emph rend="underline">two</emph>, and two and a half.</p>
                    <p> We are also informed, that<lb/> notwithstanding the fertility<lb/> of the
                        Land here, there is ve-<lb/>ry Little Grain of any kind<lb/> raised for
                        Market: the Land<lb/> being generally in possession<lb/> of the <gap/>
                        Dutch, and their De-<lb/>scendents; who have a Character<lb/> here directly
                        opposed to that of their<lb/>
                        <pb n="22" facs="SW_JP1796_023"/> Country People in
                        Pennsyl-<lb/>vania.</p>
                    <p> Thence up the River<lb/> to a little Village called <placeName key="fschy"
                            >Fort-<lb/>Schuyler</placeName> 18 Miles from our<lb/> last Stage; here
                        we crossed <del>the<lb/> River</del>on a Bridge, and pro-<lb/>ceeded on to
                            <placeName key="white">White’s Town</placeName><lb/> 4 Miles further,
                        where we<lb/>22. lodged.</p>
                    <p> Twelve or fifteen Miles of<lb/> this last Stage was through a<lb/> new
                        Settled Country; the Land<lb/> appears good, &amp; the Settlements<lb/>
                        rapid and thriving; the Set-<lb/>lers mostly from New England,<lb/> but some
                        from New Jersey:<lb/>
                        <pb n="23" facs="SW_JP1796_024"/> These people generally build<lb/>
                        their Houses contiguous to<lb/> each other, and are content<lb/> with small
                        Farms; many<lb/> of them not more than<lb/> 100 Acres with the
                        Allowance<lb/> that the Country for many<lb/> Miles together along the great
                        Road resembles<lb/> a scattered Village.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-11">11th.</date><placeName key="oneid"
                            type="unattested"/></dateline>
                    <p>This morning had<lb/> a Conference together at<lb/> our Lodgings and
                        being<lb/> now near the Indian<lb/> Country, we felt our<lb/> Minds
                        seriously impressed<lb/> with an increasing weight<lb/> of the Business we
                        are <lb/><pb n="24" facs="SW_JP1796_025"/> engaged in; and united
                        in<lb/> the expediency of keeping<lb/> Minutes of our proceedings<lb/>
                        therein; and one of our<lb/> Number was appointed<lb/> to that Service.</p>
                    <p> After which we had<lb/> a satisfactory Conference<lb/> with <persName
                            key="wfloy1">Col. Floyd</persName>, one of the<lb/> Superintendants
                        appointed<lb/> by the Government of<lb/> New York to the Special<lb/> Care
                        and Oversight of the<lb/>
                        <orgName key="brotherton">Brothertown Indians</orgName>; and<lb/> he
                        informed us, that this<lb/> Tribe is sufficiently provided<lb/> for, in all
                        necessary agricultural<lb/> Implements &amp;c. and that they<lb/>
                        <pb n="25" facs="SW_JP1796_026"/> Stand in no need of any
                        Assis-<lb/>tance from us, except in Ad-<lb/>vice, Instruction &amp;c. and
                        also<lb/> that it would be very desirable<lb/> to him, and those
                        connected<lb/> with him, that one of our<lb/> Friends should reside for<lb/>
                        Some time with this tribe<lb/> in the Capacity of an In-<lb/>structor in
                        Husbandry &amp;c.<lb/> which proposition is re-<lb/>ferred for future
                        Considera-<lb/>tion, when we may be more<lb/> fully acquainted with the<lb/>
                        Situation of the neighbour-<lb/>ing Tribes.</p>
                    <pb n="26" facs="SW_JP1796_027"/>
                    <p> This respectable Man also<lb/> informed us, that he believed<lb/> the
                        general Disposition of<lb/> the people in those parts,<lb/> tho’ so near the
                        frontiers, would<lb/> be very favorable to our Bu-<lb/>siness; which was to
                        our En-<lb/>couragement; as we had met<lb/> with Evincements of a<lb/>
                        contrary Disposition<lb/> about 40 Miles further<lb/> down the River.</p>
                    <p> After Dinner agreed to go<lb/> forward into the Indian Country;<lb/> we were
                        informed it was about<lb/> 20 Miles to the <orgName key="stockbridge"
                            >Stockbridge</orgName><lb/> Settlement, where we wished<lb/>
                        <pb n="27" facs="SW_JP1796_028"/> to go this Evening: We rode<lb/>
                        about 9 miles through the<lb/> white Settlements, and stopping<lb/> at a
                        House to enquire the<lb/> way, we found it to be the last<lb/> belonging to
                        white people:</p>
                    <p> Here we met with an In-<lb/>dian, who knowing, or at least<lb/> mistrusting
                        us, by our Appear<lb/>ance, shewed great Friendship,<lb/> calling us
                        Brothers &amp; Quakers,<lb/> and offered to pilot us to the<lb/> Indian
                        Settlement; but being<lb/> much in Liquor, and having a<lb/> Gun and
                        Hatchet, it appeared<lb/> some Trial to accept his Of-<lb/>fer; more
                        especially as the<lb/> Evening was approaching;<lb/>
                        <pb n="28" facs="SW_JP1796_029"/> but understanding the Road<lb/> was
                        difficult, and not a single<lb/> House to be found on it, we<lb/> at length
                        concluded to Submit<lb/> to it: He was one of the <orgName key="oneida"
                            >Oneida’s</orgName>,<lb/> and appeared very wild and sa-<lb/>vage, and
                        would frequently make<lb/> a loud, and frightful shouting<lb/> as he went
                        through the Woods;<lb/> but he brought us Safe to a<lb/> Small Indian
                        Settlement of<lb/> the <orgName key="oneida">Oneidas</orgName>, within about
                        three<lb/> Miles of <persName key="haupa1">Captain
                        Hendricks</persName>,<lb/> Chief of the <orgName key="stockbridge"
                            >Stockbridge</orgName>, where<lb/> we had proposed going, but<lb/> Night
                        being come upon us,<lb/> we concluded to take up our<lb/> Lodging here;
                        which we<lb/>
                        <pb n="29" facs="SW_JP1796_030"/> accordingly did, having rid-<lb/>den
                        about 17 miles, of Such<lb/>17. Roads, particularly the<lb/> last half of
                        it, as none of<lb/> our company excepting<lb/> our Indian Guide, had<lb/>
                        ever seen before.</p>
                    <p> Here we began our Indian<lb/> Fare, took our Blankets for our<lb/> Beds, and
                        Saddles for our <unclear>pillows</unclear>;<lb/> and supped on Milk, with
                        a<lb/> little Indian Bread in it, having<lb/> wooden spoons, or Ladles
                        to<lb/> sup it out of a large general<lb/> Reservoir:</p>
                    <p> But I believe we were all<lb/> favored with quiet and easy<lb/> Minds;
                        though we were cold<lb/> in the Night, and Sore and<lb/>
                        <pb n="30" facs="SW_JP1796_031"/> Stiff in the Morning. </p>
                    <p> The Name of our Host was<lb/>
                        <persName key="hsmit1">Hendrick Smith</persName>, who with his<lb/> Brother
                        in law, a Stockbridge, could<lb/> talk a little English: He had<lb/> 18 Head
                        of horned Cattle, Several<lb/> of his Cows were excellent; he<lb/> had about
                        three Acres of Indian<lb/> Corn planted, and enclosed, and<lb/> a grass Lot
                        of nearly equal<lb/> Dimensions also enclosed; and<lb/> had made some
                        preparations<lb/> for building a new House; but<lb/> he said he was afraid
                        to build;<lb/> for by and by his Chiefs would<lb/> sell the Land to white
                        people,<lb/> and then he should have to<lb/> leave it; he wished we
                        would<lb/> make their Chiefs divide<lb/>
                        <pb n="31" facs="SW_JP1796_032"/> the Land and let every one<lb/> have
                        his own Share; and<lb/> then, he said, he would clear<lb/> a great deal:
                        This he and<lb/> his Brother-in-law informed us,<lb/> was what the Indians
                        wanted;<lb/> but their Chiefs would not<lb/> agree to it.</p>
                    <p> This Sentiment appeared<lb/> to be accompanied with<lb/> Rationality, and
                        some of<lb/> us were ready to adopt Se-<lb/>cret Conclusions, that it<lb/>
                        would be our Duty to give<lb/> it our Interest; but upon<lb/> further
                        acquaintance with<lb/> those people, and more minute-<lb/>ly investigating
                        the Subject,<lb/> we found, that it<lb/>
                        <pb n="32" facs="SW_JP1796_033"/> had its origin, perhaps with<lb/> the
                        greater part who<lb/> approved it, in a Disposition<lb/> very contrary to
                        what we would<lb/> wish to encourage amongst<lb/> them; viz. that of being
                        indivi-<lb/>dually able to sell and lease<lb/> Lands to the white people;
                        which<lb/> power had been heretofore suf-<lb/>ficiently proven
                        prejudicial<lb/> to several of the Tribes, now<lb/> living in this
                        reservation, by<lb/> tending finally to root them<lb/> out of their native
                        possessions.</p>
                    <p> There nevertheless appears<lb/> great Room for prudent Exer-<lb/>tions to
                        encourage and assist<lb/> these people, in falling up-<lb/>on some safe plan
                        of securing<lb/>
                        <pb n="33" facs="SW_JP1796_034"/> to Individuals, and their
                            <del>Offsp</del><lb/> Offspring, the Fruits of their<lb/> Industry: for
                        whilst Improve-<lb/>ments remain in the present<lb/> precarious State, the
                        reflecting<lb/> Mind must inevitably feel<lb/> a Strong
                            <unclear>blunt</unclear> to the Stimulus<lb/> of Action.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-12">12th.</date><placeName key="oneid"
                            type="unattested"/></dateline>
                    <p>This Morning our Indian<lb/> Host, came in and told us his<lb/> Horse was
                        dead, he had been<lb/> ailing about three weeks; and<lb/> that this was the
                        eleventh Horse<lb/> which he had lost within five<lb/> years: this Accorded
                        with an<lb/> Account we had before received<lb/> of the Mortality of Horses
                        in<lb/> this Country.</p>
                    <p> About eight o’clock clock <persName key="haupa1">Cap. Hendricks<lb/>
                            <pb n="34" facs="SW_JP1796_035"/> Aupaumut</persName>, principle
                        Chief<lb/> of the <orgName key="stockbridge">Stockbridge Nation</orgName>,
                        and to<lb/> whom we had sent a Runner<lb/> the Evening before, came,
                        with<lb/> two others of his Tribe, to meet<lb/> us, and conduct us to his
                        Town;<lb/> with whom we went, and ariving<lb/> at his Habitation, we were
                        a<lb/> little surprised with the <unclear>smalness</unclear><lb/> and
                        meanness of it; but having<lb/> no prospect of bettering ourselves,<lb/> we
                        very deliberately lit, and after<lb/> some time ventured in, but our<lb/>
                        surprise was soon turned into<lb/> astonishment, when we saw<lb/> the Table
                        spread for our Break-<lb/>fast; the Tea Tackling was<lb/> brought out; good
                        wheat Bread,<lb/>
                        <pb n="35" facs="SW_JP1796_036"/> and Butter of a superlative
                        Qua-<lb/>lity made their appearance; that,<lb/> in short, we had a first
                        Rate<lb/> Pennsylvania Breakfast.</p>
                    <p> This being first Day, we<lb/> felt our Minds engaged, to set<lb/> down
                        together, to feel after inward<lb/> Stillness, and ability to perform<lb/>
                        Spiritual Worship; and about<lb/> eleven OClock, having obtained<lb/> leave
                        of our Host, who appears<lb/> a serious, sensible Man, we sat<lb/> down, in
                        Company with him,<lb/> his Family, and Several of<lb/> his Indian Neighbors,
                        who,<lb/> without any Invitation from us,<lb/> came in; they
                            <unclear>sat</unclear> in a good<lb/> Degree <unclear>Solid</unclear>,
                        and appeared<lb/> thoughtful<lb/>
                        <pb n="36" facs="SW_JP1796_037"/> thoughtful; but, as I conceived,<lb/>
                        shewed some Uneasiness with<lb/> our Silence: A few Words were<lb/> Spoken,
                        informing that none<lb/> of our Number were public<lb/> Ministers, and
                        pointing out<lb/> the necessity of inward and<lb/> Spiritual Worship.</p>
                    <p> In the Evening of this Day<lb/> had a Conference with
                        <del>several</del><lb/> several of the Chiefs and Coun-<lb/>selors of the
                            <orgName key="stockbridge">Stockbridge nation</orgName>,<lb/> at the
                        House of our Host <persName key="haupa1">Cap.<lb/> Hendrick</persName>; in
                        which he made<lb/> us a speech, expressive of their<lb/> Gladness to See us;
                        and that we<lb/> were heartily welcome to their<lb/> Town; then proceeded to inform<lb/>
                        <pb n="37" facs="SW_JP1796_038"/> us of their former and present<lb/>
                        Situation, which he did with<lb/> great Clearness, and precision:</p>
                    <p> We then briefly informed them<lb/> of our motives for coming to<lb/> their
                        Country; and adjourned<lb/> to meet their whole Nation,<lb/> in general
                        Council tomorrow<lb/> Morning at 10 OClock.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-13">13th.</date><placeName key="oneid"
                            type="unattested"/></dateline>
                    <p>Within about an hour of the<lb/> Time appointed, the Indians<lb/> generally
                        met, made us a<lb/> Short Speech, expressing their<lb/> Gladness to see us,
                        and apolo-<lb/>gising for their Deficiency<lb/> with regard to the Hour
                        ap-<lb/>pointed; we then proceeded to<lb/> inform them of the Nature<lb/> of
                        our Business, and read<lb/> our<lb/>
                        <pb n="38" facs="SW_JP1796_039"/> our Certificate to them; after<lb/>
                        which we were enabled, pretty<lb/> clearly to point out to them<lb/> many of
                        the obvious Causes<lb/> of their present Inferiority,<lb/> in point of
                        Living, to the White<lb/> people; together with the means<lb/> whereby this
                        disparity might<lb/> be removed, greatly to the Advan-<lb/>tage of them and
                        their posterity,<lb/> with which they appeared to<lb/> be satisfied; and
                        after a short<lb/> Consultation amongst themselves,<lb/> they informed us,
                            <q>that they had<lb/> Listened to us with Attention,<lb/> and had, as it
                            were, swallowed<lb/> down our Words, and should<lb/> deeply consider
                            them;</q> after<lb/>
                        <pb n="39" facs="SW_JP1796_040"/> which they would give us<lb/> their
                        Mind on the different<lb/> Subjects recommended to th<emph rend="underline"
                            >em.</emph></p>
                    <p> From several private Con-<lb/>ferences with some of their Chiefs<lb/> we
                        learn, that the <orgName key="stockbridge">Stockbridge<lb/>
                            Indians</orgName> (who are not of the <orgName key="Five Nations"
                            >five<lb/> Nations</orgName>) consist of about sixty<lb/> Families, and
                        300 Individuals;<lb/> The possess 23040 Acres of<lb/> excellent Land, which
                        was given<lb/> to them by the <orgName key="oneida">Oneidas</orgName>;
                        about<lb/> the Close of the American War;<lb/> and was confirmed by
                        deed,<lb/> containing a Clause baring<lb/> against their selling or
                        leasing<lb/> to white people: They divide<lb/> their Land into 100 Acre
                        Lots;<lb/> and every Family has one Lot;<lb/>
                        <pb n="40" facs="SW_JP1796_041"/> and every Son is to have a Lot,<lb/>
                        laid off by a certain Order un-<lb/>til the whole is Occupied: They<lb/>
                        have a sawmill, three Carts, three<lb/> pair of good Oxen, and perhaps<lb/>
                        some other Things which they<lb/> enjoy in common; but in gene-<lb/>ral they
                        possess their Improve-<lb/>ments, and other Fruits of their<lb/> Industry as
                        private property;<lb/> and even buy and sell, of and to<lb/> the white
                        people and one an-<lb/>other; sometimes giving their<lb/> Notes and
                        Obligations in like<lb/> Manner with them: and we<lb/> are informed our
                        Host, <persName key="haupa1">Cap.<lb/> Hendrick</persName>, raised near 100
                        Bus.<lb/> of wheat last year, besides a<lb/> Quantity of Indian Corn.</p>
                    <pb n="41" facs="SW_JP1796_042"/>
                    <p> They have also an Income<lb/> from general Government<lb/> of 350 Dollars a
                        year: They<lb/> do not appear ignorant in<lb/> any considerable Degree,
                        of<lb/> good Matters of tilling their<lb/> Ground: most Families have<lb/>
                        one Cow, and some of them<lb/> have Several; that little appears<lb/> to be
                        wanting here but a spi-<lb/>rit of Industry, Sobriety and fru-<lb/>gality,
                        to make these people,<lb/> not only tolerable, but easy<lb/> in their
                        Circumstances: <del>and</del>
                        <lb/> to this End a skillful provision<lb/> for the Security of private
                        In-<lb/>terest might much contribute.</p>
                    <p> Here it may be seasonable<lb/> to<lb/>
                        <pb n="42" facs="SW_JP1796_043"/> to remark, that we have<lb/> found,
                        since we came to this<lb/> Place, serious Occasion for<lb/> the Necessity of
                        Friends, both<lb/> in a collective and private<lb/> Capacity, being
                        scrupulously<lb/> guarded in the Letters they<lb/> send to these people; for
                        we<lb/> find them very ingenious<lb/> in construing them to their<lb/> own
                        advantage; and they<lb/> appear to hold them little<lb/> inferior, in point
                        of Obligation<lb/> to the most absolute Contrasts.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-14">14th.</date><placeName key="stock"
                        /></dateline>
                    <p>Attended a general Coun-<lb/>cil of the <orgName key="oneida"
                            >Oneida’s</orgName>, at their<lb/>
                        <pb n="43" facs="SW_JP1796_044"/> Town, about four Miles from<lb/> the
                            <orgName key="stockbridge">Stockbridge</orgName> Settlement;<lb/> and in
                        about two Hours after<lb/> the Time appointed they<lb/> collected; and the
                        Business<lb/> was opened by a short<lb/> Speech on their part,
                        ex-<lb/>pressing their Gladness<lb/> to see their old Friends<lb/> the
                        Quakers, that we might<lb/> speak Face to face. We<lb/> then briefly
                        informed them<lb/> of our Errand into their Coun-<lb/>try; and finding that
                        we had<lb/> a very imperfect Interpre-<lb/>ter, we confided to adjourn<lb/> the<lb/>
                        <pb n="44" facs="SW_JP1796_045"/> the Council ‘til 5th Day<lb/> the
                        16th. at ten OClock<lb/> in the morning, and re-<lb/>quested the Attendance
                        of<lb/> their Women and young<lb/> people: then returned<lb/> to our
                        Lodgings at <placeName key="stock">Stockbridge</placeName>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-15">15th.</date><placeName key="stock"
                        /></dateline>
                    <p>This morning three of<lb/> our Number attended with<lb/> several of the
                            <orgName key="stockbridge">Stockbridge</orgName><lb/> Chiefs and
                        principle men,<lb/> in consulting the best me-<lb/>thods of repairing their
                        Saw-<lb/>mill Dam, whilst others of<lb/> our Company were employed<lb/> in a
                        useful Improvement at<lb/> our Lodgings.</p>
                    <pb n="45" facs="SW_JP1796_046"/>
                    <p> In the Afternoon attended<lb/> a general Council of a small<lb/> Body of the
                            <orgName key="tuscarora">Tuscororas</orgName>, who live<lb/> on
                        sufferance upon the<orgName key="oneida"> Oneida</orgName><lb/> Lands; these
                        people consist of<lb/> twelve Families, about 58 In-<lb/>dividuals, have 43
                        horned Cat-<lb/>tle, 2 Yoke of Oxen, and one plow;<lb/> and have the Offer
                        of 200 Acres<lb/> of Land to a family by the<lb/> Oneidas; but only three
                        of<lb/> their Number have yet taken<lb/> up with the Offer; they be-<lb/>ing
                        generally too indolent to<lb/> enclose, clear and till Land<lb/> when given
                        to them; although<lb/> the Land here is of an excel-<lb/>lent Quality, and
                        easy of Culture.</p>
                    <pb n="46" facs="SW_JP1796_047"/>
                    <p> They also conceive themselves<lb/> under some Difficulties with<lb/> Regard
                        to the <orgName key="oneida">Oneidas</orgName> Offer<lb/> of Land; as they
                        refuse to se-<lb/>cure any Quantity to them<lb/> in a National Capacity;
                        but<lb/> merely admit them to indivi-<lb/>dually enjoy the aforesaid
                        Quan-<lb/>tity in like Manner with<lb/> their own people; and sub-<lb/>ject
                        to the future disposal<lb/> of the <orgName key="oneida">Oneida</orgName>
                        Chiefs.</p>
                    <p> These people reminded us<lb/> of an Expectation given them<lb/> by Friends
                        at a late Treaty,<lb/> of a Compensation for some<lb/> Lands settled by Friends<lb/>
                        <pb n="47" facs="SW_JP1796_048"/> and others in a certain place<lb/> in
                        Virginia; where they sup-<lb/>pose themselves to have some<lb/> Claim: this
                        led us into a<lb/> particular Enquiry into the<lb/> Nature of their Claim;
                        but<lb/> we found them very imperfect<lb/> in their Knowledge of the<lb/>
                        Matter, so that we could get<lb/> no Light from them on the<lb/>
                        Subject.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-16">16th.</date><placeName key="stock"
                        /></dateline>
                    <p>Again attended the ge-<lb/>neral Council of the <orgName key="oneida"
                            >Oneida’s</orgName>;<lb/> they assembled as usual, more<lb/> than an
                        hour after the time<lb/> appointed; and opened the<lb/> Council with a short
                        welcome;<lb/> we<lb/>
                        <pb n="48" facs="SW_JP1796_049"/> we now had <persName key="jreed1"
                            >Cap. Jacob Reed</persName><lb/> for our Interpreter, who had<lb/> been
                        educated in an English<lb/> School: We again opened the<lb/> Nature of our
                        Business; and read<lb/> our Certificate from our friends<lb/> to them; after
                        which we proceeded<lb/> to shew them the Advantage and<lb/> necessity of a
                        Change in their<lb/> Manner of Life; that their young<lb/> Men ought to
                        work, and be indus-<lb/>trious to plow and sow their Land,<lb/> to raise
                        Grain to make Bread<lb/> for themselves; and for their<lb/> old People and
                        Children who could<lb/> not work; and that they should<lb/> get many Cows to
                        give them<lb/> Milk; and keep Sheep and<lb/>
                        <pb n="49" facs="SW_JP1796_050"/> Such Things like the white<lb/>
                        people do; and that their<lb/> Women should learn to spin<lb/> the wool that
                        would come off<lb/> their Sheep, to make them<lb/> Blankets and Clothes, to
                        keep<lb/> them and their Children<lb/> warm in cold Weather; and<lb/> that
                        we were willing to shew<lb/> them how to do those things;<lb/> that some of
                        our young men<lb/> would stay a while with them,<lb/> (if they were
                        willing,) to instruct<lb/> them how the white people<lb/> tilled the land
                        (for we had before<lb/> united in the Belief that this<lb/> was the most
                        fruitable place<lb/> to make our Settlement) but<lb/>
                        <pb n="50" facs="SW_JP1796_051"/> but informed them withal, that<lb/>
                        they ought not depend too much<lb/> on their Brothers, the Quakers,<lb/> for
                        help; but that they must try<lb/> to help themselves; that we were<lb/>
                        willing to assist them a little<lb/> in the Beginning; but as we<lb/> wanted
                        to help all their In-<lb/>dian Brothers a little, and<lb/> as there was a
                        great many<lb/> of them, they could not expect<lb/> that we could do a great
                        deal<lb/> for any one Nation; and more-<lb/>over, as we saw they had a
                        great<lb/> deal of very good Land; an as we<lb/> were willing to shew
                        them<lb/> how to work their good Land,<lb/>
                        <pb n="51" facs="SW_JP1796_052"/> that they might live
                        comfortably,<lb/> and have plenty of every thing, if<lb/> they would but
                        take our Advice,<lb/> and learn to work, and to be in-<lb/>dustrious, sober,
                        and saving; but<lb/> if they would not be persuaded<lb/> to help themselves,
                        but would<lb/> still continue to live in their<lb/> old way, that their
                        Brothers<lb/> the Quakers would soon grow<lb/> tired of helping them:
                        after<lb/> we had thus fully opened our<lb/> Prospects, and relieved
                        our<lb/> Minds to them, they gave<lb/> us a short answer expressing<lb/>
                        their Willingness to comply<lb/> with our Advice: The Council<lb/> then
                        braking up they mostly<lb/>
                        <pb n="52" facs="SW_JP1796_053"/> withdrew; but the Chiefs, &amp;<lb/>
                        old Men soon returned, and<lb/> desired to speak a few more<lb/> words to
                        us; which when we<lb/> had agreed to, and were seated<lb/> down, they
                        proceeded to inform,<lb/> that their Women had heard<lb/> the good words
                        that we had said<lb/> to them; and that they had<lb/> now exorted their
                        Husbands &amp;<lb/> all their Men, to mind all<lb/> the good Words that
                        their Bro-<lb/>thers the Quakers, had said<lb/> to them; and that every
                        thing<lb/> that they had said was good;<lb/> and that they ought to do it
                        all.</p>
                    <p> Here it may be proper<lb/>
                        <pb n="53" facs="SW_JP1796_054"/> to remark, that truly the<lb/> women
                        have great Cause<lb/> to be on our side in this Bu-<lb/>siness; for in
                        proportion to<lb/> the Rudeness, and uncultiva-<lb/>tion of these people,
                        are the<lb/> Hardships and Difficulties<lb/> of their Women greatly
                        increas-<lb/>ed; for where the Men think<lb/> it a reproach for them to
                        work,<lb/> all the Chopping, Howing &amp;c.<lb/> necessarily fall upon
                        their<lb/> Women: and as they increase<lb/> in Civilization, as is
                        evident<lb/> in the <orgName key="stockbridge">Stockbridge</orgName> and
                            <orgName key="brotherton">Bro-<lb/>thertown’s</orgName>, the women
                        are<lb/> gradually relieved from this<lb/> Drudgery, and their Labours<lb/>
                        con <pb n="54" facs="SW_JP1796_055"/> confined more of their Houses,
                        and<lb/> amongst their Children, where<lb/> they ought to be.</p>
                    <p> And such has lately been the<lb/> Case, as we are creditably informed,<lb/>
                        among the <orgName key="oneida">Oneida’s</orgName>, that if a<lb/> Man was
                        catched caught by his friend<lb/> cutting off a stick of wood, or
                        how-<lb/>ing a Hill of Corn, he would<lb/> appear as much ashamed, as<lb/>
                        if he had been caught in a dis-<lb/>honorable or wicked Action.</p>
                    <p> At the Close of this Council<lb/> we had a Conference with the<lb/> Chiefs;
                        from which, and our<lb/> own Observations, we learn,<lb/> that the <orgName
                            key="oneida">Oneida’s</orgName> possess a<lb/> large Tract of excellent Land,<lb/>
                        <pb n="55" facs="SW_JP1796_056"/> supposed to be about 12 miles<lb/> by
                        20: They consist of about<lb/> 620 Individuals, have an In-<lb/>come from
                        general Govern-<lb/>ment of 700 Dollars a year;<lb/> out of which
                        Government<lb/> has Liberty to furnish them<lb/> with a Smith and
                        Materials;<lb/> which has been done at the<lb/> Expense of about 200
                        Dollars<lb/> a year; they have also Liberty<lb/> out of this Sum to
                        furnish<lb/> them with a School, by employ-<lb/>ing a Schoolmaster, which
                        is<lb/> not done, said to be from the<lb/> Difficulty of getting a
                        suitable<lb/> Teacher; which we regret, as such<lb/>
                        <pb n="56" facs="SW_JP1796_057"/> an Institution, if rightly
                        under-<lb/>taken and prosecuted must cer-<lb/>tainly be much more
                        advanta-<lb/>geous to these people than<lb/> the Money.</p>
                    <p> They have also about<lb/> 5000 Dollars annually<lb/> coming in from the
                        State<lb/> of New York; they have also<lb/> a Sawmill built by
                        Govern-<lb/>ment; and a Gristmill begun;<lb/> which Government are
                        under<lb/> Obligations to complete.</p>
                    <p> They have a considerable Num-<lb/>ber of horned Cattle, Horses,<lb/> and
                        some good working Cattle.</p>
                    <p> From the above Delineation<lb/>
                        <pb n="57" facs="SW_JP1796_058"/> of the Circumstances and
                        Si-<lb/>tuation of these people, it must<lb/> evidently appear; that
                        their<lb/> Chance for a comfortable Sub-<lb/>stance far exceeds that of<lb/>
                        the majority of the white<lb/> Inhabitants of Pennsylvania<lb/> and parts
                        adjacent. - That<lb/> in short there appears but<lb/> little in the way of
                        their<lb/> becoming good Livers but<lb/> their excessive Indolence,<lb/>
                        want of Oeconomy, and Love<lb/> of Strong Drink; in the latter<lb/> of which
                        Some Exertions have<lb/> been made by the old Men<lb/> and Chiefs here, as
                        well as<lb/>
                        <pb n="58" facs="SW_JP1796_059"/> amongst the <orgName
                            key="stockbridge">Stockbridge’s</orgName>, and<lb/> we understand no
                        strong Drink<lb/> is allowed to be sold in their<lb/> Towns; and we have, at
                        each<lb/> place, been concerned to Strength-<lb/>en these Exertions; yet it
                        is<lb/> Sorrowfully evident, that they<lb/> too frequently find Means
                        to<lb/> get this baneful Article by<lb/> applying to the frontier
                        retail-<lb/>ers: </p>
                    <p> After obtaining the above,<lb/> we returned in the Evening<lb/> to our
                        Lodgings at <placeName key="stock">Stockbridge</placeName>.<lb/><gap/></p>
                    <gap/>
                    <pb n="59" facs="SW_JP1796_060"/>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-17">17th.</date><placeName key="stock"
                            type="unattested"/></dateline>
                    <p>The forepart of this Day<lb/> some of our Company were en<lb/>gaged in
                        writing and digesting<lb/> our Concerns, whilst others<lb/> were usefully
                        employed in<lb/> the completion of a domes-<lb/>tic Improvement, some<lb/>
                        Days ago begun. </p>
                    <p> In the afternoon two of<lb/> us, at the request of the<lb/> Indians,
                        attended a Council<lb/> of the <orgName key="oneida">Oneida's</orgName>,
                            <orgName key="tuscarora">Tuscorora's</orgName> &amp;<lb/>
                        <orgName key="stockbridge">Stockbridge's</orgName> together, which<lb/> we
                        found to be on Business of<lb/> their own unconnected with<lb/> ours: The
                        business was con-<lb/>ducted with great Decorum<lb/> &amp;<lb/>
                        <pb n="60" facs="SW_JP1796_061"/> and Formality and a clear and<lb/>
                        decisive Judgment passed upon<lb/> some disorderly Walkers of unruly spirits
                        who<lb/> were endeavoring to disturb and<lb/> lay waste the internal
                        Govern-<lb/>ment of one of these nations.</p>
                    <p> The principle Leaders of<lb/> this Faction are <persName key="jkonk1">Jacob
                            Konka-<lb/>pot</persName>, <persName key="jkonk2">John
                            Konkapot</persName>, and <persName key="msonk1">Moses<lb/>
                            Sonkankeheh</persName>: these Men had<lb/> complained to the Oneida<lb/>
                        Chiefs against their own<lb/> chiefs, viz. the <orgName key="stockbridge"
                            >Stockbridge</orgName>; and<lb/> had requested of them some<lb/>
                        Seperate Lands, that they<lb/> might live independant of<lb/> their Chiefs;
                        who they said<lb/> had required them to sign<lb/>
                        <pb n="61" facs="SW_JP1796_062"/> some piece of writing, contrary<lb/>
                        to the Custom of Indians; and<lb/> that they did not understand the<lb/>
                        writing, and therefore would not<lb/> sign it; and because they had<lb/>
                        refused to sign this writing,<lb/> their Chiefs had taken away<lb/> their
                        Lots and had deprived<lb/> them of several national<lb/> priviledges; and
                        divers other<lb/> Charges they had brought against<lb/> them. </p>
                    <p> The <orgName key="oneida">Oneida</orgName> Speaker, <persName key="cpete1"
                            >Cap<lb/> Peter</persName>, opened the Council<lb/> with the customary
                        Formality<lb/> of Thankfulness to the great<lb/> Spirit for being favoured
                        to<lb/> meet Face to Face in that<lb/>
                        <pb n="62" facs="SW_JP1796_063"/> Council; then proceeded, in<lb/>
                        substance as follows: </p>
                    <floatingText type="speech">
                        <body>
                            <p> Brothers:</p>
                            <p><gap/>You remember your<lb/> former situation when you<lb/> were in
                                Distress, having leased<lb/> all your Lands, at old <placeName
                                    key="stock">Stock-<lb/>bridge</placeName> in New England,
                                one<lb/> piece after another, to the<lb/> white people, 'till at
                                last<lb/> you had no Land left for<lb/> yourselves. You know;
                                Brothers,<lb/> in this Distress, we your elder<lb/> Brother took
                                pity upon you,<lb/> and gave you this Dish, that<lb/> you might put
                                a spoon into<lb/> it and live; and in order<lb/>
                                <pb n="63" facs="SW_JP1796_064"/> that our younger Brother
                                should<lb/> never get such trouble again,<lb/> we made this Dish of
                                steel,<lb/> that it might last forever x,<lb/> and we thought,
                                Brothers, that<lb/> you had put a steel spoon into<lb/> this good
                                Dish; we admire<lb/> then, that our younger Bro-<lb/>thers should
                                get to differing<lb/> about the spoon, but we are<lb/> astonished
                                how you should<lb/> break<del rend="crossout">e</del> a steel spoon,
                                so that<lb/> you cannot all get a Living<lb/> together out of this
                                good Dish<lb/> that we have given you; but<lb/>x This steel Dish very <unclear>aptly</unclear> alluded<lb/> to a
                                clause in their Deed of Gifts,<lb/> barring against their selling
                                or<lb/> leasing to white people.</p>
                            <pb n="64" facs="SW_JP1796_065"/>
                            <p>that any of you should pretend<lb/> asto [?] A new Dish to
                                themselves:<lb/> Brothers, we can’t agree to this;<lb/> for if we
                                should give some of<lb/> you a new dish, it may be<lb/> that Dish
                                may be made of<lb/> Wood, and then it will soon<lb/> get broke, and
                                you will<lb/> have no Dish againt: No Brothers,<lb/> we will not do
                                this, but we<lb/> will try to mend your spoon<lb/> for you, so that
                                you may all</p>
                            <p>This wooden Dish represented the<lb/> Disposition of the
                                Complainants<lb/> to sell and lease Lands to the<lb/> white people,
                                for which they<lb/> have been noted.</p>
                            <pb n="65" facs="SW_JP1796_066"/>
                            <p>live happily together out of this<lb/> good steel Dish that we
                                have<lb/> given you; and maybe the spoon<lb/> is not broke yet, but
                                only bent<lb/> a little, and we will try to<lb/> straighten it for
                                you: And now<lb/> Brothers, in order to straiten the<lb/> Spoon you
                                must dig a Hole<lb/> in the Ground, and you must<lb/> dig it deep,
                                and in it you must<lb/> bury all these old Contentions<lb/> and
                                Complaints, and you<lb/> must cover them so deep, that<lb/> they can
                                never get up again;<lb/> and then the Spoon will be<lb/> mended; and
                                you will all eat<lb/> together comfortably out of this<lb/> Steel
                                Dish again; Now Brother<lb/>
                                <pb n="66" facs="SW_JP1796_067"/> we have done, think of
                                these<lb/> Things; and the Chiefs, and<lb/> young Warriors who
                                complain,<lb/> have liberty to speak for them-<lb/>selves. </p>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                    <p> Then the <orgName key="oneida">Oneidas</orgName> and <orgName
                            key="tuscarora">Tus-<lb/>cororas</orgName> withdrew to smoke<lb/> a
                        Pipe, and eat their Din-<lb/>ners; </p>
                    <p> During which Time <persName key="haupa1">Cap.<lb/> Hendrick</persName>
                        repeated the substance<lb/> of the foregoing speech, in the<lb/> Stockbridge
                        Language; to his<lb/> own people; it having been<lb/> delivered in the
                        Oneida Language<lb/> and interpreted into English;<lb/> After which they
                        consulted toge-<lb/>ther and not being able to recon-<lb/>cile<lb/>
                        <pb n="67" facs="SW_JP1796_068"/> cile and restore the
                        Compain-<lb/>ants; On the Return of the<lb/>
                        <orgName key="oneida">Oneidas</orgName> and <orgName key="tuscarora"
                            >Tuscororas</orgName>; <persName key="haupa1">Cap.<lb/>
                            Hendricks</persName>, on behalf of him-<lb/>self and his Brother
                        Chiefs,<lb/> made the following Defence;<lb/> viz.</p>
                    <floatingText type="speech">
                        <body>
                            <p> Brothers, we are happy<lb/> that the great Spirit has al-<lb/>lowed
                                us to smoke a pipe<lb/> together on this Occasion;<lb/> and we
                                understand perfectly<lb/> well all what you have said<lb/> to us:
                                now we will answer<lb/> as far as concerns us.</p>
                            <p> Brothers, it is true we have<lb/> agreed to help one another<lb/>
                                <pb n="68" facs="SW_JP1796_069"/> especially when one
                                Brother<lb/> meets with any Difficulty<lb/> the other shall help
                                him<lb/> out; Brothers, All what<lb/> you have said to us and to
                                our<lb/> young Men, we like it well,<lb/> and you know, Brothers,
                                it<lb/> is a common thing for the<lb/> Chiefs of all Nations to<lb/>
                                endeavor to promote the<lb/> Good of their Nation; and<lb/> you also
                                know that they al-<lb/>ways receive as a sallery<lb/> therefor the
                                Reproaches<lb/> of some of their people;<lb/> because, that in every nation<lb/>
                                <pb n="69" facs="SW_JP1796_070"/> there are some bad people,
                                that<lb/> will not regard good and<lb/> wholesome Rules, but
                                will<lb/> always be wanting to have<lb/> their own way; We have<lb/>
                                such: And now, Bro-<lb/>thers, we shall begin to<lb/> speak to the
                                Accusations,<lb/> which those people bring<lb/> against us; and we
                                are glad<lb/> you have had such Wisdom,<lb/> as not to judge in this
                                Mat-<lb/>ter without a general Coun<lb/>cil, and giving us Leave
                                to<lb/> speak for ourselves, that<lb/> so the Truth may come
                                out;<lb/> The<lb/>
                                <pb n="70" facs="SW_JP1796_071"/> The first thing we Shall
                                ob-<lb/>serve; they have told you<lb/> Brothers, that we have
                                done<lb/> them Injury; and they say<lb/> that we have let out
                                Lands<lb/> to white people, and that<lb/> we have taken away
                                their<lb/> Lots from them; now Bro-<lb/>thers, we deny this; we
                                have<lb/> done no Such Thing: you<lb/> know very well,
                                Brothers,<lb/> that we have maintained our<lb/> Covenant
                                    <del><gap/></del>which we<lb/> made with you at <placeName
                                    key="schen">Schenec-<lb/>tady</placeName> about this Land,
                                this<lb/> Dish; you are our Witnesses<lb/> that we have never took trouble<lb/>
                                <pb n="71" facs="SW_JP1796_072"/> to ourselves, by giving
                                Lease<lb/> of any of this Land to white<lb/> people; and also the
                                great men<lb/> of the State of New York are<lb/> our witnessest; and
                                our writ-<lb/>ings testify the same thing;<lb/> By these Things,
                                Brothers, we<lb/> are able to deny this part<lb/> of the Accusation: </p>
                            <p> Brothers, now we will speak<lb/> on the other Hand; these our<lb/>
                                young Men have been trying<lb/> this two years to take away our<lb/>
                                spoon and break<del>e</del> this Dish;<lb/> Some-</p>
                     
                            <p>This appeal to the Great Men of the<lb/> State of New York, had
                                reference, to<lb/> a petition taken in by the Complain<lb/>ants for
                                Liberty to sell and lease Lands<lb/> to white people; which was
                                opposed by the Chiefs</p>
                            <pb n="72" facs="SW_JP1796_073"/>
                            <p>Sometime, the white people<lb/> will lay hold of the Spoon,<lb/> and
                                try to bend it, and pull<lb/> it this way, and that way;<lb/> and
                                these our young Men will<lb/> join with them, and take<lb/> hold
                                with their Hands, and<lb/> try to bend it; now when<lb/> we saw that
                                our spoon was<lb/> in danger, we the Chiefs<lb/> would take hold;
                                and our<lb/> orderly young Men would take<lb/> hold, and try to
                                bring it back<lb/> again, and to straiten our<lb/> Spoon; to this
                                you are our<lb/> Witnesses, and the great Men<lb/> of<lb/>
                                <pb n="73" facs="SW_JP1796_074"/> of the State of New York,
                                are<lb/> our witnesses; And you know,<lb/> Brothers, that we have
                                kept<lb/> our Dish and our Spoon, that<lb/> they are not broke yet,
                                but<lb/> are kept bright; and we in-<lb/>tend to keep them bright
                                for<lb/> the use of our Children. </p>
                            <p> Brothers, The next thing we<lb/> shall observe, They say we<lb/>
                                take in Strangers; to this<lb/> we acknowledge; because our<lb/>
                                Covenant we made with you<lb/> was such, as to open a Door<lb/> to
                                take in Strangers of our<lb/> own Colour; Because, Brothers,<lb/> you<lb/>
                                <pb n="74" facs="SW_JP1796_075"/> you know, that it is
                                natural<lb/> amongst all nations, to have<lb/> Compassion towards
                                one another;<lb/> for Instance, Brothers, you your-<lb/>selves have
                                done Such Thing<lb/> many Years ago; for these<lb/>
                                <orgName key="tuscarora">Tuscororas</orgName>, who are now at<lb/>
                                this Council, were Strangers,<lb/> and ye took them in, and<lb/>
                                gave them a Dish; and we<lb/> ourselves were also Strangers,<lb/>
                                and ye took us in and gave<lb/> us a Dish; now Brothers, in<lb/>
                                keeping the same Rules among<lb/> us, the Chiefs of our Nation,<lb/>
                                who can find fault with<lb/> us, in that Respect.</p>
                            <pb n="75" facs="SW_JP1796_076"/>
                            <p> Brothers, We will observe another<lb/> thing, our young Men
                                have<lb/> told you, that we draw writings,<lb/> and these writings
                                are signed<lb/> by many; and they could not<lb/> understand these
                                writings;<lb/> and therefore would not sign<lb/> them: you also,
                                Brothers, seem<lb/> to be astonished yourselves at these
                                things;<lb/> you say, you do not know how<lb/> these writings should
                                come,<lb/> and why they should be signed:<lb/> Now Brothers, we
                                acknowledge<lb/> we have such writings, and<lb/> if you desire, you
                                shall hear<lb/> these writings, that ye shall<lb/> rightly
                                understand them; but<lb/>
                                <pb n="76" facs="SW_JP1796_077"/> before I read you this
                                wri-<lb/>ting, we shall let you know,<lb/> that our Chiefs always
                                had<lb/> in their Hearts the welfare<lb/> of the Nation, and often
                                con-<lb/>templated what would be<lb/> most for the welfare of
                                the<lb/> whole nation; and about<lb/> twelve years ago, before
                                we<lb/> come to your Country, we found<lb/> it would be for our
                                Welfare, to<lb/> make a Strong Covenant, to<lb/> keep us together,
                                and draw<lb/> writings to keep out Memory<lb/> bright; so long as we
                                maintain<lb/> that agreement, we find it<lb/>
                                <pb n="77" facs="SW_JP1796_078"/> do us good, and five years
                                ago,<lb/> since we come to this town,<lb/> we renew that Covenant;
                                and<lb/> since that, now lately, we be-<lb/>gin to see the same
                                spirit<lb/> which had made Disturbance<lb/> amongst us before, and
                                which<lb/> must inevitably bring ruin<lb/> both to the spirituals
                                and tem-<lb/>porals; therefore the Chiefs<lb/> was alarmed, and
                                believe it<lb/> their Duty to use their law-<lb/>ful Endeavour to
                                frustrate<lb/> that Design; and they called<lb/> the Nation together
                                in general<lb/> Council, to consult what shall<lb/> be done, and
                                they agreed to enter<lb/> into<lb/>
                                <pb n="78" facs="SW_JP1796_079"/> into Covenant, and draw
                                writings,<lb/> and sign them: now Brothers,<lb/> I will read you the
                                writings: viz.<lb/> Article 1st: The Union of the<lb/> Nation which
                                was established<lb/> at old <placeName key="stock"
                                    >Stockbridge</placeName> in the year<lb/> 1784 and afterwards
                                renewed<lb/> at different Times is hereby<lb/> again confirmed, that
                                the<lb/> same shall remain inviolable.</p>
                            <p> 2nd. As many as are thus unit-<lb/>ed shall abide firm in all
                                the<lb/> good Agreements heretofore<lb/> made in our public
                                Meetings;<lb/> which are recorded in the<lb/> Town Book; but more
                                especially<lb/> in<lb/>
                                <pb n="79" facs="SW_JP1796_080"/> in keeping our Lands; and
                                that<lb/> we never should take trouble<lb/> to ourselves, in
                                Endeavouring<lb/> to lease Land to white people.<lb/>
                            </p>
                            <p> 3rd. The Said united Inhabitants<lb/> of this town, shall equally
                                par-<lb/>take of all the privileges confered<lb/> on us from abroad,
                                and in like<lb/> manner shall equally bear all<lb/> the public
                                Business incum-<lb/>bent on the nation.</p>
                            <p> 4th. All those who refuse to<lb/> join in this happy Union<lb/>
                                shall be positively excluded<lb/> from all the aforesaid
                                privileges,<lb/> except preaching and School;<lb/> these two shall
                                remain free as<lb/> usual; yet if any of them should<lb/> see<lb/>
                                <pb n="80" facs="SW_JP1796_081"/> see his folly, and
                                disadvantage<lb/> by it, and be disposed to comply<lb/> with the
                                Articles of this Agree-<lb/>ment, he or they shall be
                                ad-<lb/>mitted, by signing the aforesaid<lb/> agreement to enjoy
                                equal pri-<lb/>vileges with the others.</p>
                            <p> 5th. Public meetings shall<lb/> be free and open, the Sachems<lb/>
                                and Chiefs of the Nation shall<lb/> be respected and obeyed in
                                all<lb/> the good Counsels they give. </p>
                            <p> 6th. If any of the members<lb/> of the Union be in distress,
                                his<lb/> Business is to inform his Situ-<lb/>ation to the principle
                                men,<lb/> and he shall be afforded all pos-<lb/>sible Relief. </p>
                            <pb n="81" facs="SW_JP1796_082"/>
                            <p> 7th. And if any man shall do<lb/> a public service he shall<lb/> be
                                entitled to a Reward.</p>
                            <p> 8th. If anyone, whether a mem-<lb/>ber of this Union or not,
                                should<lb/> brake either of the Articles of<lb/> this agreement, and
                                persisting<lb/> to do contrary, or making direct<lb/> Opposition
                                against it, as to excite<lb/> others to transgress with him,<lb/> he
                                shall be under penalty<lb/> of the Law.</p>
                            <p> Witness our Hands this<lb/>
                                <date when="1796-06-03">3rd Day of June 1796</date>.</p>
                            <p> Brothers, you see, and<lb/> understand clearly, what writ-<lb/>ings
                                we have drawn, and why<lb/> we should sign these writings;<lb/>
                                <pb n="82" facs="SW_JP1796_083"/> that we may know how
                                many<lb/> of us are of one mind: By<lb/> this Agreement you see,
                                that<lb/> we do not take any mans<lb/> property, or do any
                                Injury<lb/> to any; the matter is free<lb/> to every one to act as
                                he pleases;<lb/> if anyone is excluded any<lb/> privileges, he does
                                it himself,<lb/> of his own Choice; but it<lb/> is not the Choice of
                                the<lb/> Chiefs or of the orderly young<lb/> Men: Brothers, we<lb/>
                                have now informed you every<lb/> Thing, particular; now you<lb/> are
                                able to judge who are<lb/> in the fault; whether the<lb/>
                                <pb n="83" facs="SW_JP1796_084"/> Chiefs, or these our young
                                men;<lb/> now you must be plain, if<lb/> you find fault with us,
                                tell<lb/> us plainly; we are ready to<lb/> make up, if there is
                                any<lb/> thing against us; but we think<lb/> we can say this, that
                                in stead<lb/> of doing them hurt, we have<lb/> ever endeavoured to
                                promote<lb/> their happiness:</p>
                            <p> Brothers, this is all what<lb/> we have to say at present; only<lb/>
                                one of our young men will speak<lb/> a word to you; if you are
                                willing. </p>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                    <p> Which being admitted, <persName key="jquin2">John<lb/> Quinney</persName>
                        spoke on Behalf of him-<lb/>self, &amp;<lb/>
                        <pb n="84" facs="SW_JP1796_085"/> and the rest of the orderly young
                        men, as<lb/> follows; viz.</p>
                    <floatingText>
                        <body>
                            <p>Brother, Chiefs of the <orgName key="oneida">Oneida</orgName><lb/>
                                and <orgName key="tuscarora">Tuscorora’s</orgName>,</p>
                            <p> I would inform you, that I believe it is not<lb/> the will of the
                                great Spirit,<lb/> that we the young warriors<lb/> should usurp
                                Authority over<lb/>
                                <del>the</del> our Chiefs; but that it is<lb/> our Duty to obey our
                                Chiefs,<lb/> in all their good Counsels, be-<lb/>cause we know, and
                                have ex-<lb/>perienced that our Chiefs have<lb/> more wisdom and
                                Knowledge<lb/> than we have; and that they<lb/> have been faithful
                                in promot-<lb/>ing our Happiness; so that we<lb/>
                                <pb n="85" facs="SW_JP1796_086"/> think it is a great
                                Shame<lb/> for any of us to rise up against<lb/> them; and indeed
                                there are only<lb/> a few who have done such thing;<lb/> now
                                Brothers, we also declare<lb/> that all what our Chiefs have<lb/>
                                related to you, is true:</p>
                            <p> This is all I got to say </p>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                    <p> After a short pause <persName key="cpete1">Cap. Peter</persName>,<lb/> the
                            <orgName key="oneida">Oneida</orgName> speaker, replied in<lb/>
                        Substance, as follows.</p>
                    <floatingText type="speech">
                        <body>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <gap/>
                            <p>We are very glad<lb/> that you have opened your<lb/> Minds to us so
                                fully, that we<lb/> understand clearly all these<lb/> Circumstances
                                that you have<lb/> mentioned; we are glad to<lb/> find<lb/>
                                <pb n="86" facs="SW_JP1796_087"/> find that you have
                                maintained<lb/> all our agreements, so that the<lb/> Spoon is safe
                                and bright; and<lb/> all what you have related<lb/> to us, is very
                                agreeable to us;<lb/> and also the writing which you<lb/> have shewn
                                us is good, we<lb/> like it very well; and we do<lb/> not find any
                                fault on your<lb/> side; and we now understand<lb/> where the Blame
                                lies; that<lb/> it lies upon your young men<lb/> there; Brothers,
                                now we hear-<lb/>tily thank you Chiefs; and all<lb/> our Chiefs
                                thank you, for the<lb/> Information you have given<lb/> us<lb/>
                                <pb n="87" facs="SW_JP1796_088"/> us; and we will now
                                speak<lb/> a word to your orderly young<lb/> Warrior, who spoke a
                                few words<lb/> to us, we like all his words<lb/> well; we are glad
                                to find such<lb/> Disposition in young warriors<lb/> to obey their
                                Chiefs; and we<lb/> are very glad to hear him;<lb/> and we thank him
                                for letting<lb/> us know that there are very<lb/> few young
                                    <del>men</del> warriors among you that disobey<lb/> their
                                Chiefs; and we should<lb/> be glad all our young War-<lb/>riors
                                would be so disposed; then<lb/> addressing himself to the<lb/> young
                                Men who had com-<lb/>plained, he said,<lb/> Brothers<lb/>
                                <pb n="88" facs="SW_JP1796_089"/> Brothers, We are sorry to
                                find<lb/> that you yourselves have<lb/> created all these
                                Difficul-<lb/>ties that you complain<lb/> of; and now we wish
                                you<lb/> to make up, and Shake<lb/> Hands with your Chiefs<lb/>
                                before our Face, that we<lb/> may see it done, and then<lb/> we will
                                be very glad and<lb/> Satisfied: So Brothers that<lb/> is all we got
                                to say to you:<lb/><gap/></p>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                    <p> The Complainants refused<lb/> to comply with this Advice,<lb/> so the
                        Council broke up; all<lb/> satisfied to appearance, except-<lb/>ing these
                        Disturbers of the<lb/> public Tranquility.</p>
                    <pb n="89" facs="SW_JP1796_090"/>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-18">18th.</date><placeName key="broth"
                        /></dateline>
                    <p>This Day attended a<lb/> general Council of the <orgName key="brotherton"
                            >Bro-<lb/>thertown Indians</orgName>, at their<lb/>
                        <placeName key="broth">Town</placeName>, about 9 miles from<lb/> the
                            <orgName key="stockbridge">Stockbridge</orgName> Settlement;<lb/> who,
                        as usual, were a long<lb/> Time in getting together; we<lb/> opened our
                        Business without<lb/> any Interpreter, these people<lb/> mostly
                        understanding English,<lb/> and using no other Language<lb/> in their
                        families; after which<lb/> and reading our Certificate<lb/> to them; we
                        desired their pa-<lb/>tience, reminding them<lb/> that we had come a
                        great<lb/> way to see them in Love,<lb/> without any prospect of<lb/>
                        <pb n="90" facs="SW_JP1796_091"/> worldly Advantage to ourselves,<lb/>
                        and that we were desirous<lb/> they should endeavour<lb/> to still and quiet
                        their<lb/> Minds, as well as their<lb/> Bodies, that they might<lb/> be in a
                        proper Situation<lb/> to hear and understand, if<lb/> we should have any
                        thing<lb/> to say to them: this seems<lb/> to be too little understood<lb/>
                        by these people generally<lb/> where we have been; they<lb/> appear hardly
                        to know how<lb/> to compose themselves many<lb/> Minutes at a Time, unless we<lb/>
                        <pb n="91" facs="SW_JP1796_092"/> are speaking to them: but<lb/> we
                        were here favoured with<lb/> a Solid Opportunity; being<lb/> enabled with
                        great planning,<lb/> and Love to labour with them;<lb/> pointing out with
                        Clearness<lb/> the pernicious Effects of the<lb/> Use of Strong Drink; and
                        the<lb/> necessity of avoiding every<lb/> Occasion of Temptation<lb/>
                        thereto; as well as the Ad-<lb/>vantage of improving in In-<lb/>dustry and
                        Application to their<lb/> Farming, in order to pro-<lb/>cure to themselves
                        and their<lb/> families a comfortable Living;<lb/> and<lb/>
                        <pb n="92" facs="SW_JP1796_093"/> and also shewing them<lb/> that by
                        Industry and At-<lb/>tention to their Business,<lb/> they would be preserved
                        from<lb/> the frequent Temptations,<lb/> which a more indolant and<lb/>
                        wandering Life would expose<lb/> them to, with regard to this<lb/> Bane of
                        their Happiness,<lb/>
                        <emph rend="underline">Strong Liquor</emph>. Some of these<lb/> people
                        appear to be indus-<lb/>trious, and in general, their<lb/> Dress and manner
                        of Life,<lb/> approaches nearer to that<lb/> of the white people, than<lb/>
                        any of the other Tribes where<lb/> we have been; and <del>notwithstan</del><lb/>
                        <pb n="93" facs="SW_JP1796_094"/> notwithstanding the Gloo-<lb/>miness
                        of some of our for-<lb/>mer, as well as present<lb/> prospects relative to
                        the<lb/> Concern which we are en-<lb/>gaged in, we are in measure<lb/>
                        encouraged to believe in the<lb/> Rectitude of our Undertak-<lb/>ing; both
                        from the solid Co-<lb/>vering graciously vouchsafed<lb/> at several of our
                        Conferen-<lb/>ces, and particularly so this<lb/> Day, to the stilling, if
                        not<lb/> tendering many of the minds<lb/> of these people; and also<lb/>
                        from the Observance of an<lb/>
                        <pb n="94" facs="SW_JP1796_095"/> Advancement in Civiliza-<lb/>tion
                        amongst these differ-<lb/>ent Tribes, in proportion<lb/> to the Serious
                        Exertions<lb/> which have, from time to<lb/> time, been made by white<lb/>
                        people towards some of them,<lb/> for we understand, that, even<lb/> the
                            <orgName key="oneida">Oneida’s</orgName>, who now appear<lb/> to us in a
                        very Rude and<lb/> uncultivated State, were<lb/> still much more so, a
                        few<lb/> year ago, before their Ac-<lb/>quaintance with the other<lb/> more
                        civilized Tribes.</p>
                    <pb n="95" facs="SW_JP1796_096"/>
                    <p> The <orgName key="brotherton">Brothertown Indians</orgName><lb/> are under
                        the particular<lb/> Care of the State of New York;<lb/> there are three men
                        appointed<lb/> by Government as Commissioners,<lb/> or Superintendents of
                        their Lands<lb/> &amp;c. Two of whom are friends,<lb/> viz. <persName
                            key="epryo1">Edward Prior</persName> and <persName key="teddy1"
                            >Thomas<lb/> Eddy</persName>, both of New York; the<lb/> third is
                            <persName key="wfloy1">Col. Floyd</persName>, a repu-<lb/>table Man, and
                        friend to these<lb/> People: Four of these In-<lb/>dians, viz. <persName
                            key="dfowl1">David Fowler</persName>, <persName key="jtuhi1">John<lb/>
                            Toohie</persName>, <persName key="jskes1">John Skesuck</persName>, and
                            <persName key="iwabe1">Isaac<lb/> Wauby</persName>, have received
                        Com-<lb/>missions of the Peace from<lb/>
                        <pb n="96" facs="SW_JP1796_097"/> Government; and they have<lb/> a
                        Counsellor at Law, ap-<lb/>pointed for their Assistance<lb/> in difficult
                        Cases; viz. <persName key="jherk1">Joseph<lb/> Herkland</persName>. They
                        consist<lb/> of about 56 Families, have<lb/> 9900 Acres of Land, which
                        is<lb/> secured to them by Law, in<lb/> such a Manner, that no<lb/>
                        Individual of them has power<lb/> to sell or lease any part of<lb/> it to
                        white people; but it<lb/> is divided into Lots, some of an<lb/> hundred
                        &amp; some of fifty acres,<lb/> and they possess their Land<lb/> and other
                        Things as distinct<lb/> and private property; They<lb/>
                        <pb n="97" facs="SW_JP1796_098"/> received this Land, in the first<lb/>
                        place, with considerable more,<lb/> by Gift from the <orgName key="oneida"
                            >Oneidas</orgName>; who<lb/> afterwards sold the whole,<lb/> with other
                        Lands, to the State<lb/> of New-York; but the State<lb/> discovering the
                        prior Right<lb/> of the <orgName key="brotherton">Brothertown’s</orgName>,
                        repurchased<lb/> the greater part of them, and<lb/> secure the above
                        quantity,<lb/> in manner aforesaid: </p>
                    <p> They have one Saw mill<lb/> on their Land, which is private<lb/> property,
                        and there is a grist-<lb/>mill belonging to white peo-<lb/>ple within about
                        two miles<lb/> of<lb/>
                        <pb n="98" facs="SW_JP1796_099"/> of the Center of their
                        Build-<lb/>ings; they have some good<lb/> Cattle, Cows &amp; working
                        Oxen;<lb/> and they have £800 a year<lb/> coming in from the State<lb/> of
                        New-York; as Interest<lb/> for the purchase Money of<lb/> their Lands: That
                        they ap-<lb/>pear to be in a very promis-<lb/>ing way to do well as to
                        world-<lb/>ly Affairs, if their Industry<lb/> &amp; Sobriety keep Pace
                        with<lb/> their Knowledge and Op-<lb/>portunity.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-19">19th.</date><placeName key="stock"
                            type="unattested"/></dateline>
                    <p>Being first Day, and un-<lb/>derstanding these people<lb/> made<lb/>
                        <pb n="99" facs="SW_JP1796_100"/> made a practice of meeting<lb/>
                        together to worship, without<lb/> any Hireling, or set Minister,<lb/> we
                        felt our Minds easy to attend<lb/> with them; which we accordingly<lb/> did;
                        and altho’ they conformed<lb/> to our Manner, yet we had<lb/> reason to
                        believe Silence was<lb/> not very acceptable to them; nor<lb/> their Minds
                        sensible of true<lb/> inward Stillness and Quietude<lb/> in worship; their
                        manner<lb/> being, for some or other of<lb/> them, either Man or woman,<lb/>
                        to be almost Constantly em-<lb/>ployed in preaching, praying,<lb/> singing
                        of Psalms or some<lb/> other outward and visible Acts<lb/> of<lb/>
                        <pb n="100" facs="SW_JP1796_101"/> of Devotion.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-20">20th.</date><placeName key="fschy"
                        /></dateline>
                    <p>This morning we sepe-<lb/>rated; three of our number<lb/> going for
                            <placeName key="fschy">fort Schuyler</placeName>, to look<lb/> after our
                        Goods, and to wait<lb/> on some man in that Neigh-<lb/>bourhood, to whom we
                        had a<lb/> Letter of Credit, whilst the<lb/> Remainder of our Company<lb/>
                        concluded to make themselves<lb/> better acquainted with the Situ-<lb/>ation
                        and Circumstances of<lb/> these people, by paying<lb/> them a friendly Visit
                        in<lb/> their Cottages; in which<lb/> Service the Remainder<lb/> of this Day
                        was employed, to<lb/>
                        <pb n="101" facs="SW_JP1796_102"/> the mutual Satisfaction<lb/> of the
                        Indians &amp; ourselves.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-21">21st.</date><placeName key="broth"
                        /></dateline>
                    <p>The forepart of this<lb/> Day concluded our friendly<lb/> Visit to the
                        families of the<lb/>
                        <orgName key="brotherton">Brothertown’s</orgName>, having missed<lb/> but
                        two or three in their<lb/> whole settlement: After<lb/> which, upon a
                        Consultation<lb/> together, we united in Judgment<lb/> with that of
                            <persName key="wfloy1">Col. Floyd</persName>, here-<lb/>tofore noted in
                        these minutes:<lb/> viz. That these people were<lb/> in a promising way to
                        live<lb/> comfortably; and that they<lb/> stood in no absolute need of<lb/>
                        any present assistance, in the<lb/> way of farming Utensils &amp;c.-</p>
                    <pb n="102" facs="SW_JP1796_103"/>
                    <p> After Dinner took our Leave of<lb/> these people, who had generally<lb/>
                        expressed their Satisfaction and<lb/> thankfulness, for the brotherly<lb/>
                        freedom we had manifested<lb/> amongst them in visiting them<lb/> in their
                        Houses; then proceeded<lb/> to our Lodgings at <placeName key="stock"
                            >Stockbridge</placeName>;<lb/> where we arrived in the evening.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-22">22nd.</date><placeName key="oneid"
                        /></dateline>
                    <p>This Day about noon met<lb/> at <placeName key="oneid">Oneida
                        Town</placeName>, at <persName key="jsken1">John
                            Sho-<lb/>nandoah’s</persName> with our friends who<lb/> had left us two
                        Days since to<lb/> go to <placeName key="fschy">fort Schuyler</placeName>;
                        they inform,<lb/> that they have done the Busi-<lb/>ness for which they
                        went; but<lb/> have heard no Tidings of <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob<lb/>
                            Taylor</persName>: We now concluded it<lb/>
                        <pb n="103" facs="SW_JP1796_104"/> necessary to make ourselves
                        better<lb/> acquainted with the different<lb/> Situations of the Country
                        belonging<lb/> to this Tribe, in order to form<lb/> some Idea
                            <del>where</del> of the best<lb/> Place to make our Settlement;<lb/> and
                        a place about four Miles<lb/> from this being recommended<lb/> to us, we
                        proceeded to view it; and<lb/> after examining the nature<lb/> of the Soil,
                        situation &amp;c. we<lb/> United in Opinion that<lb/> it was not a suitable
                        place<lb/> for our purpose: Here four<lb/> of us took up our Lodgings
                        at<lb/> the House of a white Man,<lb/> who had settled on an hundred<lb/>
                        Acres of the Indian Lands, under<lb/> a<lb/>
                        <pb n="104" facs="SW_JP1796_105"/> a Licence from Government,<lb/>
                        given to his Brother, who is<lb/> Black smith for that Nation:<lb/> This
                        House being on the great<lb/> Road leading to the Genesee<lb/> Country, and
                        keeping Liquor<lb/> and other things to sell, is be-<lb/>come a place of
                        much Re-<lb/>sort; and we doubt not much<lb/> to the Advantage of the
                        Indians,<lb/> who we understand are uneasy<lb/> with his Conduct: We
                        had<lb/> a very uncomfortable Night;<lb/> and left there in the
                        morning,<lb/> being,</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-23">23rd.</date><placeName key="stock"
                        /></dateline>
                    <p>Went to <persName key="jsken1">Shonandoah’s</persName>,<lb/> this being at
                        the principal<lb/> Town, and particularly viewed<lb/> the<lb/>
                        <pb n="105" facs="SW_JP1796_106"/> the adjoining Lands; after<lb/>
                        which united in believing<lb/> somewhere near this place,<lb/> the most
                        suitable, on divers<lb/> accounts, for our Stand: we then<lb/> proceeded to
                        our Lodgings at<lb/>
                        <placeName key="stock">Stockbridge</placeName>: and in the afternoon,<lb/>
                        confered together, and entered<lb/> upon <del>a plan</del> the Digestion
                        of<lb/> a plan for our Settlement.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-24">24th.</date><placeName key="oneid"
                            type="unattested"/></dateline>
                    <p>Resumed the Consideration<lb/> of our plan of a Settlement at<lb/>
                        <placeName key="oneid">Oneida</placeName>; and after several<lb/>
                        Conferences, in which the<lb/> weight and Importance of our<lb/> Undertaking
                        was very sensibly<lb/> felt; and much Harmony and<lb/> brotherly
                        condescension experienced,<lb/> we<lb/>
                        <pb n="106" facs="SW_JP1796_107"/> we were enabled to unitedly
                        a-<lb/>gree on the following proposi-<lb/>tions to the <orgName key="oneida"
                            >Oneida Nation</orgName>.</p>
                    <p> viz.</p>
                    <floatingText type="letter">
                        <body>
                            <p> Brothers of the <orgName key="oneida">Oneida Nation</orgName>,<lb/>
                                You now know that we are sent<lb/> to you by your old Friends,
                                the<lb/> people called Quakers, of Pennsylvania and<lb/> parts
                                adjacent, not merely to<lb/> make you presents, which<lb/> would
                                soon be spent; leaving you<lb/> poor and needy; but to shew<lb/> you
                                how the white people<lb/> manage to raise a great deal<lb/> of Food
                                and Clothing off of a<lb/> little Land, that you may<lb/> become
                                able to support your-<lb/>selves, and your Children<lb/>
                                <pb n="107" facs="SW_JP1796_108"/> comfortably without
                                being<lb/> beholden to any body, and have<lb/> something to share
                                for the old<lb/> and infirm, as well as to lay<lb/> by, against
                                Times of Scarcity.</p>
                            <p> Brothers, remember that we have<lb/> left all that was dear to us
                                at<lb/> home, not to get your Lands<lb/> from you, or any thing
                                that<lb/> is yours; but to visit you, and<lb/> to stay with you, if
                                happily<lb/> we may put you in the way<lb/> to enjoy the manifested
                                Blessings<lb/> of the all bountiful Creator;<lb/> now we have seen
                                and reflected<lb/> upon your Situation, and consult-<lb/>ed one
                                another for the future<lb/> prosperity of your whole Nation<lb/> and<lb/>
                                <pb n="108" facs="SW_JP1796_109"/> and the three Tribes you
                                have<lb/> kindly permitted to settle on<lb/> your Lands; and we have
                                put<lb/> our Conclusions in writing,<lb/> that it may be known
                                what<lb/> we are willing to undertake for<lb/> you, and what we
                                desire you<lb/> to do towards it yourselves; for<lb/> we mean to set
                                you a clear ex-<lb/>ample if you will agree to follow it.</p>
                            <p> Brothers, We trust that we<lb/> possess your Confidence
                                un-<lb/>mixed with any Jealousy and<lb/> fears; and we request you
                                to<lb/> listen patiently and attentive-<lb/>ly to what we are a
                                going to<lb/> propose<lb/>
                                <pb n="109" facs="SW_JP1796_110"/> propose to you, for your
                                own<lb/> Good; and if any part of it<lb/> displeases you, tell us so
                                and<lb/> we will reconsider it. </p>
                            <p> Brothers, Three of our Friends<lb/> intend to stay with you for<lb/>
                                these purposes, namely <persName key="jtayl1">Ja-<lb/>cob
                                    Taylor</persName>, <persName key="hsimm1">Henry
                                    Simmons</persName>,<lb/> and <persName key="ewalk1">Enoch
                                    Walker</persName>; but they<lb/> are not bound to remain<lb/> by
                                any thing but good Will;<lb/> Neither are they obliged to<lb/> work
                                more than they think<lb/> necessary; nor to be altogether<lb/>
                                amongst you, as they are to go<lb/> sometimes to <orgName
                                    key="tuscarora">Tuscorora</orgName>, <orgName key="stockbridge"
                                    >Stock-<lb/>bridge</orgName>, and <orgName key="brotherton"
                                    >Brothertown</orgName>: We<lb/> earnestly desire, that none<lb/>
                                of you may discourage them<lb/> by<lb/>
                                <pb n="110" facs="SW_JP1796_111"/> by Swearing, Idleness,
                                Drunken-<lb/>ness, or misbehavior, for these<lb/> things are very
                                disagreeable<lb/> to us; as you know they are<lb/> to the good
                                Spirit.</p>
                            <p> Brothers, We must have some<lb/> Land to work upon; and we
                                should<lb/> like to begin upon that part<lb/> of the Common which
                                lies<lb/> west of the Path from Shonan-<lb/>doah’s to <placeName
                                    key="stock">Stockbridge</placeName>, South<lb/> of the Road to
                                    <placeName key="onond">Onondago</placeName>,<lb/> East of the
                                Boundaries of<lb/> the old Fort, and north of<lb/>
                                <geogName key="shana">Shanandoah Creek</geogName>, excepting<lb/>
                                any part thereof now occu-<lb/>pied by your Families.</p>
                            <pb n="111" facs="SW_JP1796_112"/>
                            <p> Brothers, If we think there is<lb/> Encouragement to undertake<lb/>
                                more another year, we shall<lb/> ask you for it seasonably, and<lb/>
                                agree together where it shall<lb/> be. </p>
                            <p> Brothers, You know it is hard-<lb/>ly practicable for all to learn<lb/>
                                <del>at once</del> together; we will begin<lb/> with a few, who much
                                stick<lb/> to the work; the rest will see<lb/> how they get forward,
                                and<lb/> be ready to take their turn<lb/> when it comes round; we
                                want<lb/> to engage five or eight Sober<lb/> young Men as
                                Apprentices<lb/> till next Spring. </p>
                            <pb n="112" facs="SW_JP1796_113"/>
                            <p> Brothers,<lb/> We suppose you will<lb/> be willing, that we should
                                feed<lb/> our Horses, Cattle &amp;c. upon<lb/> the Commons, and
                                that<lb/> you will allow us some<lb/> Suitable grass Lots to
                                provide<lb/> Hay for them in the winter;<lb/> to cut fire-wood,
                                railing, and<lb/> Timber for building in your<lb/> Woods; have the
                                use of the Saw-<lb/>mill, and Smith’s shop, when<lb/> we have
                                occasion for them;<lb/> and sometimes work your<lb/> Horses and Oxen
                                when<lb/> they are not wanted by you.</p>
                            <pb n="113" facs="SW_JP1796_114"/>
                            <p> Brothers,<lb/> You are to under-<lb/>stand that our Friends are<lb/>
                                to live plentifully, as their<lb/> own people do at home,<lb/> and
                                their live stock are<lb/> also to be kept by the pro-<lb/>duce of
                                their Labour in the<lb/> first place; then the eighth<lb/> part of
                                the Remainder is<lb/> to reserved for the relief<lb/> of your old
                                    <del>Men</del>” and infirm<lb/> people; and the rest is to
                                be<lb/> divided amongst the young<lb/> Indian Apprentices; that
                                they<lb/> may enjoy the fruit of<lb/> their Labour; and have<lb/> some-<lb/>
                                <pb n="114" facs="SW_JP1796_115"/> something to begin with<lb/>
                                for themselves, when other<lb/> Apprentices are taken in<lb/> their
                                Stead; provided they<lb/> behave well; but in case<lb/> of continued
                                Idleness, Drun-<lb/>kenness, Swearing, or other<lb/> Misbehavior in
                                any<lb/> of them, our friends must<lb/> not keep bad Company;<lb/>
                                and we request you to appoint<lb/> three of your Chiefs to
                                unite<lb/> with our Friends as Judges,<lb/> that if four of them
                                agree,<lb/> the person offending may<lb/> be justly discharged.</p>
                            <pb n="115" facs="SW_JP1796_116"/>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> Our stay amongst you<lb/> will depend upon several<lb/>
                                Circumstances, and particu-<lb/>larly the Encouragement we<lb/> may
                                have to hope that your<lb/> Nation will become, in time<lb/> Sober,
                                industrious and frugal,<lb/> laying up something for<lb/> themselves
                                against Sickness<lb/> and old Age: Whenever we<lb/> leave you, the
                                improvements<lb/> we make on your Lands<lb/> will belong to you; but
                                the<lb/> Cattle and other Things we<lb/> bring with us, we shall
                                con-<lb/>sider as our own.</p>
                            <p><table>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell><persName key="jsans1">Joseph Sansom</persName></cell>
                                        <cell><persName key="jcoop1">James Cooper</persName></cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell><persName key="hsimm1">Henry Simmons</persName></cell>
                                        <cell><persName>John
                                            <unclear>O'eirn</unclear></persName></cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell><persName key="ewalk1">Enoch Walker</persName></cell>
                                        <cell><persName key="irowl1">Isaiah
                                            Rowland</persName></cell>
                                    </row>
                                </table></p>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                    <pb n="116" facs="SW_JP1796_117"/>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-25">25th.</date><placeName key="oneid"
                        /></dateline>
                    <p>After copying the above<lb/> propositions it was agreed that<lb/> three of
                        our Number should<lb/> go to the <placeName key="oneid">Oneida
                            Town</placeName>, collect<lb/> as many of their Chiefs<lb/> together as
                        they conveniently<lb/> could; read and explain the<lb/> above propositions
                        to them;<lb/> and leave them under their<lb/> Consideration; informing<lb/>
                        them that we should expect<lb/> to meet a general Council<lb/> of their
                        Chiefs and principle<lb/> Men on Second Day the 27th.<lb/> in order to fully
                        consider,<lb/> and agree upon the Several<lb/> particulars mentioned in
                        Said<lb/> propositions.</p>
                    <pb n="117" facs="SW_JP1796_118"/>
                    <p> The rest of our Company<lb/> were employed in writing, and<lb/> paying a
                        friendly Visit to Some<lb/> of the Families of the <orgName
                            key="stockbridge">Stock-<lb/>bridge’s</orgName>: which was to
                        mu-<lb/>tual Satisfaction.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-26">26th.</date><placeName key="stock"
                            type="unattested"/></dateline>
                    <p>Being first Day, we kept<lb/> together at our Lodgings, and<lb/> had a Time
                        of private retire-<lb/>ment, which was somewhat<lb/> trying; and we hope
                        excited<lb/> profitable self examination<lb/> into the Cause.<emph
                            rend="bold"/></p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-27">27th.</date><placeName key="stock"
                        /></dateline>
                    <p>This morning as we<lb/> were preparing to go to the<lb/>
                        <placeName key="oneid">Oneida Town</placeName>, agreeable to<lb/> the
                        Conclusions of seventh<lb/> Day<lb/>
                        <pb n="118" facs="SW_JP1796_119"/> Day last, we received a Letter<lb/>
                        from <persName key="ncusi1">Nicholas Schuisick</persName> Chief<lb/> of the
                            <orgName key="tuscarora">Tuscorora’s</orgName> informing<lb/> that we
                        need not go to <placeName key="oneid">Oneida</placeName><lb/> this Day, for
                        their Chiefs in-<lb/>tended to come to us at <placeName key="stock"
                            >Stockbridge</placeName>,<lb/> we were at a loss to understand<lb/> the
                        Motives for this Change in<lb/> the State of our Business; but<lb/> could
                        readily perceive Patience<lb/> to be a very necessary Attainment<lb/> whilst
                        we have any Concerns to<lb/> transact with these people;<lb/> We therefore
                        concluded to wait<lb/> for their Reception at our Lodg-<lb/>ings; which we
                        accordingly<lb/> did, but heard no more of them<lb/>
                        <pb n="119" facs="SW_JP1796_120"/> this Day. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-28">28th.</date><placeName key="stock"
                            type="unattested"/></dateline>
                    <p>This morning dispatched<lb/> a Runner to <placeName key="oneid">Oneida
                            Town</placeName>, to<lb/> bring us Word of the Reason of<lb/> our
                        Disappointment yesterday;<lb/> and also to know when and<lb/> where we might
                        soonest<lb/> meet them in Council: </p>
                    <p> About Eleven OClock our<lb/> Messenger returned, brought<lb/> us word that
                        the <orgName key="oneida">Oneida</orgName> Chiefs<lb/> went yesterday to
                            <placeName key="fstan">Fort Stan-<lb/>wick</placeName> to meet the State
                        Com-<lb/>missioners relative to some<lb/> Land which they had sold,<lb/> and
                        they they intended to<lb/> come to us at <placeName key="stock"
                            >Stockbridge</placeName>,<lb/> after<lb/>
                        <pb n="120" facs="SW_JP1796_121"/> after their Return; which<lb/> is
                        expected this Evening: so<lb/> that it appears we can have<lb/> no
                        Opportunity with them<lb/> before tomorrow Morning.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-29">29th.</date><placeName key="stock"
                            type="unattested"/></dateline>
                    <p>Notwithstanding the<lb/> Information of yesterday re-<lb/>specting the
                            <orgName key="oneida">Oneida</orgName> Chiefs<lb/> coming to us, we
                        thought it<lb/> best to go to them; and accord-<lb/>ingly we went to <emph
                            rend="underline"><persName key="jsken1"
                        >Schonandoah</persName></emph><lb/> one of their Chiefs, where we<lb/>
                        before met; but to our Surprise,<lb/> found no preparation making<lb/>
                        either to receive us there, or<lb/> to come to us at <placeName key="stock"
                            >Stockbridge</placeName>:~<lb/>
                        <pb n="121" facs="SW_JP1796_122"/> One of us went after <persName
                            key="jreed1">Jacob<lb/> Reed</persName>, their Interpreter, who<lb/>
                        when he was come, together<lb/> with the <persName key="jsken1">Chief
                            Schonandoah</persName>,<lb/> concluded to try to collect<lb/> the most
                        of their Chiefs to-<lb/>gether or at least pretended<lb/> so to us; and that
                        they had<lb/> dispatched Runners for that<lb/> purpose: we waited ‘till
                        about<lb/> two or three OClock; when we<lb/> were informed, they were out
                        at<lb/> work, and could not be collected<lb/> this Day: but that they
                        would<lb/> meet early tomorrow Morning:<lb/> this was somewhat trying;<lb/> and<lb/>
                        <pb n="122" facs="SW_JP1796_123"/> and notwithstanding we have<lb/> met
                        with various Instances,<lb/> in each of these Tribes, of un-<lb/>feigned
                        Regard and Affection,<lb/> yet it appeared now Seasonable<lb/> to shew some
                        marks of the<lb/> Discouragements naturally<lb/> consiquent on the <del
                            rend="crossout"><gap/></del>present<lb/> seeming Ingratitude;
                        and<lb/> to hint to them our Sensibility<lb/> of such Treatment; which,
                        it<lb/> is hoped, will have some effect<lb/> upon their minds: We<lb/> then
                        agreed to meet them tomor-<lb/>row morning; and returned<lb/> to our
                        Lodgings, at <emph rend="underline"><persName key="haupa1">Captain
                                Hendricks</persName></emph>:</p>
                    <p> In the Evening resumed the <pb n="123" facs="SW_JP1796_124"/><lb/>
                        Consideration of some propositi-<lb/>ons to the <orgName key="stockbridge"
                            >Stockbridge Nation</orgName>,<lb/> which at Intervals of Leisure,<lb/>
                        for Several Days past had been<lb/> seriously before us: We now
                        unit-<lb/>edly concluded upon the follow-<lb/>ing. Viz.</p>
                    <floatingText type="letter">
                        <body>
                            <p> Brothers of the <orgName key="stockbridge">Stockbridge
                                    Nation</orgName>,<lb/> we are very glad to find, that<lb/>
                                through the Blessing of the<lb/> great Spirit, and your honest<lb/>
                                Industry, and frugal Sobriety,<lb/> you may soon be in a way to<lb/>
                                live comfortably, without being<lb/> beholden to anybody <emph
                                    rend="underline">for help.</emph></p>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> As you cannot but<lb/> thankfully acknowledge this<lb/> to<lb/>
                                <pb n="124" facs="SW_JP1796_125"/> to be the Case with
                                your<lb/> Nation in general; and as you<lb/> know we want to help
                                many<lb/> of your Indian Brothers a<lb/> little, who stand in
                                much<lb/> more need than you do; we<lb/> trust you will not
                                think<lb/> hard of us, if we do not do<lb/> a great deal for you at
                                this<lb/> time: But, Brothers, in<lb/> order to encourage you to
                                be<lb/> Still more industrious and<lb/> Saving, and to set a good
                                Exam-<lb/>ple to your indian Brothers<lb/> and neighbors, who are
                                far<lb/> behind you in point of Civil-<lb/>ization, we have agreed
                                to help<lb/> you a little, as follows; </p>
                            <pb n="125" facs="SW_JP1796_126"/>
                            <p> Brothers,<lb/> We agree to give you<lb/> our Smith’s Tools all
                                complete;<lb/> and one of our Friends can instruct<lb/> you a little
                                in using them; and<lb/> also a share of our Implements<lb/> of
                                Husbandry, which we <unclear>expect</unclear><lb/> up by our Friend
                                    <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName>,<lb/> whom we
                                left behind, in order to<lb/> bring them up by water. </p>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> We also are willing to en-<lb/>courage you in building a Grist<lb/>
                                Mill, by agreeing to advance three<lb/> Dollars to your one, of all
                                the mo<lb/>ney actually to be paid for materi-<lb/>als, mechanical
                                Labour, and victu<lb/>aling the Workmen; you finding<lb/> the<lb/>
                                <pb n="126" facs="SW_JP1796_127"/> the Timber, and
                                delivering<lb/> it on the Spot, and doing such<lb/> other parts of
                                the Business<lb/> as you may be capable of, with-<lb/>out bringing
                                it into the gene-<lb/>ral Charge, of which we have<lb/> agreed to
                                pay three fourths:<lb/> We also agree that the 100 Dol.<lb/> lent to
                                    <persName key="haupa1">Captain Hendrick</persName> by our<lb/>
                                Committee, together with 40<lb/> Dollars, lent to <persName
                                    key="jserg1">John Serjant</persName>, by<lb/> us for the use of
                                your Nations,<lb/> shall be considered as a part<lb/> of this
                                Advance; and left<lb/> in your Hands for the aforesaid<lb/> purpose:
                                provided always,<lb/> that<lb/>
                                <pb n="127" facs="SW_JP1796_128"/> if the Government
                                    <unclear>sh</unclear><lb/> at any time pay the Expen<lb/> of
                                said Mill, agreeable to an<lb/> Article which you say is
                                con<lb/>tained in a late Treaty, then, in<lb/> that Case you are to
                                refund to<lb/> our Committee all and every<lb/> part of the Advance
                                made by<lb/> us towards said Mill. </p>
                            <p> And we propose our Friends<lb/>
                                <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName> and <persName
                                    key="ewalk1">Enoch Walker</persName><lb/> to take the special
                                Care and Su-<lb/>perintendence of building said<lb/> Mill, without
                                making any<lb/> Change on you for their Trou-<lb/>ble: and we
                                further propose,<lb/>
                                <pb n="128" facs="SW_JP1796_129"/> that when said Mill is<lb/>
                                erected, that you call a general<lb/> Council, and choose a
                                Suitable<lb/> man amongst yourselves to<lb/> take the Care of this
                                Mill,<lb/> and to grind all your Grain;<lb/> and to keep the Mill in
                                Or-<lb/>der; and that you agree on<lb/> some certain and fixed
                                pro-<lb/>portion for this man to <del><gap/></del><lb/> have,
                                out of every Grist that<lb/> shall be ground, sufficient<lb/> to pay
                                him well for his <del>Trouble</del><lb/> Time and Trouble, and to
                                ena-<lb/>ble him to keep the Mill in<lb/> good repair; which he
                                ought<lb/> to do at his own Expense, out<lb/> of his profits which
                                you allow<lb/>
                                <pb n="129" facs="SW_JP1796_130"/> him: and we further
                                propose,<lb/> that you admit your Brother,<lb/> the <orgName
                                    key="tuscarora">Tuscarora’s</orgName>, to enjoy a part<lb/> of
                                the Advantages of th<emph rend="underline">is mill.</emph></p>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> We also <del>to</del> propose to<lb/> encourage you, in keeping<lb/>
                                up a School for the Education<lb/> of your Children, by agreeing
                                to<lb/> pay a part of the Salary to your<lb/> former Master,
                                    <persName key="jquin2">John Quinney</persName>,<lb/> if he will
                                agree again to teach<lb/> we are willing to pay 25 Dol-<lb/>lars a
                                Quarter, for our year, at<lb/> least, if you will agree to make<lb/>
                                up as much more as to encourage<lb/> him to keep steadily: Our
                                    Friend<unclear>s</unclear><lb/> who stay amongst you, will<lb/>
                                pay the Money punctually,<lb/>
                                <pb n="130" facs="SW_JP1796_131"/> when a Certificate is
                                produced<lb/> to them signed by two our your<lb/> Chiefs, certifying
                                that the School<lb/> has been kept steadily for the<lb/> Length of
                                Time above mentioned<lb/> for Payments; the <orgName key="tuscarora"
                                    >Tuscorora’s</orgName><lb/> being admitted to partake
                                e-<lb/>qually of the Advantages of<lb/> this School.</p>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> We further propose,<lb/> for your Encouragement in<lb/> Agriculture,
                                Industry &amp;c. that,<lb/> for the Term of two years from<lb/> the
                                third month next, we will<lb/> give the following Premiums<lb/> to
                                any Individual Indian of<lb/> the <orgName key="stockbridge"
                                    >Stockbridge</orgName> or <orgName key="tuscarora"
                                    >Tuscorora</orgName><lb/> Nations, living in this
                                Reser-<lb/>vation, upon the Conditions<lb/>
                                <pb n="131" facs="SW_JP1796_132"/> herein after mentioned</p>
                            <p> 1st. For every 50 Bushels of<lb/> Wheat raised in any one year<lb/>
                                within Said Term, by any<lb/> one Farmer, of either of these<lb/>
                                two Nations, on his own Land,<lb/> not worked by white people,<lb/>
                                the Sum of two Dollars.</p>
                            <p> 2nd. For every 100 Bushels of<lb/> Indian Corn, raised in like<lb/>
                                Manner aforesaid, the Sum of<lb/> two Dollars. </p>
                            <p> 3rd. For every 100 Bush. of Pota-<lb/>toes raised as aforesaid,
                                the<lb/> Sum of one Dollar &amp; an half.</p>
                            <p> 4th. For every three Tons of hay<lb/> raised as aforesaid, and
                                put<lb/> into a Stack or Barn, the Sum<lb/> of two Dollars.</p>
                            <pb n="132" facs="SW_JP1796_133"/>
                            <p> 5th. For every 12 yards of linnen<lb/> Cloth made by and Indian
                                Woman<lb/> out of Flax raised on her, or her<lb/> Husband’s Land,
                                and spun in<lb/> her own House, the Sum of one<lb/> Dollar, to be
                                paid to the <emph rend="underline">woman.</emph></p>
                            <p> 6th. For every 12 yards, of<lb/> Wollen Cloth, made as
                                aforesaid<lb/> out of the Wool of her own, or<lb/> her Husband’s
                                Sheep, spun<lb/> in like Manner aforesaid<lb/> the Sum of one
                                Dollar, to be<lb/> paid to the woman.* </p>
                            <p> Now the Conditions of ob-<lb/>taining the above premiums are,</p>

                            <p>*Note, The <orgName key="stockbridge">Stockbridges</orgName> having
                                an<lb/> Inclination to apply a part of their<lb/> Annual Income from
                                Government,<lb/> to the Encouragement of Industry</p>
                            <pb n="133" facs="SW_JP1796_134"/>
                            <p>that the person applying,<lb/> shall produce a Certificate<lb/>
                                signed, at least, by two of the Chiefs<lb/> of his or her particular
                                Tribe,<lb/> certifying the particular Quan-<lb/>tity of Grain, Cloth
                                &amp;c. for which<lb/> Said premium shall be demand-<lb/>ed, and
                                that it was raised or made<lb/> in the manner above
                                particularly<lb/> specified; and also that the appli-<lb/>cant has
                                not, to the best of their<lb/> knowledge, been intoxicated with<lb/>
                                Strong Drink, at least, for the<lb/> Space of one full year
                                before<lb/> such Application be made.</p>
                            <lb/>
                            <p> by premiums, defined one of us to draw<lb/> them a plan for that
                                purpose; which<lb/> gave rise to the above; this will ac-<lb/>count
                                for the smallness of the Sums<lb/> annexed to each Article.</p>
                            <pb n="134" facs="SW_JP1796_135"/>
                            <p> And we further propose,<lb/> that any man or woman of<lb/> these two
                                nations, by producing<lb/> a Certificate from two of the<lb/> Chiefs
                                as aforesaid, that he or<lb/> she is highest or foremost in<lb/> any
                                one or more of the above<lb/> particulars, of any other person<lb/>
                                in that nation, he or she shall<lb/> be entitled to a double
                                premium<lb/> for the particular in which<lb/> he or she shall be so
                                highest<lb/> or foremost.</p>
                            <p> And our Friends <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob<lb/> Taylor</persName>,
                                    <del rend="crossout">and</del>
                                <persName key="hsimm1">Henry Simmons</persName>,<lb/> and <persName
                                    key="ewalk1">Enoch Walker</persName> are hereby<lb/> authorized,
                                and desired to pay<lb/> the above mentioned premi-<lb/>ums,
                                agreeable to what is herein<lb/>
                                <pb n="135" facs="SW_JP1796_136"/> above particularly
                                mentioned.</p>
                            <p>
                                <date when="1796-06-29">Sixth mo 29th. 1796.</date></p>
                            <list type="simple">
                                <item><persName key="jpier1">John Peirce</persName></item>
                                <item><persName key="jcoop1">James Cooper</persName></item>
                                <item><persName key="jsans1">Joseph Sansom</persName></item>
                                <item><persName key="irowl1">Isaiah Rowland</persName></item>
                                <item><persName key="hsimm1">Henry Symmons</persName></item>
                                <item><persName key="ewalk1">Enoch Walker</persName></item>
                            </list>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <pb n="136" facs="SW_JP1796_137"/>
                    <dateline><date when="1796-06-30">30th.</date><placeName key="oneid"
                            type="unattested"/></dateline>
                    <p>Again attended the <orgName key="oneida">Oneida</orgName><lb/> Council,
                        agreeable to the Conclusi-<lb/>on of yesterday; met at <persName
                            key="jsken1">Schonan-<lb/>doah</persName>’s between 10 &amp; 11 OClock, and<lb/>
                        <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName> being arrived this morning
                        attended<lb/> with us; we found the Chiefs &amp;c.<lb/> Collected and
                        waiting for us; so that<lb/> we soon got to Business: Which<lb/> was opened
                        by their speaking<lb/> particularly to our propositions<lb/> of the 25th.
                        Instant, <del>and</del> left<lb/> under their Confederation;<lb/> to the
                        following Effect; viz.</p>
                    <floatingText type="speech">
                        <body>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> We find no Difficulty<lb/> in accepting your proposals,<lb/> in
                                anything but the place<lb/> you choose. <emph rend="underline">See
                                    5th. Article.</emph><lb/>
                                <pb n="137" facs="SW_JP1796_138"/> many of us are against
                                part-<lb/>ing with any of our Commons,<lb/> because we have hardly
                                pasture<lb/> enough for our Cattle now, and<lb/> if we lessen it,
                                they will be famish-<lb/>ed, and brake down our fences to<lb/> get
                                at our Corn. Besides which<lb/> we are afraid our young men<lb/>
                                will disturb you there, some-<lb/>times when they get in Li<emph
                                    rend="underline">quor.</emph></p>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> We think it right to<lb/> propose another place to you,<lb/> which
                                we think will suit you<lb/> better: we will go and shew it<lb/> to
                                you.</p>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                    <p> Upon this the Spot was<lb/> viewed, and mutually agreed<lb/> to, bounded as
                        follows; Beginning<lb/>
                        <pb n="138" facs="SW_JP1796_139"/> at a Gut or Run South,
                        South<lb/>east of <persName key="ashon1">Anthony
                        Shononghleya’s</persName><lb/> House, and running nearly South<lb/> by a
                        couple of noted trees to <geogName key="shana">Shan-<lb/>andoah
                            Creek</geogName>, extending eastward<lb/> into the woods without
                        Limi-<lb/>tation; and one of their Chiefs<lb/>
                        <persName key="ashon1">Anthony Shononghleya</persName> being<lb/> willing to
                        rent his house, which<lb/> appeared in a good Degree suit-<lb/>able for our
                        purpose; we agreed<lb/> to rent it at 20 Dollars a year<lb/> as long as we
                        should stay in this<lb/> Country under the present Con-<lb/>cern, paying him
                        one years Rent<lb/> down and covenanting to make<lb/> some Repairs: This
                        House is<lb/> Frame, about 38 feet by 18, one<lb/>
                        <pb n="139" facs="SW_JP1796_140"/> story high; and with a small<lb/>
                        Expense will be pretty warm<lb/> and comfortable; and is well<lb/> situated,
                        on an Eminence, com-<lb/>manding a view of nearly all<lb/> the aforesaid
                        Trait.</p>
                    <p> They next objected to a part<lb/> of the eighth Article relative<lb/> to the
                        Oxen and Horses and<lb/> Oxen being worked, saying, “We<lb/> have but two
                        pair of Oxen be-<lb/>longs to the Town, and some bo-<lb/>dy is always using
                        them, <del>but</del><lb/> therefore we can’t spare them;<lb/> but there is a
                        pair of Steers,<lb/> you may have them to break<lb/> and work: and our
                        Horses we<lb/> can’t spare them; because they<lb/>
                        <unclear>a'n't</unclear> good for anything to work.</p>
                    <pb n="140" facs="SW_JP1796_141"/>
                    <p> And as to they Hay you asked<lb/> us about, say they, you may<lb/> have as
                        much as you want<lb/> at such and such certain<lb/> Flats, about three miles
                        off,<lb/> which they described to us, and<lb/> which several of our
                        Company<lb/> had seen and believed to be good.<lb/>
                        <emph rend="bold"/></p>
                    <p> The above being all the<lb/> Variations they wished to<lb/> make from our
                        proposals;<lb/> we agreed to the Amendments;<lb/> and they appointed
                        <persName key="jsken1">John Scho-<lb/>nandoah</persName>, <persName
                            key="ashon1">Anthony Shononghleya</persName>,<lb/> and <persName
                            key="nshag1">Nicholas Shagorakorongo</persName> to<lb/> unite with our
                        Friends agree-<lb/>able to the 9th. Article.</p>
                    <pb n="141" facs="SW_JP1796_142"/>
                    <p> We then desired the Copy<lb/> we had given them of our<lb/> proposals in
                        order to insert<lb/> on them the foregoing Excep-<lb/>tions and amendments;
                        to<lb/> the End that we might dearly<lb/> understand one another; and<lb/>
                        that we might have it all<lb/> in writing to keep our Memo-<lb/>ries bright:
                        we then broke<lb/> up, after informing them<lb/> that we should expect
                        one<lb/> more general Meeting with<lb/> them before we went away,<lb/> which
                        we wished their Women<lb/> and young people <del>to</del> generally<lb/> to
                        attend.</p>
                    <pb n="142" facs="SW_JP1796_143"/>
                    <p> We next executed a memo-<lb/>randum of agreement between<lb/>
                        <persName key="ashon1">Anthony Shononghleya</persName> and our<lb/> Friends
                        respecting the House,<lb/> paid him the 20 Dollars for<lb/> the first years
                        Rent, took his<lb/>
                        <unclear>Reecit</unclear> therefor; and returned<lb/> to our Lodgings at
                            <persName key="haupa1">Cap. Hendricks</persName></p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-07-01">Seventh mo. 1st.</date><placeName key="stock"
                            type="unattested"/></dateline>
                    <p>Early this<lb/> Morning three of our Num-<lb/>ber set off for <placeName
                            key="fschy">fort Schuyler</placeName>, &amp;<lb/> that Neighbourhood, in
                        order<lb/> to buy a pair of Oxen, and make<lb/> some other necessary
                        prepara-<lb/>tions for our new Settlement;<lb/> and to endeavor to get up
                        some<lb/> of our Good; whilst others were<lb/>
                        <pb n="143" facs="SW_JP1796_144"/> employed in writing, and
                        arang-<lb/>ing different parts of our<lb/> Business; and a proposition<lb/>
                        for the writing of a Letter of<lb/> general Information to our<lb/>
                        Committee at <placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName><lb/> being
                        made, the Expediency<lb/> thereof was agreed to, and our<lb/>
                        <unclear>Essay</unclear> made.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-07-02">2nd.</date><placeName key="stock"/></dateline>
                    <p>Resumed our writing<lb/> and Arangements; and the<lb/>
                        <unclear>Essay</unclear> of a general Letter being<lb/> read and considered,
                        was united<lb/> with, and transcribed; being<lb/> as follows: viz.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="letter">
                    <floatingText type="letter">
                        <body>
                            <dateline><placeName key="stock">Stockbridge</placeName>
                                <date when="1796-07-01">7th. mo. 1st. 1796</date></dateline>
                            <p> Dear Friends,</p>
                            <p> We are all pretty well<lb/>
                                <pb n="144" facs="SW_JP1796_145"/> at present, and through
                                the<lb/> Blessing of Superintending Good-<lb/>ness, have been mostly
                                preserved<lb/> in a good Degree so, since we<lb/> left home, tho’
                                not without some<lb/> Exceptions: We feel ourselves now<lb/> a
                                little revived in our spirits, by<lb/> the arrival of our friend
                                Jacob <persName key="jtayl1">Taylor</persName>; of<lb/> whom we had
                                heard nothing<lb/> since we left home, ‘till he came<lb/> to us
                                yesterday, at <placeName key="stock">Stockbridge</placeName>:<lb/>
                                It appears he has had a safe,<lb/> tho’ tedious passage; has
                                safely<lb/> landed, at <placeName key="fschy">fort
                                    Schuyler</placeName> about<lb/> 22 Miles from this place,
                                all<lb/> the Goods committed to his<lb/> Care: and
                                notwithstanding<lb/> we have been between two<lb/> and<lb/>
                                <pb n="145" facs="SW_JP1796_146"/> and three weeks amongst
                                the<lb/> different Tribes in the <orgName key="oneida"
                                    >Oneida</orgName><lb/> Reservation, we have not been<lb/> able,
                                with the greatest Assiduity<lb/> and Address that we have been<lb/>
                                capable of, to bring our Business<lb/> into any tolerable State of
                                fix-<lb/>edness and arangement until<lb/> the present Time; for we
                                have<lb/> indeed found it tedious, to a<lb/> trying Degree, in doing
                                Busi-<lb/>ness with these people. </p>
                            <p> We have attended general<lb/> Councils of the <orgName
                                    key="stockbridge">Stockbridge</orgName>,<lb/>
                                <orgName key="oneida">Oneida</orgName>, <orgName key="tuscarora"
                                    >Tuscorora</orgName>, and <orgName key="brotherton"
                                    >Brother-<lb/>town’s</orgName>, as there are these four<lb/>
                                distinct Tribes living on this<lb/> Reservation; and have
                                spared<lb/> no reasonable pains to make<lb/> our-<lb/>
                                <pb n="146" facs="SW_JP1796_147"/> ourselves thoroughly
                                acquainted<lb/> with their individual and<lb/> relative Situations
                                in various<lb/> respects; having visited many<lb/> of them in their
                                private<lb/> Huts: And as we have kept<lb/> regular Minutes of
                                our<lb/> proceedings since our Arival<lb/> in this Country, which
                                was<lb/> on the 11th. of last month, we<lb/> hope, if favoured to
                                get home,<lb/> to have the Satisfaction of<lb/> laying them before
                                you:<lb/> In the mean time, trust it<lb/> will be acceptable to
                                you<lb/> to receive the following Sum-<lb/>mary of our Sense of
                                things here.</p>
                            <pb n="147" facs="SW_JP1796_148"/>
                            <p> The <orgName key="brotherton">Brothertown's</orgName> are a
                                mixed<lb/> people from various parts of<lb/> the eastern
                                Governments, set-<lb/>tled here on a Tract of Land giv-<lb/>en to
                                them by the <orgName key="oneida">Oneida’s</orgName>, and<lb/>
                                forming themselves into a kind<lb/> of national Compact under<lb/>
                                the Appellation of Brothers,<lb/> and calling their Settlement<lb/>
                                by the Name of <placeName key="broth">Brothertown</placeName>,<lb/>
                                they are considered as a distinct<lb/> Tribe under that Name. </p>
                            <p> They consist of about 56 Fa-<lb/>milies, have 9900 Acres of<lb/>
                                Land now, but their Original<lb/> Gift from the <orgName
                                    key="oneida">Oneida’s</orgName> was<lb/> much more, which has
                                been<lb/> reduced, much through their<lb/> own mismanagement, by<lb/>
                                <pb n="148" facs="SW_JP1796_149"/> leasing &amp;c. to the white
                                peo-<lb/>ple, ‘till Government out<lb/> of friendship to them,
                                took<lb/> notice of their Situation, pur-<lb/>chased the greater
                                part of their<lb/> Tract, and secured the above<lb/> Quantity to
                                them by Law, in<lb/> Such a manner that no Indi-<lb/>vidual of them
                                has a right<lb/> to sell or lease any part of<lb/> it to white
                                people;* but it<lb/> is divided into Lots of different<lb/>

                            <note>*Note. The Information in minute, of the<lb/> 18th of last mo. p. 97.
                                respecting the <orgName key="oneida">Oneida’s</orgName><lb/> selling
                                this Land to the State of New York,<lb/> was obtained after writing
                                this Letter,<lb/> and added to that minute; yet does<lb/> not
                                contradict the Reason here given<lb/> for the Loss of their Lands;
                                the State</note>
                            <pb n="149" facs="SW_JP1796_150"/>
                            Sizes, which they possess, as<lb/> they do other Things, as
                                distinct<lb/> and private property: They<lb/> have one Sawmill on
                                their Land,<lb/> which is private Property; and<lb/> there is a
                                Grist Mill belonging<lb/> to white people about two or<lb/> three
                                Miles from the Center<lb/> of their Buildings; they have<lb/> some
                                good Cattle, Cows and working<lb/> Oxen, and about ₤800 a year
                                com-<lb/>ing in from Government; so that<lb/> they seem to be in a
                                promising<lb/> way to live comfortably, being<lb/> under<lb/> having acknowledged the prior right<lb/> of the <orgName
                                    key="brotherton">Brothertown’s</orgName>, they might
                                cer-<lb/>tainly have retained their whole<lb/> Land, had not their
                                own Imprudence<lb/> rendered the above measure eligible.</p>
                            <pb n="150" facs="SW_JP1796_151"/>
                            <p>under the particular Care<lb/> and Superintendence of three<lb/>
                                <del>Men</del> reputable Men ap-<lb/>pointed by Government, two<lb/>
                                of whom are friends of New-<lb/> York, <persName key="teddy1">T.
                                    Eddy</persName> and <persName key="epryo1">E. Prior</persName>,
                                to-<lb/>gether with <persName key="wfloy1">Col. Floyd</persName>,
                                who<lb/> appears a true friend to them,<lb/> and with whom we have
                                had<lb/> a very satisfactory Conference,<lb/> relative to our
                                Business, par-<lb/>ticularly, as far as it concerned<lb/> this
                                Tribe; and after visiting<lb/> them in general Council, &amp;<lb/>
                                in many of their <del>private</del><lb/> private Habitations,
                                we<lb/> united with the aforesaid <persName key="wfloy1">Col.<lb/>
                                    Floyd</persName>, in believing this Tribe<lb/>
                                <pb n="151" facs="SW_JP1796_152"/> not necessarily objects of
                                Friends<lb/> Help at this Time, in the way<lb/> of Farming Utensils
                                &amp;c. they being<lb/> well provided for, by their
                                Super-<lb/>intendants, out of their Annual<lb/> Sum aforesaid.</p>
                            <p> The <orgName key="stockbridge">Stockbridge Indians</orgName>
                                con-<lb/>sist of about 60 Families, and<lb/> 300 Individuals, these
                                are not<lb/> of the <orgName key="Six Nations">Six
                                Nations</orgName>, but came<lb/> generally from a place called<lb/>
                                <placeName key="stock">Stockbridge</placeName> in New England,<lb/>
                                in the year 1784: They pos-<lb/>sess 23040 Acres of Land, of a<lb/>
                                good Quality, given to them by<lb/> the Oneida’s, and which
                                they<lb/> divide into 100 Acre Lots,<lb/> and every family has
                                one<lb/> Lot, and every Son is to have<lb/> a<lb/>
                                <pb n="152" facs="SW_JP1796_153"/> a Lot laid off by a Settled
                                Order<lb/> ‘till the whole is occupied;<lb/> they have a Sawmill,
                                and<lb/> sundry other Things which<lb/> they enjoy in common;
                                but<lb/> they possess their Land &amp;<lb/> the fruits of it, as
                                distinct<lb/> and private Property; but<lb/> no Individual can sell
                                or<lb/> lease Land to the white people;<lb/> they have 350 Dollars
                                a<lb/> year coming in from General<lb/> Government; but they
                                are<lb/> yet in debt for their Saw-<lb/>mill: but, in general
                                they<lb/> also appear in a promising<lb/> way<lb/>
                                <pb n="153" facs="SW_JP1796_154"/> way to live comfortably in
                                a<lb/> few years, having made con-<lb/>siderable Improvements
                                in<lb/> farming &amp;c. tho’ they have<lb/> great room still to
                                improve,<lb/> especially in Industry: –</p>
                            <p> We united in believing this<lb/> not to be the place to make<lb/>
                                our Settlement, tho’ the people<lb/> appear to us much more
                                deserv-<lb/>ing than the <orgName key="oneida">Oneida’s</orgName>,
                                the<lb/> place we have made choise<lb/> of for that purpose: we<lb/>
                                nevertheless thought it right<lb/> to give them Some
                                Encourage-<lb/>ment to move forward, and<lb/> set a good Example to
                                their<lb/> less<lb/>
                                <pb n="154" facs="SW_JP1796_155"/> less civilized
                                Neighbors;<lb/> we therefore agreed to give<lb/> them our Smiths
                                Tools,<lb/> besides their Share of the<lb/> Implements of
                                Husbandry;<lb/> and to encourage them in keep-<lb/>ing up their
                                School, (as they<lb/> have a pretty suitable Master<lb/> amongst
                                themselves) by agree<lb/>ing to pay 25 Dollars a quar-<lb/>ter as
                                part of his Salary for<lb/> one year at least: and we have<lb/> also
                                agreed to give them some<lb/> assistance in building a Grist<lb/>
                                Mill upon certain stipulated<lb/> Conditions, too lengthy to be
                                par-<lb/>ticularly mentioned in this<lb/> Letter<lb/>
                                <pb n="155" facs="SW_JP1796_156"/> Letter, together with
                                several<lb/> small conditional premiums<lb/> as Encouragement to
                                Industry<lb/> and Sobriety. </p>
                            <p> The <orgName key="tuscarora">Tuscorora’s</orgName> are an
                                in-<lb/>considerable Remnant of that<lb/> Tribe, the main Body of
                                them<lb/> being removed, as we are informed,<lb/> to <emph
                                    rend="underline"><geogName key="grand">grand
                                    River</geogName></emph>: They consist<lb/> of about 12 Families,
                                appear<lb/> very poor and heartless, almost<lb/> without a Leader
                                and without<lb/> Hope: we propose to consider<lb/> them largely in
                                the Distribu-<lb/>tion of the property sent up;<lb/> and have
                                considered them in<lb/> the aforesaid proposals to the<lb/>
                                <orgName key="stockbridge">Stockbridge</orgName>, they living on the<lb/>
                                <pb n="156" facs="SW_JP1796_157"/>
                                <orgName key="oneida">Oneida</orgName> Lands within about<lb/> one
                                mile and an half of <persName key="haupa1">Cap.<lb/>
                                    Hendricks</persName>.</p>
                            <p> The <orgName key="oneida">Oneida’s</orgName> are, by far the<lb/>
                                most considerable nation, being<lb/> the Original proprietors
                                of<lb/> all this part of the Country;<lb/> They consist of between
                                six<lb/> and seven hundred Individuals,<lb/> have yet a large quanty
                                of<lb/> Land of a good Quality, tho’ they<lb/> are frequently making
                                it<lb/> less by Sales to Government,<lb/> one of which is now a
                                surveying,<lb/> and has been some in our way,<lb/> by engaging their
                                Attention.<lb/> They appear to be a declin-<lb/>ing People, not only
                                in their<lb/> Land going one piece after<lb/>
                                <pb n="157" facs="SW_JP1796_158"/> another; but we are
                                informed<lb/> that they actually decrease in<lb/> Numbers; and there
                                is reason<lb/> to believe they will continue<lb/> so to do, unless
                                some reform<lb/> can be happily effected a-<lb/>mongst them: They
                                are<lb/> in a much less civilized<lb/> State than the <orgName
                                    key="stockbridge">Stockbridge</orgName><lb/> or <orgName
                                    key="brotherton">Brothertown’s</orgName>: they have<lb/> many
                                horses and some Cattle;<lb/> a Sawmill, and Smith’s<lb/> Shop, with
                                a smith hired<lb/> by the year, by Government;<lb/> and about 700
                                Dollars a<lb/> year from general Government,<lb/> and about 5000
                                from the<lb/> State of New-York. Here<lb/> we<lb/>
                                <pb n="158" facs="SW_JP1796_159"/> we have unitedly agreed<lb/>
                                to make our Settlement,<lb/> and have agreed with them<lb/>
                                respecting the place, as well<lb/> as the Terms and Conditions;<lb/>
                                which we hope is now pretty<lb/> clearly understood by them<lb/> and
                                us; but we have had<lb/> divers Meetings with them<lb/> on the
                                Occasion, and in seve-<lb/>ral Respects a trying Time,<lb/> before
                                we could get our plan<lb/> fully established: We have<lb/> a
                                considerable Tract of un-<lb/>cultivated Land now allotted<lb/> to
                                us near the Center of<lb/> their Settlement, and<lb/>
                                <pb n="159" facs="SW_JP1796_160"/> about four miles from
                                    <placeName key="stock">Stock-<lb/>bridge</placeName>, and ten or
                                twelve from<lb/>
                                <placeName key="broth">Brothertown</placeName>: We have also
                                    <unclear>rent</unclear><lb/> a House in a good Situation<lb/>
                                commanding a view of nearly<lb/> all our Tract; it is a frame<lb/>
                                Building about 22 by 18 one<lb/> story high, with two Rooms<lb/>
                                down stairs, and a good Loft;<lb/> and with a small Expence<lb/> can
                                be made a comfortable<lb/> Dwelling: It belonged to one<lb/> of
                                their Chiefs, who to oblige<lb/> us, as well as in
                                consideration<lb/> of a handsome Rent, has a-<lb/>greed to move out
                                and give<lb/> us possession next Second<lb/> Day<lb/>
                                <pb n="160" facs="SW_JP1796_161"/> Day: The Obtaining of
                                this<lb/> House we considered as a<lb/> favorable Circumstance<lb/>
                                to our Business.</p>
                            <p> Dear Friends, neither the<lb/> Room nor Leisure allotted for<lb/>
                                this Letter will admit the<lb/> Insertion of the various<lb/>
                                propositions and conclu-<lb/>sions which have occured<lb/> relative
                                to this Settlement,<lb/> we must ask your patience<lb/> for the
                                particulars until<lb/> we are able to furnish you<lb/> with our
                                Minutes.</p>
                            <p> Three of our Friends are<lb/> this Day gone out for <placeName
                                    key="fschy">fort<lb/>
                                    <pb n="161" facs="SW_JP1796_162"/> Schuyler</placeName> and
                                that Neighbour-<lb/>hood in order to purchase Ox<lb/>en, and some
                                other Necessaries,<lb/> for our new Settlement, and<lb/> to attend
                                to getting some of<lb/> our Goods up; so that we have<lb/> a Hope to
                                see our Friends<lb/> settled in their new Habi-<lb/>tation by
                                    <del>second</del>third Day next,<lb/> and that we shall be
                                able<lb/> to satisfactorily leave them<lb/> in a couple of Days
                                after.</p>
                            <p> We have been kindly received<lb/> by the Indians in general,
                                and<lb/> have received many marks<lb/> of unfeigned Regard and
                                Af-<lb/>fection amongst them; and<lb/> have had the Satisfaction to<lb/>
                                <pb n="162" facs="SW_JP1796_163"/> observe a very
                                agreeable<lb/> Disposition amongst the<lb/> white Inhabitants on
                                the<lb/> frontiers, relative to the In-<lb/>dians and our Concern;
                                and<lb/> we may thankfully acknow-<lb/>ledge, that in several of
                                our<lb/> public Counsels in particular,<lb/> we have been graciously
                                favoured<lb/> with the overshadowing wrong<lb/> of holy Help to our
                                humble<lb/> Encouragement; and to the<lb/> Strengthening of our
                                minds in<lb/> the Belief of the rectitude of<lb/> this Concern; and
                                that its<lb/> Origin is from the Univer-<lb/>sal Father of the great
                                family<lb/> of<lb/>
                                <pb n="163" facs="SW_JP1796_164"/> of mankind; who cannot
                                but<lb/> be graciously mindful of what-<lb/>soever his Hand hath
                                made;<lb/> yet we have had some pretty<lb/> close and Exercising
                                Seasons<lb/> to pass through, more parti-<lb/>cularly amongst the
                                    <orgName key="oneida">Oneida’s</orgName>;<lb/> who had suffered
                                their Expec-<lb/>tations to be raised to an un-<lb/>reasonable
                                Height before<lb/> our arrival; so that our pro-<lb/>posals,
                                especially at the first,<lb/> instead of exciting Gratitude,<lb/>
                                appeared rather to be received<lb/> with those Sensations
                                attendant<lb/> on disappointed Expec<emph rend="underline"
                                    >tations.</emph></p>
                            <p> We expect to move towards<lb/>
                                <placeName key="canan">Conandarque</placeName>, taking two small<lb/>
                                <pb n="164" facs="SW_JP1796_165"/> Tribes on our way; viz.<lb/>
                                <emph rend="underline"><orgName key="onondaga"
                                    >Onondago</orgName></emph>, about 30 miles<lb/> from <placeName
                                    key="oneid">Oneida</placeName>; and <orgName key="cayugaind"
                                    >Cayuga</orgName>,<lb/> about 30 further; by the<lb/> foregoing
                                friends will be<lb/> able to form some Idea, when<lb/> we may be
                                expected to reach<lb/>
                                <placeName key="canan">Conandarque</placeName>; at which<lb/> place
                                we should be very glad<lb/> to hear from our Friends,<lb/> not
                                having received any In-<lb/>structions since we left home.</p>
                            <p> With near Love and<lb/> affection to you and our<lb/> friends and
                                Connections in<lb/> general we remain, &amp;c.</p>
                            <p><list type="simple">
                                    <item><persName key="jpier1">John Peirce</persName></item>
                                    <item><persName key="irowl1">Isaiah Rowland</persName></item>
                                    <item><persName key="jcoop1">James Cooper</persName></item>
                                    <item><persName key="ewalk1">Enoch Walker</persName></item>
                                    <item><persName key="jsans1">Joseph Sansom</persName></item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                    <pb n="165" facs="SW_JP1796_166"/>
                    <p> In the afternoon of this Day<lb/> we attended a farewell Council<lb/> of the
                            <orgName key="tuscarora">Tuscorora’s</orgName>, which was<lb/> opened by
                        informing them in<lb/> what Respects we had considered<lb/> them in our
                        propositions to<lb/> the <orgName key="stockbridge">Stockbridge’s</orgName>,
                        and also that<lb/> we meant to give them a<lb/> large Share, in
                        proportion<lb/> to their numbers, of the Goods<lb/> which we should have to
                        divide,<lb/> after which we were favoured<lb/> renewedly to open before
                        their<lb/> view the Serious necessity of<lb/> a Change in their Manner<lb/>
                        of Life; together with the<lb/> probability that as they increas-<lb/> ed in
                        Industry and Sobriety,<lb/>
                        <pb n="166" facs="SW_JP1796_167"/> they would partake more<lb/>
                        plentifully of the Blessings<lb/> of the great Spirit, both in<lb/>
                        Temporals and Spirituals: </p>
                    <p> They appeared in a good<lb/> Degree serious; and <persName key="ncusi1"
                            >Nicholas<lb/> Schusick</persName>, their Chief, answered<lb/> on Behalf
                        of the whole, in<lb/> Substance, as follows, viz.</p>
                    <floatingText type="speech">
                        <body>
                            <p> “Brothers,</p>
                            <p> We sha’nt say much,<lb/> only a few words, we thank<lb/> the great
                                Spirit, that has put<lb/> it into your Hearts to come<lb/> so far to
                                see us: We acknowledge<lb/> that we are poor, and weak &amp;<lb/>
                                ignorant, and don’t do as we<lb/> ought<lb/>
                                <pb n="167" facs="SW_JP1796_168"/> ought to do; but we have
                                some<lb/> Feelings; and we heartily thank<lb/> you for your good
                                Advice, and<lb/> help to poor Indians, both for<lb/> our Bodies and
                                for our Souls:<lb/> and we promise you, we will<lb/> try to follow
                                your advice; and<lb/> we are glad you are going to<lb/> leave some
                                of your friends<lb/> with us, that they may in-<lb/>struct us, and
                                put us in<lb/> Mind of your words: for though<lb/> we desire to do
                                what you have<lb/> told us , but we are weak and<lb/> should forget;
                                but now they<lb/> will put us in mind, and<lb/> we hope we shall
                                    <emph rend="underline">improve.</emph></p>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                    <pb n="168" facs="SW_JP1796_169"/>
                    <p> In the Evening two of our<lb/> friends, who went yesterday to<lb/> the white
                        Settlements, returned,<lb/> and informed, that they have<lb/> bought Oxen, a
                        Cart and some<lb/> other necessaries, and that<lb/> the other Friend was
                        gone<lb/> to <placeName key="broth">Brothertown</placeName>, in Company<lb/>
                        with our friend <persName key="jevan1">Joshua Evans</persName>,<lb/> whom
                        they met with at <placeName key="fschy">fort<lb/> Schuyler</placeName>. </p>
                    <p> They also inform of the fol-<lb/>lowing melancholy Accident which<lb/>
                        happened last Evening at the<lb/> aforesaid <placeName key="fschy">fort
                            Schuyler</placeName>: The<lb/> House of one <persName>Jonston</persName>
                        an<lb/> Innkeeper, who had been<lb/>
                        <pb n="169" facs="SW_JP1796_170"/> settled there about two years,<lb/>
                        took fire about Eleven OClock<lb/> at Night, and in less than an<lb/> Hour
                        was burnt to the Ground;<lb/> together with much of the pro-<lb/>perty in
                        it; and what was still<lb/> abundantly more trying, one<lb/> of his
                        Daughters a Child of<lb/> about twelve years of Age<lb/> also perished in
                        the Flames:<lb/> This House was a great Re-<lb/>ceptacle for Travelers,
                        many<lb/> of whom were now here; but<lb/> our Friend who lodged in this<lb/>
                        Village, was fortunately at<lb/> the Adjoining Inn; but saw<lb/> the
                        frightful Scene. </p>
                    <p> The poor Child who suffered,<lb/> had<lb/>
                        <pb n="170" facs="SW_JP1796_171"/> had been imprudently left<lb/> up
                        the last in the House; and<lb/> going to Bed in the Garret, where<lb/> they
                        deposited their flax and<lb/> Tow, and carrying a Candle<lb/> with her, this
                        Accident is<lb/> easily accounted for: There<lb/> were two other Children
                        in<lb/> the Garret, one of which<lb/> ran through the Flames &amp;<lb/> got
                        safely down, being only<lb/> a little singed about the<lb/> Head &amp; face;
                        the other had<lb/> the Composure to recollect<lb/> that the Garret Floor
                        was<lb/> loose, and therefore lifted up<lb/> one of the Boards and sliped<lb/>
                        <pb n="171" facs="SW_JP1796_172"/> down, and was saved; but the<lb/>
                        poor Child who had been in-<lb/>strumental to the Scene was so<lb/>
                        confused, as not to know how<lb/> to get down, altho’ her Brother<lb/> had
                        opened the Way: and what<lb/> was more extraordinary the<lb/> poor Mother,
                        reflecting on the<lb/> desperate Situation of her Child,<lb/> most earnestly
                        endeavoured to<lb/> press the same on the Men, with the<lb/> possibility of
                        relieving her, by<lb/> means of the floor being loose;<lb/> but the
                        Confusion was so great,<lb/> that all were deaf to her most<lb/> moving
                        Entreaties; even the<lb/> Child’s Father himself.</p>
                    <pb n="172" facs="SW_JP1796_173"/>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-07-03">3rd.</date><placeName key="broth"/></dateline>
                    <p>This being first Day it<lb/> was considered whether we<lb/> should all go to
                            <placeName key="broth">Brothertown</placeName><lb/> to meet our
                        aforesaid Friend<lb/>
                        <persName key="jevan1">Joshua Evans</persName>, but resulted<lb/> in the
                        negative, that as we<lb/> had made a practice of hold-<lb/>ing Meetings
                        regularly amongst<lb/> ourselves, on this Day, it was<lb/> thought best not
                        to decline<lb/> it on the present Occasion;<lb/> and therefore concluded,
                        that<lb/> one of us only should go to<lb/>
                        <placeName key="broth">Brothertown</placeName>, to give our Said<lb/> Friend
                        a welcome, and if con-<lb/>venient, conduct him to our<lb/> Lodgings, which
                        was accordingly<lb/>
                        <pb n="173" facs="SW_JP1796_174"/> done, in Company with <persName
                            key="haupa1">Cap.<lb/> Hendrick</persName>; returned in the<lb/>
                        Evening, together with the afore-<lb/>said Friend, whom we were<lb/> all
                        glad to see in <emph rend="underline">this Country.</emph></p>
                    <p> Besides the above acceptable<lb/> visit, we had also <del>had</del> the
                        Com-<lb/>pany, a few Days time, of two<lb/> Commissioners departed by<lb/>
                        the Board of Presbyterians<lb/> in Boston, and sent here<lb/> in order to
                        inspect into the<lb/> Truth of some Charges exhibit-<lb/>ed by the Oneida
                        Chiefs<lb/> against their Minister<lb/>
                        <persName key="skirk1">Kirkland</persName>; These Men be-<lb/>sides
                        attending to their own<lb/> Business, enquired particu-<lb/>larly<lb/>
                        <pb n="174" facs="SW_JP1796_175"/> into the Nature and Design<lb/> of
                        ours, with which they seemed<lb/> much pleased, and pased<lb/> some
                        Encomiums on the<lb/> Benevolence of our Undertaking;<lb/>
                        <del>and</del> expressing their hearty<lb/> Wishes for its Success: </p>
                    <p> One of our Company also,<lb/> felt his mind weightily im-<lb/>pressed with
                        some serious<lb/> Considerations relative to<lb/> their Business, and
                        took<lb/> a seasonable opportunity to<lb/> express it to them;
                        reminding<lb/> them how deeply the Re-<lb/>putation of that most ho-<lb/>ly
                        Religion which we and<lb/>
                        <pb n="175" facs="SW_JP1796_176"/> they jointly profess, must be<lb/>
                        effected, in the Eyes of the<lb/> Natives, by the professed<lb/>
                        Promulgations thereof, living<lb/> answerable, or contrary<lb/> to the
                        purity of its Dictates,<lb/> and also calling to their Re-<lb/>membrance,
                        the many most<lb/> glaring and painful Abuses,<lb/> of this sacred function,
                        which<lb/> had from time to time, by<lb/> Missionaries of different
                        De-<lb/>nominations, been exhibited<lb/> towards the Natives of
                        America,<lb/> to the great Scandal and<lb/> wounding of the common<lb/>
                        Cause of Christianity: and<lb/> modestly suggesting to them, our<lb/> ap-<lb/>
                        <pb n="176" facs="SW_JP1796_177"/> apprehensions of the<lb/> present
                        Charges and Com-<lb/>plaints before them not<lb/> being wholly groundless;
                        We<lb/> earnestly pressed upon them<lb/> the necessity of great
                        serious-<lb/>ness and impartiality in<lb/> investigating and resulting<lb/>
                        <del>upon</del> this Business: They<lb/> expressed their Satisfaction<lb/>
                        with this Interview; and<lb/> parted with us very friendly;<lb/> desiring to
                        be favoured with<lb/> a Line of Information in<lb/> some future State of
                        our<lb/> Concern.</p>
                    <p> Here it may be proper<lb/>
                        <pb n="177" facs="SW_JP1796_178"/> to introduce the following
                        anec-<lb/>dote, of an Indian Bible, now<lb/> in the Hands of <persName
                            key="jserg1">John Serjent</persName>,<lb/> Minister to the <orgName
                            key="stockbridge">Stockbridge<lb/> Nation</orgName>; and which we had
                        the<lb/> Sight of; it appears to have<lb/> been entire, containing all<lb/>
                        the Books of the Old and<lb/> new Testaments, translated<lb/> into one of
                        the Indian Lan-<lb/>guages; and they have a Tra-<lb/>dition amongst them;
                        that<lb/> the Translator was so Econo-<lb/>mical as to use but two
                        Quills<lb/> in the whole work.</p>
                    <pb n="178" facs="SW_JP1796_179"/>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-07-04">4th.</date><placeName key="stock"/></dateline>
                    <p>This morning about<lb/> Eleven OClock, again attended<lb/> a general Council
                        of the<lb/>
                        <orgName key="stockbridge">Stockbridge’s</orgName>, in order to in-<lb/>form
                        them what we had<lb/> agreed to do for them, and<lb/> also to take our leave
                        of them;<lb/> Our Friend <persName key="jevan1">Joshua Evans</persName>
                        ac-<lb/>companying us: Our Council<lb/> was opened by a short
                        State-<lb/>ment of our proceedings amongst<lb/> them; and then reading
                        the<lb/> propositions agreed to on the<lb/> 29th. of last month; after
                        which,<lb/> we had a solid Opportunity<lb/> with them; in which
                        graci-<lb/>ous Goodness was experienc'd<lb/>
                        <pb n="178"/> to be near, to the tendering of<lb/> some minds, and
                        furnishing<lb/> with Ability to labour in<lb/> much plainness and Love<lb/>
                        on Several Subjects, but es-<lb/>pecially on the use of strong<lb/> Drink;
                        pointing out the<lb/> Way, and the only way, where-<lb/>by a Victory might
                        be obtain-<lb/>ed over this, and all other<lb/> Temptations of the
                        grand<lb/> Enemy of our Soul’s Happi-<lb/>ness; which consisted in
                        Watch-<lb/>fulness and inward prayer,<lb/> and faithful Obedience to
                        the<lb/> voice of the good Spirit in our<lb/> Hearts, and a careful
                        avoiding<lb/> of<lb/>
                        <pb n="180" facs="SW_JP1796_181"/> of all Places and Occasions<lb/> of
                        Temptation.</p>
                    <p> After which <emph rend="underline"><persName key="samuel"
                            >Samuel</persName></emph>, an<lb/> old Indian man, and a <orgName
                            key="moraind">Mara-<lb/>vian</orgName>, in an affecting Man-<lb/>ner
                        spoke to us in substance<lb/> as follows, viz.</p>
                    <floatingText type="speech">
                        <body>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> I glad to see you<lb/> in my Heart, and to hear<lb/> your good
                                words; you use us<lb/> just like a father; I am<lb/> old, have lost
                                all my family,<lb/> and can’t live many Days;<lb/> but all this
                                Spring I think<lb/> Jesus will send me some<lb/> Comfort in my
                                trouble;<lb/> but nobody say any thing<lb/>
                                <pb n="181" facs="SW_JP1796_182"/> to me ‘till now you are
                                come:<lb/> I wish I was young, then I<lb/> would do what you say
                                direct-<lb/>ly, and I will go and see how<lb/> your Friends work at
                                    <placeName key="oneid">Oneida</placeName>,<lb/> every two or
                                three Days, &amp;<lb/> tell our young Men how you<lb/> do: He
                                afterwards made<lb/> a moving and weighty Speech<lb/> to the Indians
                                in his own<lb/> Language; the weight of which<lb/> was sensibly
                                felt, even, by us<lb/> who did not understand a<lb/> word of what he
                                said; and we<lb/> afterwards understood was re-<lb/>markably so by
                                them; they<lb/> having never heard the like<lb/> from him before.
                            </p>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                    <pb n="182" facs="SW_JP1796_183"/>
                    <p> After a short but solemn<lb/> Pause, <persName key="haupa1">Cap.
                            Hendrick</persName>, in<lb/> Behalf of the Nation, made,<lb/> in
                        substance, the following Reply.</p>
                    <floatingText type="speech">
                        <body>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> We shall speak<lb/> but a few words: We are glad<lb/> of your
                                Company amongst<lb/> us these three weeks, that<lb/> as you told us
                                in the first<lb/> Council, you might know<lb/> what was best for all
                                the<lb/> Indians here, and now you<lb/> tell us, what you think
                                pro-<lb/>per to do for our Nation.</p>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> We rejoice that the good<lb/> Spirit has put it into your<lb/>
                                <pb n="183" facs="SW_JP1796_184"/> Hearts, and into the Hearts
                                of your<lb/> Brothers at home to do us good,<lb/> we believe it is
                                from the good<lb/> Spirit because your Words are weigh-<lb/>ty, and
                                we feel them so on our<lb/> Minds.</p>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> The Offers you make us<lb/> are great, we did not expect so<lb/>
                                much from friends at this<lb/> time; we are thankful to the<lb/>
                                great Spirit for putting it into<lb/> your Hearts, and
                                    <del>also</del> for giving<lb/> you the Ability to do it.</p>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> You give us Smiths<lb/> Tools, for which we thank you,<lb/> we have
                                suffered much for want<lb/> of them, having been obliged to<lb/> go
                                many miles, and sometimes<lb/> loose<lb/>
                                <pb n="184" facs="SW_JP1796_185"/> some Days to get one<lb/>
                                Link of a Chain mended.</p>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> Your assisting us<lb/> to build a Grist-mill, will be a<lb/> great
                                Thing for us; we have suf-<lb/>fered many years for want of<lb/>
                                one, as you are sensible of<lb/> it; and especially our women,<lb/>
                                who are obliged to pound our<lb/> Corn; they join us to thank<lb/>
                                you heartily.</p>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> Your Offer to help<lb/> us in keeping up our School is<lb/> very
                                acceptable to us, be assured<lb/> we will do our part towards<lb/>
                                it.</p>
                            <pb n="185" facs="SW_JP1796_186"/>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> What you propose re-<lb/>specting the money lent us, is<lb/> very
                                agreeable to our minds &amp;<lb/> also the Encouragement you<lb/>
                                offer to our Industry by premi-<lb/>ums: we hope our young men<lb/>
                                will have Courage to follow<lb/> those ways you point out to<lb/>
                                us.</p>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> We now freely pro<lb/>mise, that we the Chiefs, and<lb/> all our
                                orderly young men,<lb/> will endeavour to follow your<lb/> Advice,
                                and with the Blessing<lb/> of the good Spirit, we hope to<lb/> live
                                more than ever as white<lb/> people do; foe we never received<lb/> such<lb/>
                                <pb n="186" facs="SW_JP1796_187"/> such Encouragement
                                before<lb/> from any people.</p>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> We observe what you<lb/> tell us, that we must be an<lb/> Example to
                                other Indians,<lb/> who are far behind us, and we<lb/> will try to
                                be so, more an<emph rend="underline">d more.</emph></p>
                            <p> Brothers, We shall remember<lb/> what you request for the young<lb/>
                                men you leave behind you;<lb/> our minds are the same with<lb/>
                                yours, we will maintain our<lb/> Friendship with them; and will<lb/>
                                be always ready to assist them if<lb/> they get in trouble.</p>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> We spoke to you several<lb/> Days ago about the Difficulties<lb/>
                                <pb n="187" facs="SW_JP1796_188"/> We are under in not
                                receiving<lb/> our annual Income from the<lb/> United States: We
                                desire your<lb/> Friends would help us in this<lb/> Case, and
                                appoint one to take<lb/> care to get our money sent to<lb/> us
                                regularly; and we also desire<lb/> you to try to get Government
                                to<lb/> fulfil their Agreement with<lb/> us about building a
                                Mill.</p>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> This is all we got<lb/> to Say.</p>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-07-05">5th.</date><placeName key="stock"/></dateline>
                    <p>The forepart of this Day,<lb/> we were employed in writing<lb/> Letters home,
                        and making some<lb/> necessary Arangements;<lb/> In the Afternoon two of
                        our<lb/> Number<lb/>
                        <pb n="188" facs="SW_JP1796_189"/> Number went to <placeName
                            key="oneid">Oneida</placeName> to<lb/> give notice, and request a
                        gene-<lb/>ral Council next Day:</p>
                    <p> This Evening received an<lb/> Account of the fourth Murder<lb/> committed
                        amongst these peo-<lb/>ple within these few months<lb/> past; all of which
                        are sup-<lb/>posed to have been occasioned<lb/> by the Use of Spirituous
                        Li-<lb/>quors; One was of the <orgName key="tuscarora"
                            >Tuscoro-<lb/>ra’s</orgName> in the 11th. mo. last, One of<lb/> the
                            <orgName key="stockbridge">Stockbridge’s</orgName> not long af-<lb/>ter,
                        one of the <orgName key="oneida">Oneida’s</orgName> in the<lb/> 6th. mo
                        last; and the <del>last</del>other of<lb/> the <orgName key="cayugaind"
                            >Cayuga’s</orgName> a few Days since;<lb/> Three of these Cases in
                        the<lb/> very neighbourhood where<lb/>
                        <pb n="189" facs="SW_JP1796_190"/> we now are; and the other<lb/> about
                        60 miles from this <del rend="crossout">pla</del><lb/> place, on our way to
                            <placeName key="canan">Conandar-<lb/>que</placeName>. </p>
                    <p> Some of the minds of these<lb/> people are sensibly affected by<lb/> the
                        melancholy Havoc pro-<lb/>duced amongst them by this<lb/> cruel Tyrant: (for
                        so they often<lb/> call it), as the following Me-<lb/>morial to the Assembly
                        of<lb/> New-York will evince.</p>
                    <p> To the great Sachem and<lb/> Chiefs of the State of New York,<lb/> now
                        sitting around the great<lb/> Council Fire at New York.</p>
                    <floatingText type="letter">
                        <body>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> Before you cover your<lb/> Council, we beg your<lb/>
                                <pb n="190" facs="SW_JP1796_191"/> Attention to the voices of
                                your<lb/> brother, the different Tribes living<lb/>
                                <placeName key="oneid">Oneida Country</placeName>; speaks to you
                                in<lb/> the remembrance of the friendship<lb/> you have manifested
                                towards them in<lb/> all their Treaties.</p>
                            <p> We ourselves have held Councils at<lb/> different Times to
                                contemplate the<lb/> welfare of our nations because we<lb/> cannot
                                but groan to see our Situation:<lb/> It is also melancholy to
                                reflect on<lb/> the ways of our forefathers.</p>
                            <p> Brothers</p>
                            <p> You are sometimes sorry<lb/> to see the deplorable Situation of
                                your<lb/> Indian Brethren, for which<lb/> you have given us many
                                good<lb/> Counsels; tho’ we feel ourselves<lb/> willing to follow
                                your Coun-<lb/>sels, but it has made no Effect<lb/> as<lb/>
                                <pb n="191" facs="SW_JP1796_192"/> as yet. Our Situation
                                is<lb/> Still miserable: Our Ancesters<lb/> were conquered
                                immediately<lb/> after you came over this Island<lb/> by the Strong
                                Hero, who does<lb/> still reign among Indian<lb/> Tribes with
                                Tyranny; who<lb/> has robbed us every Thing that<lb/> was precious
                                in our Eyes:<lb/> But we not mention every<lb/> Thing particular how
                                this<lb/> Tyrant has used us; for your<lb/> Eyes have been open to
                                behold<lb/> our doleful Situation; By the<lb/> power of our Enemy
                                our Eyes<lb/> have been blinded Our young<lb/> Men seem become
                                willing<lb/> Slaves to this despotic Heroe<lb/> so<lb/>
                                <pb n="192" facs="SW_JP1796_193"/> so that we displeased
                                the<lb/> great good Spirit, and could<lb/> not become civilized
                                people.<lb/> In looking back we see no-<lb/>thing but Desolation of
                                our<lb/> mighty men: In looking<lb/> forward we see the
                                Desola-<lb/>tion of our Tribes. Our<lb/> Chiefs have used their
                                Endea-<lb/>vours to reform their respective<lb/> people, but having
                                seen<lb/> no Success they seem dis-<lb/>couraged, and hang down<lb/>
                                their Heads.</p>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> In remembrance<lb/> of your kind promises, we<lb/> unite our Cries
                                to you for<lb/>
                                <pb n="193" facs="SW_JP1796_194"/> help: perhaps some of<lb/>
                                you are ready to say; what<lb/> man that must be that has<lb/>
                                abused so much of our Bre-<lb/>thren: never was such
                                    <del>Tyrant</del><lb/> Hero, or Tyrant heard of, that<lb/> ever
                                meddled with Indians;<lb/> but in literally he is your<lb/> only
                                begotten Son, and his<lb/> Name you call <emph rend="underline"
                                    >rum</emph>, and<lb/> the names of his Officers<lb/> are <emph
                                    rend="underline">Brandy</emph>, <emph rend="underline"
                                    >Wine</emph>, and <emph rend="underline">Gin</emph>.</p>
                            <p> And we know you have<lb/> power to control him, and<lb/> as we
                                desire to live in peace,<lb/> and to become civilized Nati-<lb/>ons,
                                we earnestly entreat<lb/> you<lb/>
                                <pb n="194" facs="SW_JP1796_195"/> you to use your power
                                and<lb/> wisdom to prevent all peo-<lb/>ple, whether white or
                                black,<lb/> who may cause Rum and<lb/> other Spirituous Liquors<lb/>
                                throughout your State, to come<lb/> into the Hands of our
                                Tribes;<lb/> except when Sickness requir'd<lb/> our Chiefs may keep
                                little<lb/> for that purpose: for your<lb/> Compliance with this
                                our<lb/> Request, we will ever acknow-<lb/>ledge your
                                friendship.</p>
                            <table cols="2">
                                <row>
                                    <cell> Done at<lb/>
                                        <placeName key="oneid">Oneida<lb/> Village</placeName>
                                        on<lb/> the <date when="1796-03-15">15th. Day<lb/> of
                                            March<lb/> 1796</date></cell>
                                    <cell>Is from your Brothers<lb/> Chiefs and Warriors of<lb/>
                                        <orgName key="oneida">Oneida Nation</orgName>.</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell><persName key="jsken1">John Schonandoah</persName></cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell><persName key="cthon1">Christian
                                                <unclear>Thoningivensera</unclear></persName></cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell><persName key="wthad1">Wm.
                                        Thadughgwesera</persName></cell>
                                </row>
                            </table>
                            <pb n="195" facs="SW_JP1796_196"/>
                            <lb/>
                            <table cols="2">
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell><orgName key="tuscarora">Tuscorora</orgName></cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell><persName key="ncusi1">Nicholas
                                        Schuysick</persName></cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell><persName key="dtyod1">David
                                        Tydeaseagurnel</persName></cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell><persName key="pdyon1">Peter Dyongevet</persName><lb/>
                                        <orgName key="stockbridge">Stockbridge</orgName></cell>
                                </row>

                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell><persName key="haupa1">Hendrick Aupaumut</persName></cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell><persName key="jquin1">Joseph Quinney</persName></cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell><persName key="jshau1">Joseph
                                        Shanquithqueth</persName></cell>
                                </row>
                            </table>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-07-06">6th.</date><placeName key="oneid"
                            type="unattested"/></dateline>
                    <p>This Day attended the<lb/>
                        <orgName key="oneida">Oneida</orgName> Council, agreeably<lb/> to our
                        Conclusions of yesterday;<lb/> which was opened by the revival<lb/> of our
                        Plan of a settlement,<lb/> acording to the variations agreed<lb/> to at our
                        last; and having it<lb/> clearly drawn out, it was sign-<lb/>ed by all our
                        number and six<lb/> of their Chiefs; we endeavoured<lb/> to explain the
                        reason of our<lb/>
                        <pb n="196" facs="SW_JP1796_197"/> present Offers falling short<lb/> of
                        the Suggestions contained<lb/> in our general Letter of last<lb/> Spring;
                        which we understood<lb/> they had observed, with Express-<lb/>ions of
                        surprise; letting them<lb/> know, that every thing must<lb/> have a
                        Beginning; and that<lb/> it could not reasonably be<lb/> expected, that we
                        should go<lb/> into all that was mentioned<lb/> in that Letter at once:
                        They<lb/> appeared to be pretty well<lb/> reconciled to our plan; and<lb/>
                        expressed their Readiness<lb/> to adopt it; and recommend-<lb/>ed to their
                        young Men, who<lb/> were present to engage with<lb/>
                        <pb n="197" facs="SW_JP1796_198"/> willingness into the Business:<lb/>
                        This Council was however not<lb/> quite so satisfactory as could<lb/> have
                        been desired, none of their<lb/> women being present tho’ de-<lb/>sired by
                        us, and some other Cir-<lb/>cumstances was not altogether<lb/> agreeable*:
                        In the Evening<lb/> returned to our Lodgings at<lb/>
                        <persName key="haupa1">Captain Hendricks</persName>, where we<lb/> made out
                        a List, for the Divi<lb/>sion of our Articles between<lb/> the <orgName
                            key="oneida">Oneida</orgName>, <orgName key="stockbridge"
                            >Stockbridge</orgName>, and<lb/>
                        <orgName key="tuscarora">Tuscorora’s</orgName>, retaining a suf-<lb/>ficient
                        part for the use of<lb/> our Friends <emph rend="underline">who stay
                            here.</emph></p>
                    <p>*The Interpreter being in Liquor</p>
                    <pb n="198" facs="SW_JP1796_199"/>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-07-07">7th.</date><placeName key="stockbridge"
                        /></dateline>
                    <p>This morning had<lb/> a very solid and satisfactory<lb/> parting with the
                        principal<lb/> men and women of the<lb/>
                        <orgName key="stockbridge">Stockbridge Nation</orgName>, at the<lb/> House
                        of their Chief, <persName key="haupa1">Cap.<lb/> Hendrick</persName>, many
                        of their<lb/> Hearts being tenderly affected<lb/> at parting with us: we
                        then<lb/> set out for <placeName key="oneida">Oneida Town</placeName>;
                        and<lb/> after arriving at our own<lb/> rented House in that place,<lb/> we
                        felt our Minds disposed<lb/> to sit down together to wait,<lb/> for the
                        renewal of our Strength<lb/> in inward Retirement,<lb/>
                        <persName key="jevan1">Joshua Evans</persName> being also<lb/>
                        <pb n="199" facs="SW_JP1796_200"/> with us; and leaving the Door<lb/>
                        and windows open, the Indians<lb/> came and looked at us <del>in</del><lb/>
                        with silent Admiration, <del><unclear>behav</unclear></del><lb/> behaving in
                        a good Degree Solid,<lb/> and making no D<emph rend="underline"
                            >isturbance.</emph></p>
                    <p> After this Sitting <persName key="jevan1">Joshua<lb/> Evans</persName>
                        expressed a Desire to<lb/> have an Oppertunity with<lb/> the Indians, many
                        of whom,<lb/> both of men &amp; women, were now collected together,<lb/>
                        under an Expectation of the<lb/> Goods being divided, and some<lb/> of us
                        also haveing a like Desire,<lb/> not being fully relieved by<lb/> the
                        Opportunity of yesterday;<lb/> it was at length proposed<lb/>
                        <pb n="200" facs="SW_JP1796_201"/> to the Indians, and agreed<lb/> to,
                        the Interpreter <persName key="jreed1">Jacob Reed</persName><lb/> being
                        present, and in a better<lb/>
                        <del>agreeable</del> Situation for such Bu-<lb/>siness, than at last
                        Council:-</p>
                    <p> This proved a much more<lb/> Satisfactory Oppertunity than<lb/> that of
                        yesterday; our Hearts being<lb/> enlarged with unfeigned Love<lb/> towards
                        them, much Counsel<lb/> was communicated pertinent<lb/> to their Situations;
                        which was<lb/> sensibly felt by some of them,<lb/> especially of the Women,
                        who<lb/> are in general much more<lb/> Solid and reachable than<lb/> the
                        men.</p>
                    <p> After which they<lb/>
                        <pb n="201" facs="SW_JP1796_202"/> made us a short Speech,
                        ex-<lb/>pressive of their Satisfaction<lb/> with this opportunity; and<lb/>
                        our Business in general; <del>among</del><lb/>
                        <del>them;</del> Observing that all the<lb/> Time we had been amongst<lb/>
                        them we had spoken the same<lb/> Language, and made no Change<lb/> in our
                        Words or Conduct.</p>
                    <p> After which a venerable<lb/> old woman, on behalf of her-<lb/>self and
                        Sisters, observed in<lb/> substance, That it was not<lb/> common for their
                        women<lb/> to speak in Council; but<lb/> that they were very glad<lb/> to
                        hear our good Words, and<lb/> heartily thanked us.</p>
                    <pb n="202" facs="SW_JP1796_203"/>
                    <p> After this Opportunity we<lb/> agreed upon the following<lb/> Minute; a Copy
                        of which was<lb/> left with our Friends who<lb/> stay here; viz.</p>
                    <floatingText>
                        <body>
                            <p> At a Conference of the<lb/> Indian Committee held <date
                                    when="1796-07-07">7th.<lb/> mo. 7th. 1796</date>, at our rented
                                House<lb/> at <placeName key="oneid">Oneida Town</placeName>, it was
                                agreed<lb/> to appoint <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob
                                    Taylor</persName> Trea-<lb/>surer, for this Concern at this<lb/>
                                place, who is desired to keep<lb/> regular Entries of all the
                                mo-<lb/>ney received, and paid away,<lb/> and to whom and for
                                what.<lb/> And there is now left in<lb/> his Hands, after settling
                                all<lb/> Expences up to this Day, One<lb/> Hundred Dollars.</p>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                    <pb n="203" facs="SW_JP1796_204"/>
                    <p> About four in the afternoon<lb/> took an affectionate leave of<lb/> our
                        Friends <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName>, <persName
                            key="hsimm1">Hen-<lb/>ry Simmons</persName>, and <persName key="ewalk1"
                            >Enoch<lb/> Walker</persName>; and set out towards<lb/>
                        <placeName key="onond">Onondago</placeName>, lodging at an<lb/> Indian House
                        Eleven Miles<lb/> on our way.</p>
                    <p> Before we leave this Coun-<lb/>try it may be proper to note,<lb/> two
                        singular Advantages,<lb/> peculiar to these parts<lb/> above many others;
                        and<lb/> which the Indians, in Com-<lb/>mon with the white people,<lb/> may
                        and do enjoy: viz. The<lb/>
                        <emph rend="underline">Sugar Maple</emph> &amp; <emph rend="underline">Salt
                            Springs.</emph></p>
                    <pb n="204" facs="SW_JP1796_205"/>
                    <p> From the Maple, they are<lb/> able, with a small Expence,<lb/> to furnish
                        themselves with<lb/> a plentiful supply of Sugar,<lb/> Molasses, and
                        Vinegar: And<lb/> from the Salt Spring they<lb/> are furnished
                        plentifully<lb/> with that valuable Article,<lb/> equal in Quality, and
                        perhaps<lb/> lower in price, than in any<lb/> Seaport Town in the
                        United<lb/> States. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-07-08">8th.</date><placeName key="onond"/></dateline>
                    <p>Pursued our Jour-<lb/>ney, and in about a mile<lb/> and an half crossed the
                            <placeName key="india">In-<lb/>dian Line</placeName>; and a few
                        miles<lb/> further came to a place<lb/>
                        <pb n="205" facs="SW_JP1796_206"/> called <geogName key="deeps">deep
                            Spring</geogName>: This place<lb/> pertinently takes its Name from<lb/>
                        the following curious Appear-<lb/>ance: There is a nearly round<lb/> Hole in
                        the Earth, of about<lb/> 50 or 60 Feet Diameter at<lb/> the Top, and
                        tapering down<lb/> nearly to a point at the Depth<lb/> of about 50 feet: the
                        Water<lb/> Springs out of the side near<lb/> midway from the Top, <del>to
                            the<lb/> Bottom</del> and trickling down<lb/> in a small Stream, sinks
                        into<lb/> a Cavity at the Bottom.</p>
                    <p> Thence through a fertile and<lb/> well improved new Country;<lb/> more than
                        one half of the cleared Land<lb/>
                        <pb n="206" facs="SW_JP1796_207"/> within sight of the Road, being<lb/>
                        either in Grain, or Timothy and<lb/> Clover; some of the latter
                        es-<lb/>pecially exceeding any Grass<lb/> that I have ever seen in<lb/> the
                        most fertile Marshes<lb/> of Pennsylvania; dined<lb/> at <persName
                            key="mdanf1">Asa Danfords</persName>, on <geogName key="onocr"
                            >Onanda-<lb/>go Creek</geogName>; from where we lodged<lb/>18. about 18
                        miles.</p>
                    <p> In the Afternoon attend-<lb/>ed a small Council of the<lb/>
                        <orgName key="onondaga">Onandago’s</orgName>, at their Settlement<lb/> about
                        two miles up the Creek.<lb/> There are but a small Body<lb/> of them here,
                        some of their<lb/> Tribe being removed to<lb/>
                        <pb n="207" facs="SW_JP1796_208"/>
                        <geogName key="buffc1">Buffalo Creek</geogName>, in the <orgName
                            key="seneca">Seneca</orgName><lb/> Country; and many of those<lb/> who
                        live here, having nothing<lb/> to eat, were gone a hunting<lb/> and fishing
                        with their Wives<lb/> and families; The few who<lb/> were now here were very
                        un-<lb/>willing to hold a Council with-<lb/>out having their Tribe all
                        to-<lb/>gether; which, it appeared, could<lb/> not be effected without a
                        great<lb/> Detension to us; we therefore<lb/> proposed, that if they
                        would<lb/> give us an Opportunity to ex-<lb/>press our Minds to them<lb/> in
                        Council, and give us such<lb/> Information as they could<lb/>
                        <pb n="208" facs="SW_JP1796_209"/> respecting their
                        Circumstan-<lb/>ces, that we would leave the<lb/> Substance of what we
                        had<lb/> to say to them, relative to the<lb/> Business in writing; that<lb/>
                        their Interpreter might read<lb/> and explain it to them when<lb/> they
                        should get all together:<lb/> This being agreed to the Coun-<lb/>cil was
                        opened, <del>Abraham</del>
                        <persName key="ewebs1"><handShift medium="pencil"/>Ephraim <handShift
                                medium="ink"/> Web-<lb/>ster</persName> a white man, and friend<lb/>
                        to them, and who had lived ma-<lb/>ny years amongst them, being<lb/> our
                        Interpreter: We let them<lb/> know the nature of our Bu-<lb/>siness, and
                        endeavoured to press<lb/> on the necessity of a<lb/>
                        <pb n="209" facs="SW_JP1796_210"/> Change in their manner of
                        Liv-<lb/>ing; and the Advantage that<lb/> would arise to them from
                        their<lb/> Improving in Industry and<lb/> Sobriety: After which
                        obtained<lb/> the following Information, viz.<lb/> That they consist of
                        about 20<lb/> families and 135 Individuals,<lb/> have 12800 Acres of very
                        good<lb/> Land, secured to them by Law<lb/> so than no Individual of
                        them<lb/> can either sell or lease to white<lb/> people; they have 1250
                        Dollars<lb/> a year coming in from the<lb/> State of new York, besides
                        their<lb/> share of the Gratuity from<lb/> general Government to the<lb/>
                        <pb n="210" facs="SW_JP1796_211"/>
                        <orgName key="Six Nations">Six Nations</orgName>: but they have<lb/> neither
                        plow, Ox, Cow, now Horse;<lb/> and, we are informed, generally<lb/> spend
                        their Money in a few<lb/> Days after they receive it, in<lb/> Rum, and some
                        Trifles of small<lb/> Account to them; and even<lb/> the Blankets which they
                        re-<lb/>ceive from general Government,<lb/> are often pawned for Liquor<lb/>
                        before they get them home; </p>
                    <p> They appear to have form-<lb/>ed great Expectations from<lb/> our Letter;
                        and shewed evident<lb/> Marks of <del>their</del> Dissatisfac-<lb/>tion at
                        their present Disap-<lb/>pointment: we let them<lb/>
                        <pb n="211" facs="SW_JP1796_212"/> know, that our Design was more<lb/>
                        to try to prevail with them to help<lb/> themselves, and to make the
                        best<lb/> use of what they had, as well as<lb/> to help them a little in
                        the<lb/> Beginning; rather than to<lb/> make them large presents, or<lb/> to
                        hire men to come there to do<lb/> their work from them, whilst they<lb/>
                        themselves lived in Idleness, &amp;<lb/> spent their own Money
                        foolishly,<lb/> [which seems to be much their Idea<lb/> of our
                        Intention].</p>
                    <p> Upon proposing to them the<lb/> propriety of their buying Oxen &amp;<lb/>
                        Cows with their Annual Income,<lb/> instead of laying it out for Rum,<lb/>
                        &amp;c. they answered, that they had<lb/> concluded to buy a pair of
                        Oxen<lb/> with<lb/>
                        <pb n="212" facs="SW_JP1796_213"/> with the money which they<lb/>
                        received in this month; but<lb/> when they received our Letter,<lb/> they
                        thought it not necessary<lb/> to lay out their own money for<lb/> that
                        purpose; intimating that<lb/> they supposed we would find<lb/> them Teams
                        and such things:</p>
                    <p> We were deeply affected with<lb/> the unreasonableness of their<lb/>
                        Expectations; as well as their<lb/> extreme Indolence; or rather<lb/>
                        haughty Contempt of any<lb/> Thing that bore the name of<lb/> Labour;
                        together with their<lb/> apparent utter Insensibility<lb/> of any thing that
                        was said<lb/> to them, on the necessity of<lb/>
                        <pb n="213" facs="SW_JP1796_214"/> a Reformation in their Life
                        &amp;<lb/> Manners.</p>
                    <p> We parted from them under<lb/> serious Discouragments returning to the
                        afores’d <persName key="mdanf1">A. Danfords</persName> to lodge and
                        left<lb/> the following in writing with<lb/> their Interpreter, viz.</p>
                    <floatingText type="letter">
                        <body>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> We are sent out by the<lb/> people called Quakers, who<lb/> wrote to
                                the <orgName key="Six Nations">Six Nations</orgName> in the<lb/>
                                Winter to enquire whether they<lb/> were desirous to learn how
                                the<lb/> white people manage their<lb/> Lands; and to have your
                                Children<lb/> taught to read and write, and<lb/> be instructed in
                                useful Trades:<lb/> They have directed us to visit<lb/> you in your
                                Towns, and acquaint<lb/> ourselves with your Circumstan-<lb/>ces,
                                and so inform them that<lb/>
                                <pb n="214" facs="SW_JP1796_215"/> they may judge what to
                                do<lb/> for you: we have settled Three<lb/> of our Friends at
                                    <placeName key="oneid">Oneida</placeName>; and<lb/> some Time
                                hence, we could<lb/> with some of you to go and<lb/> see them: and
                                perhaps also they<lb/> may come and see you: But,<lb/> Brothers,
                                there are so few of<lb/> you here, and there are so ma-<lb/>ny
                                larger Bodies of Indians,<lb/> that it is not likely we can<lb/>
                                share any of our people to set-<lb/>tle here soon: But we
                                expect,<lb/> however that next Spring we<lb/> can send you some
                                Hoes, Axes,<lb/> Sythes, and other Tools to<lb/> work with: and if
                                you have<lb/>
                                <pb n="215" facs="SW_JP1796_216"/> a mind to send six or
                                eight<lb/> of your Boys, from Eight to<lb/> Twelve years of Age to
                                learn<lb/> reading, writing, farming &amp;<lb/> Trades our Friends
                                at <placeName key="oneid">Oneida</placeName><lb/> will tell you how
                                to send them,<lb/> and we will take Care of them,<lb/> as our own
                                Children; and if they<lb/> behave well ‘till they are twen-<lb/>ty
                                one, we will give them some<lb/>thing to begin with: And<lb/> then
                                they may return &amp;<lb/> teach you what they have<lb/>
                                learned.</p>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> We find you have<lb/> good Land, and we see you<lb/> raise some
                                Corn; we advise<lb/> you<lb/>
                                <pb n="216" facs="SW_JP1796_217"/> you to plant twice as
                                much<lb/> next year; and besides you<lb/> have 1250 Dollars a year,
                                which<lb/> give enough for each family<lb/> to buy a Cow in one or
                                two<lb/> years; we advise every Hous-<lb/>keeper to buy one with
                                the<lb/> Money divided to him and<lb/> his Children: you could<lb/>
                                keep your Cows easily; and<lb/> they would give you Milk; &amp;<lb/>
                                then you might make But-<lb/>ter and Cheese, for you to eat;<lb/>
                                and besides your Cows would<lb/> make Beef when they<lb/> got
                                old.</p>
                            <pb n="217" facs="SW_JP1796_218"/>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> Take our Advice, and<lb/> we shall be encouraged to do<lb/> more for
                                you; for we wish to<lb/> help you; if you will but be<lb/> willing
                                to help yourselves.</p>
                            <p><placeName key="onond">Onondago</placeName>
                                <date when="1796-07-08">7th. mo. 8th. 1796</date></p>
                            <list rend="simple">
                                <item><persName key="jpier1">John Peirce</persName></item>
                                <item><persName key="jsans1">Joseph Sansom</persName></item>
                                <item><persName key="irowl1">Isaiah Rowland</persName></item>
                                <item><persName key="jcoop1">James Cooper</persName></item>
                            </list>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-07-09">9th.</date><placeName key="cayug1"
                        /></dateline>
                    <p>Pursued our Journey<lb/> towards <placeName key="cayug1">Cayuga</placeName>,
                        rode 15 miles<lb/> to Breakfast, at <persName key="mcarp1">Moses
                            Car-<lb/>penters</persName>: most of this Stage<lb/> good Limestone
                        Land; but<lb/> thinly<lb/>
                        <pb n="218" facs="SW_JP1796_219"/> thinly settled; where there<lb/> are
                        farms they appear<lb/> flourishing.</p>
                    <p> Thence to <persName key="hmore1">Henry Moors</persName><lb/> where we dined,
                        16 miles:<lb/> Thence leaving the <placeName key="genes3">Genesee<lb/>
                            Road</placeName>, and travailing mostly<lb/> through the woods for
                        about<lb/> 6 Miles <persName key="fgeer1">to Frederick Gerard’s</persName>,
                        within<lb/> about 2 ½ miles of the<lb/> Indian settlement, on the<lb/>
                        <geogName key="cayug">Cayuga Lake</geogName>: Thence in<lb/> Company with
                            <del>the <gap/></del><lb/>34. him to the Indian Town;<lb/> where we
                        arrived in the<lb/> Evening; but finding se-<lb/>veral of their Number<lb/>
                        were gone out a fishing and this<lb/>
                        <pb n="219" facs="SW_JP1796_220"/> being seventh Day, we
                        con-<lb/>cluded to put off the Coun-<lb/>cil ‘till Second Day morn-<lb/>ing;
                        and returned with the<lb/> aforesaid <persName key="fgeer1">Frederick
                            Gerard</persName><lb/> to lodge: This man, with<lb/> his family, had
                        lived several<lb/> years amongst the <orgName key="cayugaind">Cayuga<lb/>
                            Indians</orgName>; but his place<lb/> is now, by a late purchase<lb/>
                        made of these people, with-<lb/>out their Boundaries.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-07-10">10th.</date><placeName key="cayug1"
                        /></dateline>
                    <p>This being first Day,<lb/> our Friend <persName key="jevan1">Joshua
                            Evans</persName> had<lb/> notice given of a Meeting<lb/> to be held at
                        the House of<lb/> our Host for the Benefit<lb/> of<lb/>
                        <pb n="220" facs="SW_JP1796_221"/> of the white Inhabitants;<lb/> which
                        we attended; as well<lb/> as about 20 of the Neighbour-<lb/>ing white
                        people; who be-<lb/>haved in a good Degree solid.</p>
                    <p> In the Afternoon Accom-<lb/>panied our aforesaid Friend<lb/> to the <orgName
                            key="cayugaind">Cayuga</orgName> Settlement<lb/> of Indians, where he
                        had<lb/> also appointed to have a Meet-<lb/>ing with the Natives, to
                        begin<lb/> at three OClock: we waited<lb/> ‘till after four, and not
                        one<lb/> them came to the place ap-<lb/>pointed, and even the
                        In-<lb/>terpreter, <persName key="jjour1"><emph rend="underline">John
                                Jourdan</emph></persName>,<lb/> at whose Cabbin we met,<lb/>
                        <pb n="221" facs="SW_JP1796_222"/> had himself gone away just<lb/>
                        before we got there, and returned<lb/> no more whilst we staid: On<lb/> our
                        Return, some of our Com-<lb/>pany met him; and he ap-<lb/>peared totally
                        insensible of<lb/> any impropriety in his own,<lb/> or people’s Conduct,
                        relative<lb/> to this Matter; alledging<lb/> that some were gone one
                        way,<lb/> and some another, and could<lb/> not well get together.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-07-11">11th.</date><placeName key="cayug1"
                        /></dateline>
                    <p>This morning agreeably<lb/> to the Appointment of seventh<lb/> Day Evening,
                        we again attended<lb/> at <placeName key="cayug1">Cayuga</placeName>; and
                        after wasting<lb/> several Hours, a few of the <del>prin</del><lb/> principal<lb/>
                        <pb n="222" facs="SW_JP1796_223"/> principal Indians, of men<lb/> and
                        women, came together:<lb/> They opened the Council by<lb/> producing our
                        Letter of last<lb/> Spring, and informing that<lb/> they had answered it by
                        Let-<lb/>ter to <persName key="ichap1">Cap. Chapin</persName>: After<lb/>
                        which we opened the Nature<lb/> of our Concern in general,<lb/> having the
                        Aforesaid <persName key="jjour1">John<lb/> Jourdan</persName>, for our
                        Interpreter,<lb/> who was a very poor one, and<lb/> then informed them
                        how<lb/> far we had proceeded in it;<lb/> particularly towards their<lb/>
                        Brothers the <orgName key="oneida">Oneidas</orgName>; and<lb/> that our
                        Regard was equally<lb/>
                        <pb n="223" facs="SW_JP1796_224"/> towards them all; but that<lb/> we
                        could not begin with all<lb/> at once; and therefore our par-<lb/>ticular
                        Business, at this Time,<lb/> with them, and all the other<lb/> Tribes
                        westward of the <orgName key="oneida">Oneida’s</orgName>,<lb/> was, to
                        enquire into their par-<lb/>ticular Circumstances, and<lb/> take word to our
                        Friends, in<lb/> Order that they might con-<lb/>sider how they might be
                        most<lb/> useful to them against another<lb/> Season; but withal
                        informed<lb/> them, that as their Number<lb/> was so small, it was not
                        likely<lb/> that we could settle any of our<lb/> Friends amongst them;
                        but<lb/> that we thought Friends would<lb/> be<lb/>
                        <pb n="224" facs="SW_JP1796_225"/> be willing to take four or<lb/> five
                        of their Boys, between<lb/> seven and twelve years old,<lb/> and learn them
                        to work at<lb/> farming, and some Trades,<lb/> and give them so much
                        school-<lb/>ing, as to learn them to read<lb/> and write English: And<lb/>
                        also that we thought they<lb/> might expect some farm-<lb/>ing Utensils next
                        spring.</p>
                    <p> They expressed their Satis-<lb/>faction with our proposals,<lb/> and a
                        willingness to send some<lb/> of their Children to us, but<lb/> said they
                        must consult some<lb/> more of their women, their<lb/>
                        <pb n="225" facs="SW_JP1796_226"/> being but few of them present,<lb/>
                        we closed the Council, after having<lb/> obtained the following
                        Information,<lb/> viz. That they consist of about<lb/> 13 Families, between
                        50 and<lb/> 60 Individuals, who live on this<lb/> Reservation; They have
                        near<lb/> four Thousand Acres of Land; we<lb/> think not of quite so good
                        a<lb/> Quality as where we have been<lb/> before; they have 2300
                        Dollars<lb/> a year coming in from the State<lb/> of New-York, besides
                        their<lb/> Share of the Gratuity from<lb/> General Government to the<lb/>
                        <orgName key="Six Nations">Six Nations</orgName>; but that part<lb/> of this
                        Tribe which has re-<lb/>moved westward, and which<lb/> is<lb/>
                        <pb n="226" facs="SW_JP1796_227"/> Is about one half; they say<lb/> has
                        a Right to their Share<lb/> of this Money if they call<lb/> for it. They
                        have<lb/> six Cows, neither oxen nor Horses,<lb/> and raise very little of
                        any<lb/> Thing, living principally by<lb/> Fishing and hunting; and
                        par-<lb/>ticularly the former, the Lake<lb/> abounding with a large
                        kind<lb/> of Eel which they catch in<lb/> great plenty. These peo-<lb/>ple,
                        as well as the <orgName key="onondaga">Onandago’s</orgName><lb/> appear
                        totally averse to all La-<lb/>bour; and very insensible of<lb/> any thing
                        that could be said<lb/> to them on the most interest-<lb/>ing Occasions.</p>
                    <pb n="227" facs="SW_JP1796_228"/>
                    <p> After this Council we proceeded<lb/> on towards <placeName key="conan"
                            >Conandarque</placeName>; and<lb/> after riding along side of the<lb/>
                        lake about 7 1/2 miles we<lb/> crossed in a good sail Boat;<lb/> and having
                        a lively Breeze<lb/> we had a short and pleasant<lb/> passage, being about
                        20 mi-<lb/>nutes, in going a mile and<lb/> a half; we dined at the
                        ferry<lb/>9. House, <emph rend="underline"><persName key="jbenn1">James
                                Bennet’s</persName></emph>; and<lb/> while our Dinner was
                        prepar-<lb/>ing one of our Company took<lb/> up a News paper, printed<lb/> a
                        few Days since at <placeName key="white">Whites;<lb/> Town</placeName>
                        within about 18 or 20 miles<lb/> of <placeName key="oneic">Oneida
                            Castle</placeName>
                        <del><unclear>Town</unclear></del>; in which<lb/> was an Account of the
                        various<lb/> Tosts<lb/>
                        <pb n="228" facs="SW_JP1796_229"/> Tosts drunk at a Dinner<lb/> in that
                        Town on the 4th. of<lb/> this month; amongst which<lb/> was the following: </p>
                    <floatingText type="speech">
                        <body>
                            <p>
                                <quote>The Enterprising and Bene-<lb/>volent Quaker
                                    Missionaries;<lb/> may they succeed in civilizing<lb/> our
                                    Neighbours the <orgName key="oneida"
                                >Oneidas</orgName>.</quote></p>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                    <p> However trifling and un-<lb/>worthy a place in these Notes<lb/> the above
                        may appear to some;<lb/> it however speaks a Language<lb/> Consonant to what
                        is herein<lb/> before noted, of the favour-<lb/>able Disposition of the
                        Fron-<lb/>tier Inhabitants in these<lb/> parts, to our Business.</p>
                    <p> After Dinner pursued<lb/> our Journey, and arived at<lb/>
                        <pb n="229" facs="SW_JP1796_230"/>
                        <placeName key="genev">Geneva</placeName>, a small Town on
                            the<lb/>14.<geogName key="senec">Seneca Lake</geogName>, about 14
                        Miles;<lb/> where we lodged.</p>
                    <p> This Lake and the <geogName key="cayug">Cayuga</geogName><lb/> are said to
                        be nearly equal in<lb/> Dimensions; being about 42<lb/> miles in Length; and
                        from<lb/> one and an half, to four in<lb/> Bredth: we rode several
                        Miles<lb/> up its Banks, and the Wind<lb/> being high and setting
                        towards<lb/> us, the Rolling of a large<lb/> and troubled water, the
                        dash-<lb/>ing of the Billows, sometimes<lb/> within a yard of our Horses
                        feet,<lb/> afforded as an agreeable Sensation<lb/> both to the Eye and
                        Ear.</p>
                    <p> At this place we had the<lb/> Com-<lb/>
                        <pb n="230" facs="SW_JP1796_231"/> Company of a female follower<lb/> of
                        the deluded <persName key="jwilk1">Jemima Wilkin-<lb/>son</persName>, whose
                        settlement is a few<lb/> Miles up this Lake; her de-<lb/>portment was Grave
                        and Sober;<lb/> we observed a cautious Guard<lb/> in her Conversation, &amp;
                        answers<lb/> to our Interrogations, not to make<lb/> use of, or any way,
                        directly or<lb/> indirectly acknowledge the<lb/> name <emph rend="underline"
                                ><persName key="jwilk1">Jemima Wilkinson</persName></emph>,<lb/> but
                        always termed her <q><emph rend="underline">the<lb/> friend</emph></q>: We
                        understand this<lb/> woman is losing her Reputa-<lb/>tion here; divers of
                        her principal<lb/> followers having left her: and<lb/> the following curious
                        Inter<lb/>view between her and <persName key="cbran1">Cap.<lb/>
                            Brant</persName>, an Indian <del>at</del>from <geogName key="grand">Grand<lb/>
                            <pb n="231" facs="SW_JP1796_232"/> River,</geogName> was related to
                        me as a<lb/> fact, by <persName key="haupa1">Cap. Hendrick</persName> at<lb/>
                        <placeName key="stock">Stockbridge</placeName>; viz. That the said<lb/>
                        <emph rend="underline"><persName key="cbran1">Brant</persName></emph> being
                        in those parts<lb/>
                        <emph rend="underline"><persName key="jwilk1">Jemima</persName></emph> sent
                        him a message<lb/> that she had a Desire to see him,<lb/> upon which he paid
                        her a<lb/> visit; and upon her asking<lb/> him a certain Question, he
                        an-<lb/>swered her in his own Language<lb/> and she not understanding
                        him,<lb/> repeated the Question, or asked<lb/> another; he again
                        answered<lb/> in another Indian Language;<lb/> and so the third time:
                        When<lb/> he observed to him that she<lb/> had heard of him, that he
                        was<lb/> a Scholar and a man of Informa<lb/>tion, and that she had promised<lb/>
                        <pb n="232" facs="SW_JP1796_233"/> herself some satisfaction from<lb/>
                        his Company and Conversation;<lb/> and that she had now asked him<lb/> a
                        civil Question; and that he<lb/> had answered her three Several<lb/> Times
                        in a Language that she<lb/> did not understand; and as she<lb/> knew he
                        could speak English, she<lb/> could not account for such treat-<lb/>ment: To
                        which <emph rend="underline"><persName key="cbran1">Brant</persName></emph>
                        re-<lb/>plied, with an Interrogation if<lb/> she did not understand
                        what<lb/> he said to her; To which she<lb/> again answered, No; I do
                        not<lb/> understand your Indian Lan-<lb/>guages: - <del>To which</del> Very
                        well<lb/> Madam, replied <persName key="cbran1">Brant</persName>, then<lb/>
                        you are not the person you<lb/>
                        <pb n="233" facs="SW_JP1796_234"/> pretend to be, for <emph
                            rend="underline">Jesus Christ</emph><lb/> understands <emph
                            rend="underline">Indian</emph> as well<lb/> as English.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-07-12">12th.</date><placeName key="conan"
                        /></dateline>
                    <p>This morning rode<lb/> to <placeName key="conan">Conandarque</placeName>,
                        about 14 miles.<lb/> The roads extremely deep and<lb/> swampy: In the
                        Afternoon<lb/> had a Conference with <persName key="ichap1">Israel<lb/>
                            Chapin</persName> Superintendant for<lb/> Indian Affairs, from which
                        we<lb/> learn that <persName key="cornp1">Captain Abeel, Alias,<lb/>
                            Cornplanter</persName>, one of the <orgName key="seneca"
                            >Seneca</orgName><lb/> Chiefs, had sent him an an-<lb/>swer to our
                        Letter of last spring,<lb/> that he was willing to receive<lb/> Friends, and
                        that he would be glad<lb/> to have them come and settle<lb/> about him;
                        because he believed<lb/> they<lb/>
                        <pb n="234" facs="SW_JP1796_235"/> they were good people; but<lb/>
                        Farmer’s Brother, on behalf of the<lb/> settlement at <geogName key="buffc1"
                            >Buffalo Creek</geogName>,<lb/> which is called the main <orgName
                            key="seneca">Seneca</orgName><lb/> Settlement, answered that he<lb/>
                        thought it best to wait, and see<lb/> our progress with their eastern<lb/>
                        Brethren, before they recei<emph rend="underline">ved us.</emph></p>
                    <p> After this Conference, hearing<lb/> of some people who were called<lb/> by
                        our name a few miles back<lb/> of this place, we concluded to<lb/> go and
                        see them; and if conve-<lb/>nient, rest ourselves a Day or<lb/> two &amp;c.
                        Accordingly we set out,<lb/> having a young man, son to<lb/> one of these
                        people for our<lb/> Guide; we seperated on the<lb/> way<lb/>
                        <pb n="235" facs="SW_JP1796_236"/> Way, some of us going to <persName
                            key="jsmit1">Jacob<lb/> Smiths</persName>, and others to <persName
                            key="ncoms1">Nathan<lb/> Cumstalks</persName> and <persName key="alaph1"
                            >Abraham Lap-<lb/>pums</persName>: amongst these people<lb/> we were
                        kindly entertained; they<lb/> being friends by Education and<lb/>
                        profession, tho' not one of the men<lb/> are actually in membership.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-07-13">13th.</date></dateline>
                    <p>Staid with our aforesaid<lb/> Friends, rested ourselves, got<lb/> our Linen
                        washed, and wrote<lb/> some Letters home.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-07-14">14th.</date><placeName key="conan"
                        /></dateline>
                    <p>Returned to <placeName key="conan">Conandar-<lb/>que</placeName>, had a
                        further Conference<lb/> with <persName key="ichap1">Cap. Chapin</persName>;
                        by which<lb/> we learn, that the <orgName key="seneca"
                        >Seneca's</orgName><lb/> have various settlements west<lb/> of the <geogName
                            key="genes2">Genesee River</geogName>, and con-<lb/>sist<lb/>
                        <pb n="236" facs="SW_JP1796_237"/> sist of the following number<lb/> of
                        Individuals; viz.</p>
                    <table>
                        <row>
                            <cell><placeName key="buffc">Main Village at <geogName key="buffc1"
                                        >Buffolo Creek</geogName></placeName>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>381</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell><placeName key="wchie">White Chiefs Village</placeName>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>107</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell><placeName key="catta1">Catauraugurus</placeName>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>225 </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell><placeName key="alleg1">Allegany</placeName> {<placeName
                                    key="cornp"><persName key="cornp1">Cornplanter’s</persName><lb/>
                                    2 Villages</placeName>}</cell>
                            <cell>331</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell><placeName key="tawna">Tawniwandic</placeName>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>104</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>* <placeName key="canaw">Canawaugus</placeName>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>22</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>* <placeName key="genes">Ghenesee Village</placeName>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>91</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>* <placeName key="bigtr">Bigtree Village</placeName>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>80</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>* <placeName key="squaw">Squakee Hill</placeName>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>190</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>*<placeName key="kaoun"> Ka-oun-o-de-o</placeName>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>113</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>1644</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>* Note such as have this mark<lb/> are said to unite with <persName
                            key="cornp1">Corn-<lb/>planter’s</persName> Answer.</p>
                    <p> The <orgName key="seneca">Seneca’s</orgName> have five<lb/> Hundred Dollars
                        a year from<lb/>
                        <persName key="ophel1">Oliver Phelps</persName>; besides their Share<lb/>
                        <pb n="237" facs="SW_JP1796_238"/> of the 4500 Dollars from the
                        gene-<lb/>ral Government, to the <orgName key="Six Nations">Six
                            Nations</orgName>.</p>
                    <p> This Evening we wrote the follow-<lb/>ing Letter to our Friends at
                            <placeName key="oneid">Oneida</placeName>,<lb/> viz.</p>
                    <floatingText type="letter">
                        <body>
                            <dateline><placeName key="conan">Conandarque</placeName>
                                <date when="1796-07-14">7th. mo. 14th. 1796</date></dateline>
                            <p> Dear Friends,</p>
                            <p> Your Situation and<lb/> the important Concerns devolved<lb/> upon
                                you, have often been the<lb/> Subjects of Serious
                                Thoughtful-<lb/>ness to us since we left you, and<lb/> we are free
                                to propose to you;<lb/> That as you may possibly find<lb/> some
                                Difficulty in getting as many<lb/> of the young Indians to
                                undertake,<lb/> and stick to the Business, on the<lb/> particular
                                portion of Land alotted<lb/> us, as was expected; we wish you<lb/> not<lb/>
                                <pb n="238" facs="SW_JP1796_239"/> not to suffer
                                Discouragements<lb/> too much to take place in your<lb/> Minds on
                                that Account; but<lb/> endeavour to get them to divide<lb/> off
                                particular portions of Land<lb/> to particular persons, in some<lb/>
                                convenient places, and bestow<lb/> the more of your Time in
                                in-<lb/>structing and helping such;<lb/> and where any who have
                                un-<lb/>dertaken with you, on your<lb/> Farm, shall be discouraged
                                from<lb/> the Length of Time, which, agree-<lb/>able to our plan,
                                they must<lb/> wait for their wages, we are<lb/> willing you should
                                advance some<lb/> necessary Goods &amp;c. to such, (which<lb/> we
                                desire you to purchase for<lb/>
                                <pb n="239" facs="SW_JP1796_240"/> that purpose) or actually
                                hire<lb/> others in Case of necessity; keeping<lb/> a regular
                                account thereof, and<lb/> letting them know, that the value<lb/> of
                                all such Advance and hire is<lb/> to be deducted out of the
                                product<lb/> of the place.</p>
                            <p> With Love we remain your Friends.<list type="simple">
                                    <item><persName key="jpier1">John Peirce</persName></item>
                                    <item><persName key="jsans1">Joseph Sansom</persName></item>
                                    <item><persName key="jcoop1">James Cooper</persName></item>
                                    <item><persName key="irowl1">Isaiah Rowland</persName></item>
                                </list></p>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-07-15">15th.</date><placeName key="conan"
                            type="unattested"/></dateline>
                    <p>This morning had a<lb/> Conference amongst ourselves<lb/> respecting the
                        further prosecution<lb/> of the Business before us; but not<lb/> being able
                        to come to a clear and<lb/> Satisfactory Judgment relative<lb/> to any
                        further Movements; and<lb/> it<lb/>
                        <pb n="240" facs="SW_JP1796_241"/> it being now near the End of<lb/>
                        the week, we concluded to spend<lb/> a day or two more amongst our<lb/>
                        Friends and to meet at <persName key="wingl1">William<lb/>
                            <del rend="overwrite">E</del>Ingles</persName> on First Day; where
                        our<lb/> Friend <persName key="jevan1">Joshua Evans</persName> had
                        appoint-<lb/>ed a meeting.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-07-17">17th. and 18th.</date><placeName key="conan"
                        /></dateline>
                    <p>Being first and<lb/> second Day, We had several seri-<lb/>ous Conferences on
                        the Nature of<lb/> our present Concern, and the<lb/> propriety of our going
                        forward<lb/> into the <orgName key="seneca">Seneca</orgName> Country at
                        this<lb/> Time; and two of our number,<lb/> now approaching they felt<lb/> a
                        releasment in their minds<lb/> from any further prosecution<lb/> of the
                        Business at the present;<lb/>
                        <pb n="241" facs="SW_JP1796_242"/> whilst the other two approached<lb/>
                        the Business not completed<lb/> for which we were sent out, and<lb/> that
                        this was the right time to<lb/> perform a visit to the <orgName key="seneca"
                            >Seneca's</orgName><lb/> in some of their different Set-<lb/>tlements;
                        our Situation became<lb/> trying, and a spirit of Sympa-<lb/>thy and tender
                        feeling for each<lb/> other was sensibly experienced,<lb/> to the tendering
                        of our Hearts;<lb/> and after various Sittings to-<lb/>gether, and feeling
                        after our<lb/> present Situation, and trying<lb/> our several Concerns and
                        pros-<lb/>pects, and a Spirit of brotherly<lb/> Condiscension prevailing, it
                        was<lb/> at length resulted, as most safe<lb/> to<lb/>
                        <pb n="242" facs="SW_JP1796_243"/> to keep together, and return<lb/>
                        homewards.</p>
                    <p> After this Conclusion we<lb/> had another Conference with<lb/>
                        <persName key="ichap1">Cap. Chapin</persName>; informed him<lb/> what we had
                        done at <placeName key="oneid">Oneida</placeName>,<lb/> and other places
                        where we had<lb/> been; read to him most of our<lb/> material Entries on
                        Business;<lb/> and informed him of our present<lb/> prospect of returning
                        home-<lb/>wards; and, with his advice,<lb/> wrote the following Letter to<lb/>
                        <persName key="cornp1">Cap. Abeel, alias Cornplan-<lb/>ter</persName>.
                        viz.</p>
                    <floatingText type="letter">
                        <body>
                            <dateline><placeName key="conan">Conandarque</placeName>
                                <date when="1796-07-18">7th. mo 18th. 1796</date></dateline>
                            <opener> To <persName key="cornp1">Captain Abeel</persName>, and the
                                differ-<lb/>ent <orgName key="seneca">Seneca</orgName> Villages, who answer<lb/>
                                <pb n="243" facs="SW_JP1796_244"/> with him to our Letter
                                of<lb/> last Spring.</opener>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> You received a Letter<lb/> from your Brothers, the peo-<lb/>ple
                                called Quakers, written<lb/> last winter, and directed to<lb/> the
                                    <orgName key="Six Nations">Six Nations</orgName> of Indians;
                                we<lb/> have now received your Answer<lb/> by <persName key="ichap1"
                                    >Cap. Chapin</persName>, informing that<lb/> you are willing to
                                receive our<lb/> proposals.</p>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> We who now write<lb/> to you are a part of your friends<lb/> who
                                wrote to you last winter,<lb/> and have been sent out by our<lb/>
                                Friends to do something for your<lb/> Brothers the <orgName
                                    key="oneida">Oneida’s</orgName>, whose
                                        <del><unclear>answer</unclear></del><lb/> answer<lb/>
                                <pb n="244" facs="SW_JP1796_245"/> answer to our Letter we<lb/>
                                had received before we left<lb/> home; we have accordingly<lb/>
                                settled three of our Friends<lb/> there, and furnished them<lb/>
                                with farming Utensils,<lb/> in order to instruct, and
                                en-<lb/>courage your Brothers, the<lb/>
                                <orgName key="oneida">Oneida’s</orgName> in farming the<lb/> Land
                                like the white people;<lb/> that so they may raise a<lb/> great deal
                                of Grain and<lb/> Grass &amp;c. off of a little La<emph
                                    rend="underline">nd. </emph></p>
                            <p> Brothers, Our Regard is e-<lb/>qually towards <del>you</del> all
                                our<lb/> Indian Brothers of the <orgName key="Six Nations">Six<lb/>
                                    Nations</orgName>; but you know that<lb/> we cannot begin with all<lb/>
                                <pb n="245" facs="SW_JP1796_246"/> at once, nor do every thing
                                at a<lb/> Time; therefore our friends at<lb/> home desired us to
                                call and see<lb/> some of our other Brothers of<lb/> the <orgName
                                    key="Six Nations">Six Nations</orgName>, in order to
                                en-<lb/>quire into their Circumstances,<lb/> and bring them word
                                again, so<lb/> that they might consider who<lb/> to help next, and
                                how to do it<lb/> best; accordingly we have been to<lb/> see your
                                Brothers the <emph rend="underline"><orgName key="onondaga"
                                        >Onandago’s</orgName></emph><lb/> and <orgName
                                    key="cayugaind">Cayuga’s</orgName>, and gave them<lb/> some
                                advice, and enquired into<lb/> their Circumstances, and shall<lb/>
                                carry a true Account home to our<lb/> Friends: Now Brothers, we<lb/>
                                had thought of coming to see you<lb/> also, for the same purpose;
                                but<lb/> it is now got late in the season<lb/>
                                <pb n="246" facs="SW_JP1796_247"/> before we could get here,
                                and<lb/> before we got your answer; and<lb/> as the Road is very
                                long through<lb/> the wilderness, and the Hot<lb/> Weather coming
                                on, we think<lb/> we can’t call to see you now;<lb/> but we have
                                enquired very<lb/> particularly into your Circum-<lb/>stances, of
                                your old Friend <persName key="ichap1">Cap.<lb/> Chapin</persName>,
                                and shall carry a true<lb/> account to our friends at home;<lb/> and
                                we desire you to enquire of<lb/> your Brothers the <orgName
                                    key="oneida">Oneida’s</orgName> how<lb/> our Friends behave
                                amongst<lb/> them, and how they like<lb/> our plan and Conduct;
                                that<lb/> so you may be fully satisfied<lb/> against we are ready to help<lb/>
                                <pb n="247" facs="SW_JP1796_248"/> you in the same way.</p>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> We must desire you<lb/> to have patience with us, if we<lb/> don’t
                                do every Thing you ex-<lb/>pect, all at once: for if we settle<lb/>
                                any Body amongst you, we know<lb/> they must be good Men, or
                                else<lb/> they may do you more hurt than<lb/> good; and we must wait
                                ‘till such<lb/> offer of their own free Will, to come<lb/> and live
                                amongst you, out of Love<lb/> to you, and by the Moving of the<lb/>
                                good Spirit in their own Heart<lb/> for good Men, such as would
                                do<lb/> you good are not to be bought with<lb/> Money, nor hired to
                                come amongst<lb/> you, without they feel this good<lb/> Spirit
                                enfluencing them there.</p>
                            <pb n="248" facs="SW_JP1796_249"/>
                            <p> Brothers,</p>
                            <p> In Love, we bid you farewell.</p>
                            <p>
                                <list type="simple">
                                    <item><persName key="jpier1">John Peirce</persName></item>
                                    <item><persName key="jcoop1">James Cooper</persName></item>
                                    <item><persName key="irowl1">Isaiah Rowland</persName></item>
                                </list></p>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-07-19">19th.</date><placeName key="conan"
                        /></dateline>
                    <p>This Morning left<lb/>
                        <placeName key="conan">Conandarque</placeName>, in order to go<lb/> directly
                        homewards; break-<lb/>fasted at <persName key="wingl1">William
                            Ingles</persName><lb/> 3 Miles on our Way; thence<lb/> up the side of
                        the <geogName key="conal">Conandar-<lb/>que Lake</geogName> about 20 miles,<lb/>
                        <del>dined</del> to <persName key="nwatk1">Nathan Watkins</persName>, at the
                        head<lb/> of it, where we dined: - This<lb/> Lake is nearly equal in Width
                        to<lb/> the <geogName key="senec">Seneca</geogName> or <geogName key="cayug"
                            >Cayuga</geogName>; but not<lb/> much more than half the Length:<lb/>
                        <pb n="249" facs="SW_JP1796_250"/> After Dinner continued our
                        Jour-<lb/>ney and lodged at one <persName key="rhook1">Huckers</persName> -;
                        about 12 miles:<lb/>Here we lay on the floor, and<lb/> our Horses fared
                        badly, having<lb/> neither pasture, hay, nor grain;<lb/> A little Grass cut
                        with a<lb/> Sickle on the Edges of a<lb/> Wheat Lot, was all that could<lb/>
                        be procured for them.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-07-20">20th.</date><placeName key="bath"/></dateline>
                    <p>This morning started early;<lb/> there being nothing here to in-<lb/>duce any
                        unnecessary Stay, break-<lb/>fasted in the woods, on Bread and<lb/> Cheese,
                        which we had with us, about<lb/> 8 miles on our way; Our Horses<lb/> having
                        no better repast after a<lb/> trying night, than what they<lb/>
                        <pb n="250" facs="SW_JP1796_251"/> could collect for themselves
                            <unclear>about/along</unclear><lb/> the Range where we stopped, &amp;
                        which<lb/> was very poor: thence to a small<lb/> Town, called <placeName
                            key="bath">Bath</placeName>, in a very poor<lb/> Country, where we
                        dined; and<lb/> got some indifferent Hay for our<lb/> Horses, but no Grain,
                        about 20<lb/> Miles: Thence to one <unclear><persName key="patt1"
                                >Pattison</persName></unclear><lb/> at <placeName key="postt">Post
                            Town</placeName>, near the painted<lb/>post, about
                        19 miles; here we<lb/> lodged: our horses faring better<lb/> having plenty
                        of pretty good Hay<lb/> but no Grain.</p>
                    <p> About a mile from <placeName key="bath">Bath</placeName> stopped<lb/> at the
                        House of <persName key="wkers1">William Kersey</persName><lb/> late of
                            <placeName key="lyork">little York</placeName>; On the Bank<lb/> of a
                        water called <geogName key="llake">little Lake</geogName>:<lb/> This Lake is
                        of a circular form,<lb/>
                        <pb n="251" facs="SW_JP1796_252"/> about half a mile Diameter, has<lb/>
                        no visible Inlet, nor outlet; the<lb/> water nevertheless being clear and
                        fresh,<lb/> and wearing no appearance of<lb/> Stagnation; and we are
                        informed<lb/> no bottom has ever been discovered<lb/> in some parts of it,
                        though sound-<lb/>ed with a Line of 40 <emph rend="underline"
                            >Fathoms.</emph></p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-07-21">21st.</date><placeName key="bath"
                            type="unattested"/></dateline>
                    <p>Pursued our Journey,<lb/> crossing the <geogName key="cohoc"
                            >Cohocton</geogName>, <geogName key="canis">Conos-<lb/>teer</geogName>,
                        and <geogName key="chemu">Shomonga Creeks</geogName>,<lb/> which are waters
                        of the <geogName key="susqu">Susque-<lb/>hannah</geogName>, breakfasted at the<lb/>
                        <persName key="wlind1">Widow Lindsley’s</persName> about 14 miles;<lb/> here
                        we got pasture, and also<lb/> Grain for our Horses; and <del>got</del><lb/>
                        a small supply of Grain to<lb/> carry with us; against tomorrow<lb/> Ride;
                        when we are informed we<lb/>
                        <pb n="252" facs="SW_JP1796_253"/> shall get no kind of
                        Entertain-<lb/>ment, either for ourselves or<lb/> Horses, for upwards of 40
                        Miles.<lb/> Thence to <persName key="wcart1">William Carter’s</persName>
                        about<lb/> 15 miles, where we lodged out<lb/>29.of necessity; there being no
                        other<lb/> House, of any kind, on this side<lb/> of the mountains: This last
                        Stage crossing<lb/> the New-York and Pennsylvania <emph rend="underline"
                            >Line.</emph></p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-07-22">22nd.</date><geogName key="savmo"/></dateline>
                    <p>This morning started be-<lb/>fore two OClock, proposing, in pos-<lb/>sible to
                        reach some Quarters on the<lb/> other Side of the <geogName key="savmo"
                            >Savage Mountains</geogName>;<lb/> breakfasted on Bread &amp; Cheese,
                        which<lb/> we had previously provided; and fed<lb/> our Horses, some on the
                        Ground, and<lb/> others in Holes cut <del>cut</del> for that<lb/> purpose in
                        the Logs; about 15<lb/> Miles on our way. Thence proceed-<lb/>ing up the
                        Mountain; our Roads<lb/>
                        <pb n="253" facs="SW_JP1796_254"/> increased not only in
                        Roughness,<lb/> but in most intolerable Bogs &amp;<lb/> Mire, for about 10
                        Miles, to<lb/> a place called the <placeName key="block">Block
                            House</placeName>:<lb/> where we dined, and fed out Horses,<lb/> much in
                        the same Manner<lb/> as we breakfasted; only that we<lb/> had better Troughs
                        to feed i<emph rend="underline">n: </emph></p>
                    <p> Here is a tolerable House, and<lb/> might be of great use to
                        Travail-<lb/>ors, was there but a suitable per-<lb/>son living in it: but
                        its present<lb/> Occupant is not only so unpro-<lb/>vided with Accommodation
                        that<lb/> it is seldom anything can<lb/> be had either for man or Beast<lb/>
                        excepting a little Liquor; but<lb/> is<lb/>
                        <pb n="254" facs="SW_JP1796_255"/> also of so desperate a
                        Charac-<lb/>ter, that most Travailers are<lb/> afraid to trust themselves
                        under<lb/> his Roof all Night. Then <lb/><del>still</del> over the Mountains
                        for<lb/> about 12 Miles further; where<lb/> we again fed our Horses at the
                        foot of this Mountain in<lb/> like manner aforesaid; then<lb/> to <persName
                            key="jthom1">James Thomson’s</persName> on <geogName key="lycom"
                            >Lycoming</geogName><lb/>46.Creek about 9 Miles; where we<lb/> arrived
                        before sun set: and tho<lb/> both ourselves and Horses were<lb/> much
                        fatigued, the satisfaction<lb/> we felt from the Reflection<lb/> of being
                        over the most dif-<lb/>ficult part of our Journey<lb/> and near a Settlement
                        of<lb/> Friends<lb/>
                        <pb n="255" facs="SW_JP1796_256"/> was reviving, and tended to<lb/>
                        sweeten our present Situ-<lb/>ation.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-07-23">23rd.</date><placeName key="muncy"
                        /></dateline>
                    <p>This morning found the<lb/> Effect of yesterday’s Ride, one<lb/> of our
                        Horses being badly bruised,<lb/> and entirely unfit to ride, we<lb/> were
                        under the Necessity of<lb/> leading, or at least letting it<lb/> follow, and
                        one of us walking<lb/>20. by turns for about 20 miles<lb/> to <persName
                            key="welli1">William Ellis’</persName> in <placeName key="muncy"
                            >Munsey</placeName>.<lb/> This being Seventh Day, we<lb/> concluded to
                        rest ourselves<lb/> and Horses here until<lb/> Second Day.</p>
                    <pb n="256" facs="SW_JP1796_257"/>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-07-24">24th.</date><placeName key="muncy"
                        /></dateline>
                    <p>Being first Day at<lb/>tended <placeName key="muncy">Munsey</placeName>
                        Meeting.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1976-07-25">25th.</date><geogName key="fishi"/></dateline>
                    <p>After Dinner left our<lb/> agreeable Quarters at munsey<lb/> and pursued our
                        Journey<lb/> homewards, lodged at <persName key="jhain1">Jesse<lb/>
                            Haynes</persName>’ at <geogName key="fishi">fishing
                        Creek</geogName>;<lb/>21. about 21 miles.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-07-26">26th.</date><placeName key="catta"
                        /></dateline>
                    <p>Proceeded on, crossed <geogName key="susqu">Sus<lb/>quehannah</geogName>, at
                            <placeName key="catta">Cattawissy</placeName>,<lb/> on Horseback, dined
                        at <persName key="jlloy1">John<lb/> Lloyds</persName>, at said place;
                        about<lb/> 15 miles: Thence to <persName key="fleve1">Frederick<lb/>
                            Levenburg’s</persName> on the east side<lb/>28. of the <geogName
                            key="lmoun">Little Mountain</geogName> about<lb/> 13 miles; where we
                        lodged.</p>
                    <pb n="257" facs="SW_JP1796_258"/>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-07-27">27th.</date><geogName key="maide"/></dateline>
                    <p>This Morning rode<lb/> about 15 miles to breakfast,<lb/> to an Inn kept by
                        one <persName key="greev1">George<lb/> Reevers</persName>; thence to
                            <persName key="rstev1">Richard<lb/> Stevens’</persName> about 18
                        miles;<lb/> Thence to <persName key="fparv1">Francis Parvins</persName><lb/>
                        at <geogName key="maide">Maiden Creek</geogName>, to lodge,<lb/> 46. about
                        18 miles.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1976-07-28">28th.</date></dateline>
                    <p>Left <persName key="fparv1">Francis Parvins</persName><lb/> after Dinner,
                        rode to <persName key="bscar1">Ben-<lb/>jamin Scarlet’s</persName> at
                            <placeName key="robin">Robinson</placeName>,<lb/>16. about 16 miles;
                        where we<lb/> lodged.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="entry">
                    <dateline><date when="1796-07-29">29th.</date><placeName key="darby"
                        /></dateline>
                    <p>This Day, at Several<lb/> Stages, reached my Habitation<lb/>40. at <placeName
                            key="darby">Darby</placeName>, about 40 Miles,<lb/> &amp; found my
                        family all well.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="undetermined">
                <pb n="258" facs="SW_JP1796_259"/>
                <p> Subduplicate ratio, The ratio of<lb/> their square roots.</p>
                <p> Duplicate ratio. The ratio of<lb/> their squares</p>
                <p> Thus the duplicate ratio of 2 to 4<lb/> is the ratio of 4 to 16.</p>
                <p> and the subduplicate ratio of 4<lb/> to 16 is the ratio of 2 to 4.</p>
                <p>" f "</p>
                <p>1 : 3 ::4</p>
                <p>4/12 feet to vibrate in 2 seconds</p>
                <p>4 : 2 :<gap/> 1 1 : <unclear>2</unclear> : 4</p>
                <p><emph rend="underline">4</emph></p>
                <p><unclear>/36/6</unclear></p>
                <p><gap/></p>
            </div>
            <div type="undetermined">
                <pb n="259" facs="SW_JP1796_260"/>
                <p> £ <del><gap/></del></p>
                <p> School to open this fall, say<lb/> beginning 11th. mo. </p>
                <p> 25 Boys admitted, and no more<lb/> this winter.</p>
                <p> No Girls admitted till Spring<lb/> say 3rd mo.</p>
                <p> Acting Commitly appointed.<lb/> their Instructions.</p>
                <p> Superintendant appointed.<lb/> Committee to settle the Books,<lb/> and make a
                        <del><gap/></del>clear statement<lb/> of <unclear>Auts.</unclear></p>
                <p> Consideration respecting Meeting.<lb/> Furniture, particularly bedding<lb/> to
                    be provided, how many sets, whether<lb/> for 2 Children in a bed, or one.<lb/>
                    Committee to provide it to<lb/> be ready by such a time.</p>
                <p> School Books necessary. a com.</p>
                <pb n="260" facs="SW_JP1796_261"/>
                <p>
                    <del>after Dinner pursued our Journey<lb/> lodged at one <persName key="rhook1"
                            >Hookers</persName> about 12<lb/>36. Miles further: Here we
                                <del><unclear>layed</unclear></del>lay on<lb/> the floor, &amp; our
                        Horses fared badly,<lb/> having neither pasture, Hay,<lb/> nor Grain; A
                        little Grass cut<lb/> with a Sickle in the Corners<lb/> of a wheat patch was
                        all that<lb/> could be procured for them.</del></p>
                <gap/>
                <p>authorized to set them to the present<lb/> and compilations.<lb/>mmittee to
                    examine some proposals.</p>
                <pb n="261" facs="SW_JP1796_262"/>
                <p>
                    <del><persName key="jhott1">James <unclear>Hotton</unclear></persName>,
                        living<lb/> No <unclear>14</unclear>North Market
                        <unclear>st</unclear><lb/></del></p>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item><del>Commissioner</del></item>
                        <item><del><persName key="cbran1">Cap. Brant</persName></del>, &amp;
                                    <del><persName key="jwilk1">Gimima</persName></del></item>
                        <item><del>Salt and Sugar.</del></item>
                        <item><del>Indian Bible</del></item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>
                    <del rend="crossout">We then agreed upon the following<lb/> Minute, and entered
                        it in the <unclear>Acer</unclear><lb/> Book of our Friends at who stay
                        here</del></p>
                <p> We then agreed upon the<lb/> following</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
