<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei-print.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="global.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Cornplanter to Quakers: Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>Mary Olesnavich</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca.8 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>This work is the property of the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore
                        College. It may be copied freely by individuals for personal use, research,
                        and teaching (including distribution to classes) as long as this statement
                        of availability is included in the text. It may be linked to freely in
                        Internet editions of all kinds, including for—profit works.</p>
                    <p>Publishers, libraries, and other information providers interested in
                        providing this text in a commercial or non—profit product or from an
                        information server must contact Swarthmore College for licensing and cost
                        information.</p>
                    <p> Scholars interested in changing or adding to these texts by, for example,
                        creating a new edition of the text (electronically or in print) with
                        substantive editorial changes, may do so with the permission of Swarthmore
                        College. This is the case whether the new publication will be made available
                        at a cost or free of charge.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2014">2015</date>
                <idno type="local">SW_Leters_1791_02_10</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Native Americans and Quakers: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>Miscellaneous Manuscripts</collection>
                        <idno>Misc Mss 1791_02_10</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>1 p.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This letter is part of a larger collection of miscellaneous correspondence and is
                    housed at Friends Historical Library, on the campus of Swarthmore College. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> The transcribers and editor attempted to render the author’s orthography and
                    grammar as they appear on the page of his journal, even when the author’s own
                    spelling and usage are inconsistent. Additionally, many questions remain about
                    spelling the names of his Quaker acquaintances, individual Native Americans who
                    populate his journal, and Indian villages and towns. The transcribers and editor
                    attempted to remain faithful to the author’s Anglicized spellings in all cases.
                </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written in 1791<date/></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Cornplanter, Seneca chief (1732?-1836)</item>
                        <item>Seneca Indians</item>
                        <item>Society of Friends - New York (State)</item>
                        <item>Society of Friends -- Missions</item>
                        <item>Indians of North America -- Missions</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item>PCO edits,<date>2015</date></item>
            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
            
                <pb n="1" facs="SW_Letters_1791_02_10_Page_1"/>
                <opener><salute> To the children of the Friends of <persName key="wpenn1"> Onas
                        </persName> who first set- <lb/>led in Pennsylvania -- The request of the
                            <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> a <lb/> chief of the
                            <orgName key="seneca">Seneca</orgName> nation <lb/>
                    Brothers,</salute></opener>
                <p> The <orgName key="seneca"> Seneca </orgName> nation see that the Great spirit
                    <lb/> intends that they shall not continue to live by hunting, <lb/> and they
                    look round on every side, and enquire who it <lb/> is that shall teach them what
                    is best for them to do. <lb/> Your Fathers have dealt fairly and honestly with
                    <lb/> our Fathers, and they have charged us to remember <lb/> it, and we think
                    it right to tell you, that we <lb/> wish our children to be taught the same
                    principes <lb/> by which your fathers were guided in their councils. </p>
                <p> Brothers, <lb/> We have too little wisdom among us: <lb/> We cannot teach our
                    children what we perceive their <lb/> situation requires them to know, and we
                    therefore <lb/> ask you to instruct some of them We wish them to be <lb/>
                    instructed to read and to write, and such other things <lb/> as you teach your
                    children; and especially, to teach <lb/> them to love peace. </p>
                <p> Brothers, <lb/> We desire of you to take under your <lb/> care two <orgName
                        key="seneca"> Seneca </orgName> boys and teach them as your own; <lb/> and,
                    in order that they may be satisfied to remain with <lb/> you and be easy in
                    their minds, that you will take <lb/> with them the son of our Interpreter and
                    teach him <lb/> also according to his desire.</p>
                <p>Brothers, <lb/> You know that it is not in our power to <lb/> pay<lb/> <pb n="2" facs="SW_Letters_1791_02_10_Page_2"/>pay you
                    for the education of these three boys -- and therefore you <lb/>must, if you do this
                    thing, look up to God for your reward.</p>
                <p>Brothers,<lb/>You will consider of
                    this request, and let us <lb/>know what you determine to do. If your hearts <lb/>are
                    enclined toward us, and you will afford our nation <lb/>this great advantage, I will
                    send my son as one of the <lb/>boys to receive your instruction, and at the time
                    which <lb/>you shall appoint.</p>
                <closer>His <signed>Corn Planter</signed> mark <lb/>
                    Signed <dateline><date when="1791-02-10">February 10, 1791</date><placeName
                            key="cornp" type="unattested"/></dateline><lb/>in the presence of
                    us<lb/><persName key="jnich1">Jos. Nicholson</persName></closer>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
