<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei-print.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="global.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Tobias Lear to Quakers: Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>Mary Olesnavich</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca.7 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>This work is the property of the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore
                        College. It may be copied freely by individuals for personal use, research,
                        and teaching (including distribution to classes) as long as this statement
                        of availability is included in the text. It may be linked to freely in
                        Internet editions of all kinds, including for—profit works.</p>
                    <p>Publishers, libraries, and other information providers interested in
                        providing this text in a commercial or non—profit product or from an
                        information server must contact Swarthmore College for licensing and cost
                        information.</p>
                    <p> Scholars interested in changing or adding to these texts by, for example,
                        creating a new edition of the text (electronically or in print) with
                        substantive editorial changes, may do so with the permission of Swarthmore
                        College. This is the case whether the new publication will be made available
                        at a cost or free of charge.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2014">2015</date>
                <idno type="local">SW_Letters_1792_02_11</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Native Americans and Quakers: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>Miscellaneous Manuscripts</collection>
                        <idno>Misc Mss 1792_02_11</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>1 p.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This letter is part of a collection of miscellaneous correspondence and is housed
                    at Friends Historical Library, on the campus of Swarthmore College. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> The transcribers and editor attempted to render the author’s orthography and
                    grammar as they appear on the page of his journal, even when the author’s own
                    spelling and usage are inconsistent. Additionally, many questions remain about
                    spelling the names of his Quaker acquaintances, individual Native Americans who
                    populate his journal, and Indian villages and towns. The transcribers and editor
                    attempted to remain faithful to the author’s Anglicized spellings in all cases.
                </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written in 1792<date/></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Lear, Tobias, 1762-1816</item>
                        <item>Society of Friends -- Missions</item>
                        <item>Indians of North America -- Missions</item>
                        <item>Cherokee Indians</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item>PCO edits<date>2015</date></item>
            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
                <pb n="1" facs="SW_Letters_1792_02_11_Page_1"/>
                <opener><dateline><placeName key="phila"> Philadelphia, </placeName>
                        <date when="1792-02-11"> February 11th: 1792.</date></dateline></opener>
                <p> The President of the United States commands <lb/>
                    <persName key="tlear1">T. Lear</persName> to return the enclosed paper, which
                    was <lb/> submitted to the consideration of the <persName key="gwash1"
                        >President</persName> last <lb/> evening, containing the sentiments
                        proposed to be <lb/> delivered, in writing, by the
                    Quakers to the deputation <lb/> from the <orgName key="cherokee"> Cherokee
                    </orgName> nation of Indians now in this <lb/> City and to inform, that the
                    President, upon <lb/> a due consideration of the subject; does not see any <lb/>
                    impropriety in the enclosed speech being delivered <lb/> to the Cherokees, as it
                    contains the same friendly <lb/> sentiments with which he has himself
                    endeavoured <lb/> to impress these people and doesn't appear to be <lb/> a
                    matter that can be drawn into precedent on any <lb/> future occasion. Neither
                    has the President any <lb/> objection to those Indians being furnished by the
                    <lb/> Quakers with such small presents as were men- <lb/> tioned to him last evening. </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName key="tlear1">Tobias Lear <lb/>Secretary to the President
                                    <lb/> of the United States</persName></signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
