<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei-print.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="global.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter to John Drinker from John Parrish et. al.: Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>Constance Hawley</name>
                </respStmt>

                <sponsor>Tri-Co Digital Humanities Initiative</sponsor>
                <funder>Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca.11 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>This work is the property of the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore
                        College. It may be copied freely by individuals for personal use, research,
                        and teaching (including distribution to classes) as long as this statement
                        of availability is included in the text. It may be linked to freely in
                        Internet editions of all kinds, including for—profit works.</p>
                    <p>Publishers, libraries, and other information providers interested in
                        providing this text in a commercial or non—profit product or from an
                        information server must contact Swarthmore College for licensing and cost
                        information.</p>
                    <p> Scholars interested in changing or adding to these texts by, for example,
                        creating a new edition of the text (electronically or in print) with
                        substantive editorial changes, may do so with the permission of Swarthmore
                        College. This is the case whether the new publication will be made available
                        at a cost or free of charge.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2014">2015</date>
                <idno type="local">SW_Letters_1793_08_24</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Native Americans and Quakers: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>Miscellaneous Manuscripts</collection>
                        <idno>Mss_004_1793_08_24</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>3 pp.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This collection of miscellaneous correspondence is housed at Friends Historical
                    Library, on the campus of Swarthmore College. In the fall semester of 2010,
                    Swarthmore students enrolled in English 50A (“Reading Red, White, and In-Between
                    in Early American Literature”) transcribed these manuscripts as part of a larger
                    project to make the library’s rich store of Quaker Indian mission writings more
                    accessible. The project was designed by Christopher Densmore, Curator of Friends
                    Historical Library, and Keat Murray, Visiting Assistant Professor of English.
                    Transcriptions were compiled and edited in the present form by Professor Murray.
                </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> The transcribers and editor attempted to render the author’s orthography and
                    grammar as they appear on the page of his journal, even when the author’s own
                    spelling and usage are inconsistent. Additionally, many questions remain about
                    spelling the names of his Quaker acquaintances, individual Native Americans who
                    populate his journal, and Indian villages and towns. The transcribers and editor
                    attempted to remain faithful to the author’s Anglicized spellings in all cases. </p>

            </editorialDecl>

        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written in 1793<date/></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Society of Friends - New York (State)</item>
                        <item>Society of Friends -- Missions</item>
                        <item>Indians of North America -- Missions</item>
                        <item>Quaker women -- Pennsylvania -- Correspondence</item>
                        <item>Seneca Indians</item>
                        <item>Philadelphia Yearly Meeting of the Relgious Society of Friends. Meeting for Sufferings.</item>

                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>

        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item><date/></item>
            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>

            <div type="letter">


                <pb n="1" facs="SW_Letters_1793_08_24_Page_1"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName key="detro">Detroit</placeName>
                        <date when="1793-08-24">6 mo 24th. 1793</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>Dear Friend<lb/><persName key="jdrin1">John
                    Drinker</persName></salute></opener>
                <p>Concluding it will be satisfactory to our Friends<lb/>of the Meeting for
                    Sufferings to be informed how we spend our time<lb/>we desire thee to acquaint
                    them that we all met together the <date when="1793-07-27">27th.<lb/>of last
                        mo</date> at <placeName key="niaga">Niagara</placeName>; in the
                    neighbourhood whereof we found a<lb/>larger number of Friends than we expected;
                    had several Meetings<lb/>with them, and distributed the Books sent by us, which
                    were<lb/>very acceptable, and many more would be useful, as some<lb/>families
                    have neither Bible nor Testament in their houses.</p>
                <p>The Commissioners being informed by <persName key="amcke1">Col. Mc.Kee</persName>
                    that the<lb/>Indians would not be collected so soon as was expected,
                    concluded<lb/>to stay at Navy Hall with <persName key="gsim">Gov.
                        Simcoe</persName> until the return of <persName key="jparr2"
                        >Jasper<lb/>Parrish</persName>, by whom we hope to hear from our beloved
                    Friends. But<lb/>it was thought best for us to proceed to this place, where we
                        arrived<lb/><date when="1793-08">two weeks ago</date>, &amp; have the
                    opportunity of seeing many of the Indians<lb/>as they pass on to the conference
                    held by them preparatory to the<lb/>Treaty--a large body from very remote parts
                    appears to be collecting<lb/>some of them have expressed themselves in very
                    friendly terms, &amp; we<lb/>hope the interviews we have had will help to open
                    the way in the<lb/>future progress of the business, which appears to us
                    increasingly im-<lb/>portant &amp; delicate. The Reports that have prevailed
                    here for some<lb/>days past of <persName key="gwayn1">Gen. Wayne</persName>'s
                    Army having moved from <placeName key="fwash1">Fort
                    Washington</placeName><lb/>to the Miami Plains, nearer to <placeName key="sandu"
                        >Sandusky</placeName>, have excited jealousies<lb/>among the Indians. On the
                    whole our situation is exercising, &amp;<lb/>requires Wisdom &amp; Patience,
                    which it is our united desire we may<lb/>be favoured with.</p>
                <p>We have had two Meetings in this place, and two on the other<lb/>side of the
                    River among some sober Germans &amp; others, which we<lb/>believe were to
                    general satisfaction. The people here as well<lb/>as the Officers &amp; Soldiers
                    of the Garrison are very civil &amp; kind to us<lb/>and appear pleased with the
                    opportunity of information respecting <pb n="2" facs="SW_Letters_1793_08_24_Page_2"/><lb/>Friends Principles, so that we hope
                    our being here will not be<lb/>altogether useless, tho' it is trying to be thus
                    detained.</p>
                <closer>We are with the Salutation of Love to all the Members<lb/>of the Meeting for
                    Sufferings &amp; others<lb/><salute>Thy Affectionate Friends</salute> <signed><list
                            rend="simple">
                            <item><persName key="jparr1">John Parrish</persName></item>
                            <item><persName key="jlind1">Jacob Lindley</persName></item>
                            <item><persName key="jelli1">John Elliot</persName></item>
                            <item><persName key="wsave1">William Savery</persName></item>
                            <item><persName key="whart1">Wm. Hartshorne</persName></item>
                        </list></signed>
                </closer>
                <note rend="asterisk" resp="author"><persName key="jmoor3">Joseph Moore</persName>, being absent
                    his name is omited</note>
            </div>

        </body>

    </text>
</TEI>
