<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei-print.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="global.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter to the Indians Assembled at the Rapids of the Miami: Electronic
                    Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>Constance Hawley</name>
                </respStmt>

                <sponsor>Tri-Co Digital Humanities Initiative</sponsor>
                <funder>Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca.11 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>This work is the property of the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore
                        College. It may be copied freely by individuals for personal use, research,
                        and teaching (including distribution to classes) as long as this statement
                        of availability is included in the text. It may be linked to freely in
                        Internet editions of all kinds, including for—profit works.</p>
                    <p>Publishers, libraries, and other information providers interested in
                        providing this text in a commercial or non—profit product or from an
                        information server must contact Swarthmore College for licensing and cost
                        information.</p>
                    <p> Scholars interested in changing or adding to these texts by, for example,
                        creating a new edition of the text (electronically or in print) with
                        substantive editorial changes, may do so with the permission of Swarthmore
                        College. This is the case whether the new publication will be made available
                        at a cost or free of charge.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2014">2015</date>
                <idno type="local">SW_Letters_1793_07_17</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Native Americans and Quakers: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>Miscellaneous Manuscripts</collection>
                        <idno>Mss_004_1793_07_17</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>2 pp.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This collection of miscellaneous correspondence is housed at Friends Historical
                    Library, on the campus of Swarthmore College. In the fall semester of 2010,
                    Swarthmore students enrolled in English 50A (“Reading Red, White, and In-Between
                    in Early American Literature”) transcribed these manuscripts as part of a larger
                    project to make the library’s rich store of Quaker Indian mission writings more
                    accessible. The project was designed by Christopher Densmore, Curator of Friends
                    Historical Library, and Keat Murray, Visiting Assistant Professor of English.
                    Transcriptions were compiled and edited in the present form by Professor Murray.
                </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> The transcribers and editor attempted to render the author’s orthography and
                    grammar as they appear on the page of his journal, even when the author’s own
                    spelling and usage are inconsistent. Additionally, many questions remain about
                    spelling the names of his Quaker acquaintances, individual Native Americans who
                    populate his journal, and Indian villages and towns. The transcribers and editor
                    attempted to remain faithful to the author’s Anglicized spellings in all cases. </p>

            </editorialDecl>

        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written in 1793<date/></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Society of Friends - Michigan</item>
                        <item>Society of Friends -- Missions</item>
                        <item>Indians of North America -- Missions</item>


                        <item>Philadelphia Yearly Meeting of the Relgious Society of Friends</item>

                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>

        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item><date/></item>
            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>

            <div type="letter">


                <pb n="1" facs="SW_Letters_1793_07_17_Page_1"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName key="detro">Detroit</placeName>
                        <date when="1793-07-15">7 mo 15th 1793</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>To the Indians<lb/>Assembled at the Rapids of the <placeName
                            key="miamr1">Miami</placeName><lb/>Brothers,</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>We who send you this Letter are of the<lb/>People called Quakers, and have left
                    our homes and Families<lb/>in Pensylvania &amp; New Jersy and taken this long
                    Journey to<lb/>see you purely from motives of Love and good Will, and<lb/>to
                    endeavour to promote peace. We have been now five<lb/>Weeks at <placeName
                        key="detro">Detroit</placeName> waiting for the opening of the Treaty
                        at<lb/><placeName key="sandu">Sandusky</placeName>, where we expected to
                    have seen you all, but as<lb/>we have heard a number of your People are gone to
                        <placeName key="niag">Niagara</placeName><lb/>to meet the Commissioners, we
                    do not know but the business<lb/> may be so concluded there, as that they may
                    come no further</p>
                <p>Brothers,<lb/>We have brought with us <gap/>an Address<lb/>to you from our
                    Brothers at Home, which we are very<lb/>desirous of presenting to you with our
                    own hands, if an<lb/>opportunity can be had. It is also in our Hearts
                    to<lb/>acquaint you that we consider all Men as the Children<lb/>of one common
                    Father, and think it our duty to Love all<lb/>as Brothers. We believe it
                    displeases the Great &amp; Good Spirit<lb/>when Men injure and kill one another,
                    therefore we <del>en-</del><lb/>endeavour to do Justice but when any despute
                    arises, we leave it to be settled by disinterested &amp; impartial<lb/>persons
                    and never go to war on any occasion <lb/><gap/>We have<lb/>been made very
                    sorrowful on account of the War and <lb/>Bloodshed between the United States and
                    our Indian Brethren,<lb/>and want much to see you, that we may open
                    our<lb/>hearts more fully than we can do by writing, for <lb/> we <lb/>
                    <pb n="2" facs="SW_Letters_1793_07_17_Page_2"/> we are fully convinced that by looking up to the Great Spirit<lb/>for
                    Counsel, all differences may be settled without fighting<lb/>and killing one
                    another, which we think is very cruel, and<lb/>attended with many distressing
                    circumstances both to you<lb/>and the White People. Our Society have experienced
                    for<lb/>more than One hundred Years great advantage and<lb/>satisfaction in
                    living peacably with all Men, and are<lb/>very desirous you may enjoy the same
                    benefits, and<lb/>to that and were made willing to expose
                    themselves,<lb/>encounter hardships and spend our substance to promote<lb/>peace
                    and Love between you, and the Government of<lb/>the United States.</p>
                <p>We Pray the Good Spirit that He may put an end<lb/>to the ravages of War and
                    unite all Men as Brothers, that<lb/>being bound together by one great Chain of
                    Love and<lb/>Friendship that cannot be broken, we may all seek<lb/>the happiness
                    of each other in this Life, and be prepared<lb/>for the enjoyment of everlasting
                    happiness in the Life<lb/>which is to come
                </p>
            </div>

        </body>

    </text>
</TEI>
