<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei-print.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="global.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>Reports of the Indian Committee to New York Yearly Meeting, 1795-1806:
                    Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>Cara Ehlenfeldt</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Reports transcribed by</resp>
                    <name>Cara Ehlenfeldt</name>


                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Tri-Co Digital Humanities Initiative</sponsor>
                <funder>Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 24 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>This work is the property of the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore
                        College. It may be copied freely by individuals for personal use, research,
                        and teaching (including distribution to classes) as long as this statement
                        of availability is included in the text. It may be linked to freely in
                        Internet editions of all kinds, including for—profit works.</p>
                    <p>Publishers, libraries, and other information providers interested in
                        providing this text in a commercial or non—profit product or from an
                        information server must contact Swarthmore College for licensing and cost
                        information.</p>
                    <p> Scholars interested in changing or adding to these texts by, for example,
                        creating a new edition of the text (electronically or in print) with
                        substantive editorial changes, may do so only with the permission of Friends
                        Historical Library of Swarthmore College. This is the case whether the new
                        publication will be made available at a cost or free of charge.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2015">2015</date>
                <idno type="local">SW_NYYMreports</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Native Americans and Quakers: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>New York Yearly Meeting minutes</collection>
                        <idno>RG2/NYy/001 1.1, 1.3</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>23 pp. in 2 volumes</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The minutes of New York Yearly Meeting are housed in Friends Historical Library,
                    on the campus of Swarthmore College. The reports were abstracted from the books
                    of minutes of the New York Yearly Meeting because the minutes of the NYYM Indian
                    Committee before 1807 were not recorded. Only the Indian Committee reports have
                    been transcribed.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> The transcribers and editor attempted to render the author’s orthography and
                    grammar as they appear on the page of his journal, even when the author’s own
                    spelling and usage are inconsistent. Additionally, many questions remain about
                    spelling the names of his Quaker acquaintances, individual Native Americans who
                    populate his journal, and Indian villages and towns. The transcribers and editor
                    attempted to remain faithful to the author’s Anglicized spellings in all
                    cases.</p>

            </editorialDecl>

        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written from <date from="1795" to="1806">1795-1806</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Quakers -- New York (State)</item>
                        <item>Indians of North America</item>
                        <item>New York Yearly Meeting of the Religious Society of Friends</item>

                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>

        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item>
                    <date when="2015"/>POD edit</item>

            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>

        <body>

            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="351" facs="SW_NYYM_reports_Page_001"/>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1795-05-30"/><placeName key="nycit">New York</placeName></dateline>
                <p>The attention of the Meeting was turned towards <lb/>the situation and
                    circumstances of the Indians in the Western <lb/>parts of the States and
                    aconcern took place for the promotion <lb/>of their Welfare and the Subject
                    spreading with weight much <lb/>sympathy was felt with them in their Scatter’d
                    &amp; remote <lb/>situation and under a deliberate view thereof there appeared
                    <lb/>apropiety and hope of usefulness in placeing the Subject under <lb/>the
                    consideration and care of the Meeting for Sufferings who <lb/>on examination
                    into their circumstances are authorised to <lb/>afford them such assistance as
                    may appear necessary to said <lb/>Meeting and the following Friends are
                    appointed to set <lb/>with the Meeting for Sufferings in the consideration
                    thereof <lb/>viz <persName key="ploss1">Peter Lossing</persName>
                    <persName key="jcorn1">John Cornell</persName>
                    <persName key="bhavi1">Benjamin Haviland</persName>
                    <persName key="cfros2">Charles <lb/>Frost</persName>
                    <persName key="jcast1">John Caste</persName>
                    <persName key="teddy1">Thomas Eddy</persName>
                    <persName key="ilegg1">Isaac Legges</persName>
                    <persName key="jtalc1">Joseph Talket</persName> William <lb/>&amp; attentive
                        <persName key="dtitu1">Dan Titus</persName>
                    <persName key="jgriff2">Joseph Griffin</persName>
                    <persName key="wseam2">Willis Seaman</persName>
                    <persName key="hhull1">Henry Hull</persName>
                    <lb/><persName key="aunde1">Abraham Underhill</persName> &amp; <persName
                        key="rlawr2">Rich. Lawrence</persName> &amp; <persName key="jferr1">John
                        Ferris</persName></p>
                <closer>Adjourned to the 9th hour on 2d day Morng</closer>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="363" facs="SW_NYYM_reports_Page_002"/>
                <dateline><date when="1796-05-27"/><placeName key="nycit">New
                    York</placeName></dateline>
                <p>27th. The Meeting assembled according to adjournment</p>
                <p> We find by the Minutes of our Meeting for Sufferings that <lb/>the concern of
                    this Meeting relative to the Indians in the Western <lb/>parts of this State had
                    been attended to by that Meeting in Company <lb/>with divers Friends appointed
                    last Year to unite with that Meeting <lb/>on this Subject that their care and
                    attention thereto had induced <lb/>an appointment to visset that People to
                    inform themselves of <lb/>their situation and circumstances that the report of
                    the Committee so <lb/>appointed claimed the attention of that Meeting and
                    impress’d <lb/>a concern for that People that led to aprospect of some further
                    <lb/>steps on their behalf and in an especial manner for the <lb/>discouragement
                    of the Spirituous liqueres being introduced amongst <lb/>them but in attending
                    to the prospect way did not open to <lb/>proceed therein for the presant – The
                    care and labour of that <lb/>Meeting with the Friends who were united with them
                    <lb/>therein appear to have been great and manifests their regard <lb/>to the
                    concern and recommendation of this Meeting and it is <lb/>satisfactory to find
                    by the information now before us that <lb/>many amongst that People have become
                    sensible of the <lb/>sorrowful effects of the use of ardent Spirits, and their
                    openness <lb/>to advice and council, and a renewed weight attending the
                    <lb/>Subject at this time, our deliberations result in the appoint- <lb/>ment of
                    a Committee to the solid Consideration &amp; attention <lb/>to the concern of
                    this Meeting on the Subject and that they <lb/>move forwards with care and
                    caution as way may open <lb/>and thereto the following Friends are appointed viz
                        <lb/><persName key="jcoop2">Joseph Cooper</persName>, <persName key="jmott1"
                        >James Mott</persName>, <persName key="sbown1">Sam Bowne</persName>
                    <persName key="jpars1">James Parsons</persName>
                    <persName key="tmosh1">Trip <lb/>Mosher</persName>
                    <persName key="epryo1">Edmund Prior</persName>
                    <persName key="twilb1">Thomas Wilber</persName>
                    <persName key="stitu1">Sam Titus</persName>
                    <persName key="rweek1">Refine Weeks</persName>
                    <lb/><persName key="jmurr1">John Murray</persName>
                    <persName key="teddy1">Thomas Eddy</persName>
                    <persName key="cduel1">Cornelius Duel</persName>
                    <persName key="ithor1">Isaac Thorne</persName>
                    <persName key="bwilb1">Browning <lb/>Wilbur</persName>
                    <persName key="ploss1">Peter Lossing</persName>
                    <persName key="ehick1">Elias Hicks</persName>
                    <persName key="rmott1">Richrd Mott</persName>
                    <persName key="gburl1">Garret Burlis</persName>
                    <persName key="jbarr1">John <lb/>Barrow</persName>
                    <persName key="wferr1">Walter Farrington</persName>
                    <persName key="wseam2">Willis Seaman</persName>
                    <persName key="fhull1">Fideman Hull</persName>
                    <persName key="jgriff2">Joseph <lb/>Griffin</persName>
                    <persName key="rbown1">Robert Bowne</persName>
                    <persName key="aunde1">Abraham Underhill</persName> &amp; <persName key="gseam2"
                        >Gideon Seaman</persName>
                    <lb/><persName key="hjudg1">Hugh Judge</persName>
                    <persName key="jpear1">Joseph Pearsall</persName>
                    <persName key="slear1">Sam Learing</persName>
                    <persName key="iunde1">Isaac Underhill</persName>
                    <lb/><persName key="wodel1">Willm Odel</persName>
                    <persName key="sdown1">Silas Downing</persName> &amp; <persName key="gembr1"
                        >George Embrie</persName> and the Meeting for <lb/>Sufferings is desired to
                    give their advice and assistance of the <lb/>Committee should see occasion to
                    call for it and to call on our <lb/>Treasurer for Money in their favour if the
                    Meeting for Suffergs <lb/>should see it advisable –</p>
                <closer>Adjourned to the 4th hour afternoon – </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="377" facs="SW_NYYM_reports_Page_003"/>
                <dateline><date when="1797-05-30"/><placeName key="nycit">New
                    York</placeName></dateline>
                <p>A report from the Comm.ee on Indian affairs is now read asolid quiet <lb/>took
                    place thereon and arenewed sympathy felt for that People and <lb/>the further
                    consideration thereof is refer’d to afuture seling the <lb/>report is as follows
                    viz </p>
                <floatingText type="report">
                    <body>
                        <p>To the Yearly Meeting now seting The <lb/>comm.ee appointed last year of
                            Indian affairs now report that we <lb/>have had in the course of the
                            year past divers Meetings on the <lb/>weighty subject refer’d to us and
                            have at times been drawn into <lb/>sympathy with the peculeir situation
                            of the Natives and while <lb/>deliberating on the best means that might
                            be adopted for <lb/>promoting their welfare if appear’d to the Comm.ee
                            that there would <lb/>be aprobable usefulness in selecting some of our
                            number to pay <lb/>them avissit and some Friends were accordingly named
                            for their <lb/>purpose but circumstances which afterwards took place
                            presented <lb/>them from proceeding on the journey and soon after this
                            the <lb/>advanced season of the year rendered it very difficult to
                            proceed <lb/>so that avissit has not taken place – It would have
                            afforded <lb/>satisfaction to us if we could have possess’d the Yearly
                            Meetg <lb/>with more full information of the State of the Indians which
                            <lb/>mights probably have been done if the intended vissit had been
                            <lb/>made We can only now say that from some information <lb/>obtained
                            anumber of the Indians have lately shewn agreater <lb/>disposition
                            towards sobriety of conduct and agricultural <lb/>improvement that
                            heretofore – And altho’ asufficient attraction <lb/>to this interesting
                            concern will probably require patience and <lb/>perseverance yet under
                            right direction we are induced to <lb/>believe it will lend to the
                            benefit and advantages of the Indians </p>
                        <closer>Signed by direction &amp; on behalf of the Comm.ee <dateline><date
                                    when="1797-05-30">5 mo 30. 1797</date><placeName key="nycit">New
                                    York</placeName></dateline> by <lb/><persName key="sbown1"
                                >Samuel Bowne</persName></closer>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>

            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="3378" facs="SW_NYYM_reports_Page_004"/>
                <dateline><date when="1797-05-31"/><placeName key="nycit">New
                    York</placeName></dateline>
                <p>The Meeting gathered at the 2d hour - <lb/>Renewed attention was given to the
                    Subject referr'd <lb/>from last seling relative to Indian Affairs and as we
                    <lb/>find that the Comm.ee had aprospect of asrvice for them <lb/>to perform
                    which they had been prevented from going <lb/>into 'till the season was too far
                    advanced and a desire <lb/>being witness'd for their encouragment in the
                    extention <lb/>of further care this important Subject is therefore continued
                    <lb/>under their care with the following Friends added to them <lb/>in this
                    concern viz <persName key="ttitu1">Thomas Titus</persName>
                    <persName key="sroge1">Stephen Rogers</persName> - <lb/><persName key="llawr1"
                        >Leonard Lawrence</persName> &amp; <persName key="gbown1">George
                        Bowne</persName> - <persName key="ehick1">Elias Hicks</persName>
                    <lb/>is releas'd from this Service at his request -</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="396" facs="SW_NYYM_reports_Page_005"/>
                <dateline><date when="1798-05-29"/><placeName key="nycit">New
                    York</placeName></dateline>
                <p>The Committee continued on this Meetings concern relative <lb/>to the Indian
                    Natives in the western parts of this state, make <lb/>the following report in
                    writing viz -</p>
                <floatingText type="report">
                    <body>
                        <dateline><date when="1798-05-29"/><placeName key="nycit">New
                                York</placeName></dateline>
                        <p>The Committee appointed by the Yearly Meeting on <lb/>its concern
                            Relative to Indian affairs, report that they have <lb/>so far paid
                            attention thereto that a visit hath been paid by <lb/>some of their
                            number, to the Indians of <orgName key="brotherton"
                                >Brothertown</orgName>, <orgName key="stockbridge">Stock-
                                <lb/>bridge</orgName>, <orgName key="oneida">Oneida</orgName>, and
                            part of the <orgName key="tuscarora">Tuscorora</orgName> Tribes, by
                            whose <lb/>report it appears, that several of these tribes have of
                            latter time <lb/>not only appear'd convinced of the necessity of their
                            becoming <lb/>more acquainted with habits of civilizasion, but have
                            given <lb/>some proofs of industry, and attention to agricultural pur-
                            <lb/>suits, which gave encouragement to hope that by a perse-
                            <lb/>virance therein, they may be enabled to acquire a more
                            <lb/>certain, and comfortable livelihood, tho at present they are
                            <lb/>mostly poor, and in streighned circumstances; and particular
                            <lb/>-lysed, while the Committee were there, by reason on an unfavour
                            <lb/>-able season, the last summer, and a very trying long Winter
                            <lb/>which induced them to afford some of the most necessitous <pb n="397" facs="SW_NYYM_reports_Page_006"/><lb/>some pecuniary assistance, mostly to procure Bread
                            Corn; <lb/>that divers of the Indians appear to be religious sober
                            minded <lb/>persons, and very sensible of the perniceous effects of
                            storng <lb/>drink, and concern'd for their People on that acccount-
                            <lb/>yet others still gave way to that weakness - That they <lb/>found
                            several young Men from <placeName key="penns">Pensylvania</placeName>
                            Members <lb/>of our Society residing amongst them, from their own
                            concern <lb/>and under the direction of a Committee, of the Yearly
                            <lb/>Meeting of <placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName>, for the
                            instruction and Improve <lb/>-ment of the Indians; who informed them,
                            that altho they <lb/>met with many discouragements, yet on the whole
                            there is <lb/>an improvement amongst them, that the Indians form a
                            <lb/>desire that their Children, may have some School learning,
                            <lb/>have several Schools amonst them, one of which is taught <lb/>by
                            one of the forementioned Friends; the other by their own <lb/>People;
                            several of the Tribes, express'd the satisfaction they <lb/>had in the
                            visit paid them by our Friends in 1795, signify- <lb/>-ing that it had
                            been useful to them, which appear'd to have <lb/>been the case - The
                            Indians viewed the visit kindly, <lb/>express'd their gratitude for this
                            further attention of care <lb/>and regard for them - That tho the visit
                            was attended <lb/>with some fateague yet they had a good degree of
                            satisfac- <lb/>-tion therein -</p>
                        <closer>Sign'd by direction, and on behalf of the Comittee <lb/><persName
                                key="jbarr1">John Barron</persName></closer>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>The care and attention manifsted by the Committee, to those <lb/>people is
                    satisfactory to the Meeting; and the comfortable quit <lb/>that <pb n="398" facs="SW_NYYM_reports_Page_007"/><lb/>that attends the present consideration, together with a free com
                    <lb/>munication of concurring sentiments pointing thereto leads to the
                    <lb/>prosperity of an appointment, to continue a care to the subject. <lb/>and
                    in encourageing them to step forward therein, in the way <lb/>that may appear
                    most likely to contribute to the well doing of <lb/>the Indians, and answer the
                    present views of this Meeting, particu <lb/>-larly, in endeavouring to turn
                    their attention to agricultural Im <lb/>-provements, and a state of
                    Civilization, and should a suitable <lb/>Friend or two, from a concern to be
                    useful to those People, be dis- <lb/>posed to step forward in residing among
                    them for a time, in order <lb/>to effect those desireable purposes, that the
                    Committee encourage <lb/>and make way therefor - And as occasion will probably
                    require <lb/>some pecuniary aid, for their and other purposes, the Committee
                    <lb/>with the advice and approbation of our Meeting for Sufferings <lb/>are
                    authoritative to call on their Meetings Treasurer to answer such <lb/>demands,
                    and to the service the following Friends are apointed <lb/>Viz <persName
                        key="jbarr1">John Barron</persName>, <persName key="slear1">Samuel
                        Learing</persName>, <persName key="cfros2">Charles Frost</persName>,
                        <persName key="gseam2">Gideon Seaman</persName>, <lb/><persName key="sbown1"
                        >Samuel Bowne</persName>, <persName key="jmurr1">John Murray</persName>,
                        <persName key="trobi1">Thomas R Robinson</persName>, <persName key="ploss1"
                        >Peter <lb/>Lossing</persName>, <persName key="tmosh1">Trip
                        Mosher</persName>, <persName key="jmott1">James Mott</persName>, <persName
                        key="fhull1">Fiddeman Hull</persName>, <persName key="jbark2">John
                        <lb/>Barker</persName>, <persName key="rbown1">Robert Bowne</persName>, and
                        <persName key="ohull1">Oliver Hull</persName> -</p>
                <closer>Adjourn'd to the third Hour tomorrow afternoon</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="425" facs="SW_NYYM_reports_Page_008"/>
                <dateline><date when="1799-05-30"/><placeName key="nycit">New
                    York</placeName></dateline>
                <p>The Committee appointed to the <lb/>Important concern, appertaining to the
                    welfare of <lb/>the Indians made the following report in writing viz.-</p>
                <floatingText type="report">
                    <body>
                        <dateline><date when="1799-05-30"/><placeName key="nycit">New
                                York</placeName></dateline>
                        <p>That during the last year they have several times met <lb/>and the
                            subject of their concern has engaged their attention <lb/>and that one
                            of their number, in company with our friend <lb/><persName key="hjudg1"
                                >Hugh Judge</persName>, has paid a visit to some of the Tribes
                            situate <lb/>in the Oneida Country since last year, to a good degree of
                            <lb/>satisfaction; having reason to believe there is a progressive
                            <lb/>improvement in civilization and agricultural pursuits. -</p>
                        <p>There are a number of Schools established amongst <lb/>them; one of which
                            has been taught by a man friend from <lb/><placeName key="penns"
                                >Pensylvania</placeName>, who appeared likely to prove useful to
                            that People, <pb n="426" facs="SW_NYYM_reports_Page_009"/><lb/>having course to believe that his
                            undertaking originated <lb/>in aright concern - Another School was also
                            taught <lb/>by a woman friend, whose devotedness and attention <lb/>to
                            this arduous undertaking, gives reason to hope that <lb/>considerable
                            benefit will result from her labours. - <lb/>Yet we observe with
                            concern, that owing to a disposal <lb/>of some of their Land to the
                            State, adjoining to the <lb/>main road, leading through their
                            settlements, which <lb/> by the introduction of Taverns, opening an easy
                            access <lb/>to the use of ardent Spirits, which has hitherto proved so
                            <lb/> painfully detrimental to their civil &amp; religious improvement,
                            <lb/>for altho many of them appear sensible of its baneful effects,
                            <lb/>and consider it as their most potent Enemy, yet their <lb/>
                            weakness is such, through the power of habit, that when <lb/>it is
                            introduced amongst them, they give way - Yet from <lb/>the covering of
                            solemnity, &amp; heart felt sympathy generally <lb/>felt on the first
                            opening of this weighty concern for their <lb/>wellfare, the evident
                            revival of it at times in our deliberations <lb/>on the subject, affords
                            encouragement for friends to persevere <lb/>in their benevolent designs,
                            apprehending it may be <lb/> ranked amongst those cases, where
                            obstructions ought to <lb/>stimulate to an increase of care &amp;
                            attention -</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>The Meeting in arenewed attention <lb/>to the subject relative to that People,
                    and the communication <lb/>&amp; feelings thereon, evidenced arevival of the
                    concern, &amp; <lb/> asatisfaction with the report of the Committee - who are
                    <lb/>desired to continue their care, &amp; attention thereto, agreeable <lb/>to
                    the minute made on this subject last year, with <lb/>ahope they may be
                    encouraged to persevere in the work <lb/>under right direction - and as their
                    number is small, <lb/>&amp; reside much scattered, it is throught a usefulness
                    might <pb n="427" facs="SW_NYYM_reports_Page_010"/><lb/>arise from an addition being made to the Committee
                    -<lb/> and the following names being proposed were united <lb/>with, &amp;
                    accordingly appointed to that service viz.&amp; - <lb/><persName key="srick1"
                        >Shadrach Ricketson</persName>, <persName key="ehavi1">Ebenezer
                        Haviland</persName>, <persName key="bcorn1">Benjamin
                        <lb/>Cornwall</persName>, <persName key="wseam2">Willett Seaman</persName>,
                        <persName key="tfran1">Thomas Franklin</persName>, <persName key="hjudg1"
                        >Hugh <lb/>Judge</persName>, <persName key="acock1">Andrew Cock</persName>,
                        <persName key="teddy1">Thomas Eddy</persName>, <persName key="bwilb1"
                        >Browning <lb/> Wilbor</persName>, <persName key="zhoxi1">Zebulon
                        Hoxie</persName>, <persName key="ilegg1">Isaac Leggett</persName> &amp;
                        <persName key="dhaig1">David Haight</persName></p>
                <closer> Adjourned to the 5th hour Afternoon.</closer>

            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="428" facs="SW_NYYM_reports_Page_011"/>
                <dateline><date when="1799-06-01"/><placeName key="nycit">New
                    York</placeName></dateline>
                <p>31st of 5th mo. The Meeting again assembled -</p>
                <p>The subject relative to the Indians being revived, <lb/>it is thought an
                    advantage would result form endeavour <lb/>to render the concern more diffusive
                    - and aprospect <lb/>opening to spread the consideration thereof in our
                    <lb/>Quarterly Meetings, which being united with, a copy <lb/>of this Minute is
                    accordingly directed to our Quarters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="445" facs="SW_NYYM_reports_Page_012"/>
                <dateline><date when="1800-05-30"/><placeName key="nycit">New
                    York</placeName></dateline>
                <p>The Committee on the concern of this Meeting <lb/>relative to the welfare of the
                    Indians, now made <lb/>the following report on that subject - viz. -</p>
                <floatingText type="report">
                    <body>
                        <dateline><date when="1800-05-30"/><placeName key="nycit">New
                                York</placeName></dateline>
                        <p>The Committee appointed by the Yearly <pb n="446" facs="SW_NYYM_reports_Page_013"/><lb/>Meeting on its
                            concern relative to Indian Affairs Report -</p>
                        <p>That during the course of last year, we have frequently <lb/>met, and the
                            subject of our appointment weightily <lb/>claimed our attention, often
                            leading our minds <lb/>into anear sympathy with the natives; and altho
                            <lb/>the exercise presented at times many discouragements, <lb/>yet as
                            we were from time to time made sensible <lb/>that the concern was owned,
                            we were encouraged to <lb/>believe, that as friends attend to the
                            pointings of <lb/>duty, and persevere therein, that they might be very
                            <lb/>useful to this People - In the course of last year <lb/>two of our
                            number, altho not appointed particularly <lb/>to the service, paid
                            avisit to some of the Tribes from <lb/>areligious concern, which was to
                            the satisfaction of <lb/>the friends, and appeared very acceptable to
                            the Indians. <lb/>The <orgName key="stockbridge">Stockbridge
                                Tribe</orgName> expressed a desire that some <lb/>suitable Person
                            might be sent among them to instruct <lb/>some of their young Men in the
                            Blacksmiths business - <lb/>as if may be difficult to meet with a
                            Friend, suitable <lb/>&amp; free, to reside among them, the Committee
                            turned <lb/> their attention to endeavour to serve them by procuring
                            <lb/>suitable places, where some of their Youth might be <lb/>placed to
                            get instruction in that Trade, - and as this <lb/>may greatly forward
                            them in civilized life, it is desirable <lb/>that friends generally may
                            aid the Committee in <lb/> finding places for them - After having made
                            <lb/>some progress in improving the general state of things <lb/>in the
                            settlement in and about <placeName key="oneid">Oneida</placeName>, we
                            find that friends <lb/>of <orgName key="pym">Pensylvania Yearly
                                Meeting</orgName> have withdrawn their members <pb n="447" facs="SW_NYYM_reports_Page_014"/><lb/>who
                            for sometime resided with the Indians there, with <lb/>aview of
                            extending their services farther westward - <lb/>As those Indians are
                            now left by Friends, who have <lb/>at a considerable expence helped them
                            with Farming <lb/>Utensils, and assissted them in erecting Mills and
                            <lb/>other improvements, their labour may in some degree <lb/>be lost,
                            unless attended by friends of this Yearly Meet.g <lb/>and as those
                            Tribes are much more convenient to us, <lb/>the Committee are desirous
                            they may claim the <lb/>sympathy &amp; attention to friends - all which
                            is <lb/>submitted - </p>
                        <closer>signed by direction &amp; on behalf <lb/>of the Committee <persName
                                key="sbown1">Saml Bowne</persName>
                        </closer>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p><date when="1800-05-26">5 mo 26-1800</date></p>
                <p>In attending to the preceding report, <lb/>the Meeting was led to the expression
                    of arenew'd <lb/>feeling towards that injured People, and asatisfaction
                    <lb/>with the attention &amp; proceedings of the Committee - <lb/>and they are
                    encouraged to continue their care and <lb/>solicitude for the promotion of the
                    religious &amp; temporal <lb/>good of that part of the human Race, agreeably to
                    the <lb/>concern of this Meeting as expressed in a Minute on the Subject in
                    1798.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="24" facs="SW_NYYM_reports_Page_015"/>
                <dateline><date when="1802-05-27"/><placeName key="nycit">New
                    York</placeName></dateline>
                <p>27th of the month friends met agreeable to adjournment</p>
                <p>The committee on the conern, relative to the Indian Natives, <lb/>produced a
                    report in writing, it obtain'd the deliberate attention of the <lb/>Meeting, and
                    is satisfactory, - by this report it appears, that the prospect <lb/>of friends
                    being useful to those people, is encourageing, as by the informa <lb/>-tion of
                    two friends of the committee, that have made a visit to several <lb/>of the
                    tribes, since last year, they appear, progressing in the knowledge <lb/>of
                    agriculture, and a disposition ot civilisation; the committees conti <lb/>-nued
                    attention to the subject, is requested, and they encouraged to <lb/>step
                    forward, in a way, that may appear most likely to answer the <lb/>views of this
                    Meeting, in promoting the welfare of that people</p>
                <p>In the attention given to this concern, the meeting was led to <lb/>consider,
                    that in friends endeavouring to be useful to them, some necessa- <lb/>ry
                    expenses are attendant; and a prospect was open'd and united with <lb/>of
                    recommending to the Quarterly Meetings, the opening subscriptions to <lb/>raise
                    a fund for the promotion of so desireable a purpose, and it is <lb/>requested,
                    that the Money raised by voluntary contributions, in the <lb/>Quarters, be by
                    them placed in the hands of the Treasurer to the Com- <lb/>-mittee, and the
                    amount reported next year</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="42" facs="SW_NYYM_reports_Page_016"/>
                <dateline><date when="1802-05-25"/><placeName key="nycit">New
                    York</placeName></dateline>
                <p>A report in writing was received from the Committee <lb/>on the Indian concern,
                    by which it appears that those friends <lb/>have given attention to the subject,
                    that a visit has been made <lb/>by me of their number since last year to divers
                    of the Indians <lb/>settlements, whose report, together with the accounts
                    received from <lb/>a friend resident amongst the Natives, furnishes encourage-
                    <lb/>ment - and gives reason to believe, that the case of this May <lb/> towards
                    that People has been useful; the Committee also state <lb/>that as our friends
                    of <orgName key="pym">Pennsylvania Yearly Meeting</orgName>, have
                    with<lb/>-drawn their attention from some of the Tribes, heretofore under
                    <lb/>their care; and extended their views to the westward, they <lb/>find it
                    increasingly incumbent on them, to continue their care <lb/>to those tribes, who
                    have from the early part of this concern more <lb/>immediately claim'd their
                    attention - the information <lb/>contain'd in the Report, appears to afford
                    satisfaction, and <lb/>the Committee are continued to the service, and
                    encouraged to <lb/>attend to the concern, in such way as may appear most
                    <lb/>likely to answer the views of the Meeting, in promoting the <lb/>welfare of
                    these Indians</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="43" facs="SW_NYYM_reports_Page_017"/>
                <dateline><date when="1801-05-28"/><placeName key="nycit">New
                    York</placeName></dateline>
                <p>5th day morning 28th the meeting again assembled</p>
                <p>It appears by the report of the Committee, continued by last Year<lb/>-ly
                    Meeting, on its concern relative to the Indian natives, that the <lb/>subject,
                    hath divers times engaged their close attention, and that a visit <lb/>has been
                    perform'd by some of their number, to satisfaction, those People <lb/> being
                    improveing in agriculture, and School learning, and that there is <lb/>cause to
                    believe, some of their minds, are at times impress'ed with religious
                    <lb/>thoughtfulness; the subject renewedly claim'd, the attention of the
                    Meeting, <lb/>under which, a desire is afresh witness'd, for the religious, and
                    temporal <lb/>welfare, of that part of the human race, the committee are
                    continued to <lb/>the service, and encouraged to move forward in the concern, as
                    may apear <lb/>to them most likely to answer the views of Friends, in promoting
                    the good of <lb/>that People, <persName key="rmott1">Richard Mott</persName>,
                        <persName key="whick1">Willett Hicks</persName>, <persName key="amott2">Adam
                        Mott</persName>, <persName key="jbird1">Joseph Bird</persName>,
                        <lb/><persName key="cwebb1">Charles Webb</persName>, <persName key="lcook1"
                        >Leonard Cook</persName>, <persName key="jgriff1">John Grifin
                        Jun.r</persName> and <persName key="ithor1">Isaac Thorne Jun.r</persName>
                    <lb/>are added to the committee; and <persName key="cfros2">Charles
                        Frost</persName>, is at his request releas'd from <lb/>the appointment.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="55" facs="SW_NYYM_reports_Page_018"/>
                <dateline><date when="1804-05-30"/><placeName key="nycit">New
                    York</placeName></dateline>
                <p>The Committee on the Concern of this Meeting relative to the <lb/>Indian situated
                    on the borders of this States, made the following <lb/>Report - To the Yearly
                    Meeting.</p>
                <floatingText type="report">
                    <body>
                        <p>The Committee on the concern <pb n="56" facs="SW_NYYM_reports_Page_019"/><lb/>relative to the Indians
                            situated on the borders of this State, Report, <lb/>That in the course
                            of their attention to the service much as not been done <lb/>in the
                            course of the present year, although it may be acknowledged, <lb/>the
                            field for exercising our benevolence, and promoting the good of that
                            <lb/>People seems to be more enlarged. - Three of our number have
                            <lb/>visited several of the Tribes, and from accounts communicated by
                            <lb/> them, as well as from other communications, we are fully impress'd
                            <lb/>with abelief, that there is encouragement for friends to persevere
                            <lb/>in endeavouring to promote the Objects which first engaged the
                            <lb/>attention of the Yearly Meeting - Civilization &amp; Agricultural
                            <lb/>improvements appear gradually progressing, and there are those
                            <lb/>amongst them who appear to have their minds impressed with <lb/> a
                            degree of religious thoughtfulness; and the Committee conceive <lb/>it
                            right for them to mention, that this appear to be the case in <lb/>
                            aparticular manner amongst anumber of the Indian Women <lb/>at
                                <placeName key="stock">Stockbridge</placeName>, who in the course of
                            several visit paid them by <lb/>different friends, seem'd to claim their
                            sympathy &amp; affectionate <lb/>regard, and as they are equally
                            entitled to our assistance as the <lb/>Men, and it may be the means of
                            increasing usefulness to <lb/>both, the Committee suggest to the
                            Meeting, the propriety of <lb/>spreading this concern before the Womens
                            Yearly Meeting - </p>
                        <closer><dateline><placeName key="nycit">New York</placeName>
                                <date when="1804-05-29">5th month 29th 1804</date></dateline>
                            <lb/>Sign'd by direction &amp; on behalf of Committee <lb/><persName
                                key="tfran1">Tho. Franklin</persName> Clerk.</closer>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>The foregoing communication rec.d from the Committee <lb/>on this interesting
                    concern, appeared to afford the Meeting, <lb/>not only asatisfaction, but a
                    comfortable prospect, that as <lb/>friends continue to bear in mind the
                    situation of that <lb/>injured People, and of the motives which led to the
                    concern, <lb/>we shall be enabled to persevere therein, &amp; stimulate <lb/>the
                    Committee to move forward as way may open in promoting their welfare.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="71" facs="SW_NYYM_reports_Page_020"/>
                <dateline><date when="1805-05-28"/><placeName key="nycit">New
                    York</placeName></dateline>
                <p>The Committee on the concern of this Meeting relative to the Indian <lb/>Natives,
                    more particularly those situated on the Frontiers of this State <lb/>now made
                    the following Report vizs.</p>
                <floatingText type="report">
                    <body>
                        <p>To the Yearly Meeting - </p>
                        <p>The Committee appointed on the <lb/>concern of the Yearly Meeting
                            relative to the Indians, have had divers <lb/>opportunities of
                            conference thereon during the course of last year, and <lb/>given such
                            attention to the subject as way open'd - Three of the Committee
                            <lb/>appointed to visit that People report - They spent about aWeek
                            among <lb/>the <orgName key="brotherton">Brothertown</orgName>, <orgName
                                key="stockbridge">Stockbridge</orgName>, and <orgName key="oneida"
                                >Oneida</orgName> Tribes, and inform, That <lb/>altho in some
                            respects things among them look discouraging, their <lb/>easy access to
                            spirituous Liquors, from the Whites settled around them, <lb/>induces
                            too many to the excessive use thereof, which joined to their <lb/>common
                            habit of Indolence, greatly obstructs the cultivation of their
                            <lb/>Land, and improvement in other respects; yet they found in each
                            <lb/>Nation those that were sober and industrious, and making agreeable
                            <lb/>improvements - That notwithstanding the many difficulties and
                            <lb/>discouragements, they labour under, the Committee thought they were
                            <lb/>making advancement in Agriculture; and that there were among
                            <lb/>them, who are not only sober and industrious, but religiously
                            disposed, <lb/>particularly among the Females, and visits from friends
                            appeared to <lb/> be very acceptable, and particularly so to this Class,
                            and that on the <lb/>whole they believe, a continuation of care suitably
                            extended towards <lb/>that People, may probably be attended with
                            salutary effects.</p>
                        <p>A communication in Writing from the <orgName key="brotherton">Brothertown
                                <lb/>Tribe</orgName>, sign'd by a number of both Sexes, and
                            addressed to this Committee <lb/>hath been received, and we apprehend it
                            proper to subjoin a copy of <lb/>it to this Report, That the Yearly
                            Meeting may have it read should <lb/>friends incline to it.</p>
                        <p>Being impressed with a desire to aid <lb/>and encourage our brethern the
                            Indians to pursue those Things <lb/>which will be promotive of their
                            present &amp; future welfare - the <lb/>committee thought it right to
                            communicate with several of the <lb/>Tribes through the medium of
                            Epistles, which being prepared, <lb/>were accordingly transmitted to the
                                <orgName key="brotherton">Brothertown</orgName>, <orgName
                                key="stockbridge">Stockbridge</orgName>, &amp; <lb/><orgName
                                key="oneida">Oneida</orgName> Nations - And altho we still feel the
                            concer to be interesting, <lb/>yet it must be acknowledged, the work of
                            Civilization is a gradual <lb/>one, and that a considerable time
                            necessarily must elapse in much <pb n="72" facs="SW_NYYM_reports_Page_021"/><lb/>fruit may be the result
                            of the labour bestowed, yet while there is <lb/>an evidence of the
                            rectitude of the concern, there is reason to hope, <lb/> Friends may be
                            enabled to facilitate the gradual improvement of the <lb/>Natives to
                            amore civilized State - and that in the issue they will <lb/>have no
                            cause to regret the part they have taken, in order to promote <lb/>their
                            present and future wellbeing</p>
                        <closer>Sign'd by direction &amp; on behalf <lb/>of the Committee -
                                <persName key="tfran1">Tho. Franklin</persName> Clk
                                    <lb/><dateline><placeName key="nycit">New York</placeName>
                                <date when="1805-05-26">5th month 26
                            1805</date></dateline>.</closer>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>The attention of the Meeting being feelingly &amp; renewedly impressed with
                    <lb/>asolicitude for the welfare of our Indian Brethren, attended with the <lb/>
                    expression of satisfaction &amp; concurrence with the foregoing Report, a <lb/>
                    desire and concern was evidenced to prevail, that friends on that <lb/>Committee
                    may be encouraged to persevere in the Work assigned them, <lb/>that so they may
                    be enabled from time to time, to extend such care <lb/>towards that part of the
                    human race, as way may open for it - &amp; <lb/>as it is desireable that the
                    Committee should be furnish'd with the <lb/>means of aiding those People in
                    apecuniary way, as circumstances <lb/>may render it proper &amp; expedient, in
                    order more fully to carry into <lb/>effect the benevolent views of this Meeting,
                    it open'd to aprospect of <lb/>propriety in authorizing the Committee to
                    circulate subscriptions <lb/>among friends in this Yearly Meeting as extensively
                    as they may <lb/>think proper for raising a Fund for that purpose. - It being
                    <lb/>suggested that an addition of a few names to the Committee would
                    <lb/>probably be useful, with which the Meeting concurs, and appoints
                        <lb/><persName key="mfran1">Matthew Franklin</persName>, <persName
                        key="smott1">Samuel Mott</persName>, of <placeName key="mamar"
                        >Mamaronik</placeName>, <persName key="aunde1">Abram. J.
                        Underhill</persName>
                    <lb/>and <persName key="spars1">Samuel Parsons</persName>.</p>
                <closer>Adjourn'd to the 4th hour tomorrow afternoon</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="90" facs="SW_NYYM_reports_Page_022"/>
                <dateline><date when="1806"/><placeName key="nycit">New York</placeName></dateline>
                <p>The Committee on the concern of this Meeting relative to divers <lb/> Tribes of
                    Indians, furnish us with areport on that subject, which <lb/> was read, and is
                    as follows - viz.</p>
                <floatingText type="report">
                    <body>
                        <p>To the Yearly Meeting -</p>
                        <p>The Committee on the concern of this Meeting relative to the <lb/>Indian
                            Natives Report -</p>
                        <p>That during the last year we have <lb/>had several conferences together,
                            and have felt our minds <lb/>engaged in sympathy with, and earnest
                            desires for the promotion<lb/> of the civil &amp; religious welfare of
                            that People, so as to engage the <lb/>attention of several of our
                            number, who have visited them, and <lb/>from the report received from
                            them, there appears an openness to <lb/>receive the advice and council
                            of friends - And altho the use <lb/>of spirituous Liquors continues to
                            retard their improvement, <lb/>yet we have reason to believe that
                            anumber of them are guarded <lb/>in that respect, and we think they
                            progress in the Arts of <lb/>civilized life - They give us apleasing
                            account of one School <lb/> being taught by an Indian at <placeName
                                key="stock">Stockbridge</placeName>, and another School <lb/>House
                            erecting at the same place - The School at <placeName key="broth"
                                >Brotherton</placeName>
                            <lb/>is kept up, and another School House in erecting - we are
                            encourag'd <lb/>to believe, the care and attention of friends have been
                            useful to <lb/>them - Subscrptions for raising money, agreeable to the
                            direction<lb/>of the Yearly Meeting, has been forwarded to friends in
                            the several <pb n="91" facs="SW_NYYM_reports_Page_023"/><lb/>parts of the Yearly Meeting, but we have as
                            yet received but little <lb/>thereon; and the Committee apprehend it may
                            be right for them <lb/>at this time to suggest to the Yearly Meeting,
                            that they continue <lb/>to feel solicitous that a Fund may be raised, so
                            as to encourage <lb/>some suitable friends to go &amp; reside among
                            them, as one principle <lb/>means of promoting their welfare - </p>
                        <closer><dateline><placeName key="nycit">New York</placeName>
                                <date when="1800-05-25">5th mo 25. 1800</date></dateline> by
                                <lb/><persName key="tfran1">Thomas Franklin</persName> Clk</closer>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>The communication now received from the Committee on this <lb/>concern, affords
                    asatisfaction to the Meeting; and altho the work <lb/>of civilization, and
                    promoting the welfare of that poor and injured <lb/>people is a gradual one, and
                    attended with many difficulties, <lb/>yet it is desireable that friends may not
                    be discouraged, in the <lb/>extension of such farther care towards them as way
                    may open for it; <lb/>and from what is felt and expressed in the Meeting, during
                    its <lb/>deliberation on this interesting subject, the Committee are
                    <lb/>requested to give renew'd attention thereto, and avail themselves <lb/>of
                    every prudent means, which may be within their reach, to <lb/>promote the
                    comfort, &amp; good of that People - And as it appears <lb/> by the report,
                    there has not been much raised during the last <lb/> Year, in order the better
                    to carry into effect the benevolent views <lb/>of this Meeting, it is proposed
                    that the subject be recommended <lb/>to the attention of our Quarterly Meetings,
                    as the most likely way <lb/>to encourage friends to aliberality equal in some
                    good degree to <lb/>raise a fund for the important purposes contemplated by the
                    <lb/>Committee, (one principal object being to encourage a friend, and <lb/>his
                    family to go, and reside among them) and the Meeting <lb/>appearing to be united
                    with the proposal, it is therefore recommended <lb/>to our Quarterly Meetings,
                    as asubject deserving of the attention of Friends, <lb/>and that Subscriptions
                    be open'd accordingly by our Monthly Meetings, <lb/>and that the Money which may
                    be raised be forwarded to <persName key="tfran1">Thomas <lb/>Franklin</persName>
                    in <placeName key="nycit">New York</placeName> Treasurer to the Committee -
                        <persName key="jdean1"> John <lb/>Dean</persName> &amp; <persName
                        key="jtalc1">Joseph Talcott</persName> being proposed as additional Members,
                    the <lb/>same is united with, &amp; they accordingly appointed thereto, - and
                        <lb/><persName key="wseam2">Willett Seaman</persName> at his request is
                    released from that appointment.</p>
                <closer>Adjourned to the 9th Hour tomorrow Morning.</closer>
            </div>
        </body>


    </text>
</TEI>
