<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei-print.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="global.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Bank of Faith and Works United: Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>Emma Remsberg</name>
                </respStmt>


            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 182 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>This work is the property of the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore
                        College. It may be copied freely by individuals for personal use, research,
                        and teaching (including distribution to classes) as long as this statement
                        of availability is included in the text. It may be linked to freely in
                        Internet editions of all kinds, including for—profit works.</p>
                    <p>Publishers, libraries, and other information providers interested in
                        providing this text in a commercial or non—profit product or from an
                        information server must contact Swarthmore College for licensing and cost
                        information.</p>
                    <p> Scholars interested in changing or adding to these texts by, for example,
                        creating a new edition of the text (electronically or in print) with
                        substantive editorial changes, may do so with the permission of Swarthmore
                        College. This is the case whether the new publication will be made available
                        at a cost or free of charge.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2015">2015</date>
                <idno type="local">SW_Ripley</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Native Americans and Quakers: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="book">

                    <monogr>
                        <author>Dorothy Ripley</author>
                        <title>The Bank of Faith and Works United</title>

                        <idno>Bx7795.R58A3</idno>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>J.H. Cunningham</publisher>
                            <date when="1819">1819</date>

                        </imprint>

                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>


        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Native Americans and Quakers: An Electronic Collection </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This electronic editon of The Bank of Faith and Works United is only the section,
                    pages 74-129, having to do with Ripley's travels among Native American groups in
                    upstate New York.</p>
                <p> The transcribers and editor attempted to render the author’s orthography and
                    grammar as they appear on the page of her book, even when the author’s own
                    spelling and usage are inconsistent. Additionally, many questions remain about
                    spelling the names of his Quaker acquaintances, individual Native Americans who
                    populate his journal, and Indian villages and towns. The transcribers and editor
                    attempted to remain faithful to the author’s Anglicized spellings in all cases.
                </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                    <list>




                        <item>Indian reservations</item>
                        <item>Indians of North America--Missions</item>
                        <item>New York (State)--Description and travel</item>
                        <item>Pennsylvania--Description and travel</item>



                        <item>Seneca Indians</item>
                        <item>Society of Friends--Missions</item>
                        <item>Voyages and Travels</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item>
                    <date when="2015"/>POD edit</item>

            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>

        <body>
            <div type="entry">

                <pb n="74" facs="Ripley074"/>
                <p>Three of my own sex gave me fifteen dollars, and I<lb/>set off for <placeName
                        key="utica">Utica</placeName>, ninety-six miles, which was a long
                    ride<lb/>for the first day. After I had gone into the Inn, a poor<lb/> woman and
                    three children, came to ask a drink of water.<lb/>They told her to go the bar
                    for it, but she returned back,<lb/>saying, <said>No one is there.</said> My
                    Merciful Jesus bid me<lb/>rise and carry this woman a glass of water, which I
                    did<lb/>immediately: and while I stood by her, a solemn awe<lb/>clothed my mind,
                    which when I sat down, affected my<lb/> heart so much, that it seemed like a
                    dagger run into me.<lb/>I enquired of my Master Jesus what ailed her, and
                    He<lb/>replied, that <said>She has no money, and thou must go and<lb/>see in the
                        yard for her.</said> I went directly, and saw her<lb/>wringing her hands in
                    the yard, crying out, <said>Whatever<lb/> shall I do? whatever shall I
                        do?</said><said who="dripl1">What is the matter<lb/> with thee?</said> said
                    I, to which she answered, <said>I am here a<lb/> stranger, and know not any
                        person, and I have not one<lb/><pb n="75" facs="Ripley075"/> shilling in the world, and have
                        one hundrend miles to go,<lb/>to my husband, who is at a new plantation. I
                        have come<lb/>one hundred miles, where we have moved from, and
                        yes-<lb/>terday I had my pocket book, with my money; but have<lb/>lost it,
                        and yet I know not how or where!</said> I went into<lb/>supper, being sent
                    for, with a pitiful tale, to the company<lb/> who eat with me, which consisted
                    of eight merchants, and<lb/>one female; but no impression could be made on
                    any<lb/>heart, by my arguments of wo, to alleviate the wretched<lb/>situation of
                    this poor woman, and her three children!<lb/> therefore, my Gracious God moved
                    my soul to go and give<lb/>her a part of my money, with this message, <said
                        who="dripl1">I can but<lb/>tell thee of one Friend, and that is God; take
                        this money,<lb/>and He who has provided this for thee to-day, will
                        pro-<lb/>vide for thee to-morrow: trust in Him.</said> I suppose
                    this<lb/>person was as much astonished as she could be; for she<lb/> had got
                    into the waggon to set off, the sun being gone<lb/>down. What a compassionate
                    Friend is our Heavenly<lb/>Father! and how mindful is He of all His creatures,
                    who<lb/>are scattered up and down over the earth! having always<lb/>servants at
                    hand, to do His Work for Him; unless He in-<lb/>tends to honour any of His
                    children, with His extraordina-<lb/>ry Love, as He did when He led through the
                    Red Sea six<lb/>hundred thousand men, besides women and children, for<lb/>whom
                    the waves divided at the Presence of Jehovah, who<lb/>appointed them at the
                    first their secret bars.</p>
                <p>The <date when="1805-07-26">26th</date> I got to <placeName key="verno"
                        >Vernon</placeName>, and was introduced to <persName key="cyoun1"
                        >Cal-<lb/>vin Young</persName>, who was Innkeeper there. The stranger
                    that<lb/>requested <persName key="cyoun1">Calvin Young</persName> to be a father
                    to me, came pas-<lb/>senger from <placeName key="utica">Utica</placeName>, and
                    was like a brother to me, reward-<lb/>ing the mercy I manifested the day before.
                    How many<lb/>times we lose the blessing of God, for want of searching<lb/>out
                    the miseries of mankind, and supplying them out of<lb/>our little stock, which
                    is the Lord’s, to do his Will!</p>
                <p>The <date when="1805-07-27">27th of 7th mo. 1805</date>, <persName key="cyoun1"
                        >Calvin Young</persName> said he would<lb/>go with me to <placeName
                        key="oneic">Oneida Castle</placeName>, to see the Indians of the
                    Six<lb/>Nations, and particularly <persName key="jsken1">Skanando</persName>,
                    the oldest Chief, who<lb/>was a great favourite of his, from his sobriety.
                    Before I <lb/><pb n="76" facs="Ripley076"/>went, I enquired of <persName key="cyoun1">Calvin
                        Young</persName>, what I was in debt to<lb/>him, having had lodgings and
                    three meals: but his answer<lb/>was, <said who="cyoun1">I am paid.</said>
                    <said who="drip1">Who has paid thee?</said> said I; my friend<lb/>replied, <said
                        who="cyoun1">All I have is lent, and so long as you can be of<lb/>service to
                        the Indians, you are welcome to stay at my<lb/>house as a daughter; and I
                        will be to you as a father.</said><lb/>This so astonished me, that I could
                    not say more than<lb/>this at the time, <said who="dripl1">I am glad thou dost
                        consider all though<lb/>hast as lent;</said> he then assured me, that I
                        <said who="cyoun1">Was welcome<lb/>to a horse, or a chaise, and that I
                        should have the compa-<lb/>ny of him, or his wife, or daughters, any time
                        when I<lb/>wanted to ride out;</said> so that I was humbled to the
                    dust,<lb/>and saw the fulfilment of the promise of the Lord imme-<lb/>diately;
                    for this man was no professor of religion, but<lb/>stumbling thereat; because
                    the ministers who were in<lb/>this part, he said, <said who="cyoun1">Were no
                        better than others, and if he<lb/>ever were converted it should be by a
                        woman’s preaching,</said><lb/>which gave me to believe the Lord had sent me
                    to his<lb/>house to seek after his precious soul, being a
                    merciful<lb/>kind-hearted man. We had a pleasant ride to the Chief’s<lb/>house,
                    which was a good framed building of wood, paint-<lb/>ed red, two stories high,
                    and two rooms on a floor.<persName key="jsken1">Ska-<lb/>nando</persName>, the
                    Chief, was pleased to see me and shewed me<lb/>his wife, introduced his
                    children, grand-children, and<lb/>great-grand-children with joy and happiness,
                    such I pre-<lb/>sume, as we do not expect, when we look at their
                    condi-<lb/>tion, as the heathen. <persName key="jsken1">Skanando</persName>
                    tried to number is pos-<lb/>terity by counting his fingers many times over, and
                    then<lb/>laughed heartily, and cried out, <said who="jsken1">I cannot
                        tell:</said> for I made<lb/>this enquiry, <said who="dripl1">How many
                        children, and grand-children<lb/>hast though?</said> My soul was so highly
                    gratified, that I gave<lb/><persName key="jsken1">Skanando</persName> a pair of
                    red stone silver buttons, which was<lb/>the only thing I had belonging to my
                    honored mother,<lb/>who was dead: for the Chief had a shirt on, with
                    his<lb/>sleeves hanging loose, and was without any coat at this<lb/>time. He was
                    ninety five, or six years old, and put his<lb/>hands together, desiring to live
                    to be one hundred; lifting<lb/>up his eyes to Heaven, with a blessed smile. My
                    friend <lb/><pb n="77" facs="Ripley077"/>/><persName key="cyoun1">C. Young</persName> told me that
                        <persName key="jsken1">Skanando</persName> was never once intoxi-<lb/>cated,
                    and was looked unto with great respect as king of<lb/>those Six Nations. The
                    wife of this Chief went into the<lb/>garden and plucked me seven ears of corn
                    just ripe,<lb/>saying, <said>Seven is a goodly number, must have
                    seven:</said><lb/>being pleased with some spoons and coffee, with a
                    tin<lb/>boiler, which I had given her. I told my friend <persName key="cyoun1"
                        >Calvin<lb/>Young</persName> to leave me till the evening, among them,
                    and<lb/>I would go from hut to hut: so he did, and I went to one<lb/>house which
                    was very neat, with a curtain bed, whose<lb/>husband was a Frenchman, and she
                    was handsome, and<lb/>had some beautiful children: but was very dirty
                    for<lb/>want of washing herself, which I made a move for her to<lb/>do. I was
                    happy to see my friend, when he came for me;<lb/>having not to eat any thing all
                    the day; and rejoiced much<lb/>in my heart, that my eyes have seen this people,
                    which had<lb/>many times been shown me in a vision by the Lord, who<lb/>has
                    brought me here to see a part of the workmanship of<lb/>His Hand; whom our Lord
                    Jesus Christ died for, when<lb/>He yielded up His Soul an Offering for sin: but
                    I was<lb/>much distressed with seeing number of drunken In-<lb/>dins, who came
                    this night and lay in the ditch: I thought<lb/>the devil sent them; for they
                    came and lay down close<lb/>by the Inn where I was. I counted six who were
                    yelling<lb/>like wild beasts; and had it not been for the goodness of<lb/>my
                    God, who sent a number of young neat squaws, well<lb/>dressed on horse back, I
                    think my mind would not have<lb/>been able to support under the wretchedness of
                    those<lb/>miserable Indians, who were leveled with the beasts by<lb/>their
                    shameful conduct.</p>
                <p>One woman, of the name of <persName key="tally1">Tally</persName>, was among
                    the<lb/>squaws, who came early this morning, and she told me,<lb/>that <said
                        who="tally1">She had been to see a <persName key="conud1">new prophet</persName>, which has risen<lb/>up from
                        among an Indian tribe two hundred miles off.<lb/><persName key="tally1"
                            >Tally</persName> said that this prophet told her, He was
                        formerly<lb/>very wicked and much given to strong drink; but being<lb/>sick
                        for three years, he became sober, and one day as he<lb/>sat by the bed side,
                        one knocked at the for, which the <lb/><pb n="78" facs="Ripley078"/>prophet opened, and saw a
                        person standing, who enquired<lb/>if he loved God? to which the prophet
                        answered, <said>Yes I<lb/>do,</said> then said the stranger, <said>You must
                            go with me,</said> to<lb/>which the prophet agreed and went out, and saw
                        other two,<lb/>like the person who rapped at the door, who joined<lb/>them,
                        which he believes to be three angels. The old In-<lb/>dian prophet said,
                        that after they led him some distance<lb/>from his habitation, they
                        commanded him to look down,<lb/>where was presented to his view Jesus
                        crucified, which he<lb/>gazed at some time.</said>
                    <persName key="tally1">Tally</persName> the stopped, and hung down<lb/>her head
                    with eyes full of teas, that she prevented with<lb/>her fingers, until the
                    fountains flowed, over, which affect-<lb/>ed me so much, that I gave her my
                    handkerchief to wipe<lb/>the tears away, saying, <said who="dripl1"><persName
                            key="tally1">Tally</persName>, keep it for my sake:</said>
                    be-<lb/>lieving she was sensible of the Love of a Dying Jesus.<lb/>We both sat
                    silent, weeping very much, and I felt my<lb/>soul drawn out in fervent
                    supplication that this young<lb/>Indian woman might feel the virtue of his
                    Death. What<lb/>undescribable peace did I feel, while hearing of the
                    con-<lb/>version of this pagan? how was my soul overcome with<lb/>love also to
                        <persName key="tally1">Tally</persName>, whom I requested to proceed
                    when<lb/>the torrent had got vent from her eyes? I never felt be-<lb/>fore as at
                    this time, when we wept in solemn silence, re-<lb/>specting the Crucifixion of
                    the Blessed Jesus. At last<lb/><persName key="tally1">Tally</persName> broke the
                    silence, lifting up her head, and open-<lb/>ing her eyes, <said who="tally1">The
                        angels, said <persName key="tally1">Tally</persName>, led the
                        prophet<lb/>further, and shewed him a large pit, which was called
                        hell,<lb/>where he saw the wicked fight, and quarrel, while
                        they<lb/>appeared drinking and in wickedness, as on earth. After<lb/>this he
                        was conducted to a place of happiness, called<lb/>Heaven, where he saw God
                        the Father, and Jesus Christ,<lb/>sitting at His Right Hand of Glory in
                        perfect bliss, among<lb/>the angels.</said>. <persName key="tally1"
                        >Tally</persName> intimated, that the prophet did not<lb/>continue long in
                    this blessed state, but was conveyed<lb/>back again by the angels, to his own
                    house, where they left<lb/>him, commanding him to <said>Refrain from sin, and go
                        and<lb/>preach to his brethren the Indians.</said> I asked <persName
                        key="tally1">Tally</persName> how<lb/>long she was at this prophet’s house?
                    and she answered, <lb/><pb n="79" facs="Ripley079"/><said who="tally1">Three days</said> and had
                    this advice from him, her husband<lb/>being present, <said who="tally1">We were
                        not to drink, lie, cheat, nor<lb/>steal, to correct our children, but not to
                        whip them too<lb/>much; and when any of our Nation was sick, we
                        must<lb/>visit, and be kind to them.</said> It was last summer that
                        <persName key="tally1">Tal-<lb/>ly</persName> was there with her husband.
                    She also added, <said who="tally1">When<lb/>the <persName key="conud1">old prophet</persName> goes out to preach,
                        he has thirty Indians<lb/>to protect him from the rage of such as may oppose
                        him.</said></p>
                <p>I have long believed in the ministration of angels, and<lb/>this is as great a
                    proof as any I have heard of in my travels<lb/>among the heathen: for those only
                    believe in God, as a<lb/>Great Spirit. <persName key="tally1">Tally</persName>,
                    the Indian squaw, is a respectable<lb/>woman, ad can speak English well; for she
                    was several<lb/>years with a Quaker’s family, who took great pains
                    with<lb/>her.</p>
                <p><date when="1805-07-28">28th 7th mo. 1805</date>. This morning at break of day,
                    I<lb/>found my soul drawn out to pray for the Pagan Indians,<lb/>who never
                    worship God but once a year, believing only in<lb/>the Great Spirit. <persName
                        key="cyoun1">Calvin Young</persName>, and his daughter <persName
                        key="pyoun1">Peggy</persName>,<lb/>with several more went with me; I suppose
                    there were<lb/>ten horses went through the woods, for the purpose of<lb/>going
                    to what is called the <placeName key="oneidss">South Settlement</placeName> ,
                    where the<lb/>Chief, <persName key="jblac2">Blacksmith</persName>, nigh an
                    hundred years old, and many<lb/>more gathered to meet me, for morning worship.
                    The<lb/>Pagan chief was glad to see me, because he thought it was<lb/>a true
                    mark of friendship coming there, as they did not<lb/>assemble to worship with
                    those in <placeName key="oneic">Oneida Castle</placeName>, where<lb/>there is a
                    good house built for the purpose of gathering to-<lb/>gether every Sabbath. I
                    never was more affected that I<lb/>know in my life: for this old chief, no
                    doubt, was a real<lb/>Pagan within, as well as outwardly so, and was
                    the<lb/>strangest figure I ever beheld. Black darkness, I thought,<lb/>covered
                    his mind; and he appeared as a beast of the earth:<lb/>yet he conducted himself
                    respectfully to me, smoking his<lb/>pipe all the time of our being together,
                    accompanied with<lb/>several younger Chiefs and night forty Indian men,
                    and<lb/>aged women. Before our worship commenced, he got hold<lb/>of my hand,
                    having it for some time as fast as possible <lb/><pb n="80" facs="Ripley080"/>while he stamped
                    earnestly with his feet at the white<lb/>preachers, whom he said, are <said
                        who="jblac2">Friendly to us, till they get<lb/>our trees, and lands, and
                        then they are no more our friends;<lb/>but the Quakers are good people, and
                        do not serve us so;<lb/>I love the Quakers,</said> nipping my hands almost
                    together,<lb/>until I was actually afraid of him, his visage was so
                    hor-<lb/>rible, while he stamped on the ground at the white preach-<lb/>ers,
                    whom he would not let come near him. I kneeled<lb/>down in the midst of them in
                    fervent supplication, while<lb/>they sat on seats all round in the place where
                    they offer<lb/>their yearly sacrifice. A large pole was standing up,<lb/>on
                    which they fix a white dog, night the top, and then<lb/>dance round it,
                    imploring the Good Spirit to give them a<lb/>plentiful crop of corn, from that
                    which is just before put<lb/>into the ground; rendering Him their thanks for His
                    bless-<lb/>ing upon the past crop the preceding summer. They have<lb/>another
                    white dog which they roast, and eat at the same<lb/>time, of their sacrifice,
                    that are instead of lambs. The<lb/>ardour of my soul was great for them, that
                    they might<lb/>worship the Eternal Spirit, through the medium of His<lb/>Only
                    Begotten Son. The text I spoke from was, <quote type="biblical">Alas,<lb/>my
                        brother!</quote> which was opened to me, by the Revealing<lb/>Light, so far,
                    as to enable me to testify to them, that I be-<lb/>lieved they were of
                    Jeroboam’s house, who were Israel’s<lb/>seed, that were carried away captives by
                    Shalmaneser,<lb/>king of Assyria, and so were come thither to keep
                    their<lb/>sacrifices, which were to typify Jesus the Son of God, who<lb/>was
                    offered up for them, and would call them back again<lb/>into their own land,
                    that should flow with milk and honey,<lb/>and they should all be taught of God,
                    who would be a<lb/>Righteous King unto them, and join them to Judah,
                    from<lb/>whom they were separated for rebellion. I also signified,<lb/>that
                    their forefathers were carried away by Shalmaneser<lb/>captives, because they
                    worshipped two <quote type="biblical">Golden calves,</quote><lb/>which my
                    Interpreter said was made of “Yellow money,”<lb/>that they might understand the
                    better: for he was a good<lb/>Indian, who was a religious man, and of the
                        <orgName key="tuscarora">Tuskerow<lb/>nation</orgName>, and spoke English
                    well, as also Indian: but there <lb/><pb n="81" facs="Ripley081"/>wanted animation in his
                    delivery, which was a great dis-<lb/>advantage; nevertheless they were very
                    attentive, and<lb/>fully satisfied by <persName key="dpete1">Doctor
                        Peter’s</persName> Energetic Speech, that<lb/>indicated, <said who="dpete1"
                        >They were thankful that the Good Spirit<lb/>had sent me over the Great
                        Water to visit them; and they<lb/>hoped the Great Spirit would take care of
                        me; and con-<lb/>duct me safe back again to my own native place,
                        request-<lb/>ing another visit from me next Sabbath morning if I
                        would<lb/>indulge them with my company.</said>
                    <persName key="dpete1">Doctor Peter</persName> was a<lb/>Chief, as well as their
                    Speaker, and delivered their speech<lb/>of gratitude with great punctuality,
                    which I lament on<lb/>account of not having it translated. <persName
                        key="jblac2">Blacksmith</persName>, the old<lb/>Pagan Chief, was highly
                    pleased with my prayer, and<lb/>sermon, and desired the favour of my <said
                        who="jblac2">Coming again,</said><lb/>when I bid him adieu. His ears were
                    slit, and hanging<lb/>down, and his forehead, nose, cheeks, and chin were
                    paint-<lb/>ed red: he had a hairy cap on, with a red tail half a yard<lb/>long,
                    with a yellow striped ruffled dress, that came down<lb/>to his feet, and the
                    sleeves thereof to his fingers, bowed<lb/>together with age, having on his brest
                    a large ornament<lb/>life a half moon of silver. In this part, they who
                    knew<lb/>him, said that he thought the white people devils, because<lb/>they
                    never were infested with rats, or crows, till they<lb/>settled round them. To my
                    eye, he appeared a complete<lb/>savage: and I venture to say, the remembrance of
                    him in<lb/>time will never wear off, I was filled with such dread awe<lb/>while
                    he described the white preachers to me, and I hope<lb/>his situation will arouse
                    me to pray for the completion of<lb/>those promises respecting Jesus Christ,
                        <quote type="biblical">He shall take<lb/>the heathen for His Heritage, and
                        the uttermost part of<lb/>the earth for His Possession.</quote>
                    <quote type="biblical">And all shall know the<lb/>Lord, from the least to the
                        greatest.</quote></p>
                <p>In the afternoons, I went two miles to the other settle-<lb/>ment of Indians, on
                    the <orgName key="oneida">Oneida</orgName>ground, where numbers<lb/>collected
                    together with the Indians, and my Interpreter<lb/>went for the purpose of
                    relieving my anxiety, which was<lb/>great, from a desire to benefit those whom
                    the Lord my<lb/>God had caused me to sow in tears for ever since I was a
                    <lb/><pb n="82" facs="Ripley082"/>child; leading me in spirit, to contemplate the awful
                    con-<lb/>dition both of the house of Judah and Israel, who are trod-<lb/>den
                    under foot until the fulness of the Gentiles. The<lb/>subject I was led to swell
                    on, was these words of Jesus,<lb/><quote type="biblical">And He shall set the
                        sheep on His right Hand, but the<lb/>goats on His left.</quote> I could not
                    forbear remarking, what<lb/>a solemn aspect the Indians wore, and especially
                    the<lb/>women, who sat pensively weeping, paying great attention<lb/>to the
                    sentences, as they flowed from my lips. I never<lb/>had an Interpreter before
                    this day, and was astonished<lb/>how the words stopped as soon as the sentence
                    was finish-<lb/>ed, which confirmed me that Jesus Christ lived in me,
                    and<lb/>spake through my mouth. I have marveled at the assist-<lb/>ance of my
                    Gracious Master, this day more than any<lb/>other: because He stopped the
                    stream, and caused it to<lb/>flow just as was necessary for them to receive,
                    through<lb/>the interpretation of the <orgName key="tuscarora"
                        >Tuskarow</orgName> Indian. After I had<lb/>given a suitable portion to my
                    Indian brethren and sisters,<lb/>I then addressed the white people present, and
                    had great<lb/>liberty to pray with each; believing the Lord would an-<lb/>swer
                    my ardent supplication in behalf of such as desired<lb/>to be instructed.</p>
                <p>In the evening I held the third meeting at <placeName key="verno"
                        >Vernon</placeName>, in<lb/>a new large barn, belonging to my kind friend
                        <persName key="cyoun1">Calvin<lb/>Young</persName>, which contorted his
                    spirit among the rest who<lb/>were deeply affected under the Power of that God,
                    who<lb/>sends by whom He will and uses the most feeble instru-<lb/>ments to
                    glorify His Name, which is had in remembrance<lb/>by all who revere His Majestic
                    Person, for His Mercy,<lb/>Love and Justice. This was large gathering, and
                    my<lb/>heart was filled with thankfulness that the Lord had fur-<lb/>nished me
                    with strength to go from one part to another<lb/>this day, and at the close to
                    enable me, in His Fear, to<lb/>testify, <quote type="biblical">Her ways are ways
                        of pleasantness, and all Her<lb/>paths peace,</quote> thus Wisdom was
                    honoured with the Lord<lb/>my God, who has prepared my way, and given me an
                    in-<lb/>crease of Faith in Him for this people, whom my lot is<lb/>cast among. </p>
                <pb n="83" facs="Ripley083"/>
                <p>My friends followed me this day from the <placeName key="oneidss">South
                        Settle-<lb/>ment</placeName> of Pagans, to the <orgName key="oneida"
                        >Oneida</orgName> Indians, and from thence<lb/>back again to the Barn, which
                    is the first I ever preached<lb/>in; an din this small village we had at least
                    three hundred<lb/>people assembled, of whom were many deeply humbled at<lb/>the
                    goodness of my Master, that was mouth and Wisdom<lb/>to me at each different
                    place. I feel myself much obliged<lb/>to all who have accompanied me, being a
                    lonely stranger,<lb/>but more especially to those who prepared my way,
                    and<lb/>found me a horse to ride through the woods. May the<lb/>God of Jacob
                    return it back again upon their posterity;<lb/>and keep in remembrance my desire
                    to please Him, and<lb/>profit every individual who has sat under the sound
                    of<lb/>His Gospel, which was sanctioned by His Adorable Pre-<lb/>sense. </p>
                <closer><dateline>[<placeName key="verno">Vernon</placeName>, <placeName
                            key="oneida">Oneida County</placeName>, <date when="1805-07-20">20th 7th
                            mo. 1805.</date>]</dateline></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <p>I went out to the other end of the village to have a<lb/>meeting in a
                    school-house, where many assembled to wor-<lb/>ship God, and hear a stranger.
                    May the blessing of the<lb/>Highest attend my feeble efforts, for without this,
                    in vain<lb/>will my labour prove: yet, I am of opinion, that my work<lb/>will
                    have its reward in that day, when every secret thing<lb/>shall be made public to
                    all Nations, and this my love, for<lb/>the salvation of precious souls. I can
                    appeal to Thee, my<lb/>God, who art the Searcher of all hearts, that the
                    Kingdom<lb/>of Jesus Christ is my glory, yea, my chiefest joy,that ab-<lb/>sorbs
                    all my powers of soul and body. When I came<lb/>from <placeName key="nycit">New
                        York</placeName>, it was to suffer Thy Will; trusting for<lb/>mercy from Thy
                    Endless Liberality, that has thus far pre-<lb/>pared the hears of the people to
                    receive my labour, and<lb/>entertain me as a messenger sent out from God, the
                    Father<lb/>of our Lord Jesus, and the whole family of Heaven and<lb/>earth.</p>
                <p>Any one who depends upon God, doing His Special<lb/>Work, will acknowledge that
                    He is with me to provide my<lb/>daily bread, as occasion requires, which is
                    according to<lb/>His ancient promise, “They that Fear the Lord shall<lb/>lack no
                    good thing.” The Love of God to His children is<lb/>great; how am I made
                    sensible of His Fatherly Care at <lb/><pb n="84" facs="Ripley084"/>this time! when I am as in a
                    wilderness, far from my na-<lb/>tive land, and all who were once dear to me by
                    the ties of<lb/>friendship, and my honoured father’s house. The Lord<lb/>assured
                    me He would come along with me, to prepare my<lb/>way, and prosper my goings:
                    and I can say, thus far His<lb/>Promises are fulfilled to the joy of my
                    heart.</p>
                <p>Yesterday I went to the <placeName key="oneic">Indian Castle</placeName> alone,
                    and walked<lb/>from one cottage to another, till I had a number of women<lb/>to
                    join in supplication with me, and feeling great sorrow<lb/>of heart on their
                    account, I besought the Benign Parent<lb/>of us each, to open their blind eyes,
                    that they might see<lb/>Jesus, the Saviour of His people; and believe in
                    Him,<lb/>who is the Light of the world. I felt great refreshment<lb/>in my
                    spirit thereby, and a hope that He who is merciful<lb/>will meet those after
                    their own way, and according to<lb/>His unbounded Love and Goodness, which is
                    manifested<lb/>in and through His Son Jesus. They were very solemn,<lb/>and sat
                    as still as possible during the time of prayer,<lb/>while the tears trickled
                    down their cheeks. When I arose<lb/>they each lifted up their eyes to Heaven,
                    and then looking<lb/>earnestly at me, lay their hands on their breasts or
                    hearts,<lb/>still melted in tenderness in my presence, and gave me
                    to<lb/>understand that they knew something of the God whom I<lb/>approached, and
                    felt what was said, though it was not in<lb/>their language, and they knew not
                    mine. We parted in<lb/>much affection, and I returned home to my friend
                        <persName key="cyoun1">Young’s</persName>,<lb/>and was thankful that I could
                    go and refresh my body<lb/>with the comforts of life, having fasted from morning
                    to night.</p>
                <p>I am no ways calculated to live as the Indian squaws;<lb/>yet believe the Lord
                    can enable me to endure great hard-<lb/>ship if He sees meet to call me to work
                    in that part of<lb/>His vineyard, or soften my sorrows, and assuage my
                    grief,<lb/>by supplying me bountifully, as at this time by His
                    extra-<lb/>ordinary kindness, sending me help from a quarter that I<lb/>might
                    the least expect. I conclude the day with holy<lb/>aspirations to the Giver of
                    all my Mercies, for His Spirit<lb/>to whisper peace, and free salvation unto all
                    this people,<lb/>who appear in a forlorn condition. </p>
                <pb n="85" facs="Ripley085"/>
                <p>The number of Indians here a bouts are seven or eight<lb/>hundred; but those
                    tribes have been greatly diminished,<lb/>through the wicked white people
                    introducing strong drink<lb/>among them, to defraud and take every advantage of
                    their<lb/>weakness and gross ignorance. Was not the Merciful<lb/>God to provide
                    a little food for them, as He does for the<lb/>birds of the air, they must
                    utterly perish from off the face<lb/>of the earth, being almost strangers to
                    economy and in-<lb/>dustry; which two things, enrich the most miserable
                    na-<lb/>tions, when the <quote type="biblical">Blessing of Heaven is upon their
                        basket<lb/>and store.</quote></p>
                <closer><dateline>[<date when="1805-08-01">1st 8th mo.
                    1805.</date>]</dateline></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <p>Every day brings me nearer my mansion of bliss, that<lb/> is prepared for me to
                    dwell in at God's Right Hand. In<lb/> all my conflicts betwixt flesh and spirit,
                    the world<lb/> and satan, my prospect is sure: for a determination is in my
                    <lb/> soul, through Christ's strengthening me, to abide faithful.<lb/>Fiery
                    baptisms are my lot here; but they all tend to make<lb/> me more complete in
                    holiness; more like the Image of my <lb/>Lord and Master. Earthly joys cannot
                    delight me; no,<lb/>it is the salvation of the lost sons and daughters of
                    Adam,<lb/>that I am comforted with: therefore, O my god! give me<lb/> seals to
                    my ministry, that I may rejoice therein, and be a<lb/>useful instrument in my
                    day and generation. Thou art<lb/>growing up in me, and I shall be perfect by Thy
                    Spirit's<lb/> Covering, by Thy Robe of Righteousness put around me.<lb/>How
                    beautiful will the King's Duaghter be then! How<lb/> comely to the eye! How
                    precious in His Sight! no cross,<lb/>no suffering shall I decline; moving by His
                    direction, and<lb/>submitting to His justice, when His holy fire burns up
                    the<lb/>dross of sin, that remains from the contaminating influ-<lb/>ence of
                    satan, whose dark influence is poured forth all<lb/>around this world, while he
                    walks up and down, to and<lb/>fro, seeking whom he may overturn or devour. </p>
                <p><persName key="cyoun!">Calvin Young</persName> lent me his chaise this morning,
                    to go<lb/>to see the Christian Chief <persName key="jsken1">Skanando</persName>,
                    who was very glad<lb/>to see me again, and told me he was formerly a
                    warrior,<lb/>and shewed me how his ears were cut in the midst, and<lb/>his neck
                    with powder marked to distinguish him thereby, <lb/><pb n="86" facs="Ripley086"/>which he said
                    made him shriek aloud. Such things as I<lb/>could spare, I took and divided
                    among them, trusting in<lb/>the Lord for a future supply, knowing all fulness is
                    in<lb/>Him. The women were well pleased to accept of my<lb/>linen shifts, which
                    I spun in England, and told me they<lb/>would make gowns of them, as they do
                    without under gar-<lb/>ments, and almost every necessary of apparel, we
                    conceive<lb/>that we want. Some Christian professing sisters, who<lb/>abound in
                    garments and gold and silver, charged me thus,<lb/>as I was coming along,
                        <said>You must take care of your trunks<lb/>and clothes; for the Indians are
                        great thieves, they will<lb/>steal what you have.</said> I answered, <said
                        who="dripl1">I mean to save them<lb/>the trouble of stealing my clothes, for
                        I shall give them,</said><lb/>and so have taken the first opportunity to
                    disperse abroad<lb/>whatever I have, believing it my duty to try to gain
                    their<lb/>affection by shewing disinterestedness unto them, while I<lb/>am here.
                    The women opened their boxes and shewed<lb/>me all they had, which surprised
                    some of the white people<lb/>so much, that they said, <said>We have seen more of
                        the In-<lb/>dians since you came than we have for years, while we<lb/>have
                        lived in their neighbourhood: for they do not put con-<lb/>fidence in us, as
                        they do in you.</said> I anwered, I do not<lb/>wonder they can trust me, as
                    I have prayed for them<lb/>many years; and have shed thousands of tears for
                    their<lb/>miserable situation. Marks of their gratitude, in being<lb/>thankful
                    for the smallest favours, cheered my heart, and<lb/>revived my spirits for a few
                    moments; but on comparing<lb/>my line of inheritance with theirs, I was ready to
                    sink<lb/>into despair, and was overwhelmed in the midst of them:<lb/>however, I
                    again bowed in the Presence of Him, who is<lb/>our Wise Creator, and besought
                    His Divine Favour, and<lb/>the Light of His Reconciling Countenance to shine
                    upon<lb/>their dark minds. My heart was truly affected while<lb/>praying with
                    them, lamenting the disadvantage they la-<lb/>boured under for want of
                    cultivation, both in spiritual and<lb/>natural things: but I was sharply
                    reproved by the Lord<lb/>with this language, <quote type="biblical">The
                        foolishness of God is wiser than<lb/>the wisdom of men.</quote> I learnt by
                    His Spirit, that He had <lb/><pb n="87" facs="Ripley087"/>placed them so remote in the earth,
                    that they might evi-<lb/>dence <quote type="biblical">The foolishness of
                        God,</quote> that should display<lb/>itself in His time <quote
                        type="biblical">Wiser than the wisdom of men.</quote><lb/>Thus did I return
                    home weeping, with perfect acquiescence<lb/>to His hidden mystery, while I
                    remained silent, and full<lb/>of sorrow, having my mind awed through the rebuke
                    of<lb/>the King of Saints, and was afterwards abundantly filled<lb/>with praise
                    and love, to my Creator, for His Distinguish-<lb/>ing Mercies, that I have
                    partook of all my life long to the<lb/>present: and I desire every breath to
                    utter forth thanks,<lb/>which are due to His Great Name: and to tell of
                    His<lb/>Loving Kindness in chastening my foolish heart, that<lb/>would dispute,
                    and judge His Marvellous Providence, who<lb/>has required of my hands diligence,
                    obedience, and a<lb/>faithful reliance on His Promises; that I may perform
                    His<lb/>Sovereign Will, and answer His Divine Purpose, as a child<lb/>of His
                    Widom, who shall be justified at the last in the<lb/>sight of all Nations,
                    having suffered his Will, and done<lb/>all which the Lord my God appointed,
                    while among mu-<lb/>table creatures; born to give account at the last
                    for<lb/>every thought, word, and action in time. </p>
                <closer><dateline>[<date when="1805-08-03">3d 8th mo. 1805</date>,<lb/><placeName
                            key="verno">Vernon</placeName>, <placeName key="oneida"
                            >Oneida</placeName> County.]</dateline></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <p>This morning, my friend <persName key="eyoun2">Eve Young</persName>, went with me
                        to<lb/><persName key="jdean2">Judge Dean’s</persName>, to ask if he would
                    interpret for me, as he<lb/>knew the Indian language, being among them much
                    when<lb/>a child; he said, <said who="jdean2">Few know an Indian’s heart, but I
                        do;<lb/>and I think, they are not of the same species which we
                    are.</said><lb/>I smiled with contempt at his opinion, believing the
                    Lord<lb/>will visit them with gracious outpouring of His Spirit;<lb/>then shall
                    it be evidenced, their genius, or mental powers,<lb/>are bright as ours: and
                    that their hearts are as suscepti-<lb/>ble of divine impressions: for my part, I
                    believe many of<lb/>them are wrought upon by the Light, but heir dwelling
                    in<lb/>the woods obscurely, have made them appear in the eyes<lb/>of men, almost
                    like the brute creation. The white peo-<lb/>ple, who are of a bad principle,
                    receive their clothes, and<lb/>small necessaries for rum, or money to procure
                    it, which<lb/>I think should be severely punished. There is a fine for <lb/><pb
                        n="88" facs="Ripley088"/>taking advantage over them by selling rum to them, but<lb/>it is so
                    trifling, that it is not regarded by the wicked pro-<lb/>fessors of
                    Christianity. One poor Indian came into one of<lb/>those professing Christian’s
                    house, with a brass candlestick,<lb/>that was worth four shillings sterling, and
                    begged two shil-<lb/>ling loaves of bread for it, but the inhuman woman
                    only<lb/>gave him one loaf, which I was ashamed at, and am sorry<lb/>that she is
                    the mother of children; knowing this is not<lb/>the way to secure bread here for
                    them, neither lay up<lb/>riches in Eternity, which will not wax old. I was
                    invit-<lb/>ed to stay there, and was told by this person, that the<lb/>man where
                    I stayed was a deist: but I answered, He<lb/>acts like a Christian to me, being
                    merciful. What a<lb/>strange view must the Indians have of the Christian
                    reli-<lb/>gion; no wonder they do refuse to practise it, and dare<lb/>not place
                    confidence in the fruitless professors: for it<lb/>must be acknowledged, that
                    they have made many of the<lb/>Indians two fold more the children of the devil,
                    by bring-<lb/>ing strong drink unto them, and setting an example
                    of<lb/>wickedness before their eyes, which a Holy God will<lb/>punish them
                    severely for, as they were taught to believe<lb/>Jesus Christ has Died to take
                    away sin: and can avail<lb/>themselves with the privilege of reading the
                    inspired writ-<lb/>ings of Moses and the Prophets, and the Miracles of
                    our<lb/>Lord and Saviour, who crowned His life with Mercy, Love,<lb/>and
                    Righteousness, and His followers must obey Him if<lb/>they worship His Sceptre
                    of holiness, that rules in the<lb/>heart of every believer who submits to the
                    Government<lb/>of King Immanuel, the Prince of Peace.</p>
                <p>I was not sorry that <persName key="jdean2">Judge Dean</persName> gave me a
                    refusal:<lb/>for as soon as I saw him, it passed through my mind, that<lb/>he
                    was not a suitable person to administer spiritual com-<lb/>fort; he might do to
                    make treaties, and receive of their<lb/>lands a reward, if they were disposed to
                    trust him so far.<lb/>Our riding eighteen miles, will not lose its reward of
                    the<lb/>Lord my God, who has heard the sentiments of this wise<lb/>man,
                    respecting his poor Indian brethren: and I have no<lb/>doubt, when all Nations
                    are at the Bar of the Eternal <lb/><pb n="89" facs="Ripley089"/>Judge, that he will see those
                    stand with him there, although<lb/>he thinks they are not of the same species
                    with us. God<lb/>grant that none of them may rise up to condemn him in<lb/>the
                    awful day of Judgment, when all shall receive ac-<lb/>cording to the mercy they
                    manifest in this world.</p>
                <closer><dateline>[<date when="1805-08-04">4th 8th<lb/>mo. 1805</date>, <placeName
                            key="verno">Vernon</placeName>, <placeName key="oneida">Oneida County,
                            New York State.</placeName>] </dateline></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <p>As I continued in this part, I went among the Pagans<lb/>again, and sat in
                    silence with them sometime at the pale<lb/>where I held the last meeting. All
                    the week I had tra-<lb/>vailled in my spirit for <persName key="jblac2"
                        >Blacksmith</persName>, the Chief, who was<lb/>nigh an hundred years old,
                    and in a state of gross dark-<lb/>ness, which has bowed down my mind in awful
                    silence<lb/>before God, during the last night, that I might be a <quote
                        type="biblical">Sa-<lb/>vour of life unto him, and a sweet smelling Savour
                        to the<lb/>Lord my God,</quote> who has crowned my life with His
                    Loving<lb/>Kindness, and Rich Mercy, from the consequence of being<lb/>offered
                    unto Him before I was born, by a man of faith, to<lb/>succeed him in his Gospel
                    Labour; for, before he expired,<lb/>he cried out, <said>When you are doing well,
                        if it be possible,<lb/>I will look down from Heaven, and smile on
                        you,</said> which<lb/>has come into my mind at this present moment,
                    expecting<lb/>this little service of mine will give additional pleasure
                    to<lb/>him, from whose loins I proceeded, to glorify his God<lb/>and mine, in
                    the regions of blessedness, when time is swal-<lb/>lowed up in Eternity.</p>
                <p>The Old Chief received me with cordiality; but my<lb/>Interpreter was gone a long
                    journey, and I had to apply<lb/>to the Spirit to make them understand, as He did
                    by the<lb/>same Spirit in the day of Pentecost, when they all had
                    the<lb/>revelation of Jesus Christ made manifest in their hearts<lb/>through the
                    outpouring of the Spirit, while they were as-<lb/>sembled together. As I was
                    praying, my desire was<lb/>very great for the Salvation of their precious souls;
                    and I<lb/>saw the heart of <persName key="jblac2">Blacksmith</persName>
                    exceeding hard and dark,<lb/>like a beast’s heart, such as King Nebuchadnezzar’s
                    when<lb/>in his state of degradation in the field grazing: but con-<lb/>tinuing
                    in supplication with great ardency of sprite, the<lb/>Lord shewed me, through
                    His Revealing Power, that He <lb/><pb n="90" facs="Ripley090"/>would give him a new heart, or
                    change his nature to grace,<lb/>and clothe him with His own Spirit, which I have
                    no<lb/>doubt concerning, as the Lord is more ready to shew<lb/>mercy than we are
                    to accept it. I have faith to believe<lb/>God will convert this man, and my
                    desire is, that I may<lb/>never forget his situation, till he is a changed,
                    renewed<lb/>creature, to glorify King Jesus, who shall reign over
                    the<lb/>Heritage of the heathen, and Rule them with His Righte-<lb/>ous Sceptre
                    to endless Ages. I took my leave of this part<lb/>of the Indians, called the
                        <orgName key="pagan">Pagan party</orgName>: and had the plea-<lb/>sure of
                    seeing them well satisfied with my labour of love,<lb/>which I am thankful for;
                    knowing my God will give<lb/>His Blessing thereunto, as well as cause them to
                    hear<lb/>with the utmost attention, all paying respect unto my<lb/>ministration,
                    by their act of friendship, in smoking their<lb/>pipes till I had finished,
                    which as it is their distinguish-<lb/>able mark of approbation to testify their
                    love, I can, in as<lb/>much charity receive it, as any other custom or
                    form<lb/>among the professing Christians; whereby they manifest<lb/>their
                    sincerity or gratitude: for I am fully convinced<lb/>that our God looks beyond
                    all forms, customs, and appear-<lb/>ances outwardly; and regardeth the motives
                    which in-<lb/>fluence man, whether they are good or bad; therefore
                    the<lb/>heathens, He will judge as such, and the Christians after<lb/>their
                    profession; yet, know, O man! no act of mercy,<lb/>love, or obedience to His
                    Spirit, which is in every one ac-<lb/>cording to their mental ability, shall go
                    unnoticed by the<lb/>Father of all Nations, whose prerogative alone it is
                    to<lb/>weigh all thoughts, words, or actions; seeing all hearts,<lb/>and knowing
                    all things from Eternity to Eternity.</p>
                <p>After I went to my lodgings, I set off three miles, to<lb/>attend an appointment,
                    which I had engaged for five this<lb/>evening; and I am thankful I can say, my
                    Great Master<lb/>that He was made a Mock King for our sakes, although<lb/>Heaven
                    was His Throne, and Earth His Footstool. His<lb/>submitting to have His Back
                    scourged by Pilate, who made<lb/>long furrows thereon, affected me so much, that
                    I could <lb/><pb n="91" facs="Ripley091"/>have spent my last breath testifying of His Dying
                    Love<lb/>to all people, created by His Inimitable Widom, who<lb/>formed all
                    flesh for His own pleasure, and man for His<lb/>special Glory, so that it is no
                    wonder that He should lay<lb/>down His own Life to influence them to serve,
                    love, and<lb/>adore Him, as their Lord and God forever, having not on-<lb/>ly
                    Power to take up His own Life again on the third day,<lb/>according to the
                    prophecy, or sign of Jonah the prophet,<lb/>but also is the Resurrection, or
                    Life, of all who are in the<lb/>tomb, waiting for His Voice to call them forth,
                    when the<lb/>Mystery of Righteousness is fulfilled, and the Kingdom<lb/>of our
                    Lord Jesus Christ completed, so that there requireth<lb/>no longer an High
                    Priest to atone for sin: but He shall<lb/>be adored as God over all, by the seed
                    whom He has re-<lb/>deemed through the Spilling of His Most Precious
                    Blood,<lb/>an eternal sign to them of His Merit and Soverign Love,<lb/>which
                    undertook the cause of all, to reinstate them<lb/>in paradisiacal happiness,
                    which was lost when satan beguil-<lb/>ed our first parents, when the milk of
                    human kindness<lb/>flowed from each heart, to one another; and innocence<lb/>was
                    sealed on their forehead, as a mark of divine favour,<lb/>which they lost the
                    moment they both transgressed, and<lb/>found they were naked, having bereaved
                    themselves of<lb/>inherent Righteousness, that might be compared to
                    Life<lb/>Eternal, which is found only in Jesus Christ, the Second<lb/>Adam,
                    whose Life is diffused into every true believer on<lb/>His Name, who calls
                    Himself the Resurrection and Life.</p>
                <closer><dateline>[<date when="1805-08-06">6th 8th mo. 1805.</date>
                        <placeName key="verno">Vernon</placeName>, <placeName key="oneida"
                            >Oneida.</placeName>]</dateline></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <p>Yesterday <persName key="pyoun1">Peggy Young</persName>, daughter of <persName
                        key="cyoun1">Calvin</persName> and <persName key="eyoun2"
                        >Eve<lb/>Young</persName>, rode with me nine miles further to the West,
                    to<lb/>have a meeting with a Presbyterian congregation. As<lb/>we were going the
                    horse stopped al on a sudden, and<lb/>would not go one step, but as I expected
                    we both should<lb/>be thrown out, as we ere on the midst of a hill,
                    which<lb/>scared my dear companion so much that I was obliged to<lb/>force her
                    to jump out of the chaise, to prevent her fainting<lb/>away, which she did, as
                    she reached her father’s residence,<lb/>running thither for some one to make the
                    horse move. <lb/><pb n="92" facs="Ripley092"/>When my dear young friend was going, I feel a
                    weeping,<lb/>thinking my case very hard: but as my tears were flow-<lb/>ing from
                    a heart, which desired to know the Will of God,<lb/>it immediately passed
                    through my mind that <quote type="biblical">Balaam’s<lb/>Ass,</quote> would not
                    go once because an angel stood before it<lb/>with a drawn sword; I therefore
                    besought the Lord to<lb/>reveal His Will to me, that I might know why the
                    horse<lb/>would stand still there; and the answer was, <said>I do not<lb/>want
                        thee to go further West than <placeName key="oneida">Oneida</placeName>,
                        where the<lb/>Indians are.</said> Astonished at this salute, I recollected,
                    that<lb/>the week before, I had a meeting appointed at the same<lb/>house for
                    worship, and such a heavy rain came, that no<lb/>person could go with me, and I
                    knew not the road, so put<lb/>it by saying, <said>I would go next week,</said>
                    but I suppose, did<lb/>not either add <said>If God permit,</said> or else forgot
                    to enquire<lb/>of the Lord whether I should accept this offer, yea, or<lb/>nay,
                    begin solicited to go fifty miles further, to appoint<lb/>meetings all round the
                    neighbourhood. With dread awe,<lb/>I ventured to request the Lord to permit me
                    to go and<lb/>fulfil my engagement, in pity to the people, acknowledg-<lb/>ing
                    my folly, in hastily complying to go any where un-<lb/>sent of Him; also
                    acquiescing with His Providential<lb/>Will, who had limited me to answer His own
                    purpose,<lb/>which I should find was right when I saw it fulfiled; and<lb/>in
                    order to shew my willingness to comply with His Di-<lb/>vine command, I agreed
                    to eat no bread there, if He re-<lb/>quires me to return back the nine miles in
                    the evening;<lb/>to which was answered, <said>Thou mayest go if thou wilt
                        ap-<lb/>point no more meetings there,</said> and immediately my<lb/>horse
                    started without my speaking; and I went back for<lb/>the dear young woman, who
                    had been in a fainting fit all<lb/>the time that the direction of God was given
                    me. She<lb/>was so alarmed, that I expected I should be obliged to
                    go<lb/>without her, but as I assured her no further harm would<lb/>befall us,
                    and I would not stay there all night, once more<lb/>she resumed her office, and
                    was a very pleasant companion<lb/>to me although not <said>Born again,</said>
                    the second time. Very<lb/>short notice collected the people, who were
                    disappointed <lb/><pb n="93" facs="Ripley093"/>the last week: but while I sat with them in
                    silence, they<lb/>kept whispering all the time, which made me bow
                    in<lb/>reverential awe before God, and afterwards in the name<lb/>of the Lord
                    commanded all thus, <quote type="biblical">Watch therefore, for<lb/>ye know
                        neither the day, nor the hour wherein the Son<lb/>of man cometh.</quote> The
                    foolish virgins were awfully set<lb/>before me, and it appeared that individuals
                    there would<lb/>be in the situation at the last; and I should
                    witness<lb/>against them, having exhorted them to a preparation by<lb/>inforcing
                    the necessity of furnishing their vessels with<lb/>spiritual oil; that is, get
                    grace in their hearts, that their<lb/>lamps of profession may burn bright;
                    testifying to them,<lb/>that some present, and a lamp of profession, but no
                    oil<lb/>in their vessels, and therefore their light did not
                    shine,<lb/>signifying now was their day of visitation; now the best<lb/>time to
                    apply for spiritual oil in their soul and body. As<lb/>the minister was present,
                    I observed to him, how impro-<lb/>per it was for the people to whisper while
                    were were silent-<lb/>ly waiting on the Lord: but he made a very
                    handsome<lb/>apology for them, by saying, <said>They are not accustom-<lb/>ed to
                        this manner of worship, and thought the meeting<lb/>did not begin, till the
                        minister begun.</said> I begged him to<lb/>reprove them, as I was not at
                    liberty to make any re-<lb/>mark on their conduct, having to exhort them to the
                    pur-<lb/>suit of righteousness, by an ample supply of grace, which<lb/>was free
                    for all, who sought the Lord while He may be<lb/>found.</p>
                <p>We got safe home, and I feel thankful that the God<lb/>of Jacob preserved our
                    lives; and I am fully satisfied with<lb/>my journey, and can assign a sufficient
                    reason at the close<lb/>of this day, why I was stopped on the road, which I
                    have<lb/>learnt from an Indian, who has come to inquire, <said>Why I<lb/>did not
                        go to <placeName key="stockbridge">Stockbridge</placeName>, four miles off,
                        yesterday?</said> as<lb/>the hunters, and the fishing Indians stayed at
                    home, hav-<lb/>ing being informed, that I intended going there; which was<lb/>a
                    mistake from some who took a wrong message. In all<lb/>my ways may I acknowledge
                    the Hand of Jehovah, which<lb/>guards my naked head.</p>
                <pb n="94" facs="Ripley094"/>
                <p>In peace I shall lay down this night, with a conscience<lb/>void of offence
                    towards God and man; desiring to walk<lb/>humbly all the days of my pilgrimage,
                    while a resident of<lb/>time.</p>
                <p>I went to-day to take my leave of the Indians settled<lb/>on the <placeName
                        key="oneida">Oneida</placeName> ground. which is a beautiful tract of
                    land,<lb/>and I could not but notice how love to them unites my<lb/>heart to the
                    Lord more abundantly; for, He delights in<lb/>His creatures shewing mercy one to
                    another. An Indian<lb/>woman lent me her horse to ride on, from one hut to
                    the<lb/>other, till I paid many visits: but, not being accustomed<lb/>to ride on
                    horseback without saddle or pillion, the horse<lb/>was going to throw me off,
                    which perceiving, I took the<lb/>advantage of the creature, and jumped several
                    yards, and<lb/>it was out of sight before I recovered from the surprise<lb/>and
                    stun that I received by falling heavy on the ground<lb/>after I alighted: but
                    even in this instance, I have to say,<lb/>the Delivering Hand of god was ready
                    to assist in this<lb/>solitary place, when only a little Indian boy was with
                    me;<lb/>for, on looking behind me I saw a chaise, with two men,<lb/>advancing
                    forward as fast as possible; having seen me fly,<lb/>and the horse take its
                    departure, who cried out to me,<lb/>while I sat on the ground, <said>Don’t go
                        after the horse; we<lb/>will go after it,</said> and the youngest lifted me
                    into the<lb/>chaise and then enquired where I was going, and set me<lb/>safe at
                    the cottage, with the politeness of Christians or mer-<lb/>ciful men, which I
                    praise God on the account; and that<lb/>my bones were not broken by His not
                    suffering me to dash<lb/>myself against a stone, believing death, and ten
                    thousand<lb/>dangers at all times, surrounded all mortals.</p>
                <p>I was greatly led into sympathy with my Indian sisters,<lb/>and their little
                    helpless infants, whom with pleasure I could<lb/>aid, was the Lord to give
                    ability to heart filled with<lb/>generous sentiments to all His offspring. The
                    women<lb/>brought me some Indian corn bread, with large beans stuck<lb/>all over
                    it, which I thought were raisins: but, found my<lb/>mistakes as soon as I took
                    one: and it being very sad, and<lb/>boiled, I chose to fast all day till night,
                    rather than eat it; <lb/><pb n="95" facs="Ripley095"/>which suited one of my poor sisters very
                    well: for, observ-<lb/>ing my uncommon delicacy, she looked at me, and
                    made<lb/>me understand that she was hungry, and could it fast<lb/>enough; so I
                    gave it to her, and she wrapped it up as the<lb/>richest dainty with
                    thankfulness, which was a lesson I<lb/>mean ever to to remember, while I sojourn
                    below.</p>
                <p>In returning home alone I saw a number of Indians<lb/>lying all their length on
                    the ground, with a small fire in<lb/>the midst, smoking their pipes; and as I
                    looked up to Hea-<lb/>ven, for a blessing to come upon them through an
                    outpour-<lb/>ing of His Spirit, they all cried, <said><foreign xml:lang="iro"
                            >Sago, sago,</foreign></said> which I<lb/>accepted as a salutation of
                    their love. I might, and should<lb/>have been alarmed at this sight of miserable
                    looking men,<lb/>had not my mind recollected, that I felt love, and good
                    will<lb/>to all; neither would I injure a worm, could I pass by it<lb/>I had no
                    other companion that day; for I thought I would<lb/>try and go alone, which I
                    did several other times, unno-<lb/>ticed here; and I feel thankful, that I can
                    say some of bad<lb/>disposition said, <said>No Indian hurt you, need not fear
                        them:</said><lb/>which, I answered, that I believe; for I love, and pray
                    for<lb/>them all.</p>
                <closer><dateline>[<date when="1805-08-07">7th 8th mo. 1805</date>, <placeName
                            key="verno">Vernon</placeName>, <placeName key="oneida">Oneida
                            County</placeName>.]</dateline></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <p>A solitary ride of twelve miles has been my lot to-day,<lb/>being scarcely able
                    to sit up all the time: and as I was go-<lb/>ing I heard a terrible howling,
                    which threw a damp on my<lb/>spirit; but pursuing further my journey a drunken
                    Indian<lb/>of the <orgName key="pagan">Pagan party</orgName>, advanced me,
                    crying out like one al-<lb/>most scared to death, stung with remorse and the
                    rebuke<lb/>of the Spirit. I stopped the chaise, and hearkened to what<lb/>he had
                    to say, which was, <said>Lord! Lord! you madam, you<lb/>madam,</said> and then
                    he remained silent; for he was quite asham-<lb/>ed of his conduct, having a few
                    days before made me believe<lb/>that he felt very good when I was preaching
                    among the<lb/>Pagans, telling me where, by laying his hands on his<lb/>breast;
                    bemoaning at the same time, that he had no one to<lb/>boil his pot; for his wife
                    was killed by one of the wicked<lb/>Indians, who pretended she was a witch; he
                    told me they<lb/>came and took him a great distance; and then went into <lb/><pb
                        n="96" facs="Ripley096"/>his log house and knocked her down with an axe: but be-<lb/>ing a
                    strong woman, she got up again, and endeavoured<lb/>to make her escape from
                    those instruments of cruelty, who<lb/>cut her throat from ear to ear, and then
                    buried her, and<lb/>laying earth several inches deep over her, made a fire
                    on<lb/>the earth to burn out the spirit of witchcraft that they said<lb/>was in
                    her. Two women were served thus by this wick-<lb/>ed Indian, who pretended to be
                    wiser than his brethren.<lb/>This circumstance happened two years ago. I passed
                    by<lb/>his house, that was desolate: for he was hated by the rest<lb/>of his
                    brethren, and obliged to leave the place. A third<lb/>woman was condemned to die
                    for witchcraft, but being<lb/>innocent, and willing to die, she desired that
                    they would<lb/>let her dress herself, that she might die decently: so
                    they<lb/>let her put on a white gown, which after she had done, she<lb/>then
                    said, <said>I am willing to die, but my blood will be upon<lb/>you; for I die
                        innocent.</said> This so affected some of the<lb/>feeling Indians, that they
                    let her depart in peace to her<lb/>own home. While I stood by the poor man, who
                    had lost<lb/>his wife thus barbarously, I though I would say some-<lb/>thing to
                    him for yelling in this manner, throwing his arms<lb/>about as he came along:
                    but my Merciful Jesus made me<lb/>stand as one dumb, for the space of five
                    minutes, and then<lb/>we parted, which seemed to confound the Indian
                    more<lb/>than ten thousand words would have done.</p>
                <p>There was a youth with me in the chaise, who was<lb/>much surprised that I was
                    not afraid; he said, <said>There is<lb/>not a woman in this neighbourhood, who
                        durst have gone<lb/>by that Indian,</said> but I fear the Lord, who has made
                    the<lb/>wildest beast of the field, and therefore, I trust He will<lb/>have
                    compassion on me and preserve me from every harm:<lb/>but His Will be done.</p>
                <p>I have held this day, a meeting in a large barn, where<lb/>many assembled
                    together. The attention of the people<lb/>was fixed upon me, which I labored to
                    draw to that Gra-<lb/>cious God, who restored David’s soul, and led him
                        in<lb/><quote type="biblical">The paths of righteousness for His Name’s
                        sake.</quote> I told<lb/>my hearers they must pass through a death unto sin,
                    if <lb/><pb n="97" facs="Ripley097"/>ever they walked in the paths of righteousness, or
                    wit-<lb/>nessed a table spread for them in the midst of their ene-<lb/>mies,
                    which by faith the Lord’s people partake of, eating<lb/>His Body, and drinking
                    His Blood mystically.</p>
                <p>I think, without God had aided me in my soul and<lb/>body, it would have been
                    impossible for me to support<lb/>under what I felt for the people this day, as
                    they were<lb/>many of them in total darkness. Few are the number
                    of<lb/>Christians in this part; but may they be increased by the<lb/>faithful
                    labourers, exercising their graces upon the Merits<lb/>and Mercy of a Redeemer:
                    for He it is who restoreth<lb/>from the fall, and maketh true Christians. I am
                    anxious<lb/>for the kingdoms of this world, to become the Kingdom<lb/>of our
                    Lord Jesus Christ. </p>
                <closer><dateline>[<placeName key="peter">Petersburg</placeName>, <date
                            when="1805-08-08">8th 8th mo. 1805.</date>]</dateline></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <p>From <placeName key="peter">Petersburg</placeName>, I returned back to <placeName
                        key="verno">Vernon</placeName> this morn-<lb/>ing, and am rejoiced that I
                    have got nearer Eternity, that<lb/>pleasant sound, the Saint’s delight. There I
                    shall not<lb/>pass through one spiritual baptism for sinners, neither<lb/>feel
                    the fatigue one moment that I go through now, be-<lb/>cause the children of men
                    are so unlike their Maker, and<lb/>are swallowed up with trifles of meanest
                    fort. In this<lb/>world the Kingdom of Grace is my glory: How much<lb/>more will
                    it be in Eternity? There I shall never weep<lb/>for the would of men; nor feel
                    pain, or weariness of flesh<lb/>or spirit, occasioned by moving to and fro, and
                    refusing to<lb/>be comforted, knowing Israel’s seed is sifted over the<lb/>earth
                    and fast bound in the captive chains of the devil;<lb/>but that happy day is
                    hastening, when satan shall be<lb/>bound, and his power lost for a thousand
                    years; then the<lb/>Lord my God will comfort His saints, and great shall
                    be<lb/>their peace, who have laboured to build up Jesus Christ’s<lb/>Kingdom, by
                    precept and example; doing and suffering<lb/>His Will from one year to another.
                    May the purity of<lb/>my soul, qualify me to enjoy complete happiness in
                    Christ,<lb/>in God, my only Friend, my sure support, when the mount<lb/>gains
                    melt as wax before the fire, and all the proud shall<lb/>stand aghast,
                    confounded by His Might. I tremble for<lb/>the unwise, when I contemplate their
                    awful situation, <lb/><pb n="98" facs="Ripley098"/>when the Mediatorial Office of the Great High
                    Priest will<lb/>be finished, Jesus no longer being appointed as
                    Interces-<lb/>sir to plead with God for rebellious man. No: His Office<lb/>must
                    be changed from an High Priest, to a Judge who<lb/>must pass sentence upon all
                    the proud monarchs, all the<lb/>unrighteous nobles, judges, and the wicked of
                    every de-<lb/>scription, who have despised His Clemency, and refused<lb/>the
                    visitation of His Dying Love and Sovereign Mercy,<lb/>which have at last ceased,
                    unto all the impenitent sons<lb/>and daughters, who choose death, darkness,
                    horror, des-<lb/>pair, banishment from God and the holy angels, to
                    become<lb/>servants of sin, and slaves to their own lusts forever,<lb/>being
                    companions to the dragon, whose <quote type="biblical">Tail drew a
                        third<lb/>part of the stars,</quote> or angels of God after it, when he was
                    cast<lb/>out of Heaven, in enmity to Jesus Christ, Heir of all<lb/>things, in
                    Heaven and earth.</p>
                <closer><dateline>[<date when="1805-08-09">9th 8th mo. 1805</date>, <placeName
                            key="verno">Vernon</placeName>,<lb/><placeName key="oneida">Oneida
                            County</placeName>.]</dateline></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <p>As I was desiring the Lord to enlarge my coast, a<lb/>person came for me with a
                    horse, to hold a meeting five<lb/>miles from this, so I immediately went, and
                    found already<lb/>a people gathered in a barn. After sitting a little
                    in<lb/>silence, I arose with the words of King David, <quote type="biblical">The
                        Lord<lb/>is my Shepherd, I shall not want.</quote> I felt renewed
                    life<lb/>and power to rise in me, which covered the place; and<lb/>others bore
                    testimony, that it was good for them to be<lb/>there. Having no where to lodge
                    this night, a woman of<lb/>the name of Webster asked me home with her when
                    the<lb/>congregation separated. The house was a small log one,<lb/>made with two
                    places for light to come in, but no glass to<lb/>keep the air out; and it being
                    a damp night, the cold<lb/>seized me, and my body was brought into affliction,
                    which<lb/>made me groan under the weigh of a corruptible house,<lb/>that I shall
                    be as glad to part with, as the log one. How<lb/>many times when I am
                    comfortable, am I made restless<lb/>by the Spirit of the Living God, who moves
                    me to stir up<lb/>the gift of faith in my heart, and thereby seek the
                    lost,<lb/>that have wandered from the Sheepfold of Jesus Christ, my<lb/>Merciful
                    Master, who ever excites His servants to suffer <lb/><pb n="99" facs="Ripley099"/>His Will, as
                    well as delight to do it. My trials are many<lb/>and complicated, yet Though,
                    Lord, deliverest my soul at all<lb/>seasons, out of the hand of the adversary,
                    who seeketh<lb/>my life by various means, and has tried every new
                    tempta-<lb/>tion to beguile and entangle my soul; knowing my delight<lb/>and
                    glory is the overthrow of his kingdom of darkness,<lb/>in the hearts of poor
                    sinners, whom I feel much for on<lb/>account of being misled by his base
                    machinations, where-<lb/>with millions are undone, choosing to yield the
                    members<lb/>of their bodies servants to sin, and their souls an
                    habituation<lb/>myself called upon also, to exalt the Redeemer of the<lb/>world,
                    as a Gracious, Long suffering God, full of pity to<lb/>the children of men,
                    whose clemency is so great to all,<lb/>that each must be his own accuser at His
                    Righteous Bar,<lb/>condemned by their reiterated sins, which have ben
                    vio-<lb/>patins of His Just, and Holy Law, made to model the life<lb/>of man by,
                    or that whereby his actions shall be examined:<lb/>for the Law is fixed in the
                    heart of man, and therefore<lb/>many are a Law to themselves who never saw the
                    Tables<lb/>of Stone, or read the Outward Letter. <quote type="biblical">The
                        Grace of our<lb/>Lord Jesus Christ hath appeared unto all men,
                        teaching<lb/>them to deny themselves of all ungodliness, and
                        wordily<lb/>lusts,</quote> that they may live soberly, righteously, and
                    bodily<lb/>in this present evil world.</p>
                <closer><dateline>[<date when="1805-08-11">11th 8th mo.
                    1805.</date>]</dateline></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <p>Having rode five miles in the burning sun this morning,<lb/>I feel like Jonah,
                    and mourned for a shade, as he did for<lb/>his pleasant Gourd, which withered
                    away for his instruc-<lb/>tion. The person who went with me, left me in
                        <placeName key="stockbridge">Stock-<lb/>bridge,</placeName> at the house of
                        <persName key="aserjea1">Abraham Serjeant</persName>, who has been
                    a<lb/>missionary to the Tribe of Indians nineteen years suc-<lb/>cessively, and
                    since he first visited the Indians, he told<lb/>me <said who="aserjea1">It was
                        thirty.</said> Feeling much distressed by a violent<lb/>pain in my head,
                    first with cold, and then with heat, I<lb/>could not take the satisfaction I
                    would, in case I had been<lb/>of the Indian women, whom I felt dear to me.
                    Kneeling<lb/>in the midst, my prayer was offered in faith for them and <lb/><pb
                        n="100" facs="Ripley100"/>their children, that they might feel renewed by the Power<lb/>of
                    the Holy Ghost, and live the true life of Faith. These<lb/>women could all
                    understand English; and several of<lb/>them professed to be Born again. Eve, the
                    oldest squaw,<lb/>said <said>I have been Christian thirty years,</said> being
                    four-<lb/>score years old; yet walked one day to hear me perch four<lb/>miles,
                    which my Master bid me reward her for it double.<lb/>I was sorry that it was not
                    in my power to clothe them<lb/>with necessary things; for I had but four gowns,
                    and I<lb/>gave them three of my little number, and from one dozen<lb/>pieces of
                    new linen, I left but one change: so the God of<lb/>Heaven and Earth, put it
                    into the hearts of my rich Chris-<lb/>tian sisters to supply my returning wants,
                    when I go<lb/>among them; and above all, clothe my poor Red sisters<lb/>with the
                    saint’s pure white linen, that I may meet them<lb/>in the Kingdom of our Lord
                    Jesus Christ.</p>
                <p>I saw a white woman among the rest of the females,<lb/>who was from the State of
                    New jersey, she was smoking,<lb/>and had two children named, being married to an
                    Indian.<lb/>I was told that she had a third child, an infant; but
                    last<lb/>winter it perished for want of clothes: poor babe! its<lb/>sorrows are
                    at an end, and it is shining with the robe of<lb/>Jesu’s Righteousness! I told
                    her, <said who="dripl1">She ought to be a pat-<lb/>tern to the Indian
                        women;</said> and to induce her, I gave her<lb/>a long morning gown, to make
                    her helpless children each<lb/>one, requesting <persName key="aserjea1">Abraham
                        Serjeant</persName> to let his daughter<lb/>make them: but he said <said
                        who="aserjea1">It is too good.</said>
                    <said who="dripl1">It will last<lb/>the better I replied, for being fine and
                        good.</said> Afterwards<lb/>I had the pleasure to see this white woman at a
                    meeting:<lb/>for she with many others came a long way, and I had
                    an<lb/>opportunity to preach repentance and Faith in Jesus<lb/>Christ, and was
                    blessed in my own soul abundantly, for<lb/>feeling the miseries of my
                    fellow-creatures in every direc-<lb/>tion, attending to the Spirit of God in me </p>
                <closer><dateline>[<date when="1805-08-12">12th 8th mo.<lb/>1805</date>, <placeName
                            key="stockbridge">Stockbridge</placeName>.]</dateline></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <p>Much concern I feel for the Indians here, as well<lb/>as for those I have
                    mentioned: but those have better<lb/>houses, and have a school for their
                    children, and many <lb/><pb n="101" facs="Ripley101"/>can speak English so as to be understood. I
                    went to<lb/>their church, which is distinguished by a steeple, that<lb/>you can
                    see some distance off. It is a neat, clean, wood<lb/>building, with glass
                    windows, and a handsome entrance,<lb/>having a gallery all round excepting where
                    the minister<lb/>sits. The minster took his seat in the pulpit, desiring<lb/>me
                    to sit in a pew underneath, where three of his daugh-<lb/>ter sat along side of
                    me, dressed as fashionable as any<lb/>women in middle rank, although there were
                    but few to see<lb/>them, except the Indians, who all came with a
                    blanket<lb/>round them, unless it were the young men and women,<lb/>who were
                    foolishly hung with features, and head tires of<lb/>bright tin mettle. The
                    Indians fantastically dressed,<lb/>sung a psalm feelingly, which moved my
                    passion of love,<lb/>so that I wept all the time tears of joy. After this
                        <persName key="aserjea1">Abra-<lb/>ham Serjeant</persName> prayed in Indian,
                    and then in English, and<lb/>gave out a second psalm, which was sung as the
                    other ad-<lb/>mirably. The minister then read part of the fourteenth<lb/>chapter
                    of Mark, which <persName key="haupa1">Captain Hendrick</persName>, a Chief,
                    read<lb/>also in Indian; and I was at liberty to preach to them,<lb/>and had
                        <persName key="haupa1">Captain Hendrick</persName> to interpret for me as
                    long as I<lb/>thought proper, or in other words, while my Master furnish-<lb/>ed
                    me with matter for the occasion, having desired Him<lb/>to be both Mouth and
                    Wisdom to me, and also to lead me<lb/>to the passage which would be the most
                    enlightening to<lb/>them: for I much delighted to be a messenger of
                    peace<lb/>individually to them. My subject I took from Isaiah<lb/>who
                    prophetically said, <quote type="biblical">He was wounded for our
                        trans-<lb/>gressions: He was bruised for our iniquities; the
                        chas-<lb/>tisement of our peace was upon Him, and with His Stripes<lb/>we
                        are healed.</quote> I felt alive in the Truth, therefore deliver-<lb/>ed
                    each sentence with energetic love and streaming eyes,<lb/>shewing in what manner
                    the Blessed Jesus was wounded<lb/>and bruised for us! I do not remember a time
                    that I<lb/>could more freely excite to believe on Him by Faith,<lb/>which I told
                    them was His Gift, and He would dispense<lb/>it to them if they would seek it by
                    prayer, and avoiding<lb/>all sin that offended Him who was without sin: for He
                    <lb/><pb n="102" facs="Ripley102"/>was an obedient Son, and never transgressed: yet
                    the<lb/>Father laid upon Him the iniquity of us all. The ar-<lb/>dency of mind
                    which I felt was great, and I am thankful<lb/>the spirit of prayer was imported
                    to me, that I might in-<lb/>tercede thereby for the application of his Virtuous
                    Blood,<lb/>which poured forth from His Wounds, when He hung a<lb/>Spectacle in
                    the air, Dying for all Nations, who were<lb/>Made by Him. I gave <persName
                        key="haupa1">Captain Hendrick</persName> my pocket book,<lb/>as I had not a
                    crown to reward him with, for interpreta-<lb/>tion. When I came out, many of the
                    Indians gladly took<lb/>me by the hand, which affectionately I saluted after
                    the<lb/>same manner, knowing, One God was our Father, Re-<lb/>deemer, and
                    Sanctifier of all, who are made whole with<lb/>His Stripes.</p>
                <p>I went a few miles, and held a second meeting in a<lb/>barn: for the people, in
                    many places, have to assemble<lb/>thus, being not able to accommodate themselves
                    better.<lb/>My text was, <quote type="biblical">Master which is the first and
                        great co-<lb/>mandment?</quote> The fervency of my spirit made me bold
                    as<lb/>a lion, and I thought I could finish my life in exciting<lb/>them to love
                    the Lord their God with all their heart,<lb/>soul, mind, and strength. This is
                    my experience, said I,<lb/>and O that it was each of your’s! Several times I
                    stood<lb/>silent, being powerfully prevented by weeping; no won-<lb/>der if some
                    from this evening, love God with all their<lb/>heart, and keep me in
                    remembrance, for the exercise of<lb/>my faith and prayer. The day was finished
                    by riding five<lb/>miles alone, contemplating the Love of God in Christ
                    to<lb/>me.</p>
                <closer><dateline>[<date when="1805-08-13">13th 8th mo. 1805</date>, <placeName
                            key="verno">Vernon</placeName>, <placeName key="oneida">Oneida
                            County</placeName>.]</dateline></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <p>Appointments are made for me in five places, one for<lb/>each day; so my work
                    follows me, though I feared being<lb/>kept idle. The insatiate thirst for souls
                    which I feel,<lb/>is a thousand times more than for my daily bread, or
                    ne-<lb/>cessary raiment, therefore I am continually brought
                    into<lb/>perplexities and doubts for the different situations of my<lb/>hearers.
                    In many corners here, I find some desiring to<lb/>know what they shall do to
                    obtain Life Eternal; which I<lb/>am baptized for, as I pass along from one place
                    to another, <lb/><pb n="103" facs="Ripley103"/>Surely, no one’s sorrows are equal to mine;
                    because my<lb/>heart seems to share in the bitterness of everyone one whom<lb/>I
                    mix with.</p>
                <p>I am going to the Centre, six miles from this, and my<lb/>feeble fabric can
                    scarcely support itself; but obedience is<lb/>required if I faint by the way.
                    This is consequence<lb/>of leaving some of my morning’s work to do at
                    noon.<lb/>Take warning, O reader! and do the work of thy life sea-<lb/>sonably,
                    then thou wilt be at liberty to rest in pain, and<lb/>thy vigorous hours will
                    honour Him, who finished His<lb/>work at noon, by thirty-three, being Obedient
                    all His Days.<lb/>Had I gone forth at the first call of my Heavenly
                    Father,<lb/>my flesh and bones would now have rested in hope, and<lb/>my spirit
                    entered the pearly gate of the City of the New<lb/>Jerusalem, which is free, and
                    the Mother of us all, who<lb/>are sealed to the Day of Redemption, when our
                    bodies shall<lb/>be raised from the dust and formed a celestial temple,
                    for<lb/>the glorified soul and Spirit of the Living God to swell in<lb/>forever.
                        <quote type="biblical">It is sown a natural body, it is raised a
                        spi-<lb/>ritual body. There is a natural body, and there is a<lb/>spiritiual
                        body: and so it is written, The first a Adam<lb/>was made a living soul, the
                        last Adam was made a quick-<lb/>ending spirit.</quote>
                    <quote type="biblical">And as we have borne the image of the<lb/>earthy, we
                        shall also bear the image of the Heavenly:</quote><lb/><quote
                        type="biblical">For the trumpet shall sound; and the dead shall
                        be<lb/>raised incorruptible, and we shall be changed.</quote></p>
                <closer><dateline>[<date when="1805-08-14">14th 8th<lb/>mo. 1805</date>, <placeName
                            key="verno">Vernon</placeName>, <placeName key="oneida">Oneida
                            County</placeName>.]</dateline></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <p><persName key="skirk1">Samuel Kirkland</persName>, a Presbyterian missionary to
                        the<lb/><orgName key="oneida">Oneida Indians</orgName>, called upon me this
                    day to give me an<lb/>invitation to his residence. I felt unwilling for the
                    pre-<lb/>sent to comply with his request; but my aged friend ap<lb/>peared
                    determined to have me home with him. He said,<lb/><said><persName key="jsken1"
                            >Skanando</persName>, the Old <orgName key="oneida">Oneida</orgName>
                        Chief, had come thirteen miles<lb/>after him, to bring me again, for my last
                        Interpreter had<lb/>not done me justice, when I took my leave of them:
                        be-<lb/>sides, he could not trust any so well as his old
                            friend<lb/><persName key="skirk1">Kirkland</persName>, who administered
                        the bread and wine unto him;<lb/>being the only man, and Chief, who joined
                        the Indians <lb/><pb n="104" facs="Ripley104"/>squaws in that holy ordinance: for the women
                        are much<lb/>better than men, and have a greater knowledge of<lb/>God before
                        their eyes, which preserves them from intoxi-<lb/>cation, and other evils,
                        that the men are liable to be over-<lb/>taken with, when they are deprived
                        of their reason by<lb/>strong drink.</said> I told my friend <persName
                        key="skirk1">Kirkland</persName> that <said who="dripl1">I had<lb/>taken my
                        leave of the <orgName key="oneida">Oneida Indians</orgName>, but was willing
                        to<lb/>go again in case they might be benefited.</said> We parted,<lb/>and I
                    rode with a sick head-ache to the Centre, six miles<lb/>off, and the first
                    salutation I received was, that <said>Many<lb/>were determined to hinder me of
                        preaching, declaring a<lb/>woman had no right to preach.</said> I was very
                    still, and kept<lb/>silence till the way opened of itself, without my
                    making<lb/>one effort to promote it; for the Lord stirred up a
                    goodly<lb/>number, who positively said, <said>I should preach, and if
                        I<lb/>could not be accommodated with the Presbyterian church,<lb/>I should
                        have the schoolhouse, as it was free for all.</said> I<lb/>had no companion,
                    and knew not one soul among all this<lb/>confusion: therefore I relied on the
                    Arm of Jehovah, my<lb/>strong defence, and saw satan once more defeated by
                    the<lb/>God of Jacob; for I had patiently waited for the Lord to<lb/>put him to
                    flight who had rose up an host against me, to<lb/>cause me to be confounded
                    before my opposers.</p>
                <p>As I had made the best of it that I could, strength<lb/>was given to me to
                    evidence to all present that I feared none<lb/>but the Living God, saying in the
                    midst of my subject,<lb/><quote type="biblical">Wo! be to me if I preach not the
                        gospel,</quote> feeling as my<lb/>day of suffering was, my inward peace and
                    power abound-<lb/>ed, which was a fresh manifestation of the Father’s
                    Love<lb/>unto me, and confirmation that I still moved in the line of<lb/>my
                    duty.</p>
                <p>When the meeting closed, six persons came unto me,<lb/>to request I would go with
                    them, each having a horse; but<lb/>I was as much at a stand to know how I should
                    dispose of<lb/>myself after meeting! as to comprehend how I should<lb/>obtain
                    admission among them! One cried out, <said>You must<lb/>go with me,</said>
                    another, <said>She shall go with me,</said> and my<lb/>friend <persName
                        key="skirk1">Samuel Kirkland</persName>, missionary to the <orgName
                            key="oneida">Oneida Indians</orgName>, <lb/><pb n="105" facs="Ripley105"/>said, <said
                        who="skirk1">I have come six miles for her, and will not be ex-<lb/>cused
                        from taking her to my house: therefore she must<lb/>come with me; for I have
                        promised to take her to <orgName key="oneida">Oneida</orgName><lb/>next
                        Sabbath, as <persName key="jsken1">Skanando</persName>, the old Chief, will
                        not be<lb/>satisfied without it.</said></p>
                <p>The contest was finished, and I thought I was richly<lb/>rewarded for my
                    faithfulness, having exhorted them to be<lb/>ready for the approach of the
                    Bridgegroom, who would<lb/>come in such an hour as they thought not of. As I
                    went<lb/>home with <persName key="skirk1">S. K.</persName> we had a very solemn
                    die, and our tears<lb/>flowed reciprocally: for the Lord our God, had been
                    with<lb/>us in ten thousand dangers, where death threatened us in<lb/>the most
                    poignant manner. He told me that he has been<lb/>minister forty years, and
                    twenty of that time he adopted<lb/>an Indian’s life, living among them for their
                    benefit. When<lb/>his lot was first cast there, he was fixed with the best
                    man<lb/>they had, who died a few days after; which they attri-<lb/>buted to him,
                    and were determined to have revenge, life<lb/>for life. He said, <said
                        who="skirk1">I was commanded to fall asleep, and<lb/>a fire was prepared;
                        but while they were all around me,<lb/>I kept singing hymns, trusting in God
                        to deliver me, yet<lb/>they often said to me, <said>Go to sleep, why do you
                            sing?</said><lb/>at last one of the Chiefs was wright on, and made
                        an<lb/>affecting speech, signifying, that <said>This brother had
                            fallen<lb/>down few steps short a few paces, were they to kill a
                            white<lb/>brother for it,</said> saying, <said>It will bring innocent
                            blood upon<lb/>our Nation if we kill him:</said> therefore they
                        hearkened unto<lb/>this Chief, and I was marvelously delivered from the
                        jaws<lb/>of death. Another wonderful escape I had through the<lb/>goodness
                        of God: I had taught a number of the young In-<lb/>dins to sing psalms, and
                        they used to come and sing<lb/>with me, and I prayed, so that many of them
                        were become<lb/>civilized, and did not like to go out among the
                        warriors,<lb/>which enraged the men of war much, so that they agreed<lb/>to
                        take my life from me, saying, <said>I wanted to teach them<lb/>to milk, and
                            hoe, and make women of them.</said> The night<lb/>they fixed for putting
                        me to death, I was fast asleep, and <lb/><pb n="106" facs="Ripley106"/>an old woman came and
                        tried to wake me, knowing their<lb/>intention, crying, <said>Up; up;
                            up;</said> many times, and then<lb/>left me; but being very sound, I did
                        not regard what was<lb/>said unto me, and therefore lay still, till she came
                        and<lb/>shook me by the shoulders, and said <said>Up; up; flee; flee<lb/>for
                            life;</said> giving me a blanket to hide me; I run among<lb/>some thick
                        bushes, and covered myself all over, laying<lb/>down under them, which I had
                        no sooner done, but I<lb/>heard them march along, sounding through the
                        woods,<lb/>singing their warlike songs and passed by me, to go to<lb/>the
                        hut where I came from, and sought me with great<lb/>fury, threatening the
                        aged woman that they would kill<lb/>her unless she would tell where I was,
                        but she said I <said>Was<lb/>not there,</said> and then cried out pitiably,
                            <said>What! kill an<lb/>old granny! kill an old granny!</said> so they
                        went away, and<lb/>I remained to hide myself several days, until their
                        rage<lb/>was pacified against me.</said></p>
                <p>I was pleased to hear the deliverance that God wrought<lb/>out for my friend, and
                    remarked, that if he had been more<lb/>faithful, the Lord then would have
                    blessed his labours<lb/>more abundantly, which he with tears acknowledged
                    he<lb/>believed; yet said, <said who="skirk1">I have seen fruit of my labour:
                        for<lb/>there are thirteen women brought to believe on our Lord<lb/>Jesus,
                        and <persName key="jsken1">Skanando</persName>, the old Chief, is a
                        Christian,</said> weep-<lb/>ing all the way. Let the time past suffice, I
                    cried, but if<lb/>thou hadst only taken thought for the Indians, God
                    would<lb/>have cared for thee and they children; and I am fully sensi-<lb/>ble
                    that no one will ever profit the Indians unless they<lb/>can lay aside their own
                    interest, and I am thankful that<lb/>thou hast done the good thou hast: but I
                    wish though<lb/>wouldst let the time past suffice, and what they hand
                    find-<lb/>set to do, do it with all they might. My aged brother, with<lb/>tears
                    said he <said who="skirk1">Would take my advice: for what I had<lb/>advanced was
                        the truth;</said> and I found great peace in de-<lb/>claring what I did, and
                    hope that useful lesson, which the<lb/>Lord my God taught me by His Spirit to
                    give him, will<lb/>be put in practice by myself, in every point of view,
                    as<lb/>touching my spiritual labour in His Vineyard; for unless <lb/><pb n="107" facs="Ripley107"/>the heart is centred in Him, and weaned from all worldly<lb/>attainments, or
                    earthly possessions, it is not possible that<lb/>He will honour us with
                    spiritual riches, and qualify us to<lb/>bring home many souls to Him, as
                    instruments in His own<lb/>Hands, to bring about that wonderful event, when the
                    out-<lb/>pouring of His Spirit causeth All to know the Lord, from<lb/>the least
                    unto the greatest.</p>
                <closer><dateline>[<date when="1805-08-15">15th 8th mo. 1805.</date>
                        <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName>.]</dateline></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <p><persName key="ekirk1">Eliza Kirkland</persName>, an amiable young woman,
                    daughter<lb/>of <persName key="skirk1">S. K.</persName> took me in a chaise to a
                    Quaker’s house, four<lb/>miles off, where I had a solemn meeting, which was
                    in<lb/>a barn, and warned the scoffers there whom I felt for, lest<lb/>they
                    should be of the number of such who would inward-<lb/>ly groan, saying, <quote
                        type="biblical">We fools thought their lives madness,<lb/>and their end to
                        be without honour.</quote> It was a satisfacto-<lb/>ry time, notwithstanding
                    some scorners being there. The<lb/>Quaker took me home to his house, where I
                    abode that<lb/>night in great sorrow of mind for some of the family
                    not<lb/>fearing God.</p>
                <p>The <date when="1805-08-16">16th</date> I went to <placeName key="broth"
                        >Brothertown</placeName>, to collect the Indians<lb/>there together, in the
                    school-house. My advice to them<lb/>was, <quote type="biblical">Seek ye first
                        the Kingdom of God and His Right-<lb/>eousness, and all these things shall
                        be added unto you.</quote><lb/>Which things I explained, were the
                    necessaries of life, that<lb/>the Christians are entitled to, by the special
                    promises and<lb/>care of our Heavenly Father, who watches over His
                    chil-<lb/>dren from day to day. Those Indians were Baptists, di-<lb/>vided from
                    two classes, one part believed in election, and<lb/>the other in free salvation.
                    Where I was, they had re-<lb/>fused their minister, because they said <said>They
                        would not<lb/>worship such a cruel God as he served, as He only
                        took<lb/>care of a part of his creatures,</said> and drew this
                    comparison,<lb/>by asking a question concerning their women: <said>Would<lb/>not
                        she be a cruel mother, who having two children,<lb/>took the one and nurse
                        it; and left the other to perish?<lb/>so we will worship a God who takes
                        care of all His chil-<lb/>dren;</said> which I think was an excellent
                    conclusion, and a<lb/>sound argument was advanced to shew how far an
                    Indian<lb/>is capable of believing in the Living and True God, who <lb/><pb
                        n="108" facs="Ripley108"/>is no Respecter of persons, further than they disregard
                    his<lb/>Righteous Commandments and slight His offered mercy.</p>
                <p>After meeting, I rode eight miles, and slept very little<lb/> in the night, by
                    reason of poor accommodations, for we<lb/>all lodged in one room, where I could
                    see the firmament<lb/>from a breach which had been made by fire. They sky
                    at-<lb/>tracted my notice, and prevented my sleeping, as I had<lb/>not before
                    met with such poor lodgings, yet I had the best<lb/>this miserable log house
                    afforded, being welcome there.</p>
                <p>A large number assembled on the <date when="1805-08-17">17th</date> for
                    worship,<lb/>who had come, from two miles to ten round this neigh-<lb/>bourhood;
                    but having no other place better than a school-<lb/>house, when it was full, the
                    people came and requested<lb/>me to <said>Go out into the open air, to
                        accommodate them<lb/>who had come so far.</said> I therefore got into a car,
                    and<lb/>lift up my voice with authority, and said in the words of<lb/>my Lord
                    and Master, <quote type="biblical">Let your light so shine before<lb/>men that
                        they may see your good works, and glorify your<lb/>father which is in
                        Heaven.</quote> I was much favoured with<lb/>the Presence of God; for this
                    opportunity required great<lb/>fortitude, as I never was before called to stand
                    out i nthe<lb/>air, exposed to the burning sun, though I screened my-<lb/>self
                    as well as I could. There is great courage also ne-<lb/>cessary for such a
                    calling as this, which females are not<lb/>in general possessed of; because a
                    false delicacy prevails<lb/>over the mind that is termed refinement, which
                    shudders<lb/>at the very idea of standing a gazing stock to men of
                    the<lb/>basset passions; unless they have been betrayed, and de-<lb/>sire to
                    insnare their fellow-mortals, which is now become<lb/>so common, that a prudent
                    woman must be very guarded<lb/>to sun the censure of the vulgar, if she wish to
                    maintain<lb/>her character, as a virtuous woman, among mankind.</p>
                <p>When I had opened the passage, and stood a consider-<lb/>able time, I gave over,
                    and was succeeded by one of my<lb/>sisters, who appeared astonished at me, and
                    longed for a<lb/>vacant moment to testify, that, <said>The spirit of
                        prophecy<lb/>was not to continue always within the narrow limits of<lb/>our
                        brotherhood, as male and female, are one in our Lord <lb/><pb n="109" facs="Ripley109"/>Jesus, when they become members of One Mystical Body,<lb/>even the
                        Spiritual Body, or Bride of Christ, whom He<lb/>will remain Head of, or
                        Bridgeroom to, forever, by law-<lb/>ful inheritance,</said> having <quote
                        type="biblical">Swallowed up death in victory.</quote><lb/>As soon as she
                    had finished, I made way for another, by<lb/>sanctioning what was already
                    advanced; and then, the<lb/>third time, I resumed my office, almost like a
                    mother in<lb/>Israel, although but a babe, comparatively speaking. It<lb/>was a
                    time whig will be remembered, I verily believe,<lb/>because no other person
                    spoke, or prayed, but us three<lb/>women, who never had seen each other’s face
                    before.<lb/>We witnessed according to this declaration, <quote type="biblical"
                        >Where<lb/>the Spirit is, there is Liberty,</quote> and I am of opinion, if
                    we<lb/>never see one another again in the flesh, we shall be ad-<lb/>kitted into
                    that Mansion, where there is joy and pace,<lb/>and everlasting pleasure, to
                    reward every soul, who have<lb/>denied themselves of all ungodliness, and worldy
                    lusts,<lb/>and taken up the Cross of our Lord Jesus Christ.</p>
                <p>A person asked me home with her, two miles off,<lb/>whose name was Sloan, who was
                    a tender hearted woman,<lb/>a Baptist by profession: thus I mix among all,
                    regarding<lb/>no name, if only the image of Jesus Christ is there. I<lb/>had to
                    lodge again in the same room where the whole fa-<lb/>mily were, it being a log
                    house, with poor accomoda-<lb/>tions.</p>
                <p>One the <date when="1805-08-17">17th</date>, <persName key="wsloa1">William
                        Sloan</persName> went with me from <placeName key="augus"
                        >Au-<lb/>gusta</placeName> to <placeName key="stockbridge"
                        >Stockbridge</placeName>; and this merciful man having but<lb/>one horse,
                    walked four long miles through the woods and<lb/>mud, to let me ride on his
                    valuable creature. This person<lb/>was a Scotchman, who fought for the
                    Americans, and in<lb/>the war received a ball that passed under his left
                    should<lb/>blade to his back bone, where it has been twenty-eight<lb/>years. I
                    offered him out of my little stock of money,<lb/>half a dollar, but he would
                    only take two shillings.</p>
                <p>A meeting was held again in <placeName key="stockbridge">Stockbridge</placeName>,
                    for the in-<lb/>struction of the poor Natives, who are dear to me. There<lb/>are
                    some of the Jersey Indians among this tribe, and the<lb/>whole number here, are
                    rising three hundred, which infor-<lb/><pb n="110" facs="Ripley110"/>mation I got from <persName
                        key="aserjea1">A. S.</persName> their minister. This day two of<lb/>the
                    missionaries, and young clergyman were present,<lb/>while my soul was earnestly
                    engaged for the good of the<lb/>Indians: but I verily believe by their
                    proceedings, it was<lb/>their opinion that a woman ought not to preach: for
                    one<lb/>of them said afterwards, had I <said>Come to teach them to<lb/>knit and
                        sew, it would be very well.</said> From two until six,<lb/>I abode, and told
                    them I hoped to see them among Christ’s<lb/>sheep at His Right Hand. The women
                    presented me an<lb/>address, written by <persName key="haupa1">Capt.
                        Hendrick</persName>, an Indian Chief, who<lb/>was my interpreter. This
                    address was to shew their affec-<lb/>tion and gratitude, for crossing the Great
                    Ocean, to call<lb/>them to the Fold of Jesus, which some already are in,
                    be-<lb/>ing Lambs of His Care, and Sheep of His Pasture. I felt<lb/>sorry to be
                    obliged to trouble <persName key="aserjea1">A. S.</persName> for a horse, but if
                    it be<lb/>ever in my power, I will reward him; and I am equally<lb/>obliged to
                    him for his kindness, in setting me four miles<lb/>to <placeName key="verno"
                        >Vernon</placeName>, to the residence of my kind father Young.</p>
                <closer><dateline>[<date when="1805-08-19">19th 8th mo. 1805</date>, <placeName
                            key="verno">Vernon</placeName>, <placeName key="oneida">Oneida
                            County.</placeName>]</dateline></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <floatingText type="letter">
                    <body>
                        <opener>AN ADDRESS<lb/>From the Women of the <orgName key="stockbridge">Muhheconnuk
                                nation</orgName> of Indians,<lb/>written on their behalf, in their
                            native language, and<lb/>translated into English by <persName
                                key="haupa1">Captain Hendrick</persName>, one of the<lb/>Indian
                            chiefs, and presented to Dorothy Ripley, on her<lb/>departure from
                            amongst them. <salute>DEAR SISTER,</salute></opener>
                        <p>WE, the poor women of the <orgName key="stockbridge">Muhheconnuk
                            nation</orgName>,<lb/>wish to speak few words to you, to inform you,
                            that while<lb/>our forefathers were sitting by the side of their
                            ancient<lb/>fire-place, about eighty years ago, our father, <persName
                                key="aserjea1">Rev. Mr.<lb/>Sergeant</persName>’s father, came
                            amongst them with the message<lb/>of the Great and Good Spirit, which he
                            then began to de-<lb/>liver to them. He was the first minister of the
                            gospel<lb/>that ever preached to our fathers, and the Great and
                            Good<lb/>Spirit blessed his labours, by which means many of our<lb/>poor
                            natives were turned from darkness to light.</p>
                        <p>Our ancestors loved their minister, whom they looked <pb n="111"
                            facs="Ripley111"/><lb/>upon as father, because he was willing to live and die
                            with<lb/>them.</p>
                        <p>Sister, We will also inform you, that since our father,<lb/><persName
                                key="aserjea1">Mr. Sergeant</persName>’s father died, he began to
                            manifest a com-<lb/>passionate feeling towards our dismal situation; he
                            in the<lb/>first place began to teach us to read and write, this he
                            did<lb/>several years; after this he then began to deliver the
                            word<lb/>of the Good Spirit, and his labours have been blessed,
                            by<lb/>which means we who are commonly called by the white<lb/>people
                            Squaws, are enquiring the way to Zion.</p>
                        <p>Sister, While we were sitting by the side of our fire-<lb/>place here, we
                            saw you coming, and when you opened<lb/>your mouth we believed you was
                            sent by the Great and<lb/>Good Spirit to visit us (poor natives of this
                            Island.) We<lb/>feel thankful to Him that He has put such a love in
                            your<lb/>heart, that you was willing to undertake such a long
                            and<lb/>tedious journey on the purpose to deliver His message to
                            us.<lb/>We thank the Great Good Spirit that He has protected<lb/>you on
                            the way, that you arrived here safely.</p>
                        <p>Sister, In behalf of the rest of our woman, we now<lb/>heartily thank you
                            for your kindness and for the pains you<lb/>have taken to visit us.</p>
                        <p>We hope by the help of the Great Good Spirit, we shall<lb/>ever remember
                            you, and the good words which you deli-<lb/>vered to us. Although we do
                            not expect ever to see you<lb/>again, yet we believe that the Lord Jesus
                            is able to help<lb/>us that we may hold out unto the end, that we may
                            see you<lb/>among His Sheep on His Right, where we shall never
                            be<lb/>parted again.</p>
                        <p>May the Good Spirit protect you on your way, that<lb/>you may have
                            pleasant journey unto the end, farewell.</p>
                        <closer><signed>
                                <persName key="lhend1">Lydia Suhquauwkhuh, or Hendrick</persName>.<lb/>
                                <persName key="cquaw1">Catharine Quauquwchon</persName>.<lb/>
                                <persName key="emauk1">Eliz. Maukhtoaquauwusquch, or
                                    Jersey.</persName><lb/>
                                <persName key="kquin1">Catharine Quinney</persName>.<lb/>
                                <persName key="eknoh1">Eve Knohtcaunmeu</persName>. In behalf of the
                                rest. </signed>
                            <dateline><placeName key="newst">New Stockbridge</placeName>. <date
                                    when="1805-08-19">19th August, 1805</date>.<lb/>In the State of
                                <placeName key="nycit">New York</placeName>.</dateline></closer>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <pb n="112" facs="Ripley112"/>

                <p><persName key="skirk1">Samuel Kirkland</persName> took me to have my
                    appointment<lb/>fulfilled, which he engaged me to perform agreeable to
                    the<lb/>request of <persName key="jsken1">Skanando</persName>, the old Chief,
                    king of the <orgName key="oneida">Oneida nation</orgName><lb/>: but when I got
                    there, the Presbyterian minis-<lb/>ter came, who said <said>She had better teach
                        them to knit<lb/>and sew, as preach to them,</said> enquiring <said>What
                        apology<lb/>he should make to them for my preaching, as they did
                        not<lb/>teach the Indians, that women had any right to preach?</said><lb/>I
                    told him candidly, to <said who="dripl1">Save himself trouble; for no<lb/>one
                        had any business to interfere respecting this, since I<lb/>was accountable
                        to no one but God, who had brought me<lb/>hither, neither was any answerable
                        for what I did.</said> I<lb/>was sitting in silence a little, with a large
                    collection of<lb/>Indians, when this missionary walked in with a pompous<lb/>air
                    into the pulpit, unlike a humble preacher of the<lb/>Righteousness of our Meek
                    and Lowly Jesus: however, I<lb/>thought it best to set him an example of love,
                    so permitted<lb/>him to partake of the opportunity, which had been
                    merci-<lb/>fully prepared for me, by the Providential Mercy of God.<lb/><quote
                        type="biblical">Woman why weepest though? whom seekest thou?</quote>
                    was<lb/>my text, therefore I confined myself to my Indian sisters;<lb/>and told
                    the men, as there were two preachers there, I<lb/>left them to the instruction
                    of those missionaries; testi-<lb/>fying boldly, <said who="dripl1">That if the
                        disciplines had watched with the<lb/>same assiduousness, as Mary did at the
                        Sepulchre, they<lb/>would have had the joyful tidings to preach, “That
                        Jesus<lb/>Christ the Lord was Risen from the Dead;”</said> this
                    chagrined<lb/>the missionaries so much, who oppossed me among the<lb/>Indians,
                    that I believe the next woman whom the Lord<lb/>sendeth, he will not dare to
                    insult: for the Indian women<lb/>resented it with great indignation, having
                    proved me their<lb/>sympathizing sister, who felt for their bodies and souls,
                    and<lb/>desired no reward, further than their present peace.</p>
                <p><persName key="skirk1">Samuel Kirkland</persName>, their stationed minister and
                    father,<lb/>who had been with them forty years, acted as a kind bro-<lb/>ther to
                    me, interpreting for me, as the Lord my God gave<lb/>ability to us each.
                    Although satan was seeking an occa-<lb/>sion to sow tares, or make discord among
                    us, I trust He <lb/><pb n="113" facs="Ripley113"/>would give this people to see where their help
                    must come<lb/>from, as it appeared my duty to impress their minds with<lb/>the
                    great obligation they owed to the Lord Jesus, who<lb/>waited to bring them into
                    His Fold of Love, that He might<lb/>be their Merciful Shepherd, and Guide them
                    as His Flock,<lb/>being <quote type="biblical">The True Light, which eightieth
                        every man that<lb/>cometh into the world.</quote></p>
                <p>After we separated, I went to <persName key="jsken1">Skanando’s</persName>, the
                    oldest<lb/>Chief’s house, where the good women all followed me,<lb/>that we
                    might have another opportunity; for we had been<lb/>interrupted by the uncivil
                    minister, who followed me with<lb/>my friend <persName key="skirk1"
                        >Kirkland</persName>; but I was determined that there<lb/>should be none
                    present, who wanted the true mark of<lb/>Christ’s Disciples, even Love:
                    therefore told him to <said>Go<lb/>away, and attend to his own preaching
                        elsewhere,</said> which<lb/>he did, when he found I was resolute and saw the
                    displea-<lb/>sure which he had raised in the breasts of the women
                    uni-<lb/>versally. <persName key="skirk1">S. K.</persName> rejoiced the heart of
                        <persName key="jsken1">Skanando</persName> and the<lb/>women by telling
                    them, <said who="skirk1">If I were spared, I intended to<lb/>return back again
                        to see them;</said> and we had a favoured<lb/>time, with God’s parting
                    blessing.</p>
                <p>Returning to <placeName key="verno">Vernon</placeName>, <persName key="cyoun1"
                        >Calvin Young</persName> signified that I<lb/><said who="cyoun1">Could go no
                        where, that they were more wicked than<lb/>there,</said> and requested me to
                    stay a month longer, to have<lb/>meetings up and down, in the neighbourhood;
                    and, as an<lb/>inducement, he proposed taking me to <placeName key="alban"
                        >Albany</placeName> in his car-<lb/>riage, with his wife, which was above
                    one hundred miles<lb/>off, at the end of that period, having to go there: but
                    en-<lb/>quiring of my Master Jesus, I was commanded to return<lb/>back, as my
                    work was done there, and I was wanted else-<lb/>where. Knowing I had not money
                    sufficient to pay my<lb/>expenses, I desired the Lord to incline the heart of
                    my<lb/>generous friend to give me one dollar, which I thought<lb/>would be
                    enough, with economy, to take me to <placeName key="alban"
                    >Albany</placeName>,<lb/>where the Lord had richly supplied me with money to
                    come<lb/>thither. I was astonished immediately, when I acquaint-<lb/>ed my
                    friend that I could not stay another day, that he<lb/>answered the desire of my
                    heart so cheerfully, by taking <lb/><pb n="114" facs="Ripley114"/>a silver dollar out of his
                    pocket, saying, <said who="cyoun1">Well, if you<lb/>will stay no longer, take
                        this piece of money,</said> which made<lb/>me burst into a flood of tears,
                    and acknowledge, that <said who="dripl1">No<lb/>sum of gold could ever reward
                        him for his disinterested<lb/>love, and fatherly care over me, in a strange
                        land, where<lb/>I knew no mortal when I came here; begging the Lord<lb/>to
                        return his mercy upon his children;</said> having three<lb/>amiable women,
                    whom I loved as sisters, who were a cre-<lb/>dit to him, and his beloved wife,
                    who with himself, will<lb/>ever be gratefully remembered, as friends raised up
                    by<lb/>God, to answer His own Purpose by me; and I trust when<lb/>all the
                    children of God will be received into the King-<lb/>dom, I shall see them, and
                    hear it say unto them, among<lb/>His sheep, <quote type="biblical">Verily I say
                        unto you, in as much as ye have<lb/>done it unto one of the least of these
                        my brethren, ye<lb/>have done it unto me.</quote> We parted with much
                    affection,<lb/>and my friends gave me this letter to keep in remem-<lb/>brance
                    their names.</p>
                <closer><dateline>[<date when="1805-08-20">20th 8th mo. 1805</date>, <placeName
                            key="paris">Paris</placeName>.]</dateline></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <floatingText type="letter">
                    <body>
                        <opener>A testimonial received from <persName key="cyoun1">Calvin
                                Young</persName>, who introduc-<lb/>ed <persName key="dripl1"
                                >Dorothy Ripley</persName> to the <orgName key="oneida">Oneida
                                Tribe</orgName>, or <orgName key="pagan">Pagan<lb/>Party.</orgName>
                            <dateline><placeName key="verno">Vernon</placeName>, <date
                                    when="1805-07-26">July 26, 1805.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>A LADY from England, by the name of <persName key="dripl1">Dorothy
                                Rip-<lb/>ley</persName>, was introduced to me by a gentleman who
                            came pas-<lb/>senger with her in the mail stage, for the purpose
                            of<lb/>preaching to the <orgName key="oneida">Oneida</orgName> and the
                            neighbouring Indians.<lb/>On Sunday, the <date when="1805-08-28"
                                >28th</date>, I had the pleasure of introducing her<lb/>to a part of
                            the <orgName key="oneida">Oneida Tribe</orgName>, called the <orgName
                                key="pagan">Pagan party</orgName>,<lb/>who believe not in the
                            Christian Religion, but in worship-<lb/>ing the Great Spirit, by
                            sacrificing and dancing. I in-<lb/>formed the Great Chief that she had
                            come a great way to<lb/>preach to them. This Chief is called the
                            <persName key="jblac2">Blacksmith</persName>, and<lb/>is a
                            complete savage in every respect, and very envious<lb/>to the white
                            people; but in this instance seemed to be<lb/>well pleased with her
                            visit, and expressed himself in this<lb/>manner, <said who="jblac2"
                                >That the white people generally came to them<lb/>under a pretence
                                of friendship, that after they had obtained <lb/><pb n="115" facs="Ripley115"/>their
                                object they were no more friends, but treated them<lb/>unkindly and
                                destroy their property, but said he liked<lb/>the people called
                                Quakers, that they were good people and<lb/>would do them no
                                harm.</said> After the meeting was over,<lb/>they generally
                            expressed a wish that she would pay them<lb/>another visit. This is the
                            only instance that I ever knew<lb/>this Chief to be pleased with white
                            people coming amongst<lb/>them, or paying any attention to the preaching
                            of the<lb/>Gospel.</p>
                        <closer><signed>
                                <persName key="cyoun1">CALVIN YOUNG</persName>,<lb/>
                                <persName key="eyoun2">EVE YOUNG</persName>. </signed></closer>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>

                <p>My friends set me to <placeName type="augus">Augusta</placeName>, where I had a
                    favoured<lb/>meeting, but was obliged to go into the woods, for the<lb/>house
                    would not hold the people collected from various<lb/>motives. I sat in silence
                    for some minutes, and then<lb/>stood upon the stump of a tree, and looking
                    steadfastly at<lb/>a well dressed man, I pronounced those words, <quote
                        type="biblical">If they<lb/>hear not Moses, and the prophets, neither will
                        they be<lb/>persuaded though one rose from the dead.</quote> I
                    signified<lb/>there are such present, who neither believed in Moses,<lb/>nor the
                    prophets; and although my soul was risen from<lb/>the dead spiritually, they
                    would not give credit to it unless<lb/>they believed in the outward Record,
                    which testified of<lb/>Him who was the Resurrection of soul, as well as
                    body,<lb/>and who was beheld by the children of Israel, when Moses<lb/>lifted up
                    the brazen serpent on a pole, for those stung by<lb/>serpents to behold, as
                    though they beheld the Son of Man,<lb/>the Son of God lifted up, who should Cure
                    the deadly<lb/>wound of the old serpent, even satan, who brought a
                    spi-<lb/>ritual death into the souls of all, since the day that Adam<lb/>fell by
                    disobeying the Righteous Commandment of the<lb/>Living God. I labored until I
                    had no more strength,<lb/>either to pray or preach, as I thought, and therefore
                    gave<lb/>over; and the man whom I particularly addressed, when<lb/>he could no
                    longer stand the Truth, slipped off out of my<lb/>sight. i was told, <said>He
                        had been educated a Quaker; but<lb/>had not been at a meeting for religious
                        worship for twenty <lb/><pb n="116" facs="Ripley116"/>years, being a professed Deist in this
                        part, and made this<lb/>excuse for coming to day, “As it is a woman who is
                        going<lb/>to preach, I will go and hear what she has to say:”</said>
                    there-<lb/>fore it was no wonder that the Merciful Jesus should find<lb/>him out
                    among the multitude. Had I known the man<lb/>was a Deist, and despised the sect
                    of religious professors,<lb/>I could not have reached him with a more suitable
                    testi-<lb/>mony; but I am better pleased, that the Spirit, who<lb/>searcheth all
                    things, directed my heart and eyes to him:<lb/>for he must think it strange, as
                    I was not known by any<lb/>there.</p>
                <p>Coming out of the woods, many <said>Besought me to return<lb/>back, as they had
                        come unseasonably, four and six miles<lb/>distance; and did not know that
                        the meeting was so early.</said><lb/>Standing to know the Will of my
                    Gracious Master, I was<lb/>surprised with the Spirit of prayer, which came on me
                    in<lb/>the twilling of an eye, and I supplicated Heaven for a<lb/>parting
                    blessing upon this people, who had come to hear<lb/>a stranger, who had left all
                    to follow Jesus, the Friend of<lb/>sinners; that I might be an instrument in His
                    Hands to<lb/>seek out the lost sheep of the house of Israel.</p>
                <p><persName key="iwobb1">Isaac Wobby</persName> came for me, and we rode together
                    six<lb/>miles, from <placeName key="augus">Augusta</placeName> to <placeName
                        key="paris">Paris</placeName>. This man was an Indian<lb/>from <placeName
                        key="longi">Long-Island</placeName>, who lives in <placeName key="broth"
                        >Brothertown</placeName>, and teaches<lb/>some of that Tribe, as God giveth
                    him ability. He told<lb/>me he was converted fourteen years ago, and fell
                    away,<lb/>and was very wicked; but since that, he was restored to<lb/>Divine
                    Favour, and now enjoys the Love of Jesus Christ.<lb/>I rode on one of his
                    horses, for the white people did not<lb/>lend me one, which I think was a great
                    neglect, as I was<lb/>willing to spend my strength, and last breath in
                    promo-<lb/>ting the Gospel of our Lord and Saviour, any where that<lb/>His
                    Spirit leads me to suffer, or do His Will.</p>
                <p>Though I have in this part had many kind friends, yet<lb/>various have been my
                    sorrows, which have come from un-<lb/>expected quarters, and from such who
                    should heal, and<lb/>not try to wound. My friend <persName key="skirk1">Samuel
                        Kirkland’s</persName> daugh-<lb/>ter <persName key="ekirk1"
                    >Eliza</persName>, has treated me as a sister, and conducted me to <lb/><pb
                        n="117" facs="Ripley117"/><placeName key="broth">Brothertown</placeName>, where we had a very
                    good meeting, at <persName key="iwobb1">Isaac<lb/>Wobby’s</persName> place for
                    worship, among the Close Communi-<lb/>cants, who are separated from the rest of
                    their Baptist<lb/>brethren, called the Open Communicants, if I am
                    rightly<lb/>informed. I had a meeting with the others before. The<lb/>Indians
                    here strive to imitate the white people, and there<lb/>is no need of an
                    interpreter, as they speak English. My<lb/>young friend took me back in her
                    father’s chaise, which he<lb/>lent us, after meeting; as I have been much
                    fatigued<lb/>with having to go beyond my strength: but to lay on a<lb/>good bed,
                    in a comfortable clean house, revived my spirits,<lb/>knowing I was welcome
                    there, and invited to tarry to rest<lb/>myself, and bring up my journal. The
                    friendship of this<lb/>family, I desire to record to the honour of <persName
                        key="skirk1">Samuel Kirk-<lb/>land</persName> and his wife <persName
                        key="mkirk2">Mary</persName>; who sympathized with me in my<lb/>solitude,
                    and administered a little comfit to my tribula-<lb/>ted spirit, which I offer my
                    thanks unto the Lord my God,<lb/>who alone Has all Power, to open and shut the
                    hearts He<lb/>Has made.</p>
                <p><persName key="cquaw1">Catharine Quachemut</persName>, an Indian sister, being
                    much<lb/>grieved at the incivility of the missionary who opposed<lb/>women’s
                    preaching, wrote me the following letter; and<lb/>then walked eight miles to
                    bring it.</p>
                <floatingText type="letter">
                    <body>
                        <opener>A Letter from an Indian Squaw (woman,) addressed to<lb/><persName
                                key="dripl1">Dorothy Ripley</persName>, and received when in
                            America. <salute>DEAR SISTER IN THE LORD,</salute></opener>
                        <p>I BELIEVE that there is but One, the Only, the Living<lb/>and True God,
                            and that he is the Maker and Preserver of<lb/>our lives, and upholder of
                            all things here below, and that<lb/>he sent his Only Begotten Son into
                            this world to be the<lb/>Saviour of mankind, and that all those who
                            believe and<lb/>confess the Lord Jesus with their mouth, and believe
                            in<lb/>their hearts, that God the Father of our Lord Jesus did<lb/>raise
                            him up from the dead, shall he healed by His stripes,<lb/>as thou hast
                            very well observed to us; and I hope and<lb/>pray God, that thou mayest
                            be the means of stirring up<lb/>our stony hearts to turn unto Him, the
                            Living and the <lb/><pb n="118" facs="Ripley118"/>True God, and that the words which thou
                            has dropped<lb/>among us may take deep impression upon our
                            hearts.<lb/>Dear Sister, be pleased to pray for us, that we may
                            be<lb/>enabled through divine assistance to worship God in
                            spirit<lb/>and in truth. I fully believe that thou art sent by
                            the<lb/>Great and Good Spirit into this part of the world to do<lb/>good
                            to thy fellow creatures, to preach the gospel unto<lb/>every kind of
                            people; and although many people are led<lb/>to believe that it is not
                            the duty of women to preach,<lb/>still I pray to God that thou mayest
                            not be discouraged,<lb/>there being many infallible proofs in the
                            scriptures of<lb/>women labouring in the gospel; one greatest
                            encouragement<lb/>is, our Lord Jesus appeared to a woman first after
                            His<lb/>Resurrection. I hope therefore my dear sister, thou may-<lb/>est
                            keep on thy gospel labour, and may that Great and<lb/>Good Spirit who is
                            able to protect thee by His Almighty<lb/>Power through all the changing
                            scenes of this life, guide<lb/>thee by His Wisdom, and bless all they
                            endeavors, and<lb/>crown them with success wheresoever He in His
                            Wisdom<lb/>may cast thy lot.</p>
                        <p>My dear sister, although we are uncertain whether<lb/>ever we shall see
                            each other’s faces again, and though the<lb/>billows and the wide ocean
                            may roll between us, still I<lb/>hope our hearts will be united together
                            in love, and one<lb/>voice in glorifying God, and in celebrating His
                            praises for<lb/>His unbounded Love for such vile creatures as we
                            are.<lb/>And now my dear sister, as I a about to bid thee
                            farewell,<lb/>I must beg of thee to remember me in thy prayers; as
                            for<lb/>my part I shall never forget thee, but shall ever pray
                            that<lb/>thou mayest be preserved through all they trials on
                            this<lb/>earth, and be preserved by the Almighty’s protection
                            to<lb/>arrive safely on thy native shore, and finally that we
                            may<lb/>meet when our day’s work is done here, at the right hand<lb/>of
                            God the Father, amongst the lambs of His fold, and<lb/>never to part
                            again, which is the sincere prayer of thy<lb/>sister in the Lord, who
                            wishes thy welfare both here and<lb/>hereafter.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName key="cquaw1">CATHARINE
                                QUACHEMUT</persName></signed>
                            <salute><foreign xml:lang="iro">Neyuh
                                    Dinnaukomuh</foreign></salute><dateline><placeName key="newst"
                                    >New Stockbridge</placeName>, <date when="1805-08-19">8th mo.
                                    19th, 1805.</date></dateline></closer>

                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <pb n="119" facs="Ripley119"/>
                <p>This woman, who is a Christian, went three hundred<lb/>miles to <orgName key="pym"
                        >Philadelphia Yearly Meeting</orgName> in <date when="1802">1802</date>,
                    when I was<lb/>there, the last time I was in the country.</p>
                <closer><dateline>[<placeName key="utica">Utica</placeName>, <date when="1805-08-21"
                            >21st<lb/>8th mo. 1805.</date>]</dateline></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="emtry">
                <p>This day I took my leave of <persName key="skirk1">Samuel Kirkland’s</persName>
                    family,<lb/>whom I hope to meet in the Kingdom of our Lord Jesus<lb/>Christ, if
                    I see them no more in time. <persName key="ekirk1">Eliza</persName> was a
                    very<lb/>pleasant companion, and assuaged my grief, in bringing<lb/>me hither in
                    her father’s chaise, being almost spent: for I<lb/>have preached, prayed, and
                    inwardly groaned so mud,<lb/>hungering and thirsting after Righteousness for the
                    Indians<lb/>of the <placeName key="oneidss">South Settlement</placeName>,
                        <placeName key="oneida">Oneida</placeName>, <placeName key="stockbridge"
                        >Stockbridge</placeName>, and <placeName key="broth"
                        >Brother-<lb/>town</placeName>, that they may know the Love of Jesus, and
                    witness<lb/>the Power of God. I bid all those different Tribes
                    adieu,<lb/>believing my seed sown among them, shall be watered by<lb/>Him who
                    has richly provided for me, amidst so many<lb/>scenes of wo and poverty that my
                    eyes have beheld.</p>
                <p>The white people, whom I have mixed among, are<lb/>principally dead in trespasses
                    and sins; and have a worse<lb/>chance at salvation than their neighbouring
                    brethren,<lb/>whom they despise; because they conceive themselves a<lb/>little
                    better off than those; being able to contrive better<lb/>than they, who have
                    laboured under so many disadvanta-<lb/>ges from the want of the peculiar Smile
                    of an Indulgent<lb/>Parent, who will Justify all His Proceedings at the
                    last,<lb/>and require of us all according to what knowledge he im-<lb/>parts. My
                    friend <persName key="ekirk1">Eliza Kirkland</persName> copied me this
                    Address<lb/>at my request: for, I thought it proved the Indians are<lb/>capable
                    of improvement when their day of knowledge ap-<lb/>proaches by the Special
                    Providence of God, who setteth<lb/>up one and putteth down another, that it may
                    be seen by<lb/>all, He Ruleth on earth as well as in Heaven, being the<lb/>Only
                    Potentate, who seethe all things.</p>
                <closer><dateline>[<date when="1805-08-22">22d 8th mo. 1805</date>,<lb/><placeName
                            key="lfall">Little Falls</placeName>.]</dateline></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body>
                        <head>Speech of <persName key="peter1">Peter</persName>, the <orgName
                                key="pagan">Pagan</orgName>, alias Sategealithea.</head>
                        <p>A YOUNG Indian of the <orgName key="pagan">Pagan party</orgName>, in a
                            fit of in-<lb/>toxication, had attempted to stab with a tomahawk, a
                            white <lb/><pb n="120" facs="Ripley120"/>man who had uniformly been friendly to Indians;
                            he im-<lb/>mediately demanded redress, consequently a number of<lb/>the
                            young man’s friends waited on the offended person,<lb/>and one of them
                            made the following speech: it loses<lb/>much of its native beauty in the
                            translation, owing to the wide<lb/>difference between the idioms of the
                            two languages.</p>
                        <said who="undetermined"><p>Brothers of the <orgName key="oneida">Oneida
                                    Nation</orgName> here convened; open<lb/>your ears and
                                listen—you likewise, our brother the white<lb/>man, attend.</p>
                            <p>Brothers, the preservation of our lives, to the bright<lb/>shining of
                                the sun this morning, must be ascribed to God<lb/>our Maker, who
                                resides in the Heavens, but extends the<lb/>Arm of His Power to all
                                his creatures.</p>
                            <p>Brothers, let us all be thankful and duly acknowledge<lb/>the Mercy
                                of God our Creator.</p>
                            <p>Brothers, the occasion of the present meeting reminds<lb/>us of the
                                uncertainty of human life, and the instability of<lb/>man’s
                                resolutions. Our brother, the white man, thinks he<lb/>narrowly
                                escaped being killed by one of our men, so lately<lb/>as yesterday
                                morning, this young Indian man but a<lb/>little while ago, made a
                                solemn promise to refrain for<lb/>ever from the intoxicating
                                draught, which disarms the man<lb/>of his right mind. Alas! how
                                uncertain our enjoyments,<lb/>both as to life and its peace and
                                quiet! had blood been<lb/>spilled, this day would have been darkness
                                to us! and we<lb/>all buried in a flood of tears and grief! Let us
                                all again<lb/>thank God, that no vein has been opened to
                                endanger<lb/>human life; the wound of friendship can easily be hear
                                led.<lb/>It is truly a grief to us, that the abuse was given to a
                                man<lb/>who has always been friendly to us Indians, and
                                never<lb/>did them an injury since the time he first came by
                                their<lb/>fire-side. But other white-skins have whipped and
                                beaten<lb/>some of us poor Indians, because of our frailties and
                                fol-<lb/>lies; and chased them from their houses, with such
                                whips<lb/>as they use upon refractory horses. Alas! how are
                                the<lb/>times changed; in the days of the glory of our
                                forefathers<lb/>it was not so, the language then was <said>Brother
                                    walk in,<lb/>sit down, rest yourself, here is a dish, refresh
                                    yourself, <lb/><pb n="121" facs="Ripley121"/>and sleep by my fire-side.</said>
                                Brother White Man, be not<lb/>angry at what I say: though you
                                individually may wash<lb/>your hands in innocence, the white skin
                                race, as a body,<lb/>are become proud, and some of you too proud:
                                you glory<lb/>in your riches, your great and commodious houses,
                                your<lb/>large fields and your plenty; you wear a white shift,
                                and<lb/>sometimes ruffled; and you despise us Indians, for
                                our<lb/>poverty, our low huts, our scanty allowance, and our
                                dirty<lb/>shirts: but brother white skin, do your people think
                                that<lb/>God our Maker, who is in the Heavens, will make such
                                a<lb/>discrimination in the end? Will the White man, with
                                his<lb/>riches, his fine house, and his white clean shirt, fare
                                so<lb/>much better than the poor Indian in his mean
                                cottage,<lb/>with his dirty shirt, and tattered jacket? He looks
                                not<lb/>only on the outside, but carefully examines what is
                                within.<lb/>A foul spirit may be concealed in a body of
                                gorgeously<lb/>clothed; and a pure heart may reside unseen in a
                                body<lb/>covered only with a dirty, tattered garment. God
                                our<lb/>Maker will judge right, in respect to the worth of
                                souls,<lb/>whatever complexion the bodies wear. But Brother,
                                be<lb/>not angry, I have rather stepped aside from the
                                direct<lb/>object of our present meeting, and have been
                                addressing<lb/>you as in the place of the white skin race at large.
                                But<lb/>I am an Indian, and have lively feelings for my
                                nation,<lb/>especially when I see them abused. I don’t think it
                                is<lb/>right for the White people to give so much rum to
                                the<lb/>Indians, when they know the weakness of Indians;
                                and<lb/>that they are not blessed with that capacity and
                                resolution<lb/>which some white people possess, who can make use
                                of<lb/>strong drink, without inquiry to themselves, or
                                disturbing<lb/>the peace of society. But I must remark, lest you
                                should<lb/>be too much lifted up, that there are to be found
                                among<lb/>white skinned people, some, or now and then one, who
                                has<lb/>brought himself quite on a level with Indians. And if<lb/>we
                                Indians must bear this reproach of loving rum, the<lb/>white man
                                certainly loves money; which will deserve the<lb/>heaviest
                                punishment, I presume not to determine.</p>
                            <p>I consider myself as in the presence of God our Maker, <lb/><pb
                                n="122" facs="Ripley122"/>who resides in the Heavens. Our father (<persName
                                    key="skirk1">Mr. Kirkland</persName>)<lb/>the Minister, sees and
                                hears me. I can say, I believe he<lb/>is full of thoughts, and many
                                anxious ones have revolved<lb/>in his mind, since this council was
                                called.</p>
                            <p>Brother, enough has been said; what is your wish?<lb/>tell us
                                plainly! Do you want money to repair the breach<lb/>and heal the
                                wound made in your heart? or do you prefer<lb/>a confession from the
                                young man, who thus insulted you,<lb/>and a request for your
                                forgiveness, promising before all<lb/>the Chiefs, that he will never
                                do the like again? and can<lb/>you on these conditions, freely, and
                                from the heart, forgive<lb/>him? if so, the Chiefs will be
                                responsible for the young<lb/>man.”</p></said>
                        <p>The latter proposition was accepted; a noble and<lb/>generous confession
                            was made by the young Indian, and<lb/>he received the full pardon of the
                            White Man, to the great<lb/>joy of all present.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName key="ekirk1">ELIZA KIRKLAND</persName><lb/>[Copied
                                for her friend <persName key="dripl1">DOROTHY
                                RIPLEY</persName>.]</signed><dateline><date when="1805"
                            /></dateline></closer>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>I feel very languid with riding 22 miles in the stage,<lb/>yet have appointed a
                    meeting in the Presbyterian church,<lb/>which I held to great satisfaction, many
                    people attending<lb/>from curiosity, which I hope will be profited, and my
                    soul<lb/>free from their blood. As I was on my journey I knew<lb/>not how to get
                    the day over, but comforted myself with<lb/>this prospect, Eternity is my
                    resting place, where all my<lb/>joys will commence.</p>
                <p>A person of the name <persName key="alexa1">Alexander</persName>, who keeps
                    store<lb/>here, invited me to sup and lodge; thus the Lord still<lb/>follows me
                    with earthly mercies, which makes me pass<lb/>over many insults; and I had
                    rather ten thousand pierced<lb/>me by vile reports, as myself be found once in
                    the practice<lb/>of evil. To-morrow I purpose leaving here, though <persName
                        key="wcarr1">Wm.<lb/>Carr</persName>, Inn keeper, has told me if I tarry
                    with them over<lb/>first day, to have a meeting, it shall be no expense to
                    me.<lb/>My money I hope will hold out, that I may not want in<lb/>this quarter,
                    where it seems so scarce; for I am more<lb/><pb n="123" facs="Ripley123"/>ready to give to the
                    necessitous than receive from such<lb/>who offer it.</p>
                <p>A kind Quaker, who heard me in <placeName key="augus">Augusta</placeName>, gave
                    me<lb/>one dollar, which is the second I have received during five<lb/>weeks,
                    and I have relieved three or four with it. This<lb/>friend attended a meeting
                    before, and spoke admirably,<lb/>from the <quote type="biblical">Dry bones in
                        Ezekiel,</quote> which after he had done,<lb/>I arose and sanctioned it, as
                    life and power were in the<lb/>testimony. When I sat down, he got up, and told
                    that<lb/>people, his concern of this day had impressed his mind<lb/>twenty
                    years, which he had believed it his duty to come<lb/>and pay them a visit: but
                    the way never opened until that<lb/>time, which had relieved his spirit much. he
                    again sat<lb/>down, and I resumed my place, feeling great love and<lb/>faith,
                    with an ardent solicitude to benefit all present:<lb/>which stirred up the Gift
                    of my aged brother, whom the<lb/>Lord sent after me to help in His vineyard:
                    therefore,<lb/>our meeting continued long, and the people were favoured<lb/>to
                    hear the sound of his voice the third time, which quick-<lb/>ened the fire of
                    Celestial Love in my heart, so that I was<lb/>induced to supplicate the Throne
                    of Mercy for preserva-<lb/>tion, and an increase of faith and love for each,
                    when he<lb/>had closed his message, and then endeavoured to conclude<lb/>the
                    meeting: but, a Methodist preacher requested I would<lb/>permit him to say
                    something to the people, which I was<lb/>free to do, and he with tears told all
                    present, to <said>Trea-<lb/>sure up what they had heard; for Jesus Christ male
                        and<lb/>female were one. When you go home, don’t you say as I<lb/>said last
                        week, <said>It is only a woman.</said> My brethren and<lb/>sisters, I went
                        to hear this woman in a barn, and the Word<lb/>reached me powerfully, and
                        followed me home, and has<lb/>brought me miles to-day, to testify this among
                        you; for<lb/>before this, I did not think a woman ought to preach:
                        but<lb/>now I am convinced God has sent her to preach Jesus<lb/>Christ’s
                        Gospel.</said> This person sat down, and an Indian<lb/>sister rose
                    immediately, and testified thus, <said>If I was to<lb/>hold my tongue, and not
                        tell that it is thirty-three years<lb/>since I became a Christian, those
                        beams would speak <lb/><pb n="124" facs="Ripley124"/>against me: and I believe I may call
                        this my sister: for<lb/>I think it is in the scriptures, that strangers
                        shall be our<lb/>sisters, and I feel united to her.</said> Much more was
                    said<lb/>by this man and woman, which proved our gathering to-<lb/>gather was of
                    the Lord, and we at last parted as children<lb/>of one Heavenly Father, who made
                    us to love one another.</p>
                <closer><dateline>[<date when="1805-08-25">25th 8th mo. 1805</date>, <placeName
                            key="alban">Albany</placeName>.]</dateline></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <p>Yesterday I had a long tiresome ride, which wearied<lb/>me exceedingly, and
                    caused my spirits to feel great de-<lb/>pression, so that I knew not how to
                    endure under the<lb/>pressure of morality, having felt great darkness
                    covered<lb/>the minds of the people, as I passed along the road,
                    from<lb/>village to village, in the stage!</p>
                <p>As I had but three shillings left, I thought I would go<lb/>and ask <persName>J.
                        Taylor</persName> to give me lodgings: and he calmly re-<lb/>plied, <said>I
                        feel free, tell your wants to my wife and daugh-<lb/>ters: for it is my
                        desire they should be kind to you.</said> I<lb/>thought this a particular
                    mark of the Love of God to me,<lb/>whom I have unbounded favours from. I suppose
                    if my<lb/>money had not been spent, it would have been my inclina-<lb/>tion to
                    abide at an Inn.</p>
                <p>When I sat down, two letters were given me from<lb/>my precious friend <persName
                    key="aeame1">Abigail Eames</persName>, in <placeName key="nycit">New
                        York</placeName>, wherein<lb/>was testified great love and sympathy to a
                    little one, and<lb/>a fresh supply of money from her and <persName>J——
                        E———</persName>, who<lb/>had sent me a letter from <placeName key="nycit">N.
                        Y.</placeName> requesting me to call<lb/>upon an acquaintance of his in
                        <placeName key="alban">Albany</placeName> for the sum of six<lb/>dollars,
                    fearing my necessity would be great among the<lb/>Natives; but I could not feel
                    free to take it of another in<lb/>his name, lest a bad use should be made of it:
                    so he gave<lb/>it to a dear friend here, to hand me on my return, which<lb/>I am
                    unfeignedly thankful for, unto my God, He being the<lb/>moving cause of this
                    benevolence, and all other mercies<lb/>that I am blessed with.</p>
                <p>I could not sleep last night, for the Love of God to<lb/>me in those fresh
                    instances of His care, in continuing me<lb/>the favour of my old friends, whom I
                    esteem far above<lb/>rubies or fine gold. <persName key="aeame1">Abigail
                        Eames</persName> is entitled to a daugh-<lb/><pb n="125" facs="Ripley125"/>ter’s affection
                    from me, because in sickness she forsook<lb/>me not: but performed a mother’s
                    part to me, a stranger<lb/>in a strange land, when many passed by, and noticed
                    not<lb/>the sorrows that came on me, to qualify me to seek the<lb/>salvation of
                    mankind in general.</p>
                <p><placeName key="alban">Albany, New York State</placeName>, <date
                        when="1805-08-26">26th 8th mo. 1805.</date></p>
                <floatingText type="letter">
                    <body>
                        <opener>
                            <salute> MY ENDEARED FRIEND <persName key="aeame1">A.
                                E.</persName>,</salute></opener>
                        <p>LAST evening I returned from my visit to the Indians<lb/>of <placeName
                                key="oneida">Oneida</placeName>, <placeName key="oneidss">South
                                Settlement</placeName>, <placeName key="stockbridge"
                                >Stockbridge</placeName>, and <placeName key="broth"
                                >Brother-<lb/>town</placeName>, and I was presented with two letters
                            from thee,<lb/>whom I am united to by the strongest ties of
                            Christian<lb/>friendship, that will no doubt end in the full felicity
                            of<lb/>our spirits, when they enter into the City of our God.<lb/>Here
                            our joys are mixed with pain; our love with anxious<lb/>desire, that
                            causes bitterness of spirit, through a separa-<lb/>tion: but in Heaven,
                            one Object will attract our notice,<lb/>even the Spiritual Bridegroom,
                            who is now the Head of<lb/>the Invisible Church, as well as the Visible
                            One, which<lb/>we are members of. Since we were parted, many
                            have<lb/>been the baptisms my soul hath endured for the children<lb/>of
                            men, while I have travelled five hundred miles, and<lb/>have had above
                            thirty appointments, which were held in<lb/>the Court-house,
                            Steeple-houses, School-rooms, Barns,<lb/>Fields, or Woods; yet there has
                            been sufficient time for<lb/>me to think of my precious <persName
                                key="aeame1">A. E.</persName> although I assure thee, I<lb/>watch
                            with a godly jealousy over my natural affections,<lb/>lest I give to
                            thee, or any other sincere acquaintance,<lb/>more than is due to mutable
                            creatures. Thou must ac-<lb/>knowledge God, the Father of us each, is
                            entitled to our<lb/>ardency of soul, and continual thoughts; and I
                            believe, as<lb/>we are more weaned from terrestrial objects (in whom
                            we<lb/>should place no confidence) we shall have our minds
                            sub-<lb/>jected, and lay passively in His Hand, doing His Will,
                            and<lb/>suffering patiently for His sake, while employing the<lb/>whole
                            of our time, which I imagine though dost call
                                <said>One<lb/>business.</said> If I were to indulge myself in
                            expression at<lb/>this time, I should use strong tender words to thee:
                            but I <lb/><pb n="126" facs="Ripley126"/>must forbear, or else the past uneasiness will
                            return,<lb/>which Grace has conquered by her attractive charms,<lb/>when
                            solitary saying, I hope my precious friend hath not<lb/>forgot me.</p>
                        <p>When I came hither, a little money was acceptable<lb/>from such who were
                            disposed to watch my necessity, so<lb/>far distant as <placeName
                                key="nycit">New York.</placeName> Please to present my love
                            and<lb/>thanks to <persName>J. E.</persName> for his care in supplying
                            my present ne-<lb/>cessity; tell him I had not quite an half dollar, and
                            I<lb/>hope this will be returned when he is on an errand of love<lb/>for
                            my Master Jesus. I have been much tried with <persName>J.
                            T</persName>.<lb/>this evening. He told me scornfully, I might do to
                            in-<lb/>struct the Indians, or Blacks; but said, <said>As for
                                white<lb/>people, they have good preachers, and enough of
                                preach-<lb/>ing from them.</said> My answer was, I had rather teach
                            the<lb/>Indians and Africans, than white people: for their
                            souls<lb/>were more precious to me, having suffered much for
                            them.<lb/>He then told me thus, <said>You are on the Pinnacle, and as
                                for<lb/>your talents they are very small, though you think
                                much<lb/>of yourself.</said> Why he spoke after this manner was,
                            be-<lb/>cause I faithfully let him know, he was but half a
                            Chris-<lb/>tian, although he had been a Methodist almost
                            twenty<lb/>years. I made him no further answer, but went to
                            my<lb/>trunk, and prepared for leaving them to-morrow, while
                            he<lb/>continued talking all the time, which I suppose was
                            to<lb/>provoke me; and then he finished the day, with family<lb/>prayer.
                            I thought his place was, to lay his had on his<lb/>mouth, not daring to
                            utter words before God, whom I am<lb/>certain will repove him for this
                            conduct; but I pray the<lb/>Long suffering Father, not to lay this sin
                            to his charge, for<lb/>the sake of Him, who became a Sin Offering in our
                            stead,<lb/>that the folly of man might be passed over. I am
                            bound<lb/>under new obligations to the Lord, to serve Him with
                            my<lb/>reaming strength, while a probationer in time; for
                            His<lb/>Delivering Goodness, and Mercy, that is magnified in
                            my<lb/>preservation thus far: knowing that by my own ability,<lb/>it was
                            not possible to pass through such complicated ex-<lb/>ercises as have
                            fallen to my lot, during this year, which <lb/><pb n="127" facs="Ripley127"/>the annuals
                            of Eternity will shew forth, when my day’s<lb/>work is finished to the
                            Glory of King Jesus, my Everlast-<lb/>ing Spouse, whom I adore in the
                            temple of my soul. I<lb/>would rehearse to thee, many of the blessings
                            of my life,<lb/>since our separation; but hope thou wilt be spared, to
                            read<lb/>the dealings of my God in my journal; which I have
                            re-<lb/>corded to honour Him forever: as, He by His Spirit
                            di-<lb/>rected thereunto, when on the brink of the grave, raised<lb/>up
                            for the Special Purpose of shewing forth His Love,<lb/>Mercy, Power, and
                            Goodness, to the children of men.</p>
                        <closer><salute>With much affection I conclude, and remain thy sin-<lb/>cere
                                sister in the Lord Jesus Christ.</salute>
                            <signed><persName key="dripl1">DOROTHY RIPLEY</persName>.</signed>
                            <dateline><date when="1805-08-29">29th 8th mo. 1805</date>, <placeName
                                    key="checkPlace"/></dateline> on board of Sloop<lb/>William, to
                            <placeName key="nycit">New York</placeName>.</closer>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>I have been two nights in this sloop, which <persName key="lhack1">Captain<lb/>L.
                        Hackstaff</persName> commands. We have three passengers be-<lb/>sides
                    myself, and one is a complete Deist. Openly he<lb/>said, <said>I have been a
                        Methodist, Presbyterian, Univer-<lb/>salist, and now am a Deist.</said> I
                    told him I believed he<lb/>would make another change before he died yet:
                        <said>What<lb/>is that?</said> he cried, <said who="dripl1">A
                        Christian,</said> my answer was; for I<lb/>had felt uncommonly distressed
                    about him, before he so<lb/>daringly said he was thus changeable; and I have a
                    hope<lb/>that satan will be disappointed of this bold servant of his<lb/> whom
                    he employs to lay waste the Religion of the Re-<lb/>deemer of the World. I shall
                    say right, if add, I never<lb/>saw one so profane before, yet have faith in
                    Jesus Christ<lb/>to believe for him, knowing all things are possible to
                    him<lb/>that believeth; and it may be, that the Lord will deliver<lb/>his soul
                    out of the gin, which he blindly has been insnar-<lb/>ed with; being in gross
                    darkness, and under the power<lb/>of temptation. It is probable that we shall
                    get into <placeName key="nycit">New<lb/>York</placeName> in a few hours, and
                    then his language will not cause<lb/>my soul to be exceeding sorrowful! no; I
                    shall be with<lb/>some of the righteous, where we shall recount the
                    Lord's<lb/>tender Mercies since our separation. How dismal is my<lb/> situation,
                    when I am but one day with the ungodly!<lb/><pb n="128" facs="Ripley128"/>What then would
                    Eternity be, if it were to spend with<lb/>them? O for a pure spirit! that I may
                    behold my God<lb/>forever! O for an holy soul and body! that I may
                    adore<lb/>Him, who by His Wisdom, strengthened me, to <quote type="biblical"
                        >Choose<lb/>the good, and refuse the evil.</quote> This is a beautiful
                    river<lb/>we are going down: but my heart is in Heaven, and all<lb/>earthly
                    things are too mean to divert me (this moment)<lb/>from my inheritance, which
                    fadeth not away. My rest<lb/>draws near, and sorrow will soon take its flight,
                    and joys<lb/>rapay the tedious days I mourn for sinners.</p>
                <p>In all my ways, I long to speak good of the Name of<lb/>my God, who leads me by
                    His Spirit, and protects me from<lb/>the rage of the dragon, who insults me
                    often by his agents,<lb/>when I am obliged to reprove them for sin, and
                    exhort<lb/>them to repentance, and believe on the <quote type="biblical">Lamb of
                        God<lb/>which taketh away the sin of the world.</quote> I am under<lb/>a
                    necessity of paying my vow unto the Lord; of render-<lb/> ing Him my grateful
                    thanks for the preservation of my<lb/>life;and although my stock of raiment is
                    reduced much,<lb/> by contributing to the wants of my Indian sisters; yet
                    I<lb/>am blessed with this consideration, that my heart was<lb/> open to relieve
                    them with such as the Lord made me a<lb/>steward over: therefore, I may expect
                    the <quote type="biblical">True Riches<lb/>of His Kingdom</quote> in return, as
                    no one hitherto hath been<lb/>kind enough to give me the last piece of raiment,
                    in tra-<lb/>velling six hundrend and sixty miles. Array me with<lb/>the royal
                    vestment of innocence, that I may worship with<lb/>the angels, Thee, whom my
                    soul loveth intensely: so that<lb/>at Thy request, I can follow Thee every
                    where, strength-<lb/>ened by Thee, to complete that which Thou dost
                    design<lb/>me to do, for Thy poor dying mortals like myself, who<lb/>live, to
                    ripen for Eternity; or, as fewel, will be cast into<lb/>the fiery furnace, where
                    there is wailing and gnashing of<lb/>teeth.</p>
                <p>In seven weeks, I have finished this arduous journey,<lb/>setting off alone, in
                    the Name of Abraham's God, who<lb/>took care of him, when he went forth at the
                    Voice of His<lb/>Command, to view the land, which afterwards he gave him
                    <lb/><pb n="129" facs="Ripley129"/> by promise to reward his faith, and crown his hope;
                    his<lb/>children were inheriting it, from generation to generation,
                    until<lb/>they were driven out of it, for the lack of wisdom, and<lb/>rebellion.
                    O my soul! praise God for the Gift of Faith,<lb/>and obedience to live in His
                    Fear, so shalt thou possess<lb/>the Land of Light, Life, and Peace, which
                    Abraham's obe-<lb/>dience entitled him to forever, which was typified by
                    the<lb/>outward Canaan, that his seed did inherit, by the special<lb/>Promise of
                    Jehovah, who conversed with him from Hea-<lb/>ven. I am surrounded with angelic
                    spirits, who seem to<lb/>encourage me to be faithful a little longer, then
                    Abraham<lb/>the father of the faithful, will see one, who went out at
                    the<lb/>Command of God, not knowing whither she went, but as<lb/>the Spirit
                    directed her feet in righteousness, to seek the<lb/> lost sheep of the house of
                    Israel.</p>
                <closer><dateline>[<placeName key="nycit">New York,</placeName>
                        <date when="1805-08-31">31st 8th<lb/>mo. 1805.</date>]</dateline></closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
