<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei-print.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="global.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>Some Account of Rachel Coope (Journal B): Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>Emma Remsberg</name>
                </respStmt>

                <sponsor>Tri-Co Digital Humanities Initiative</sponsor>
                <funder>Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 63 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>This work is the property of the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore
                        College. It may be copied freely by individuals for personal use, research,
                        and teaching (including distribution to classes) as long as this statement
                        of availability is included in the text. It may be linked to freely in
                        Internet editions of all kinds, including for—profit works.</p>
                    <p>Publishers, libraries, and other information providers interested in
                        providing this text in a commercial or non—profit product or from an
                        information server must contact Swarthmore College for licensing and cost
                        information.</p>
                    <p> Scholars interested in changing or adding to these texts by, for example,
                        creating a new edition of the text (electronically or in print) with
                        substantive editorial changes, may do so with the permission of Swarthmore
                        College. This is the case whether the new publication will be made available
                        at a cost or free of charge.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2014">2014</date>
                <idno type="local">SW_RC1805b</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Native Americans and Quakers: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>Journals (Ms) Coope</collection>
                        <idno>Mss003/043</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>35 pp. (1 volume)</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Rachel Coope manuscript is housed at Friends Historical Library, on the
                    campus of Swarthmore College. In the fall semester of 2010, Swarthmore students
                    enrolled in English 50A (“Reading Red, White, and In-Between in Early American
                    Literature”) transcribed this manuscript as part of a larger project to make the
                    library’s rich store of Quaker Indian mission writings more accessible. The
                    project was designed by Christopher Densmore, Curator of Friends Historical
                    Library, and Keat Murray, Visiting Assistant Professor of English. Student
                    transcribers included: . Transcriptions were compiled and edited in the present
                    form by Professor Murray. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> The transcribers and editor attempted to render the author’s orthography and
                    grammar as they appear on the page of his journal, even when the author’s own
                    spelling and usage are inconsistent. Additionally, many questions remain about
                    spelling the names of his Quaker acquaintances, individual Native Americans who
                    populate his journal, and Indian villages and towns. The transcribers and editor
                    attempted to remain faithful to the author’s Anglicized spellings in all cases. </p>
                <p>Journals "a" and "b" represent transcriptions of Rachel Coope’s actual diaries.
                    Journal "a" her “esteemed parents”; however, her mother died before the letter
                    was written, and so it may have been meant for her parents­in­law, to whom she
                    was deeply attached) copied over twice. No version of this letter is included in
                    journal four. Except for this, the differences were small, such as variance in
                    phrasing and spelling, and not in content. It seems as though journal "a"
                    preceded journal "b"; it is less polished. The handwriting seems more rushed and
                    the paper size varies, while in journal "b", the handwriting is neater, and the
                    paper used is consistent. It is possible that these, especially journal three,
                    could have been handwritten by Coope.</p>
                <p>The author of the original journal does not include page numbers on the
                    manuscript; the page numbers have been interpolated by the transcribers to
                    correspond with the manuscript sheets.</p>
            </editorialDecl>

        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written in <date when="1807">1807</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Society of Friends -- Missions</item>
                        <item>Indians of North America -- Missions</item>
                        <item>Quakers -- Pennsylvania -- Diaries</item>
                        <item>Seneca Indians</item>
                        <item>Philadelphia Yearly Meeting of the Relgious Society of Friends</item>
                        <item>Voyages and Travels</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>

        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>

        <body>

            <div type="narrative">
                <pb n="1" facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_01"/>
                <head>Some notes kept of a journey from <placeName key="bradf">Bradford</placeName>,
                    the place of our late re-<lb/>sidence, to <placeName key="tunes"
                        >Tunecessah</placeName> on the <geogName key="alleg">Alle-<lb/>geny
                        River</geogName> in York State</head>

                <p>In the fall of 1804 my dear Hus<lb/>band &amp; myself informed fnd s of
                        <orgName>Bradford<lb/> Moly Meeting</orgName>, of a concern that had for
                    some<lb/> time attended our Minds, of offering<lb/> ourselves to go and reside
                    some time<lb/> among the Indian Natives near the<lb/>
                    <geogName key="alleg">Allegeny River</geogName>, to endeavor to instruct<lb/>
                    them in Agriculture, Spinning, Dairy,<lb/> &amp;c, and having obtained the Unity
                    and <lb/> Sympathy of our fnd s at home, and also<lb/> the concurrence of the
                    Yearly Meetings<lb/> Committee on Indian Affairs, <persName key="hjack2"
                        >Hannah<lb/> Jackson</persName> likewise having a minute<lb/> from
                        <orgName>Newgarden Monthly Meeting</orgName>, and<lb/> the concurrence of
                    the Committee to<lb/> accompany us. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-05-20">1805<lb/>5 one 20 and 2nd of the
                        Week</date><placeName key="bradf"/></dateline>
                <p>After a time of comfortable quiet<lb/> wherein we were favoured to feel the<lb/>
                    overshadowing of divine regard to<lb/>
                    <pb n="2" facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_02"/> be near, a considerable number of our near
                    relations<lb/> and fnd s being present, we took leave of<lb/> them in the
                    feeling embraces of endearing<lb/> love, <persName key="ncoop1">Father
                        Coope</persName> &amp; Brother Ezra bearing<lb/> us company to <persName
                        key="membr1">M. Embrees</persName>, there we<lb/> took an Affectionate
                    farewell of dear<lb/> James and his Wife, and we parted with<lb/> Father, a
                    close trial, tears flowed in an<lb/> abundance under a feeling sympathy for<lb/>
                    him, &amp; ardent desires were raised in my<lb/> heart, that he might be
                    enriched with<lb/> that Peace, now in his lonesome and<lb/> advanced Stage of
                    Life, which is the<lb/> precious enjoyment of all the sincere<lb/> hearted.
                    Brother continuing with us<lb/> to <persName key="wtrum1">Wm.
                    Trueman</persName>’s 11 miles, my husband<lb/> and Brother lodged in the Waggon,
                    Cousin<lb/> and myself were more comfortably ac<lb/>commodated with a good Bed,
                    I soon<lb/> fell asleep, but on wakeing about 3 the<lb/> recollection of the
                    parting season so forc-<lb/>ably revived, that Tears flowed from<lb/> my Eyes,
                    &amp; sleep departed. Thou Oh my<lb/> God has at Seasons been pleased in
                    thy<lb/> unmerited goodness to make bare thy<lb/> Arm, and in times of trial
                    afford sweet<lb/> consolation as patience was abode in,<lb/>
                    <pb n="3" facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_03"/> under an humbling sense thereof may<lb/> I
                    a little interceede for the renewed con-<lb/>tinuence of thy love.<lb/>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-05-21"> 21st 3day </date><placeName key="checkPlace"/>
                </dateline>
                <p>A fine morning, after a smart<lb/> shower, takeing breakfast, we parted<lb/> with
                    our Brother, and set off at 6, we<lb/> went to the Rising Sun Tavern 11m
                    were<lb/> we fed our horses, and took some re-<lb/>freshment ourselves in the
                    Waggon, then<lb/> pursueing our Journey to <persName key="wbrin1">Wm
                        Brinton</persName>’s<lb/> 8m , but neither he nor his Wife being at<lb/>
                    home we proposed going on, but the<lb/> Grand Mother, who was there on a visit,
                    &amp;<lb/> daughter insisted on our going in, an<lb/> excellent dish of Coffee
                    was soon pre-<lb/>pared which was very grateful, we<lb/> then proceeded on &amp;
                    got to our Bro-<lb/>ther <persName key="gjohn1">Griffith John</persName>'s 4m
                    about 4 OClock<lb/> where we lodged, <persName key="wembr1">Wm Embree</persName>
                    met us here<lb/> agreeably to appointment and went<lb/> with us through the
                    Journey, he put<lb/> his Horse to the Waggon which with<lb/> our two made three
                    in number,<lb/> 23 miles to day</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-05-21">22nd</date> 4th day <placeName key="eliza"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>breakfasted and set off<lb/> half past 5, Brother and Sister bore us<lb/> company
                    to <placeName key="lanca">Lancaster</placeName>, we stoped at<lb/><pb n="4"
                        facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_04"/>
                    <persName key="jgibb1">James Gibbon</persName>’s door and bid farewell,<lb/> at
                        <placeName key="lanca">Lancaster</placeName> we fed our Horses and got<lb/>
                    some necessaries for our Journey, then<lb/> set off, Brother going a piece to
                    put us<lb/> in the right Road, 9 miles from <placeName key="lanca"
                        >Lancaster</placeName><lb/> we crossed <geogName key="lcone1">little
                        Canestoga</geogName>, we proceded<lb/> along being entire strangers, the
                    Roads<lb/> exceedingly bad and cut in holes with<lb/> heavy loaded Waggons, and
                    very muddy,<lb/> tho the Country was beautiful, fine grain<lb/> and clover,
                    crossed by <geogName key="chiqu">Chickisalango</geogName><lb/> a large stream 9
                    miles from <placeName key="lanca">Lancaster</placeName>, got<lb/> some
                    refreshment for ourselves and horses<lb/> at <placeName key="helle">Heller's
                        Tavern</placeName>, then proceeded on our<lb/> Journey to <placeName
                        key="eliza">Elisabeth Town</placeName> 9 miles, where<lb/> we arrived a
                    while before sunset, the<lb/> Roads still bad, the land good, tho more<lb/>
                    hilly than nearer <placeName key="lanca">Lancaster</placeName>. My
                    atten-<lb/>tion has been so taken up with viewing<lb/> the Roads and Country
                    that I have had<lb/> but little serious reflection, yet have<lb/> not felt much
                    unpleasant sensations, nor<lb/> enjoyed so large a Portion of that precious<lb/>
                    consolation which my soul often de-<lb/>sires, O that I may abide in the
                    patience<lb/> with mine Eye single to him whose Fa-<lb/><pb n="5"
                        facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_05"/> therly protection is as a Wall around<lb/> about
                    those who are sincerely devoted<lb/> to serve him, where ever their lot<lb/> may
                    be cast. we lodged at the <placeName key="beart">Bear Tavern</placeName> 25
                    miles.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-05-23">23 rd </date>. 5 th <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>day A fine Morning, rose early,<lb/> set out about 4, crossed <geogName
                        key="conmo">Conowago moun<lb/>tain</geogName> and <geogName key="concr"
                        >creek</geogName>, the Hills exceedingly Rocky, the<lb/> Roads rather better
                    near <placeName key="middl">Middletown</placeName>, some of<lb/> the land good,
                    we forded <geogName key="sweet">Sweetaraw Creek</geogName><lb/> a large wide
                    water and so deep as to run<lb/> into the Waggon Bed, we got to <placeName
                        key="middl">Middletown</placeName><lb/> in Dauphin County to Breakfast 8
                    miles<lb/> here I sent a few lines home by a fnd from<lb/>
                    <placeName key="phila">Philadelphia</placeName>. 9 OClock proceeded on our<lb/>
                    Journey, through a beautiful Valley and<lb/> very fertile Country for several
                    Miles,<lb/> about 11 we got in sight of the River, the<lb/> Country on the right
                    was soon after ob-<lb/>structed by a large Ridge of Limestone<lb/> Hills, the
                    Rocks in places were 30 or 40 feet<lb/> high, the Ridge continued till we came
                    near on <del>the</del><lb/> bank of the River. got in sight of <placeName
                        key="harrisb">Harrisburg</placeName><lb/> about 1 OClock, 9 miles, we stoped
                    under the<lb/> Shade of a Tree, bought grass for the Horses,<lb/> and took some
                    refreshment in the Waggon.<lb/> ½ past 2 proceeded on, we crossed a
                        small<lb/><pb n="6" facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_06"/> Creek called <geogName
                        key="paxto">Paxtang</geogName> over an Elegant<lb/> Stone Bridge, then
                    passed through <placeName key="harrisb">Haris-<lb/>burgh</placeName> a
                    considerable Town, and beautifully<lb/> Situated, having a fine prospect of
                    the<lb/> River, we then travelled 7 miles close on the<lb/> Bank of Sd River,
                    with A considerable distance of a<lb/> fine Cultivated Country on the Right,
                    the<lb/> River flowing Close on the left, and a great<lb/> many Locosts Trees in
                    full bloom on each<lb/> hand made the prospect truly delightful,<lb/> but after
                    a calm sometimes comes a storm,<lb/> we now crossed <geogName key="fishi"
                        >Fishing Creek</geogName> a large<lb/> stream, and then for three Miles it
                    was a-<lb/>stonishing to behold the romantic appear-<lb/>ance, one rough stony
                    Cartway near<lb/> the River and great Rocks from 400<lb/> to 600 feet high
                    hanging, as it were,<lb/> over our heads, we then crossed <geogName key="stonc"
                        >Stony<lb/> Creek</geogName> and put up at <geogName key="elder">Elders
                        Tavern</geogName> 10 m <lb/> we are now at the foot of the <geogName
                        key="bluem">blue Moun-<lb/>tain</geogName> having gone round it by the
                    side<lb/> of <placeName key="susqueh">Susquehanna</placeName>. it is computed to
                    be<lb/> 600 feet high, and I could scarcely keep<lb/> my Eyes of it, the
                    prospect was so<lb/> Wonderful 27 miles</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="7" facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_07"/>
                <dateline><date when="1805-05-24">24 th </date> 6th day <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>

                <p> Started this Morning about 4,<lb/> had a very good road tho a little hilly<lb/>
                    with some spots of Cultivated land for about<lb/> 2 miles, then Crossed
                        <geogName key="clark">Clarks Creek</geogName> and<lb/> prepared to ascend
                        <geogName key="petem">Peters Mountain</geogName>,<lb/> the road pretty good,
                    we were 1¼ hour go-<lb/>ing over it, called two Miles, it was<lb/> remarkable to
                    see several lively springs<lb/> near its summit. Shortly after we left<lb/> this
                    Mountain we crossed <geogName key="powel">Powells Creek</geogName><lb/> a large
                    stream, and had an excellent<lb/> Road to <placeName key="halif"
                        >Hallifax</placeName> a small Town, 10 miles,<lb/> here we got Breakfast and
                    are in sight of the River. Some parts of the<lb/> last stage Cultivated, the
                    grain chiefly Rye,<lb/> some fields of a changable Red with some<lb/> Clover.
                    the Soil gravelly and of a Red-<lb/>ist colour. Started at 9, crossed <geogName
                        key="armst">Armstrong<lb/> Creek</geogName>, passed along a very rough
                    road,<lb/> with some rain, close on the River, at the<lb/> foot of <geogName
                        key="berry">Barry's Mountain</geogName>, then crossed <geogName key="wicon"
                        >Wi-<lb/>kinisky Creek</geogName> a stream as large as <geogName key="brand"
                        >Brandywine</geogName>,<lb/> we now began to get among the Pines,<lb/> a few
                    places, here and there Cultivated,<lb/> the Soil not very productive, poor
                    look-<lb/>ing Houses, Stoped by the side of the Road<lb/> and refreshed
                    ourselves out of the Waggon 10m.<lb/> Started at 2 had 3 miles of a good Road
                        to<lb/><pb n="8" facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_08"/>
                    <geogName key="mahmo">Mahantango Mountain</geogName>, ½ an hour took us<lb/>
                    over, we then crossed <geogName key="mahat">Mahantango Creek</geogName><lb/>
                    over a high Frame Bridge, this is a longer<lb/> stream, we were then a little
                    surprised<lb/> with the Road turning so much easterly,<lb/> but we found it was
                    to lead us through<lb/> a gap in a Mountain, we have had a num-<lb/>ber of such
                    gaps to go through between<lb/> great Mountains, indeed for many miles<lb/> back
                    there is a very little but Mountains.<lb/> we got to a Dutch house a while
                    before<lb/> night, 10 miles, but every thing looked<lb/> so dirty, that with
                    their leave, we prepar-<lb/>ed out of the Waggon, our own Supper<lb/> and went
                    to bed, but there was our<lb/> greatest mortification, we had not<lb/> been long
                    in bed, before the Landlady, sent<lb/> two Men who were travelers into<lb/> our
                    Room to lodge in another Bed,<lb/> My Husband and Wm sleeping in the<lb/> Waggon
                    as usual, we lay very quiet<lb/> and rose before day. 30 miles</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-05-25">25</date> 7th day <placeName key="milto"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>had a very rough Road 4 miles to<lb/> Hoonston’s Tavern, where we wished<lb/> to
                    have gotten last evening, we then<lb/> crossed green Briar Creek &amp; passed
                        along<lb/><pb n="9" facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_09"/> through the Woods, except a
                    small Culti-<lb/>vated spot where, for a rarity, we saw<lb/> some wheat growing,
                    came on the bank<lb/> of <geogName key="mahac">Mahony Creek</geogName>, went up
                    the side of it<lb/> a Considerable distance between won-<lb/>derful Mountains,
                    it is a very large<lb/> Creek, after crossing it we came to <geogName
                        key="mahan">Ma-<lb/>hony Mountain</geogName> it took us near and<lb/> hour
                    to go over, the north side of it was<lb/> amazingly steep, stoped 11 miles fed
                    our<lb/> Horses, and made some Chocolate for Break-<lb/>fast, started ½ past 9
                    had a very Rough<lb/> Road crossed <geogName key="shamo">Shomokin
                        Creek</geogName>, then pass-<lb/>ed through <placeName key="sunb"
                        >Sunbury</placeName>, the Capital of <placeName key="north"
                        >North-<lb/>umberland County</placeName>, we then crossed<lb/> the East
                    branch of <geogName key="susqu">Susquehanna</geogName>, ½ an<lb/> hour Ferrying
                    over, 1 mile across.<lb/> Fed in <placeName key="north1">Northumberland
                        Town</placeName> 8 miles,<lb/> thence through rather a barren Soil, tho<lb/>
                    considerably cultivated, crossed <geogName key="chill">Chilis-<lb/>quaque
                        Creek</geogName>, a considerable stream,<lb/> got on the West branch of
                        <geogName key="susqu">Susquehanna</geogName>,<lb/> the land good, as was
                    also the road, reach-<lb/>ed <placeName key="milto">Milton</placeName> a small
                    Town about 6, 12 miles<lb/> put up at <placeName key="brady">Brady's
                        Tavern</placeName>, but I being very<lb/> unwell, soaked my feet, took a
                    little medicine<lb/><pb n="10" facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_10"/> and went to Bed
                    without my supper,<lb/> before Sunset. Cousin being very kind<lb/> in waiting on
                    me, it was a time of<lb/> much Rude Company here, and they<lb/> were drinking
                    and Fighting most of<lb/> the night so that we were very much<lb/> disturbed,
                    indeed their Conduct did<lb/> so impress my Mind with Sorrow, that<lb/> I could
                    not refrain from Weeping.<lb/> 31 miles</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-05-26">26 th </date> and 1st of the Week, <placeName
                        key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>set out at 4,<lb/> traveled several miles on the bank<lb/> of the River, good
                    road, cool Morn-<lb/>ing, considerable white frost.<lb/> Stoped at <persName
                        key="dshan1">David Shannon</persName>'s 8 miles, where<lb/> we got a very
                    good Breakfast and<lb/> grain for our Horses. As soon as we<lb/> got into the
                    House I discouvered<lb/> something was the matter with our<lb/> Landlord, he
                    made such heavy moans,<lb/> and querying of him what Ailed him<lb/> he said that
                    he was about building<lb/> and that he had thought so much a<lb/>bout it, that
                    he was got low in his mind,<lb/><pb n="11" facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_11"/> I told
                    him he had a fine Barn, a<lb/> good looking place, and meterials<lb/> ready for
                    Building his House, and<lb/> that I saw no sufficient cause for him to<lb/> be
                    discouraged, he said he had been<lb/> a hardworking Man, and helped<lb/> through
                    many difficulties by the<lb/> hand of Providence, but all was<lb/> as nothing to
                    him now, we told him<lb/> that hand that hand which had hi-<lb/>therto helped
                    him, would continue<lb/> to help if he did but rely upon, and<lb/> put his trust
                    in it, he said he had<lb/> strove with all his might but he<lb/> could not help
                    his situation, if he<lb/> was as he once was, and saw one<lb/> of us as he is
                    now, he would have<lb/> thought we might have helped it<lb/> but we do not know
                    untill we are<lb/> tryed. he seemed very sensible of his<lb/> situation and
                    possessed of tender feel-<lb/>ings, indeed I felt a near sympathy<lb/> for him,
                    and my Mind was impressed<lb/> with more of a lively sense of human<lb/><pb
                        n="12" facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_12"/> frailty, excepted aided and
                    supported<lb/> by an Almighty Power, than I had<lb/> heretofore known. ½ past 8
                    pro-<lb/>ceeded, passed through a small Village,<lb/> crossed <geogName
                        key="muncr">Munsy Creek</geogName>, a large stream,<lb/> and got to
                        <persName key="welli1">William Ellis</persName>’s ½ past 12,<lb/> 10 miles.
                    They were gone to meeting<lb/> and it seemed pleasant to be among<lb/> fnd s
                    again, having scarcely had the<lb/> sight of one since we left <placeName
                        key="lanca">Lancaster</placeName>.<lb/> this Afternoon I wrote home,
                    and<lb/> in the evening the family were col-<lb/>lected, and <persName
                        key="welli2">William Ellis</persName> Junior read<lb/> several Chapters in
                    the Testament,<lb/> wherein a Comfortable time of silence<lb/> was witnessed to
                    prevail. 18 miles</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-05-27">27 th </date> 2nd day, <placeName key="willi1"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>this morning washed some Clothes<lb/> 3 OClock PM set out on our Journey,
                    had<lb/> a good Road tho mostly through the Woods,<lb/> Crossed <geogName
                        key="loyac">Loyalsock</geogName> a large Water, got<lb/> to <placeName
                        key="willi1">William's port</placeName>, the Capital of <placeName
                        key="lycom1">Lycoming County</placeName><lb/> put up at <persName
                        key="jwint1">James Winter</persName>s, where we were<lb/> Comfortably
                    accommodated, we had the<lb/> Company of <persName key="welli1">William
                        Ellis</persName>, who was there<lb/> on business 12 miles</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="13" facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_13"/>
                <dateline><date when="1805-05-28">28 th </date> 3rd day, <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>

                <p> Started this Morning a<lb/>little after 4, in about 1 mile we stoped<lb/>at a
                    house to by buy some Grain for<lb/>the Horses, being informed that it<lb/>was so
                    scarce an Article further a<lb/>head that we should not be able to<lb/>procure
                    any as we went along, Cou-<lb/>sin and I steped into a little house by<lb/>the
                    Side of the land; while the Men were geting<lb/> the grain, where we met with a
                    Fa-<lb/>mily from Chester County, Baily's by name<lb/> who invited us to eat
                    Breakfast, which<lb/>kindness we accepted of, and proceed-<lb/> ing we crossed
                        <geogName key="lycom">Lycoming Creek</geogName> a large<lb/>Water, then
                    passed through a small<lb/>Village called <placeName key="newbe1"
                        >Newberry</placeName>, and asscend-<lb/>ed the Hill, then went through
                    a<lb/>Wilderness Country very Moutainous<lb/>5 miles to one Brook's, the Men
                    took<lb/>their Breakfast of a Cup of Milk and<lb/>Rye bread while the Horses
                    were feeding<lb/>½ past 9 started, a very rough Road to<lb/> the foot of the
                        <geogName key="allmo">Allegany</geogName> 6 miles, where<lb/> we fed the
                    Horses, had a Rock for our<lb/>Table, some of our Waggon store, with<lb/><pb
                        n="14" facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_14"/>excellent Water that issued from
                    to-<lb/>ward the Top of the Mountain, serv-<lb/>ed to refresh the Weary
                    Travelers,<lb/>but no peace for them, nor the Horses,<lb/>by reason of such
                    swarms of little<lb/>Knats. ½ past one we moved forward,<lb/>the Road excessive
                    Stony, computed<lb/>to be 6½ Miles over, which we were<lb/>3¾ hours <del>a</del>
                    going, we put up at<lb/>Hookens Just at the otherside, were<lb/>were some of the
                    tallest Pines, Hem-<lb/>locks &amp;c that I ever saw 17½ miles</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-05-29">29</date><lb/>4th : <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>Started about 4, after going<lb/>over a hill, had a very rough<lb/>swampy road
                    along a Valley between<lb/>great Mountains, through such an a-<lb/>mazing
                    thicket of Pines &amp;c, and the<lb/>wheather being a little Cloudy, that
                    it<lb/>looked almost dark, Cousin and I<lb/>I haveing prepared ourselves
                        with<lb/><unclear>Stoves</unclear>, while we were traveling<lb/>along before
                    the Waggon, we heard<lb/>a noise, and looking back to see what was<lb/>the
                    matter, we found, that as the Waggon<lb/>
                    <pb n="15" facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_15"/>was going down a Steep, and
                    excessively<lb/> Muddy place, a Bed that we had tyed<lb/>up in a Blanket, but
                    was not suffi-<lb/> ciently secured, Sliped out of the<lb/>fore end of the
                    Waggon down into<lb/>the Mud, and a bottle of Milk that<lb/>we had purchased for
                    Breackfast<lb/>which was stuffed within the Blanket<lb/>sliped out, yet it
                    recieved no da-<lb/>maged, we took the blanket of the<lb/>bed and tyed it up in
                    the Sheet, and<lb/>proceeded on, Washing the Blan-<lb/>ket at the first Creek we
                    came to,<lb/>and sufficiently securing it on the<lb/>Top of the Waggon Cover to
                    dry, we<lb/>presently came on a lively stream<lb/>of Water which followed the
                    Road for<lb/>Several Miles Crossing it a great many<lb/>times, the last of which
                    times the<lb/>bridge being gone, I observed a sap-<lb/>ling across the streem
                    about 2 yards<lb/>from the Water, and on attempting<lb/>to go over on sd. tree
                    when I got a-<lb/>bout ½ way; the log shaking, my foot<lb/>sliped, and in I
                    went, tho the Water<lb/>was but shallow yet I had to wade through<lb/>tho it was
                    early to stop for Breakfast<lb/>
                    <pb n="16" facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_16"/>Yet as I had got my feet Wet, we<lb/>
                    concluded to make a fire and get<lb/>our Breakfast, and feed the horses,
                    continu-<lb/>ing through the Wilderness we came to<lb/><geogName key="pinec"
                        >Pine Creek</geogName>, in five or 6 miles crossed<lb/>it thirteen times,
                    got to Morris's Mills<lb/>about 12 OClock 12½ Miles from where<lb/>we lodged.
                    When at <persName key="welli1">William Ellis</persName>'s we<lb/>met with
                        <persName key="fking1">Francis King</persName>'s daughter, and<lb/>she told
                    us we could not get the Wag-<lb/>gon through the Wilderness to her
                    Fa-<lb/>thers, and at this Mill we recieved<lb/>the like information, which
                    account<lb/>was very discouraging, after feeding<lb/>our Horses &amp; geting
                    some dinner we<lb/>set off, half past two, Cousin &amp; I set<lb/>of on foot,
                    having a Mountain to as-<lb/>scend we got a great distance before<lb/>the
                    Waggon, <del>and</del> and stoping at one<lb/> Jackson's, until the Waggon came
                    up,<lb/>they appeared glad to see us, tho no ac-<lb/>quaintance, the woman said
                    she was pleased<lb/> to see us so chearfull, but her hus-<lb/>band said it would
                    take us 6 weeks<lb/> to get to <persName key="fking1">King</persName>s
                    Settlement with the<lb/>Waggon, he advised us to call at <persName key="mwils1"
                        >Moses<lb/>Wilson</persName>'s and get his Son to assist us in<lb/><pb
                        n="17" facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_17"/> getting along, we then Crossed <geogName
                        key="pinec">Pine<lb/>Creek</geogName> at the 2 nd fork, stoped a few
                    mi-<lb/>nutes to see <persName key="sbabs1">Sampson Babb</persName>, who
                    re-<lb/>moved from Chester County, and got<lb/>to <persName key="jyarn1">James
                        Yarnall</persName>'s, 6 miles, his Father's<lb/>name was <persName
                        key="dyarn1">Daniel</persName>, and used to live<lb/> somewhere about
                        <placeName key="middl"> Middletown</placeName> in<lb/>Delaware County, we
                    lodged here 18½ m</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-05-30">30 th </date> 5th day <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>set of at 5 OClock,<lb/>proposing to get our Breakfast<lb/>at <persName
                        key="mwils1">Moses Wilson</persName>'s which was 5 miles<lb/>on our way and
                    the first house<lb/>we would come to, but when<lb/>we arrived at it, the house
                    was<lb/>empty, and no body left to en-<lb/>quire of, for here we were to
                    get<lb/>furter information, but being<lb/>a <del>little</del> cold, and a great
                    way before<lb/>the Waggon, we made bold to open<lb/>the door and go in, where we
                    found<lb/>a little fire, which we kindled<lb/>up and sat warming ourselves<lb/>
                    near half an hour before the Wag-<lb/>gon came. then on confering togather<lb/>
                    concluded to go on at a Venture, by a Map of<lb/>the Road, our kind fnd
                        <persName key="tstew1">Thomas Stewardson</persName> had<lb/><pb n="18"
                        facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_18"/>furnished us with, we knew that we had left
                    the<lb/>State Road, we pursued our Journey, and in<lb/>about half a Mile we came
                    to a fork where tak-<lb/>ing the left hand road, went on a piece look-<lb/>ing
                    every way for a house, through very<lb/>swampy Woods, we presently<lb/>came to
                    a<lb/>2 nd fork, we were now entirely at a loss<lb/> which path to take, but
                    after going along<lb/>both roads a considerable distance, we<lb/>were informed
                    where <persName key="mwils1">Moses Wilson</persName> had<lb/> moved to, but his
                    House was so much out<lb/>of the way and such a bad road to it, that<lb/>we
                    concluded to go about one mile fur-<lb/>ther on, to <persName key="jidin1">James
                        Iddings</persName>'s to breakfast,<lb/>his House being near the Road,
                        where<lb/><persName key="mwils1">Moses</persName>, and Wife came over to see
                    us,<lb/>and I thought it strange to see such<lb/>good looking fnd s in the
                    Wilderness, so<lb/>remote from Meetings, and more sur-<lb/>prising to see
                        <persName key="midin1">Mary Iddings</persName> in such a little<lb/>Cabbin,
                    however we spent an hour or<lb/>two very agreeably with them, tho the<lb/>
                    account the gave us of the Road was very<lb/>discouraging, <persName
                        key="mwils1">Moses</persName> informing, that<lb/>he did not think we would
                    be able to get<lb/>the Waggon more than 10 or 15 miles fur-<lb/>ther, and that
                    far with difficulty, and<lb/>that he would send one of his sons with<lb/><pb
                        n="19" facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_19"/>us to the next house, which was
                    about<lb/>8 miles. at 11 OClock we bid our kind<lb/>fnd s farewell and pursued
                    our Journey,<lb/>Cousin and I going before, giving Warn-<lb/>ing of the
                    difficult places, My <persName key="bcoop1">Husband</persName><lb/>and <persName
                        key="mwils2">Moses Wilson Junr</persName> holding the Wag-<lb/>gon, the
                    banks were so steep and sidling<lb/>that it appeared impossible to get
                    along<lb/>without upsetting. in a while we cross-<lb/>ed another large branch of
                    the <geogName key="pinec">Pine Creek</geogName>, and<lb/>after traveling a piece
                    further we got<lb/>stoped by the trees that were across the<lb/>Road, we then
                    got help from one Boat-<lb/>mans, and it took 5 men near two<lb/>hours to open
                    to Road to his House,<lb/>so as to get the Waggon along, tho it<lb/>was not half
                    a Mile, here it looked<lb/>likely we must leave it, tho we en-<lb/> deavoured to
                    hire help to go with us<lb/>to <persName key="fking1">King</persName>s
                    Settlement<lb/>to assist in open-<lb/>ing the Road, but there were but two<lb/>
                    families here, and no neighbours<lb/>near, and they busy planting corn
                    &amp;<lb/> nearly out of Provisation, and no Mill<lb/>within 20 miles, the Woman
                    said she could<lb/>supply us with Milk and butter, but that<lb/>she had nothing
                    else except a little Veneson<lb/><pb n="20" facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_20"/>which was
                    a very good relish for our<lb/>Coffee that we had prepared for our<lb/>Dinner,
                    we now got to unloading<lb/>our Waggon, and packing up our<lb/>goods suitable to
                    be carried on horse-<lb/>back, we laped up one Bed in the<lb/>Waggon Cover,
                    which Cover served us<lb/>for a Tent the two nights we lodged in<lb/>the Woods,
                    we sewed up a sheet <del>and</del><lb/>and filled it and a Bag with Clooth-<lb/>
                    ing &amp;c and after other arangments<lb/>the day was so far spend, we
                    conclud-<lb/>ed to stay all night, we got supper,<lb/>put some Bread to rise,
                    and went<lb/>to Bed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-05-31">31 st </date> 6th day <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>a Clear Cold Morning, very<lb/>white frost, some Clothes I washed<lb/>last night
                    were frozen stiff, baked<lb/>Bread, got Breakfast, and after load-<lb/>ing our
                    Horses, about 9 OClock set out<lb/>on our Journey pretty chearful, tho we
                    stoutly<lb/>loaded on three Horses, yet we were<lb/>Oblidged to leave behind us
                    one Bed<lb/>and two large Trunks, hoping to get<lb/>them along sometime this
                    summer,<lb/>We presently had <geogName key="pinec">Pine Creek</geogName>to
                    Cross<lb/> which our Landlady, put Cousin and<lb/><pb n="21"
                        facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_21"/>myself over, in a Canoe, we traveled<lb/>on
                    through the Wilderness, up the <geogName key="pinec">Pine<lb/> Creek</geogName>
                    until about one, when we turn-<lb/>ed our Horses out to pasture while<lb/>we
                    prepared our Dinner, there being<lb/>plenty of fine grass on the
                    bottoms<lb/>near Sd Creek, about 2 OClock we startd<lb/>and Journeyed on until ½
                    past 6, then<lb/>pitched Camp, and prepared for<lb/>a Nights Lodging in the
                    Woods, we<lb/>put forks in the Ground, and with<lb/>our Waggon Cover, made a
                    pretty<lb/>good Tent, then after taking some<lb/>Chocolate went to Bed, tho our
                    lodg-<lb/>ing was pretty Comfortable yet I<lb/>got but little Sleep, by the
                    marks<lb/>on the trees we came 15 miles</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-06-01">6 mo 1 st </date> 7th day <placeName
                        key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>a Clear Cool Morn-<lb/>ing, at 5 OClock we set out again,<lb/> travelled till 8
                    then stoped and got<lb/>Breakfast, it is almost impossible<lb/>to tell how often
                    we have Crossed<lb/><geogName key="pinec">Pine Creek</geogName> since we first
                    came on<lb/>its waters, but now being up the third<lb/>fork we expect shortly to
                    leave it. ½ past<lb/>9 set out again, I mounted one of<lb/>the Horses having the
                    Bed for a saddle<lb/><pb n="22" facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_22"/> the Road very Baggy
                    and Rough<lb/>until after <del>after</del> leaving the Waters<lb/>of <geogName
                        key="pinec">Pine Creek</geogName>, then pased through<lb/> some good land
                    near the head Wa-<lb/>ters of the <geogName key="alleg">Allegeny</geogName>, and
                    towards<lb/> evening at the foot of a Mountain<lb/>where we had plenty of Water,
                    we<lb/> pitched our Camp, and prepared<lb/>for Lodging, had a good nights
                    rest<lb/> after a fataguing days Journey of<lb/>26 miles, Cousin Walking all
                    the<lb/> way, I the greater part, she did it<lb/>of Choice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-06-02">2 nd </date> 1 day of the Week <placeName
                        key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>a Cloudy Morning<lb/>Set out at 5 OClock, <del>traveling until</del><lb/>
                    traveling until 8, on Crossing<lb/><geogName key="osway">Oswago
                    Creek</geogName>, a Branch of the <geogName key="alleg"
                    >Allegeny</geogName>,<lb/>it began to Rain, we pitched camp &amp;<lb/>got
                    Breakfast, started at 9 and<lb/>arrived at <persName key="jbell1">John
                        Bell</persName>'s at 12 in <persName key="fking1">Kings</persName><lb/>
                    Settlement his Wife seeing us coming<lb/>ran out to meet us with Tears run-<lb/>
                    ing down, we were glad to see her,<lb/>the Joy was mutual, the sight of a<lb/>
                    fnd after so perelious a Journey, how<lb/>consoleing, having been more than<lb/>
                    <pb n="23" facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_23"/> two days and nights in the
                    Wilder-<lb/>ness, since we left the last house. Altho<lb/>the Journey has been
                    trying, yet I felt<lb/> something so animating, and <del>reviving</del><lb/>
                    encouraging to revive, that my<lb/> Heart was filled with a precious
                    sweet-<lb/>ness which was a full consolation<lb/>for our most trying seasons,
                    Oh<lb/>may I abide in the patience with<lb/>my Eye single to him who know-<lb/>
                    eth what is best for us. -- After<lb/>dinner, <persName key="bcoop1"
                        >Benjamin</persName> and <persName key="welli1">William</persName><lb/> went
                    3 miles to <persName key="fking1">Francis Kings</persName><lb/>to see after a
                    Canoe to take us<lb/>down to <placeName key="tunes">Tunesassah,</placeName>,
                    where they staid<lb/>all night, and we continued with <persName key="mbell1"
                        >Mary<lb/>Bell</persName>, her Husband not at home.<lb/>12 miles</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-06-03">3 rd </date> 2nd day of the Week, <placeName
                        key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>a Cloudy Morn-<lb/>ing, about 10 my <persName key="bcoop1">Husband</persName> and<lb/>
                    <persName key="welli1">Wm </persName> returned, <persName key="fking1">Francis
                        King</persName> coming<lb/>with them, bringing Horses for Cousin<lb/> and
                    myself to Ride on, We went to<lb/><persName key="fking1">F King</persName>s to
                    dinner, and it looking<lb/>likely for Rain, they wished us to stay<lb/>
                    <pb n="24" facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_24"/>all night but being desirous to<lb/>get to
                    our distined home, thought<lb/>if we could get 12 miles down the<lb/>River to
                        <persName key="rhoop1">Robert Hoops</persName>'s, we might<lb/>next day
                    reach <placeName key="tunes">Tunesassah</placeName>, where<lb/>we were anxious
                    to get, we left <persName key="fking1">Fran-<lb/>cis</persName>'s about 3 his
                    son and daughter go-<lb/>ing with us, butbefore we had got<lb/>far it began to
                    thunder, and the<lb/>Gust increased, until it became<lb/>a very great rain, we
                    stoped at a little<lb/>Cabbin a While until the heaviest<lb/>of it was over, but
                    our Bed, Clothes<lb/>&amp;c were on the Horses I was afraid<lb/>they would get
                    very Wet, and hav-<lb/>ing nothing but a foot path to<lb/>travel and the
                    Bushes<lb/>thick and<lb/>Wet, made it very disagreeable<lb/>getting along, we
                    got to <persName key="rhoop1">Robert<lb/>Hoops</persName>'s about 7 and were
                    kindly<lb/>received by his Housekeeper, he not<lb/>being at home, but was out
                    look-<lb/>ing after Provision, in several<lb/>places where we have
                        <del>been</del> latterly been it has<lb/>been the case, scarce of Provisions<lb/>
                    <pb n="25" facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_25"/>which is their situation here, none
                    for<lb/>us, nor no Canoe to take us down,<lb/>we having some with us, got
                    our<lb/>own supper and went to Bed 15m</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-06-04">4 th </date> 3rd day <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>Cloudy and like for Rain, my<lb/><persName key="bcoop1">Husband</persName>, and
                        <persName key="wembr1">Wm Embree</persName> with <persName key="fking1">F
                        King</persName><lb/>set of on Horseback for <placeName key="tunes"
                        >Tunesassah</placeName>, pro-<lb/>posing to get <persName key="jswai1">Joel
                        Swain</persName> with some<lb/>other help to bring up a Canoe to<lb/>take us
                    and our baggage down</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-06-05">5 th </date>4th day of the week, <placeName
                        key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>this day has<lb/>been spent with anxious desires<lb/>to see a Canoe, we feel very
                    dull<lb/>and lonesome, two days waiting.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-06-06">6 th </date> 5th day <placeName key="tunes"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>Rose early, got break-<lb/>fast and set of with a Man that<lb/>was going down the
                    River, and in<lb/>about 11 miles we met <persName key="jswai1">Joel
                        Swain</persName> &amp;<lb/> an Indian with a Canoe coming<lb/>for us, which
                    Sight was very agree-<lb/>able, and we pretty soon got into<lb/>their Canoe,
                    with our baggage and<lb/>proceeded, about 12 OClock we stoped<lb/><pb n="26"
                        facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_26"/> at <persName key="psnid1">Peter
                        Sniders</persName>
                    <del>Saunders</del>, a White Man, his Wife<lb/>was taken Captive by the Indians
                    when<lb/>she was about three years Old, and had<lb/>lived among them ever since,
                    she<lb/>cannot talk any English, we got<lb/>some Milk of them to eat with
                    our<lb/>Bread, then proceeded, and by<lb/> 5 OClock got to <placeName
                        key="tunes">Tunesassah</placeName>, were<lb/>my dear <persName key="bcoop1"
                        >Benjamin</persName> was burning<lb/>brush, and William at Work with<lb/>the
                    Planes, they were all glad to see<lb/>us, as we were to get home and
                    see<lb/>them, 40 miles</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-06-07">7 th of the Mo </date> 6th day <placeName
                        key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p>we got to wash<lb/>ing some of our dirty Clothes, a great<lb/>many of the natives
                    came to see us<lb/>through the coarse of this day, <del>am</del><lb/>among our
                    Visitters, was <persName key="cornp2">Corn-<lb/>Planter</persName>s sister, who
                    said she was<lb/>glad the good spirit had brought us<lb/>safe through our long
                    Journey, which<lb/>raised something so endearing toga-<lb/>ther, with such
                    comfortable sensations<lb/><pb n="27" facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_27"/> that my Heart
                    was filled with gratitude,<lb/>and in the secret effusions of my spirit<lb/>was
                    ready to utter this Language, "great<lb/>and marvelous are thy Works, Lord
                    God<lb/> Almighty</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-06-10">10 th </date> 2nd day <placeName key="tunes"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>
                    <persName rend="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName> went to<lb/>inform the Indians
                    of our being come,<lb/>and the Young Men here having sent<lb/>an address to
                    them, they told him they<lb/>would confer togather and let us know.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-06-11">11 th </date> 3rd day <placeName key="tunes"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>We recieved word from<lb/>the Indians, that they had concluded<lb/>to meet in
                    Council in three days, at<lb/>a place called <placeName key="colds">Cold
                        Spring</placeName> 3½ miles<lb/>from this place,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-06-14">14 th </date> 6th day <placeName key="tunes"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> Agreeable<lb/> to the conclusion<lb/>of the Indians we went this day to
                    the<lb/>Council, <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName> having been<lb/>
                    very unwell for several days, tho<lb/>so much better this Morning, that we<lb/>
                    encouraged his going with us, and<lb/>about 9 OClock we all set of togather<lb/>
                    taking a little provision with us, which<lb/>we partook of under a shed in the
                    Town<lb/>while the Indians were collecting, about<lb/><pb n="28"
                        facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_28"/>11 OClock we went into the Council House<lb/>
                    where were a large number of Indians.<lb/> 10 Chiefs, and a good many Women.
                    Old<lb/> Connidias, after our sitting a While,<lb/> opened the Council with
                    expressing<lb/> thanks to the great spirit in bringing<lb/> us safely through
                    our long Journey,<lb/> also, that so many of these were col<lb/>lected there to
                    day. Desiring the War<lb/>riors to pay attention to what should<lb/> be
                    communicated to them, then in<lb/>formed they were ready to hear <del>what</del>
                    <lb/> what we had to <del>lay</del> lay before them, <persName key="habee1"
                        >Henry O'Bail</persName>
                    <persName key="cornp2">Corn<lb/>planters</persName> Son was our
                    interpreter.<lb/>
                </p>
                <p>The Adress from the Committee<lb/> on our behalf was first read, then part<lb/>
                    of an Epistle to the Women, likewise<lb/> a speech from the Young Men
                    residing<lb/> here, concerning sowing, grinding<lb/> &amp;c. They were also
                    informed, not with<lb/>standing our Journey had been long<lb/> and trying, we
                    felt peace of Mind<lb/> in being with them, and hoped that<lb/> our sisters the
                    Indian Women, when<lb/> we became a little more acquainted<lb/> would be willing
                    to be instructed, tho<lb/> we let them know we had no more to<lb/><pb n="29"
                        facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_29"/>Day at present. After a considerable<lb/> time of
                    conference among themselves<lb/> the following is the substance of a speech<lb/>
                    delivered by one of the Chiefs.</p>
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <dateline><date when="1805-06-14"/><placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>

                        <p>Brothers <foreign xml:lang="iro">Deweista</foreign>, meaning Quakers</p>
                        <p>We return thanks to the great<lb/> Spirit to see you all well, and that
                            the<lb/> great Spirit has preserved your Wo<lb/>men on so long a
                            Journey, and that<lb/> they are arrived safe in our country, &amp;<lb/>
                            we are much pleased they are going to<lb/> stay amongst us to instruct
                            our Wo<lb/>men. We return thanks to the great<lb/> Spirit that he has
                            put this into your<lb/> Hearts. We wish you therefore to<lb/> make your
                            Minds easy. </p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>

                <p>They also<lb/> seemed pleased with <persName key="hjack1">Hollidays</persName> Epis<lb/>tle, but that they were at
                    a loss for<lb/> an answer, as two of the heads<lb/> of the Women were not there.
                    After<lb/> sitting near three hours in<lb/> Council, exceed ing ly Warm and
                    Close,<lb/> we were dismissed, the Indians conti<lb/>nuing their conference two
                    horus longer<lb/> on the business the young men laid before them<lb/> and
                    appeared much pleased with their proposals<lb/><pb n="30"
                        facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_30"/> which were as follows</p>
                <floatingText>
                    <body><dateline><date when="1805-06-14"/><placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                        <p>Brothers attend</p>
                        <p>You know we have<lb/> often talked to you about opening a good Road<lb/>
                            from this Town to Tunasapah in or<lb/>der to make it more easy for
                            your<lb/> People to come to Mill. If you will<lb/> join together and
                            open this Road, we<lb/> have concluded to give you 7000<lb/> feet of
                            Boards. This will enable you<lb/> to finish your Houses, to have
                            them<lb/> warm against next winter.</p>
                        <p>Brothers, you know we began to<lb/> grind for you about the time you<lb/>
                            were making sugar last spring, we<lb/> will continue to grind for you
                            until<lb/> next season for sugar making, with<lb/>out taking toll which
                            will make<lb/> one year. And if any of you want<lb/> boards we will sell
                            them to you<lb/> for four shillings but we don’t<lb/> intend to trust
                            any, because we want<lb/> to keep the Chain of frendship bright,<lb/>
                            and if you Want any of your own logs<lb/> sawed into boards, or
                            Scantling, if you<lb/> will cut and haul the logs to the Mill<lb/><pb
                                n="31" facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_31"/> we will saw them for one half</p>
                        <p>Brothers these advantages which<lb/> we now proposed unto you, are
                            intend<lb/>ed to encourage you to pursue habits<lb/> of Industry and
                            Sobriety. We wish you<lb/> to keep your Minds strong to pursue this<lb/>
                            path, then we think your Substance will<lb/> increase, and the great
                            Spirit will<lb/> help your Labours.</p>
                        <p>Brothers we don’t want to tire your<lb/> Ears with many words, but it
                            affords us much<lb/> Satisfaction to see your Industry this Spring,<lb/>
                            in enclosing so many fields to plant corn<lb/> &amp;c in, and that you
                            continue your good<lb/> resolution against the use of Spirits<lb/> and
                            Liquours. We repeat it again, be<lb/> strong in your Minds against this
                            great<lb/> Enemy, and never let him rise up a<lb/>gain. We have all
                            united our Minds<lb/> together in this Speech, and shall de<lb/>liver
                            you a Copy of it, in order that<lb/> your memories may be kept
                            bright.</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>

                <p>I have felt satisfaction in being<lb/> with the Indians today, and <persName
                        key="jtayl1">Jacob Tay<lb/>lor</persName> says he has felt as much peace
                        in<lb/><pb n="32" facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_32"/> attending some of their
                    Councils, as is<lb/> common to experience in attending a<lb/> Quarterly Meeting.
                    But it will take us<lb/> some time before their Language will be<lb/>come
                    familiar and we can get to<lb/> understand it. __ About 30 of<lb/> the Indians
                    has since joined, and opened<lb/> the Road proposed, which will be<lb/> an
                    advantage to us as well as to<lb/> them, a grand piece of work for<lb/> Indians,
                    it being copletley done.</p>
                <p><persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> did not attend the<lb/> Counsil,
                    but has since been here. I<lb/> did not deliver the message to him<lb/> for want
                    of an Interpreter, <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob<lb/> Taylor</persName> saying he
                    thought he could<lb/> not make him understand which<lb/> of the friends that
                    were here was thee.</p>
                <p>There was a paragraph in the address<lb/> from the Committee, to the Indians,
                    sent<lb/> by us, recommending, that when<lb/> any of them has done any thing,
                    that a<lb/>nother does not like, they should not differ<lb/> about it, but
                    forgive him that had<lb/> done the wrong, for the good Spirit<lb/><pb n="33"
                        facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_33"/> forgives us when we do wrong, if we<lb/> are
                    sorry for it. I do not know but it<lb/> had some good effect, for about two
                    days<lb/> after, they called a Council, sent for <persName key="cornp2"
                        >Corn<lb/>planter</persName>, made up all the uneasiness, &amp;<lb/>
                    restored him to his former post, with<lb/> the same powers. He has since
                    been<lb/> here, and said when any thing happened<lb/> to them in future, they
                    had better try to<lb/> make it up among themselves, and<lb/> not go tell it
                    abroad over the<lb/> Country for that made it worse, he<lb/> also told us of
                    some other advice he gave<lb/> them, which I thought was very suitable.<lb/> And
                    he further said that Old friends<lb/> down the Country might be informed<lb/>
                    that the difference was all done away,<lb/> and that there was nothing
                    between<lb/> us, meaning the Quakers, and them.</p>
                <p>It was very agreeable information to<lb/> us, to hear that <persName key="cornp2"
                        >Cornplanter</persName> was restor<lb/>ed, for his Judgment in matters of
                    im<lb/>portance was of consequence. He wanted<lb/> to see some of our linnen, or
                    Manufac<lb/>turing, and said if two or more of their<lb/> Women could get in the
                    way of making<lb/> they could learn the others.<lb/><pb n="34"
                        facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_34"/></p>
                <p>I think best of further describing the<lb/> new house we are settled in, and its
                    Si<lb/>tuation. It is a pretty Commodious<lb/> two story Log house 22 by 36
                    feet, the<lb/> Floors and partitions laid rough until<lb/> the Floor season, the
                    Lower story is intended<lb/> to be finished this summer, and the re<lb/>maining
                    Work of the House next<lb/> Winter. It is divided into a Parlour,<lb/> Kitchen,
                    and two Chambers. One of the<lb/> Rooms is occupied by my husband<lb/> and I,
                    the other by Cousin, up stairs<lb/> one fine place, 4 rooms intended ,where<lb/>
                    the Men sleep. The small hosue where<lb/> the Young Men lived before the
                    move<lb/> into this is occupied by a white fa<lb/>mily who has undertaken to
                    clear<lb/> 20 Acres of Land this Summer, and<lb/> are now engaged in it. When
                    that is<lb/> done, the House finished, and some other<lb/> improvements made, it
                    will be a<lb/> handsome place. With the mills about<lb/> 30 Veareh from the
                    house, South West corner<lb/><pb n="35" facs="SW_RC1805b_Page_35"/> the Mill
                    Race about 8 veareh from<lb/> the Door, South, the Garden north, a<lb/> Road
                    South to the Whitemans house<lb/> the Road to River nearly a North<lb/> Coarse ¾
                    of a Mile from our dwelling.<lb/> The house of Ipenesinguhla, where the<lb/>
                    Young Men lived when they first<lb/>
                    <del>into th</del> settled when they came to the<lb/> Indian Country, 2 ½ miles
                    from the<lb/> nearly a West Coarse.<lb/>
                </p>

            </div>
        </body>


    </text>
</TEI>
