<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei-print.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="global.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>Some Account of Rachel Coope (Journal A): Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>Emma Remsberg</name>
                </respStmt>

                <sponsor>Tri-Co Digital Humanities Initiative</sponsor>
                <funder>Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>This work is the property of the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore
                        College. It may be copied freely by individuals for personal use, research,
                        and teaching (including distribution to classes) as long as this statement
                        of availability is included in the text. It may be linked to freely in
                        Internet editions of all kinds, including for—profit works.</p>
                    <p>Publishers, libraries, and other information providers interested in
                        providing this text in a commercial or non—profit product or from an
                        information server must contact Swarthmore College for licensing and cost
                        information.</p>
                    <p> Scholars interested in changing or adding to these texts by, for example,
                        creating a new edition of the text (electronically or in print) with
                        substantive editorial changes, may do so with the permission of Swarthmore
                        College. This is the case whether the new publication will be made available
                        at a cost or free of charge.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2014">2014</date>
                <idno type="local">SW_RC1805a</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Native Americans and Quakers: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>Journals (Ms.) Coope</collection>
                        <idno>MSS003/043</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>35 pp. (1 volume)</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Rachel Coope manuscript is housed at Friends Historical Library, on the
                    campus of Swarthmore College. In the fall semester of 2010, Swarthmore students
                    enrolled in English 50A (“Reading Red, White, and In-Between in Early American
                    Literature”) transcribed this manuscript as part of a larger project to make the
                    library’s rich store of Quaker Indian mission writings more accessible. The
                    project was designed by Christopher Densmore, Curator of Friends Historical
                    Library, and Keat Murray, Visiting Assistant Professor of English. Student
                    transcribers included: Miriam Lise Hauser. Transcriptions were compiled and
                    edited in the present form by Professor Murray. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> The transcribers and editor attempted to render the author’s orthography and
                    grammar as they appear on the page of his journal, even when the author’s own
                    spelling and usage are inconsistent. Additionally, many questions remain about
                    spelling the names of his Quaker acquaintances, individual Native Americans who
                    populate his journal, and Indian villages and towns. The transcribers and editor
                    attempted to remain faithful to the author’s Anglicized spellings in all cases. </p>
                <p>Journals "a" and "b" represent transcriptions of Rachel Coope’s actual diaries.
                    Journal "a" her “esteemed parents”; however, her mother died before the letter
                    was written, and so it may have been meant for her parents­in­law, to whom she
                    was deeply attached) copied over twice. No version of this letter is included in
                    journal four. Except for this, the differences were small, such as variance in
                    phrasing and spelling, and not in content. It seems as though journal "a"
                    preceded journal "b"; it is less polished. The handwriting seems more rushed and
                    the paper size varies, while in journal "b", the handwriting is neater, and the
                    paper used is consistent. It is possible that these, especially journal three,
                    could have been handwritten by Coope.</p>
                <p>The author of the original journal does not include page numbers on his
                    manuscript; the page numbers have been interpolated by the transcribers to
                    correspond with the manuscript sheets.</p>
            </editorialDecl>

        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written in <date when="1805">1805</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Society of Friends -- Missions</item>
                        <item>Indians of North America -- Missions</item>
                        <item>Quakers -- Pennsylvania -- Diaries</item>
                        <item>Seneca Indians</item>
                        <item>Philadelphia Yearly Meeting of the Relgious Society of Friends</item>
                        <item>Voyages and Travels</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>

        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="letter">
                <pb n="1" facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_01"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline><placeName key="tunes">Tunesassah</placeName>
                        <date when="1804-06">6 mo</date></dateline>
                    <salute>My dear Parents,</salute></opener>
                <p>About two weeks<lb/> ago I wrote to you and sent it by an Indi-<lb/>an that was
                    going to <placeName key="pitts">Pittsburgh</placeName> for<lb/>the things they
                    Committee has sent<lb/>for us, in which I promised to give a<lb/>more full
                    account of our Journey by<lb/><persName key="jembr1">Jm. Embree</persName> when
                    he returned, and<lb/>I feel myself so indebted to Father, as<lb/>renders it
                    requesite for me to com-<lb/>ply with his request, but on looking<lb/>over the
                    notes which I have kept,<lb/>seeing how unperfectly they are, it has
                    al-<lb/>most discouraged my attempting, for<lb/>I cannot concieve they will be
                    any way<lb/>entertaing, excepting a little bare infor-<lb/>mation, I often feel
                    myself very defecti[ve]<lb/>in literary knowledge, and my Ideas<lb/>in matters
                    of Consequence, much con-<lb/>tained, let those whose genius are<lb/>more
                    bright, have Charity, and ac-<lb/>cept, dear Father, my
                    communication<lb/>flowing from the Sincerity of the heart<lb/>
                    <gap/> Mind has felt very much wear<lb/><pb n="2" facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_02"
                    /><gap/>the Worlds applause, knowing<lb/>
                    <unclear>that</unclear> it is not human literature, or<lb/>the acquirements of
                    Man, we are<lb/>to be enriched with, but with the<lb/> blessings of the Poor in
                    Spirit. I frequent-<lb/>ly look towards my native home, with<lb/>longing desires
                    to hear from you, not<lb/>having heard a Word from Chester County<lb/>Since we
                    left there. My dear <persName key="bcoop1">B.</persName> has not<lb/>been very
                    well since we came here, tho<lb/>mostly keeps about, <persName key="jtayl1"
                        >Jacob Taylor</persName> often<lb/>charges him to take care of
                    himself<lb/>until he becomes accustomed to the<lb/>Climate and Water, Cousin and
                    my-<lb/>self have been bravely. -- The young<lb/>Men had moved into their new
                    House<lb/>about two weeks before we came, which<lb/>when finished will be a very
                    comfortable<lb/>one, and a pleasant situation, those<lb/>lately cleared, that it
                    looks fough about<lb/>here yet, and the Garden &amp;c will not be<lb/> very
                    productive this season, They have<lb/>two Men hired, one a Carpenter
                    finish-<lb/>ing the Mill, the other diging or <unclear>mond</unclear><lb/>
                    <gap/>are kept very busy <unclear>at</unclear><lb/><pb n="3"
                        facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_03"/>home so far, together with
                    housewo<gap/><lb/>and sewing for the young Men, indeed <gap/><lb/> was time
                    for them to have some fema<unclear>les</unclear><lb/>among them, their Situation
                    was trying<lb/>let those who are favored with all<lb/>convenienceies, and
                    necessaries of Life<lb/>calmly reflect on the many advantages<lb/>they enjoy,
                    and the Obligations they are<lb/>under to their gracious benefactors.
                    I<lb/>Salute you all in near affection, hoping<lb/>to hear from you before long,
                    and I wish<lb/>to be affectionately remembred to all en<lb/>quiring fnds. &amp;
                    relations, not forgetting<lb/>GrandMother, in which my husband<lb/>and Cousin
                    joins. I mentioned it was<lb/>thought letters would come this summer<lb/>on the
                    state Road, but that communicat<gap/><lb/> will be entirely Stoped in the
                    Winter<lb/>Season, <persName key="jbark1">Jesse</persName> or <persName
                        key="abark1">Abner Barker</persName> at <placeName key="pitts"
                        >Pitts-<lb/>burgh</placeName> will take care to forward letters<lb/>to us. I
                    hope thou wilt not expose my<lb/>notes, tho have no Objection to some<lb/>of my
                    near relations seeing them, if<lb/>I get time, I propose makeing out a<lb/>short
                    draught for Brother Ezra, as<lb/>I intend writing to him. I had
                        intend<unclear>ed</unclear><lb/><pb n="4" facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_04"/>to have
                    written to my Brothers and<lb/>Sisters, but could not to all except
                    com-<lb/>prized in one letter, therefore must post-<lb/>pone it at present, and
                    perhaps may<lb/>send an answer when they Write to me.<lb/><date
                        when="1804-06-30">
                        <emph rend="underline">6 mo</emph> 30</date> when I wrote to the foregoing
                    I<lb/> expected <persName key="jthom2">J Thomas,</persName> and <persName
                        key="wembr1">Wm Embree</persName><lb/> would have set off sometime last
                    week<lb/>but <persName key="jthom2">Jonathan</persName> was desirous to see
                    the<lb/>Indian return from <placeName key="pitts">Pittsburgh</placeName>,
                    and<lb/>it is probable he may come to day<lb/>or tomorrow, but <persName
                        key="wembr1">Wm</persName> being uneasy<lb/><del>being uneasy</del> I expect
                    they will set<lb/>of early tomorrow Morning whether<lb/>the Indian returns or
                    not, and I hope<lb/>when he comes, I shall not be disap-<lb/>pointed of hearing
                    from Chester Coun-<lb/>ty, we are enjoying a pretty good state<lb/>of Health </p>
                <closer> in near Affection, I remain<lb/> Your Daugher <signed><persName
                            key="rcoop1">Rachel Coope</persName></signed></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <pb n="5" facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_05"/>
                <opener><placeName key="tunes">Tenusassa</placeName>
                    <date when="1804-06-23">6th m 23rd 1804</date><salute>Estemed
                    Parents</salute></opener>

                <p>About two weeks ago I wrote and sent by an Indi<lb/>an that was going to
                        <placeName key="pitts">Pittsburg</placeName> for the things that the
                    com-<lb/>mittee sent for us, in which I promis'd to give a more full<lb/>account
                    of our journey by <persName key="wembr1">Wm Embree</persName>, and I felt myself
                    so in<lb/>-debted to father as rendered it requisite for me to comply
                    with<lb/>his request, but looking over, and seeing how imperfect<del>ly</del>
                    it<lb/>was, almost discouraged me attempting, for I cannot con<lb/>-cieve it
                    will be any way entertaining excepting a lit<lb/>-tle bare information. I often
                    feel myself very defective<lb/>in literary knowledge and my Ideas in matters of
                    conse<lb/>quence much confined, let those whose genius are more<lb/>brightened
                    have charity, and accept dear father my com<lb/>munications flowing from the
                    sincerity of the heart, my <lb/>mind has felt very much wean'd from the worlds applause<lb/>
                    <pb n="6" facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_06"/>knowing it is not human literature or the
                    invention of<lb/>man we are to be enriched with but the blessings of the
                    poor<lb/>in spirit. - I frequently look toward my native home with<lb/>longing
                    desires to hear from you, having not heard a word<lb/>from chester C since we
                    left there, my dear <persName key="bcoop1">B</persName> has not<lb/>been very
                    well since we came here tho mostly keeps<lb/> about <persName key="jtayl1">J
                        Taylor</persName> often charges him to take care of himself<lb/>till he
                    becomes a little accostumed to the climate and<lb/> water, I have been bravely,
                    cousin also. They had moved<lb/>into their new house about two weeks before we
                    came which<lb/>will be a very comfortable one when it is finished and<lb/>a
                    pleasant situation tho so lately clear'd that the gardens<lb/> &amp;c will not
                    be very productive this season. they have<lb/>two men hired one a carpenter
                    finishing the mill <del>wright</del> and another digging <del>in</del><lb/><pb
                        n="7" facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_07"/>or mending. The <gap/> that we are kept
                    very busy at home<lb/>so far, together with housework and sewing for the young
                    men<lb/>indeed it was time for them to have females among<lb/>them, their
                    situation was trying, let those who are favourd<lb/> >with all the necessaries
                    of life calmly reflect on the advantages<lb/> they possess, and the necessity of
                    rendering thanks to their<lb/>gracious benefactor. I salute you all in near
                    affection<lb/>hoping to hear from you before long, and wish to be
                    rem<lb/>embered to all enquiring friends and relations, not<lb/>forgeting dear
                    Grandmother, in which my husband and<lb/> cousin joins. I mention'd it was that
                    letter would come<lb/> this summer on the state road that communication
                    will<lb/>be entirely stoped in the winter <persName key="jbark1"
                        >Jesse</persName> or <persName key="abark1">Abner Barker</persName>
                        at<lb/><placeName key="pitts">Pittsburg</placeName> will take care to
                    forward letters to us I hope thou<lb/>wilt not expose<lb/><pb n="8"
                        facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_08"/>my history have no objection to some of my near
                    relations<lb/>seeing it, if I get time shall draw a short draught for B<lb/>Ezra
                    as I intend writing to him, I had some thoughts of<lb/>writing to my own
                    brothers and sisters but could not write<lb/>to all excepting compris'd in one,
                    therefore must post<lb/>pone it at the present and perhaps will send an
                    answer<lb/>when they write to me. <date when="1804-06-30">6th <emph
                            rend="underline">mo</emph> 30th</date> When I wrote the foregoing
                    I<lb/>expected <persName key="jthom2">J Thomas</persName> and <persName
                        key="wembr1">Wm E</persName> would have set off sometime<lb/>last week but
                        <persName key="jthom2">Jn.</persName> was desirous waiting till the Indian
                    returnd<lb/> from <placeName key="pitts">Pittsburg</placeName> it's probable he
                    may get here today or to<lb/>morrow but <persName key="wembr1">Wm</persName>
                    being uneasy I believe they will set off<lb/>early tomorrow whether he comes or
                    no I hope I shall not be<lb/> disappointed when <del>he</del> the Indian comes
                    of hearing from C. County<lb/>we are enjoying a reasonable state of health </p>
                <closer>I am in near affection.<lb/>your <del>dutiful</del> daughter
                            <signed><persName key="rcoop1">R Coope</persName></signed></closer>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>


            <div type="narrative">
                <pb n="9" facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_09"/>
                <p>In the fall of the year <date when="1804">1804</date> my dear<lb/>husband and I
                    inform'd friends of <orgName key="meetbrad">brad-<lb/>ford mo. meeting</orgName>
                    of a concern that had attend<lb/>ed our minds to go and reside some
                    time<lb/>with the Indian natives near the <geogName key="alleg">
                        Alleghany<lb/>River</geogName>, to endeavour to instruct them in<lb/>
                    agriculture, spinning, dairies, &amp;c; &amp; Obtaining<lb/>the unity and
                    sympathy of our friends<lb/>at home, also the concurrence of the yearly<lb/>
                    meeting's <orgName key="pymindian">committee on Indian affairs</orgName>,
                        <persName key="hjack1">H.<lb/>Jackson</persName> likewise having a minute
                        from<lb/><orgName key="meetngard">Newgarden mo meeting</orgName> to
                    accompany us</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-05-20">5th mo 20th<lb/> 1805</date> 2nd day. <placeName
                        key="bradf"/></dateline>
                <p>After a time of comfortable<lb/>quiet, wherein we were in some degree
                    favour<lb/>ed to feel the overshadowing of divine regard<lb/>to be near a
                    considerable number of our<lb/>near relations and friends being present,
                    we<lb/>took leave of them in feeling embraces of<lb/>endearing love, <persName
                        key="ncoop1">Father Coope</persName> and Brother<lb/>Ezra bearing in company
                    to M. Embree's<lb/>there bid farewell to dear
                    <persName key="jembr1">James</persName> and Wife<lb/>and parted with father, a close trial, tears<lb/> flowed in
                    abundance under a feeling sym'<lb/>pathy for him, and ardent desires
                    were<lb/>raised in my heart that he might par<lb/>-ticipate of that peace which
                    is the preci<lb/>ous enjoyment of all the sincere heart<lb/>ed, now in his
                    lonesome and advanced<lb/>
                    <pb n="10" facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_10"/>stage of life, Brother continuing with
                    us<lb/>to <persName key="wtrum1">Wm. Truman's</persName> 11<emph
                        rend="underline">m</emph>, where we lodged.<lb/>my dear husband and B took
                    their repose<lb/>in the waggon, Cousin and I more comfort<lb/> ably accommodated
                    with a good bed, I <del>soon</del><lb/>soon fell asleep, near 3 Oclock
                        awaking<del>ed</del><lb/>the recollection of the parting season<lb/>
                    presented and no focibly revived that tears<lb/>flowed from my eyes, &amp; sleep
                    departed. --<lb/>Thou O my God has at seasons been<lb/>pleased in thy unmerited
                    goodness to<lb/>make bare thy arm, and in times of trial<lb/>afford sweet
                    consolation, as patience<lb/> was abode in, under a humble sense<lb/>Thereof may
                    I a little intercede for a<lb/> renewed continuation of thy love.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-05-21">21st.</date> 3rd day . <placeName
                        key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>A fine morning, after a<lb/>smart
                    shower, taking <del>tooking</del> breakfast parted<lb/>with our brother, and set
                    of ab. 6, went<lb/>11m to the rising sun tavern, fed our horses<lb/>&amp; took
                    some refreshment in the waggon,<lb/>then pursuing on travelled 8<emph
                        rend="underline">m</emph> &amp; stoped<lb/>at <persName key="wbrin1">Wm
                        Brinton</persName> door <gap/> him nor<lb/>wife not at home, we were
                    willing<lb/>to go on. but the daughter and <del>gran</del><lb/> grandmother
                    insisted on our <del>our</del> going in,<lb/> &amp; an excellent dish of coffee
                    was soon<lb/>prepared, which was grateful to the pa-<lb/> late, then proceeding
                    on, got to our<lb/><pb n="11" facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_11"/>Brother, G John 4m
                    about 4 oclock, and<lb/> lodged here <persName key="wembr1">Wm Embree</persName>
                    met us agree<lb/>ably to appointment.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-05-22">22nd</date> 4th day  <placeName
                        key="eliza"/></dateline>
                <p>Breakfasted and set off half<lb/>past
                    5, Brother and sister going with us<lb/>stop'd at the door of <persName
                        key="jgibb1">J Gibbons</persName> and bid<lb/>farewell, proceeded to
                        <placeName key="lanca">Lancaster</placeName> 7<emph rend="underline"
                        >m</emph><lb/>gave the horses a little feed while we got<lb/>some
                    necessaries for our journey, set<lb/>off brother going a piece to put us in
                    the<lb/>right road, 3<emph rend="underline">m</emph> from L crossed <geogName
                        key="lcone">little con<lb/> nostoga,</geogName> proceeded along being
                    entire<lb/>strangers. the roads exceedingly badly <del>&amp;</del><lb/>cut in
                    ugly holes, and very muddy,<lb/>the country beautiful, fine grain
                    and<lb/>clover, crossed <geogName key="chiqu">big chaques creek,</geogName> a
                    large<lb/>stream 9<emph rend="underline">m</emph> from L. got some
                    refresh-<lb/>ment for our selves and horses at<lb/><persName key="cshel1"
                        >Christian Shellers</persName> Inn keeper 1/4 past 2<lb/>proceeded on our
                    journey <del>and pursuing</del><lb/> to <placeName key="eliza"
                        >Elizabethtown</placeName> where we arrived a while<lb/> before sunset
                        9<emph rend="underline">m</emph>, Lodged at the blackbear<lb/>tavern, the
                    road continuing bad the land<lb/><emph rend="underline">good</emph> tho more
                    hilly than nearner L., My atten<lb/>-tion has been so employed in viewing
                    the<lb/> roads and country that I have scarcely<lb/>had any time for serious
                    reflection, tho<lb/>have not felt much anxious unpleasant<lb/><pb n="12"
                        facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_12"/>sensations, nor enjoyed a large portion<lb/>of
                    that precious consolation that is so<lb/>desirable. O that I may abide in the
                    pa<lb/>-tience with an eye <unclear>riagle</unclear> to him whose<lb/>fatherly
                    protection is as a wall around<lb/>those who are sincerely devoted to
                    serve<lb/>him wherever their lot may be cast</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-05-23">23rd</date><lb/>5th day. <placeName
                        key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>A fine morn. rose early,
                    set<lb/> out about 4, crossed <geogName key="conmo">connowaga
                        moun-<lb/>tains</geogName> and <geogName key="concr">creek,</geogName> the
                    hills exceedingly<lb/>rocky, the roads rather better near <placeName key="middl"
                        >Mid<lb/>-dletown,</placeName> some of the land good, forded<lb/>over
                        <geogName key="sweet">sweet arrow Creek</geogName> a very large<lb/>water,
                    it ran into the bed of the waggon<lb/>>it was of a considerable wealth, got to
                        <placeName key="middl">Middle-<lb/>town</placeName> in dauphin County to
                        breakfast<lb/>8<emph rend="underline">m</emph>, met with <persName
                        key="rtune1">Richard Tunes</persName> send a few<lb/>lines home. 9 oclock
                    proceeded on our<lb/>journey Thus a beautiful valley and<lb/>very fertile soil
                    for several <emph rend="underline">m</emph>, came<lb/>in sight of the river
                    about 11 oclock, the<lb/>prospect of the country on the right<lb/>hand was soon
                    after obstructed by a<lb/>large ridge of limestone mountains<lb/>some places the
                    Rocks were 30 or 40 feet high from the<lb/>surface of the ground and
                    continued<lb/>till we came near on the bank of the<lb/>river. got in sight of
                        <placeName key="harrisb">Harrisburg</placeName>about<lb/>1 oclock. 9<emph
                        rend="underline">m</emph>, stoped under the shade of a tree<lb/><pb n="13"
                        facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_13"/>bought grass for our horses and took
                    some<lb/>refreshment in the waggon. 1/2 past 2 on<lb/>proceeded on, crossed a
                    small creek calld<lb/><persName key="paxto">paxton</persName> over an elegant
                    stone bridge,<lb/>then pass'd thru <placeName key="harrisb"
                        >Harrisburg</placeName> a very consi<lb/>derable Town, &amp; beautiful
                    situation having<lb/>a fine prospect of the river, travelled<lb/>7<emph
                        rend="underline">m</emph> close on the bank thereof, a distance<lb/>of fine
                    cultivated land on the right hand<lb/>the river on the left, a great
                    many<lb/>Locust trees in full bloom on each side<lb/>together with the prospect
                    of the water<lb/>made it delightful, but after a calm comes<lb/>a storm, crossed
                    a large stream called <geogName key="fishi">fish<lb/>ing creek</geogName> and
                    for 3<emph rend="underline">m</emph> it is astonishing, to be<lb/>hold just one
                    path along the bank of the river and<lb/>great rocks hanging from 400 to 600
                    feet<lb/>high almost over our head<del>s</del> the roads exceed<lb/>ingly stony
                    but not dangerous, we crossed <geogName key="stonc">stony<lb/>creek</geogName>
                    &amp; put in at <persName key="delde1">David Elder's</persName> tavern 10<emph
                        rend="underline">m</emph><lb/>here we were just at the foot of <geogName
                        key="bluem">cattatinna<lb/>or blue mountain</geogName>, came round it,
                    by<lb/>the side of <geogName key="susqu">Susquehanna</geogName> it is computed
                        <del>by some</del><lb/>to be 600 feet high, I could scarce keep my<lb/>eyes
                    off it, <del>it looked</del> the prospect was so wonderful </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-05-24">24th</date><lb/>6th day  <placeName
                        key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>Set out this morn 20m past<lb/>4,
                    had a very good road a little up hill and<lb/>down with some spots of cultivated
                    land<lb/>for about 2<emph rend="underline">m</emph>, then cross'd
                        <del><gap/></del>
                    <geogName key="clark">Clarks creek</geogName> and pre<lb/> pared to ascend
                        <geogName key="petem">peters' mountain,</geogName> the<lb/><pb n="14"
                        facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_14"/> road good, we were one hour and quarter
                    going<lb/>over it about a mile up, remarkable to see<lb/>several lively springs
                    so near the top, after<lb/> we left this mountain we cross'd a large
                    stream<lb/>of water call>ed <geogName key="powel">powells Creek,</geogName> and
                    had an ex<lb/>-cellent road to <placeName key="halif">Hallifax</placeName> a
                    small town 10<emph rend="underline">m</emph>,<lb/>some parts cultivated, the
                    grain chiefly rye<lb/>some fields of a changeable red, with some clover<lb/>the
                    soil rather gravelly, and of a reddish co-<lb/>lour. got breakfast at <persName
                        key="jewig1">John Ewigs</persName> Tavern,<lb/>here we came on the river
                    again, proceeded<lb/>from H. about 9 &amp; crossed <geogName key="armst"
                        >armstrong Creek,</geogName><lb/><del>it begining to</del> with some rain we
                    pass'd along a very<lb/>rough road close on the river at the foot
                        of<lb/><geogName key="berry">Berry's mountain</geogName>, cross'd
                        <unclear>wishinisky</unclear><lb/> creek considerably larger than <geogName
                        key="brand">Brandywine</geogName><lb/>now we began to get among <del>come
                        upon</del> the pines, a few<lb/> places here and there cultivated, the soil
                    not<lb/>very productive, poor looking houses, stoped<lb/>by the road side to
                    regale ourselves and horses<lb/>10<emph rend="underline">m</emph>, set out again
                    at 2, had a good Road 3<emph rend="underline">m</emph> to<lb/><geogName
                        key="mahmo">Magantango mountains</geogName>, 1/2 an hour going<lb/>over,
                    cross'd <geogName key="mahat">Magantango creek</geogName> over a high<lb/>frame
                    bridge, a large stream. The road<lb/>turning so much east seemed to
                    surprise<lb/>us, but found it was to go thro a gap <del>between</del><lb/>in
                    several places between great mountains,<lb/>indeed for many miles there is
                    very<lb/>little but mountains, got to a dutch<lb/>man's a while before sunset
                        10<emph rend="underline">m</emph>, and<lb/>lodged. but every thing looked so
                    dirty<lb/>I knew not what to do. however we<lb/><pb n="15"
                        facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_15"/>prepared of our own <del>ourselves</del> a
                    supper, and went to<lb/> bed, but the greatest mortification of all<lb/>was,the
                    landlady sent two men who were<lb/>travellers to the other bed in our room,<lb/>
                    our men as usual in the waggon, we<lb/>were very quiet, &amp; rose before
                    day</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-05-25">25th</date><lb/>4th day <placeName
                        key="milto"/></dateline>
                <p>Set off at 4 had a very
                    rough<lb/> road between mountains 4<emph rend="underline">m</emph>, came to
                    the<lb/> reading road at Hioustons tavern, where we<lb/> wished to have gotten
                    last night, cross'd <unclear>GreenBoror</unclear>
                    <del><unclear>revals</unclear></del><lb/>&amp; pass'd along thro the woods,
                    except a<lb/>small cultivated spot where we saw some<lb/>fine wheat growing for
                    a rarity, came<lb/>on the bank of <geogName key="mahac">Mahaney</geogName> &amp;
                    went up.<lb/> The ride of it a considerable distance<lb/>between wonderful
                    mountains, cross'd<lb/>over it, being a very large stream, pro<lb/>ceeded and
                    came to the <geogName key="mahan">Mahanoy moun<lb/>tain</geogName> 52m going
                    over. rather different from the others, we<lb/> ascended all so far with leaving
                    the ridge<lb/>on the left hand, &amp; when on the top made<lb/>a short turn and
                    went down with the<lb/>ridge on same ride, but this we travelled<lb/> a
                    considerable distance on the top a<lb/>fence on one side and went down in<lb/>
                    the form of an X it was amazing to<lb/>see the steepness on the north side<lb/>
                    stoped 11<emph rend="underline">m</emph> and fed our horses made
                    some<lb/>chocolate for breakfast, proceeded on 1/2 past 9<lb/><pb n="16"
                        facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_16"/>had a rough road, cross'd <geogName key="shamo"
                        >Shamokin C.</geogName> past thro<lb/><placeName key="sunb"
                        >Sunbury</placeName> the capital of <placeName key="north"
                        >Northumberland<lb/>County</placeName>. ferryed over the river in 1/2
                    an<lb/>hour a mile across, fed our horses in <placeName key="north1">North<lb/>
                        umberland</placeName> town 8<emph rend="underline">m</emph> proceeded along
                    thro<lb/>rather a barren soil, tho considerably culti<lb/>-vated, cross'd
                        <geogName key="chill">Chilasquaky C.</geogName> came on the<lb/>bank of the
                    west branch of <geogName key="susqu">Susquehanna</geogName>,<lb/>the land good,
                    as also the road, got to<lb/>
                    <placeName key="milto">Milton</placeName> about 6 a small town 12<emph
                        rend="underline">m</emph> put up<lb/> at <placeName key="jbrad1">John
                        Brady's</placeName> tavern, I being very un-<lb/> well took a little
                    medicine, soaked my<lb/>feet and went to bed before sunset with<lb/>out supper.
                    cousin being very kind in<lb/>waiting on me, they call'd for their sup<lb/>per.
                    it being a time of frolicing a great<lb/>many men were there drinking
                    and<lb/>fighting most of the night, that we<lb/>could not take our usual rest,
                    indeed<lb/>it did so impress my mind with sorrow<lb/>that I could not refrain
                    from weeping</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-05-26">26th</date><lb/>1st day <placeName
                        key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>Set out at 4 travelled
                    seve<lb/>ral <emph rend="underline">m</emph> on the bank of the river,
                    good<lb/>road, cool morn. considerable white<lb/>frost, stoped at David Shannon
                        8<emph rend="underline">m</emph> got a very<lb/>good breakfast and grain for
                    the horses,<lb/>as soon as I went into the house I dis<lb/>cover'd somthing
                    ailed the landlord, he<lb/>he made such heavy moans, and query'd<lb/>
                    <pb n="17" facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_17"/>what was the matter, he said he had got
                    about<lb/>building, and thought so much, that he had got<lb/>low in his mind. I
                    told him he had a fine barn<lb/>a good looking place and materials ready<lb/>for
                    building his house, and had no cause<lb/>to be discouraged, he said he had been
                    a hard<lb/>working industrious man and <del>had been help</del> helped
                    thro<lb/>many difficulties by the hand of providen<lb/>ce but all was nothing to
                    him now, we told<lb/>him that hand that had helped would yet, if<lb/>we did but
                    trust. he said he had strived all he<lb/> could but could not help it. if he was
                    as he<lb/>once was and saw one of us so, he would have<lb/>thought we might help
                    it, but we knew not<lb/>till we were tried. he seemed very sensible<lb/>of his
                    situation and possess'd of tender feelings</p>
                <p>Indeed I felt a near sympathy for him<lb/>and it revived a stronger impression on
                    my Mind of our<lb/>own weakness than I almost ever felt before<lb/>unless aided
                    by a power superior to our own.<lb/>half past 8 proceeded, passed thro a
                    small<lb/>village, crossed <geogName key="muncr">muncey C.,</geogName> &amp; got
                    to <persName key="welli1">Wm Ellis's</persName><lb/> half past 12. 10<emph
                        rend="underline">m</emph> they were gone to meeting<lb/>it seemed pleasant
                    to get amongst friends<lb/>having scarcely now the sight of one since
                    we<lb/>left <placeName key="lanca">Lancaster.</placeName> This afternoon wrote
                    home, in<lb/>the evening the family was collected <unclear>Mrs</unclear><lb/>
                    Ellis just read several chapters in the testamen<lb/><pb n="18"
                        facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_18"/> wherein a comfortable time of silence
                    was<lb/>witnessed to prevail.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-05-27">27th</date><lb/>2nd day <placeName
                        key="willi1"/></dateline>
                <p>This morning washed some
                    clothes<lb/> 3 oclock PM set out on our journey, had<lb/>a good road chiefly
                    thro the woods, crossd<lb/><geogName key="loyac">Loyalsock C.</geogName> a very
                    large water, got to<lb/>
                    <placeName key="willi1">Williamsport</placeName> the capital of <placeName
                        key="lycom1">Lycoming C.</placeName><lb/>7<unclear>h</unclear> 12<emph
                        rend="underline">m</emph> put up at <persName key="jwint1">James
                        Winter</persName> (<persName key="welli1">Wm<lb/> Ellis</persName> being
                    there on business) <del>where</del> we were<lb/>comfortably accommodated,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-05-28">28th</date><lb/>3rd day <placeName
                        key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>Started this morn a little
                    after<lb/>4 went about 1m 1/2 stoped at a house to buy<lb/>grain for the horses,
                    hearing that we could<lb/>not get any further on. while the men<lb/> were
                    employ'd cousin and I stoped in<lb/> to a little house by the road side where we
                    met<lb/>with some who formerly lived in C. County<lb/>Baileys by name, who
                    invited us to eat<lb/>breakfast we accepting of their kindness,<lb/> proceeded
                    on, cross'd <geogName key="lycom">Lycoming C.</geogName>very large<lb/> pass'd
                    thro a small village, called <placeName key="newb1">newberry.</placeName>
                    then<lb/> ascended the hill, and went thro a
                        <del>moun</del><lb/><del>tainous</del> wilderness country very mountainous
                        5<emph rend="underline">m</emph> to one Brooke,<lb/> fed the horses, the men
                    took their breakfast<lb/>of a cup of milk and some rye bread, half<lb/>past 9.
                    set out again, a very rough road,<lb/>6<emph rend="underline">m</emph> to the
                    foot of the <geogName key="allmo">Alleghany Mountain,</geogName><lb/><pb n="19"
                        facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_19"/>fed the horses, and had a rock for a table,
                    some<lb/>of the waggon store together with excellent water<lb/>that issued from
                    toward the top of the <emph rend="underline">m</emph>
                    <del>servd</del><lb/>served to refresh the weary travellers, but mo
                    peace<lb/>for them nor the horses because of the little knats.<lb/> half past 1
                    pursuing on, the road being excessive<lb/>stony computed to be 6<emph
                        rend="underline">m</emph> 1/2 over, 3 hour 3/4 going,<lb/>put up at
                        <persName key="jkook1">Kookens</persName> just at the foot, where<lb/>were
                    some of the tallest hemlocks pines, &amp;c that<lb/>I ever saw.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-05-29">29th</date><lb/>4th day <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>Set out this morn 1/4 past 4
                    af-<lb/> ter passing a hill, had a very rough swampy<lb/>road along a valley
                    between great mountains<lb/>Thro <del><unclear>wash</unclear></del> a thicket of
                    amazeing tall trees of<lb/>different kinds, it being cloudy seemed at<lb/>most
                    dark. cousin and I preparing our<lb/>selves with staffs set out on foot, while
                    we<lb/>were traveling <del>pursuing</del> along before the waggon we heard<lb/>a
                        <del>&amp;</del> noise, &amp; looking round to see what was the<lb/>matter,
                    beheld, as the waggon was going down<lb/>a very steep &amp; excessive muddy
                    place a Feather <del>the</del> bed<lb/>pitched out before, and was conveyed
                    under<lb/>the waggon in the mud, and a bottle of milk,<lb/> which we had
                    purchased for breakfast, &amp; was<lb/> pushed in the blanket that tied it, got
                    out<lb/>without any damage. however we took of<lb/>the blanket, got a sheet and
                    tied it up<lb/>again, &amp; proceeding along crossed a lively<lb/>stream of
                    water which followed the<lb/><pb n="20" facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_20"/> the road
                        <del>backward and forward</del> for several<lb/><emph rend="underline"
                        >m</emph> after crossing it a great many times, and<lb/>coming to it again I
                        percieved<del>g</del> a tree<lb/>across a little down, which appeared
                    about<lb/>two yards high from the water &amp; attempting it<lb/>for a bridge.
                    when near the middle it swagging my<lb/> foot slipping, in I went not much
                    over<lb/>shoe tops and was forced to wade thro. altho we had not travelled a
                    great<lb/> distance this morn. but it was difficult<lb/> geting along and my
                    feet being wet, con<lb/> cluded to make a fire <del>and</del> get
                    breakfast<lb/>and feed the horses, we then proceeded, continuing<lb/>thro the
                    wilderness, we came to <geogName key="pinec">pine C.</geogName> cross'd<lb/> it
                    13. times in about 5 or 6<emph rend="underline">m</emph> got to
                    Morris's<lb/>Mills about 12 oclock 12 1/2<emph rend="underline">m</emph> from
                    where we<lb/>lodged, we met with <persName key="fking1">Francis Kings</persName>
                    daughter when <del>was</del> at <persName key="welli1">Wm Ellis</persName>
                    <lb/>and she told us we could not get thro the wil<lb/>derness with the waggon,
                    and also the man<lb/>that lives here said the name which
                    seemed<lb/>discourageing, got dinner, set off half past<lb/>2, cousin and I
                    travelling on foot having a moun<lb/>tain to ascend got a great distance.
                    before<lb/>the waggon, we stoped at one Jackson's till<lb/>the men come <del>who
                        were</del> the people seemed glad<lb/>to see us tho no acquaintance,
                        <del>the</del> woman said she<lb/>was pleased to see us so chearful, but
                    her<lb/>husband, said it would take us six weeks<lb/> to get there with the
                    waggon, but told<lb/><pb n="21" facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_21"/>us to call at
                        <persName key="mwils1">Moses Wilson's</persName> and get his Sons<lb/>to
                    assist, we proceeded along &amp; crossd <geogName key="pinec">pine C</geogName>
                    at<lb/>the second fork, stoped a few minutes to see<lb/><persName key="sbabs1"
                        >Sampson Babs</persName>. got to <persName key="jyarn1">James
                        Yarnall's</persName> 6<emph rend="underline">m</emph>,<lb/>I suppose a
                    relation, his father's name was<lb/> Daniel, from toward Midn, a while
                    before<lb/>sunset and lodged- </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-05-30">30th</date><lb/>5th day <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>Set out at 5 oclock
                    purposing<lb/> to breakfast at <persName key="mwils1">Moses Wilson</persName>,
                    being informd<lb/> it was 5<emph rend="underline">m</emph> and the first house,
                    but <del>beheld</del>, when<lb/>we came to it the house was empty, and
                    nobody<lb/>to enquire of, however we being a great way<lb/>before the waggon,
                    and cold, made bold to<lb/>open the door and go in, where we found<lb/>fire, put
                    it <del>up</del> together and sat half an<lb/>hour warming ourselves till the
                    waggon<lb/>came; after conferring together a while conclud<lb/>-ed to go on at a
                    venture, <del>as</del> we having expected to<lb/>get some information of the
                    road at <persName key="mwils1">M Wilson</persName>, but<lb/>by a draught <del>of
                        the road</del> which our kind<lb/>friend <persName key="tstew1">T
                        Stewardson</persName> had given us, knew we<lb/>left the state road, shortly
                    after pursuing 1/2<lb/>
                    <emph rend="underline">m</emph> came to a fork, takeing the left hand<lb/>road
                    went on a piece (looking every way<lb/>for a house) thro the woods,
                        <del>over</del> being excessive<lb/><pb n="22" facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_22"
                    />swampy we came to another fork, then stoped<lb/>being quite at a loss; after
                    going along<lb/>on foot both roads a considerable distance found<lb/><persName
                        key="mwils1">M Wilsons,</persName> but it was out of the way to<lb/>go to
                    his house and a very bad road; thought <del>thot</del><lb/>best to go 1m further
                    on to <persName key="jidin1">James Idings</persName><lb/>to breakfast it being
                    near the road, M and<lb/>his wife coming over there, I thought it strange to
                    see<lb/> such good looking friends settled in the<lb/>wilderness, and no remote
                    from meeting<lb/>and surprising to see M Idings in such<lb/>a little cabbin,
                    however we spent an <del>the</del><lb/><del>time</del> hour or two very
                    agreeably, excepting the<lb/>bad accounts of the road<del>s</del> M Wilson
                    telling<lb/>we might with difficulty get the waggon<lb/>10 or 15<emph
                        rend="underline">m</emph> further and one of his Sons<lb/>might go with us
                    to the next house <del>whi</del><lb/>which was 80<emph rend="underline"
                    >m</emph>, 11 o clock we set off, cousin<lb/>and I going before giving warning
                    of<lb/>the bad places, <persName key="mwils2">M Wilson Jr</persName> and
                        <persName key="bcoop1">Ben<lb/>-jamin</persName> holding the hindpart of
                    the<lb/>waggon, the banks so steep and
                    <del><unclear>sidling</unclear></del><lb/>that one would think it impossible
                    to<lb/>get along without oversetting; <del>cossing</del><lb/>
                    <del>as</del>
                    <del>crossing</del> we crossed an <del>the pine</del> another another large
                    branch of the <geogName key="pinec">pine<lb/>C,</geogName> &amp; after
                    travelling a piece got stoped<lb/> by the trees that were across the<lb/><pb
                        n="23" facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_23"/>road, our 3 men with the assistance
                    of<lb/> two more got the axes to work it being<lb/>about 1/4m to Boatmans which
                    took near two<lb/>hours to get the waggon up where we must<lb/>leave it, we
                    endeavoured to persuade<lb/>some of them to go with us and help to open
                    the<lb/>road, but there being but two families and no <del>neig</del><lb/>
                    neighbours near, &amp; they very busy planting<lb/>corn and out of provision, no
                    mill with<lb/>in 20<emph rend="underline">m</emph>, the woman said she could
                    let<lb/>us have plenty of milk and butter but<lb/>had nothing else excepting a
                    little fresh<lb/>venison which was <del>being</del> a very good relish with
                    out<lb/>coffee; having <del>just</del> got our dinner, we then set to
                    unload<lb/>-ing our waggon and packing having two mens<lb/>saddles along welaped
                    one bed up in the wag<lb/>gon cover and tied on one horse sewed<lb/>up a sheet
                    for a sack filled it and a <lb/>bag we had along with clothing a load
                    for<lb/>another, allowing the provision for selves<lb/> and horses for the
                    other, night coming on<lb/>we got supper put some bread to rise and<lb/>went to
                    bed </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-05-31">31st</date><lb/>6th day <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>A clear cold morning very<lb/>
                    white frost some clothes I washed last<lb/>night being froze stiff, baked bread,
                    got<lb/>breakfast, <del>and</del> our horses Loaded, &amp; set<lb/>out on our
                    journey pretty chearful<lb/><pb n="24" facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_24"/>9 oclock
                    having left one bed, our trunks, &amp;c<lb/> behind, hoping to get them some
                    time<lb/>this summer, after crossing <geogName key="pinec">pine
                    C,</geogName><lb/> the land lady pushed cousin and I over in a canoe<lb/>
                    travelled till near 1 thro the wilderness<lb/>up the <geogName key="pinec">pine
                        C</geogName>being fine grass for the<lb/>horses where we let them partake
                    while<lb/>we got dinner, 2 journeyed on till 1/2<lb/>past 6 then prepared to
                    take our rest<lb/>in the woods, put up some forks and<lb/>spread the waggon
                    cover over, after mak<lb/>ing some chocolate went to bed but I<lb/>could not
                    sleep much, we came by the<lb/>marks on the trees 15<emph rend="underline"
                        >m</emph></p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-06-01">6th <emph rend="underline">m</emph> 1st</date><lb/>7th
                    day <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>A clear cool morn. 5 oclock<lb/>set out again, travelled till 8 then
                    stopd<lb/> and got breakfast, almost impossible<lb/>to tell how often we crossed
                        <geogName key="pinec">pine C</geogName> 1/2<lb/>past 9 proceeded, I mounted
                    one of the<lb/>horses having the bed for a saddle, a very<lb/>boggy rough road
                    till after leaving <geogName key="pinec">pine<lb/>C,</geogName> then pass'd thro
                    some good land<lb/>near the head waters of the <geogName key="alleg"
                        >Alleghey</geogName><lb/>and came down to the foot of a moun<lb/> tain
                    concluding it time to prepare<lb/>for lodging, had a good nights rest af<lb/>ter
                    a fatiguing days journey of 26<emph rend="underline">m</emph><lb/>cousin walking
                    all the way, I the<lb/>most part, she did it of choice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry"><pb n="25" facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_25"/>
                <dateline><date when="1805-06-02">2nd</date><lb/>1st day <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                
                <p>Cloudy morn 5 o clock set
                    out,<lb/> travelling till 8 cross'd the <geogName key="owego">Oswago
                        C</geogName> it begin<lb/> -ing to rain thot best to get breakfast
                    9.<lb/>proceeded again, got to <persName key="jbell1">John Bell's</persName> 12
                        oclock<lb/>12<emph rend="underline">m</emph> his wife seeing us coming ran
                    out to<lb/>meet us with tears running, we were<lb/> glad to see her, having been
                    better than<lb/>two days and two nights in the wilderness,<lb/>altho the journey
                    has been a little trying<lb/>yet I felt <emph rend="underline">som</emph>thing
                    animating and en<lb/> -courageing 6 revive<del>d</del>, and my heart was<lb/>
                    filled with a precious sweetness which was<lb/>a sufficient consolation for the
                    most<lb/>trying seasons, O may I ever abide in the<lb/>patience with my eye
                    single to him<lb/>who knoweth <del>best</del> what is best for us,<lb/>after
                    dinner <persName key="bcoop1">Benjamin</persName> and <persName key="welli1"
                        >Wm</persName> went 3 miles<lb/>to <persName key="fking1">Francis
                        King's</persName> to see about a canoe<lb/> and staid all night, we staying
                    with M.<lb/>Bell her husband not at home</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-06-03">3rd</date><lb/>2nd day <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>Cloudy about 10 o clock they<lb/>
                    came &amp; <persName key="fking1">F King</persName> with them, and fetched<lb/>
                    some horses for cousin and I, we went to<lb/> F. to dinner it looking like for
                    rain<lb/>they &amp; wished us to stay all night, but<lb/>we thot to get 12<emph
                        rend="underline">m</emph> down the river to<lb/><persName key="rhoop1"
                        >Robert Hoops's.</persName>
                    <del>could get thro</del> hoping next day<lb/>
                    <pb n="26" facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_26"/>to reach <placeName key="tunes"
                        >Tunesassah</placeName>
                    <del>and were</del> where we were anxious to get<lb/><del>home</del> set off
                    about 3 F, his son and daug<lb/>-hter with us, before we had gone far
                    it<lb/>began to thunder and the Gust increased till there<lb/>was a very heavy
                    shower, we stoped at a<lb/>little house a while till the heaviest<lb/>was over,
                    but the loads being on the<lb/> horses I was afraid our clothes would<lb/>be
                    very wet. and having nothing but<lb/>a foot path, and the bushes very
                    wet<lb/>made it disagreeable travelling. but<lb/>we got <persName key="rhoop1">R
                        Hoopss</persName>
                    <del>there</del> 7 o clock and were kindly reli<lb/>-eved, but <del>t</del>he
                        <del>man</del> was not at home, be<lb/>-ing gone to seek provision, several
                    places<lb/>we have been at latterly it has been<lb/> the case, scarce of
                    provision, which is<lb/>the case here, none for us, no canoe to<lb/>take us
                    down, haveing some with us<lb/>got our supper and went to bed </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-06-05">5th</date><lb/>4th day <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>Cloudy and like for rain
                        <persName key="bcoop1">Ben</persName><lb/>&amp; <persName key="welli1"
                        >Wm</persName>, and <persName key="fking1">Frances</persName> with them set
                    off for<lb/><placeName key="tunes">Tunesassah</placeName> on horse back, leaving
                    us be<lb/>-hind, purposing sending a canoe<lb/>for us</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-06-05">5th</date><lb/>4th day <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>This day has been spent<lb/>with
                    anxious desires to see a canoe,<lb/>we feel very dull and lonesome, two<lb/>
                    <pb n="27" facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_27"/>days waiting</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-06-06">6th</date> 5th day <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p>Rose early got breakfast set<lb/>of
                    with a man that was going down<lb/>the river got 11<emph rend="underline"
                        >m</emph>, met <persName key="jswai1">Joel Swain</persName> and<lb/>an
                    Indian with a canoe <del>going</del> coming for us we got<lb/>in with them and
                    proceeded, about<lb/>12 oclock stoped at <persName key="psnid1">Peter
                        Sniders</persName> a white<lb/>man his wife was taken captive when
                    about<lb/> 3 years old, has lived with the Indians<lb/>ever since, and cannot
                    talk any en<lb/> glish, got some milk of them to eat with<lb/>our bread, set off
                    again got to <placeName key="tunes">Tune<lb/>sassah</placeName> 5 o clock
                        40<emph rend="underline">m</emph> my dear <persName key="bcoop1"
                        >B</persName> was<lb/><unclear>borning</unclear> brush <persName
                        key="welli1">Wm</persName> at work with the<lb/>planes they all glad to see
                    us and we<lb/>to get home</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-06-07">7th</date><lb/>6th day <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p>got to washing some of our<lb/>
                    dirty clothes, a great many of the na-<lb/>tives coming to see us thro the
                    course<lb/>of the day, <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanters</persName> sister
                    said<lb/>she was glad the good spirit had<lb/>brought us safe on our long
                    journey,<lb/>which revived somthing endearing toge<lb/>ther with comfortable
                    impressions and<lb/>caused the grateful returns of grati-<lb/>tude so to
                    enforce; that in the secret<lb/><pb n="28" facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_28"/>effusions
                    of my spirit I was ready to<lb/> utter the Language, "great and
                    marvell-<lb/>lous are thy works."</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-06-10">10th of the <emph rend="underline"
                    >m</emph></date><lb/>2nd day<placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p> <persName key="jtayl1">Jacob Taylor</persName> went
                    to in-<lb/>form the Indians of our coming and<lb/>our brothers had sent an
                    address to them<lb/> they told him they would confer toge<lb/>ther and let us
                    know</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-06-11">11th</date><lb/>3rd day <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p>recieved word from the Indi<lb/>
                    ans. they had concluded to meet in<lb/>counsil in three days at a
                    place<lb/>called <placeName key="colds">cold spring</placeName> 3 1/2<emph
                        rend="underline">m</emph> from our house</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-06-14">14th</date><lb/>6th day <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p>Agreeably to the
                    conclusion<lb/>of the Indians, we went to the counsil. <persName key="jtayl1"
                        >J<lb/>Taylor</persName> having been very unwell several<lb/>days, tho'
                    better this morning and we<lb/>desirous of having him with us, all<lb/>set off
                    at 9 o clock, taking a little provi<lb/>-sion in the saddlebags; while
                    the<lb/>Indians were collecting, we took some<lb/>refreshment under a
                        <unclear>shed</unclear> in the town<lb/> 11 clock went into the counsil
                    house<lb/>where were a large number of Indians<lb/><pb n="29"
                        facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_29"/>10 chiefs, and a good many women;
                        old<lb/><persName key="conud1">Connidiu</persName> after sitting a while
                    opened<lb/>the counsil with expressing thanks<lb/>to the great spirit in
                    bringing us safe<lb/>thro our long journey, also that so ma<lb/>ny of them were
                    collected there to day<lb/>desiring the warriors to pay attention<lb/> to what
                    should be communicated to<lb/>them, then informed the were ready<lb/> to hear
                    what we had to say, <persName key="habee1">Henry O<lb/>Bail</persName>
                    <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter's</persName> son being our<lb/>interpreter. -
                    The address from the com<lb/>mittee on our behalfs was read, part of<lb/>an
                    epistle from <persName key="hjack1">Halliday Jacksons</persName> to<lb/>the
                    Indian women, likewise a speech<lb/>from the young men residing here<lb/>
                    concerning <del>temporary affairs</del> saving<lb/>grinding &amp;c, they were
                    also inform'd<lb/>notwithstanding our journey had been<lb/>long and trying we
                    felt peace of<lb/>mind in being with them and hoped<lb/>our sisters the Indian
                    women would<lb/>be willing to be instructed; after we<lb/>became a little
                    acquainted, then tel-<lb/>ling them we had no more to say at<lb/>
                    <pb n="30" facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_30"/>present. After a considerable time<lb/>of
                    conferrence between themselves<lb/>the following is part of the substance<lb/>of
                    a speech delivered by one of the<lb/>Chiefs</p>
                <floatingText type="speech">
                    <body>
                        <p>Brothers Deweista (meaning Quakers)</p>
                        <p>We return thanks to the great<lb/>spirit to see you all well, and
                            that<lb/>the great spirit has preserved your<lb/>women on so long a
                            journey, and<lb/>that they arrived safe in our country<lb/>we are all
                            glad to see them, and are<lb/>
                            <del>pleased</del> much pleased to find they are go-<lb/>-ing to stay
                            amongst us to instruct<lb/>our women. we return thanks to<lb/>the great
                            spirit that he has put<lb/>this into their minds, we wish
                            you<lb/>therefore to make your minds<lb/>easy; they also seemed pleased
                                at<lb/><persName key="hjack1">Hallidays</persName> epistle,
                            signifying they<lb/>were at a loss for an answer, for<lb/>as two of the
                            heads of their women<lb/>were not there. After sitting near<lb/>3 hours
                            in counsil (exceedingly<lb/><pb n="31" facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_31"/>warm
                            and close) we were dismissed<lb/>they continuing their conferrence
                                <del>on</del><lb/> 2 hours longer on the business the young Men laid
                            before them<lb/><del>those temporary affairs</del>. broke up
                                in<lb/><del>2 hours after</del>, and appeard much<lb/>pleased with
                            their proposals <del>of our</del><lb/><del>young men</del>, which were
                            as follows</p>
                        <p>Brothers Attend -<lb/>You know we have of-<lb/>-ten talked to you about
                            opening a<lb/>good road from this town to <placeName key="tunes"
                                >Tunesas-<lb/>sah</placeName> in order to make it more easy
                            for<lb/>your people to come to mill, if you<lb/>will now join together,
                            and open this<lb/>road, we have concluded to give you<lb/> 7000 thousand
                            feet of boards; This will<lb/>enable you to finish your houses, to<lb/>
                            have them warm against next<lb/>winter</p>
                        <p>Brothers you know we began to<lb/>grind for you about the time
                            you<lb/>were making sugar. we will continue<lb/>to grind for you untill
                            the next sea-<lb/>son for sugar,making, without<lb/>taking toll which
                            will make one<lb/><pb n="32" facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_32"/>year. And if any
                            of you want<lb/>boards we will sell them to you<lb/>for four shillings
                            per hundred but<lb/>we dont intend to trust any,<lb/>because we want to
                            keep the chain of<lb/>friendship bright. And if you<lb/> want any of
                            your own logs saw<lb/>ed into boards or scan thing, <del>if</del> to
                            do<lb/>your own buildings. if you cut<lb/>and haul the logs to the
                            mill<lb/> we will saw them for one half</p>
                        <p>Brothers <gap/> These advantages which<lb/>we now propose to you, are
                            in-<lb/> tended to encourage you to pursue ha<lb/>bits of industry and
                            sobriety - We<lb/>wish you to keep your minds strong<lb/>to pursue this
                            path, then we think<lb/>your substance will increase, and<lb/>the great
                            spirit will bless your<lb/>labours.</p>
                        <p>Brothers We don't want to tire<lb/>your ears with many words but<lb/>it
                            affords us much satisfaction<lb/><pb n="33" facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_33"
                            />to see your industry This spring in<lb/> enclosing so many fields to
                            plant<lb/>in, and that you continue your good<lb/> resolution against
                            spiritous liquors,<lb/>we repeat it again be strong in<lb/> your minds
                            against this great<lb/>enemy and never let him rise up<lb/>again. We
                            have all united our <del>mind</del><lb/>minds <del>in</del> together in
                            this speech<lb/>and shall deliver you a copy <del>that</del><lb/>in
                            order that our memories may<lb/>be kept bright</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
          
                <p>I felt satisfaction in being there<lb/><persName key="jtayl1">Jacob
                        Taylor</persName> says he has felt<lb/>more peace in attending some<lb/>of
                    their counsils than any<lb/> quarterly meeting; but it will<lb/>take us some
                    time to get a little<lb/> acquainted with their language.</p>
                <p>About 30 of the Indians has since join<lb/>ed together and opened the road
                    which<lb/>will be an advantage to us as well<lb/><pb n="34"
                        facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_34"/> them, a grand piece of work for<lb/>Indians, it
                    being done completely</p>
                <p><persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> did not attend<lb/>the counsil but
                    has been here since<lb/>I did not deliver thy message for<lb/>want of an
                    interpreter <persName key="jtayl1">J Taylor</persName><lb/>said he thought he
                    could not make<lb/>him understand which was thee.<lb/>there was a paragraft in
                    the addres<lb/>from the committee sent by us<lb/>refering that when any of
                    them<lb/>has done any thing another does not<lb/>like, they should not differ
                    but<lb/>forgive him that does wrong<lb/>for the good spirit forgives<lb/> as
                    when we <del>are</del> do wrong if we are horror for it</p>
                <p>I know not but <del>whether it had not</del><lb/>it had a good effect for about
                    two<lb/>days after they calld a counsil, sent<lb/>for <persName key="cornp2"
                        >Cornplanter</persName> and made up<lb/>all the uneasiness, and
                    restord<lb/>him to his former power, he<lb/>has since<lb/><pb n="35"
                        facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_35"/> been here and he said he told them when<lb/>any
                    thing happened among them<lb/>in future they had better try to<lb/>make it up
                    among themselvs, and<lb/>not go and tell it abroad over<lb/>the country for that
                    made it worse<lb/>he also told us some more advise he<lb/>gave them, which I
                    thought very just<lb/><del>in regard to such trifals</del> and said<lb/>the old
                    friends down the country<lb/>might be inform'd that the differ<lb/>ence was all
                    done away and there<lb/>was nothing between us the quakers and them.</p>
                <p>It was very agreeable news to hear<lb/><persName key="cornp2"
                        >Cornplanter</persName> was restored, for his<lb/>judgment in matters, was
                    of <del>some</del><lb/> consequence, he wanted to <del>see</del> see some<lb/>of
                    our linen or manufacturing,<lb/>and said <del>he tho</del> if one or two of<lb/>
                    their women could get in the way<lb/>they could learn the other</p>
                <pb n="36" facs="SW_RC1805a_Page_36"/>




            </div>
        </body>


    </text>
</TEI>
